第十八章

门虚掩着，他们进去了。

“约翰！”

从卫生间里传来了那种典型的令人不快的声音。

“出什么事了吗？”赫尔姆霍茨问。

没有人回答。那种令人不舒服的声音又传来了，一次，两次，然后是一片静寂。过了一会儿，卫生间的门咔嗒一声打开了，野蛮人走了出来，脸色苍白。

“我说，”赫尔姆霍茨关切地喊道，“约翰，你看起来真像生病了！”

“你吃了什么不合你胃口的东西了吗？”伯纳德问。

野蛮人点点头说：“我吃了文明。”

“什么？”

“我中毒了，我被玷污了。”他接着放低了声音补充道，“我吃了我自己的邪恶。”

“好吧，到底是什么呢？我是说，你刚才在……”

“现在，我净化了自己，”野蛮人说，“我喝了些温水冲服的芥末。”

那两个人吃惊地盯着他。“你是说，你刚才是故意那么做的？”伯纳德问。

“印第安人总是这么净化自己的。”他坐下来，叹口气，用手抹了抹额头，“我要休息几分钟，”他说，“我很累。”

“我一点也不吃惊。”赫尔姆霍茨说，沉默了一会儿，他又说，“我们是来跟你告别的，”他换了种语气，“我们明天早晨就离开。”

“是的，我们明天走。”伯纳德说，野蛮人注意到他的脸上新添了一种坚忍的、听天由命的表情。“顺便说一句，约翰，”他继续说，坐在椅子上的身体前倾，将一只手放在野蛮人的膝盖上，“我想说，我为昨天发生的事情抱歉，”他的脸红了，“多么耻辱，”他继续说，虽然声音有些颤抖，“真的，多么……”

野蛮人打断他的话，抓住他的手，亲切地捏了捏。

“赫尔姆霍茨对我太好了，”伯纳德停顿了片刻，接着说，“要没有他的话，我可能……”

“别说了，别说了。”赫尔姆霍茨抗议了。

他们陷入了沉默。虽然有些伤心，甚至正是由于这种伤心的情感，因为他们的伤心正是他们彼此爱对方的表现，这三个年轻人感到非常开心。

“今天早晨我去见了控制官。”最后，野蛮人说。

“去干什么呢？”

“去问问我能否和你们一起去岛上。”

“他怎么说？”赫尔姆霍茨急切地问。

野蛮人摇摇头。“他不允许。”

“为什么呢？”

“他说他想继续这个实验，可是，我才不会干呢，”野蛮人突然怒气冲冲地说，“我才不会让他继续拿我做实验呢。即使世界上所有控制官都请我来做，我也不做。我明天也要离开。”

“可是去哪里呢？”两个人一起问。

野蛮人耸了耸肩。“任何地方。我不在乎，只要我能够独自一人就行。”

*

下行线路从吉尔福德出发，沿着威谷径直下到戈德尔明，然后，越过米尔福德和威特利，通向黑斯尔米尔，再穿过彼得斯菲尔德，到达朴茨茅斯。和这条线路大概平行的上行线路，则经过沃普尔斯顿、堂海姆、普坦汉姆、埃尔斯坦德和格雷肖特。在野猪背和欣德黑德之间的一些地方，这两条线路之间的距离不超过六七英里。对那些漫不经心的驾驶员来讲，这段距离太小了，尤其是晚上他们多吃了半克唆麻之后。曾经出过一些事故，很严重的事故。后来决定将上行线往西挪移几英里。在格雷肖特和堂海姆之间，有四座废弃的航空灯塔，标志着从朴茨茅斯到伦敦的那条旧路线。这些灯塔的上空寂静无声，一片荒凉。现在，那些直升机是在塞尔伯恩、博尔敦和法纳姆的上空飞行，不间断地嗡嗡着，呼啸着。

野蛮人选择了一座旧灯塔作为自己的隐居地，这个灯塔位于普坦汉姆和埃尔斯坦德之间的一座小山上。这是个铁架水泥建筑，状况良好。当野蛮人首次勘查这个地方的时候，觉得这个住处简直过于舒服、过于文明化、过于奢侈了。他保证将以更加严酷的自律和更加彻底的净化加以弥补，以此安慰自己的良心。在隐居地度过的第一个晚上，他刻意没有睡觉。他整夜都跪在地上祈祷，一会儿向身负罪孽的克劳狄斯(1)曾经乞求过宽恕的上天祈祷，一会儿又用祖尼语向阿沃纳威娄纳祈祷，一会儿向耶稣和菩公祈祷，一会儿又向自己的守护兽雄鹰祈祷。他不时将胳膊展开，好像在十字架上那样。他一直保持这个姿势，随着时间一分一秒地流逝，他胳膊上的疼痛逐渐加剧，直到变成一阵阵刺骨的痛楚；他就这样挺着，承受着自发的钉刑，咬着牙，嘴里不断地重复着（同时，汗水顺着脸颊淌下来）：“哦，宽恕我吧！哦，让我变得纯洁！哦，助我变得善良！”一遍又一遍，直到他几乎因为疼痛而晕死过去。

天亮了，他感到已经赢得了住在这个灯塔里的权利，尽管大多数窗户上的玻璃还在，尽管从塔顶平台看过去的风景很美。最初他选择这个灯塔的原因现在几乎成了他想马上去别处的理由。起初，他决定在这里生活就是因为风景太美了，因为，从他的那个制高点，他正在面对着的似乎是神灵的化身。可是，他又有何德何能，得到如此的娇宠，能够每天、每小时都看到如此美景？他是谁，能够一直与上帝面对面？他只配生活在某个肮脏的猪圈里，某个阴暗的地下洞穴里。经过漫长一夜的折磨，他浑身依旧僵硬酸痛，但正是因此，他的良心才更加平静，他爬到了灯塔顶部的平台上，眺望着那个日出时分明亮的世界，感觉他已经重新赢得了在这个世界生存的权利。他北面的风景被野猪背长长的灰白色山脊包围，最东头的山脊后面，耸立着七座摩天大楼，那里就是吉尔福德。看到这些大楼，野蛮人苦笑了一下，但是，随着时间的推移，他将习惯这个景观。夜晚，这些摩天大楼或是装饰着亮闪闪的、几何形的星座，或是打着泛照灯，像通体透亮的手指（在英格兰，除了野蛮人，没有人能够明白这个手势的意义），庄严地指向天穹深不可测的奥秘之中。

一个山谷将野猪背和他的灯塔坐落的这座砂质小山隔离开来，在那里，普坦汉姆就像一个不起眼的小村庄，只有九层楼高，只有几个筒仓、一个家禽场和一个不大的维他命D工厂。在灯塔的另一侧，地势向南面渐渐下降，先是长长的长满石楠的缓坡，然后降低为一长串池塘。

在更远处，比树林更远的地方，矗立着一座十四层的塔楼，这就是埃尔斯坦德了。在英格兰薄雾笼罩的空气中，欣德黑德和塞尔伯恩看上去有点朦胧，吸引着你将视线往那蔚蓝的浪漫远处望去。不过，最初将野蛮人吸引到灯塔这里来的，并不仅仅是这种远景，近景也一样令人迷醉。树林，连绵不绝的石楠和黄色的金雀花，一丛丛的苏格兰桦树，杉树掩映下的闪闪发光的池塘，池塘里的睡莲和一簇簇的灯芯草，这些都是那么美丽，对于习惯了美洲干旱沙漠的眼睛来说，简直令人震惊。还有那孤独！几天过去了，他从来没有见过一个人影。这个灯塔离查令T字塔只有一刻钟的飞行距离，可是，就算是玛尔帕斯的山脉几乎也不比这位于萨里郡的荒野更加寂寥。一群群人每天离开伦敦，只是为了去玩电磁高尔夫或者网球。普坦汉姆那里没有高尔夫球场，最近的黎曼曲面网球场是在吉尔福德，野花和风景是这里唯一的吸引力。因此，没有来这里的充分理由，也就没有人来这里。在最初的几天里，野蛮人完全是一个人生活，毫无打扰。

他刚到文明世界的时候，领到了一笔款项，作为他日常花销之用。他把这笔钱大多花在了买装备上面。离开伦敦之前，他购买了四床人造丝-羊毛毯、粗粗细细的绳子、钉子、胶水、几件工具、火柴（虽然他计划着过一段时间就钻木取火）、几个锅壶、二十多包种子、十千克小麦面粉。“不，不要那种合成淀粉和废棉做的代面粉，”他坚持着，“即使它更有营养也不要。”可是，在面对泛腺体饼干和添加维生素的代牛肉时，他没有抵挡住店员的劝服。看着那些罐头瓶子，他猛烈地谴责自己的软弱。可憎的文明化的东西！他已经下定决心，坚决不吃那东西，即使快要饿死了也不吃。“给他们一个教训。”他报复似的想。对他自己也是一个教训。

他数了数钱，希望剩下的那点足够让他凑合着度过冬天。到来年春天，他的菜园里将生产出足够的食物，他就不用依赖外面的世界了。同时，总会有一些猎物的。他看到过许多野兔，池塘里还有水禽。他立刻动手制作一副弓箭。

灯塔附近有一些白蜡树，还有长满挺拔漂亮的榛子树苗的灌木林，可以做箭杆。他开始砍伐一棵嫩白蜡树，砍出一段六英尺长、没有枝杈的树干，剥掉树皮，开始切削，刮下白白的木屑，就像老米斯玛教他的那样，最后，剩下了一段与他的身高大致相等的木棍，中间稍粗且坚硬，两头纤细、灵活而柔软。这项工作给了他极大的乐趣。他在伦敦度过了好几星期懒散的日子，无所事事，需要什么东西的时候，只需按一下开关或者转一下手柄，现在，做一些需要技巧和耐力的事情，真是一大乐趣。

快要将木棍削出形状来的时候，他突然意识到自己在唱歌，他吃了一惊——唱歌！就好像，他碰巧刚刚从外面回来，看到自己正在干一件大坏事，抓了个正着。他惭愧了，脸唰地红了。毕竟，他来到这里，不是为了唱歌和享受，而是为了逃离文明生活的污秽对他进一步的腐蚀，是为了净化自己，让自己变得更好，是为了积极地赎罪。他沮丧地意识到，专注于切削他的弓的时候，他已经忘记了发誓要时刻牢记的事情——可怜的琳达，以及自己对她的凶狠和残忍，那些可憎的多胞胎，像虱子一样爬着，亵渎了琳达之死的奥秘，他们的存在不仅侮辱了他自己的悲伤和悔恨，更侮辱了天神们。他曾经发誓要牢记这些，他曾经发誓要不停地赎罪。可是，他却坐在这里，开心地坐在这里，忙着做弓，还唱歌，真的在唱歌……

他走进屋子，打开一盒芥末，倒了些水，放到火上开始煮。

半个小时之后，来自普坦汉姆的一个波卡诺夫斯基组别的三个德尔塔－农民开车去埃尔斯坦德，恰巧经过这里。到达山顶时，他们吃惊地发现一个年轻人站在废弃的灯塔外面，上身赤裸，正在用一根打了结的鞭子抽打自己。他的后背上面横亘着一道道深红色的印迹，从这些鞭痕上流下细细的血水。卡车司机将车停在路边，和两个同伴一起，目瞪口呆地盯着这不同寻常的景象。一下，两下，三下——他们数着鞭打的次数。打完第八下，年轻人停止了自我惩罚，跑到树林边上，开始猛烈地呕吐。吐完之后，他拾起鞭子，又开始鞭打自己。九下，十下，十一下，十二下……

“福帝啊！”司机低声说，他的两个同伴也深有同感。

“福帝！”他们说。

三天后，记者们来了，犹如落在尸体上的秃鹫。

弓体在绿色木头生起的文火上烤干变硬之后，就做好了。野蛮人正忙着做箭。已经削出三十支榛子木棍，晾干了，一头钉上了尖尖的铁钉，弦口也仔细刻好了。有一天晚上，他突袭了普坦汉姆的家禽场，现在他已经有足够的羽毛来装备整个武器库。他正在加工箭杆上的羽毛，这时，第一个记者找到了他。这个人穿着充气鞋子，悄无声息，从他的身后突然出现。

“早上好，野蛮人先生，”他说，“我是《每时广播》的记者。”

野蛮人吓了一跳，好像被蛇咬了一下，他跳了起来，箭杆、羽毛、胶水瓶子和刷子散落一地。

“请你原谅，”记者说，真心地感到愧疚，“我没有想……”他用手碰触了一下帽子，那是一顶铝制的烟囱形状的帽子，在帽子里面装有无线电接收器和发报器，“原谅我没法把它摘下来，”他说，“有点沉。如我刚才所说，我代表的是……”

“你想干什么？”野蛮人阴沉着脸说。记者报以他最讨好的笑容。

“哦，当然，我们的读者会非常感兴趣……”他的头歪向一边，脸上的笑容几乎像是在献媚。“野蛮人先生，就说几句话。”他做出了一系列快速的仪式般的动作，解开两团电线接上围在他腰间的便携式电池；将它们同时插入铝制帽子的两侧；碰了一下帽顶上的弹簧，一根天线射向了空中；碰了一下帽檐顶端的另一个弹簧，跳出一个麦克风，就像从玩偶盒子里跳出一个玩偶一样，麦克风悬在那里，在离他的鼻子六英寸处颤动着；拉下一对接收器，戴在耳朵上；按了一下帽子左边的开关，从里面传来微弱的黄蜂般的嗡嗡声；拧了一下右边的旋钮，嗡嗡声之上立刻又增添了听诊器里那种呼呼声和咳咳声、咯咯声和突然的吱吱声。“喂，”他对着麦克风说“喂，喂……”他的帽子里突然传出了一声铃响。“是你吗，厄泽尔？我是普利莫·梅尔伦。是的，我抓到他了。野蛮人先生现在要对着麦克风说几句话。你会说的吧，野蛮人先生？”他抬头看着野蛮人，脸上又挂上了他最迷人的笑容。“就告诉我们的读者你为什么会来这里。你为什么突然离开伦敦？（再等会儿，厄泽尔！）当然，还有那鞭子的事。”（野蛮人吃了一惊，他们怎么知道鞭子的事的？）“我们都非常想知道那鞭子是怎么回事。再说点对文明的看法。你知道的，就那类东西，‘我如何看待文明的姑娘’，等等。寥寥数语就行，寥寥……”

野蛮人照他的话做了，真的就只有令人不安的几个词。他只说了五个词语，只有五个，就是他对伯纳德说过的同样的话，他对坎特伯雷首席歌唱家的看法：“哈尼！桑斯埃索嚓那！”他抓住记者的肩膀，把他的身子扳过去（这个年轻人包裹得很严实，真是诱人），瞄准，然后像个职业足球运动员一样，猛力而准确地向他踢过去，狠狠的一脚。

八分钟之后，《每时广播》的最新一期就在伦敦的大街小巷售卖了。头版头条印着“《每时广播》记者被神秘野蛮人狠狠踢中尾骨”“轰动整个萨里郡”。

“甚至轰动了伦敦。”这个记者返回后，看到这些词句时心里想。况且，这种轰动还是那么痛苦。他小心翼翼地坐下，开始吃午饭。

又来了四个记者，他们丝毫没有被同事尾骨上那本可以用以警戒的踢伤吓倒，他们分别是《纽约时报》、法兰克福《四维闭连报》、《福帝科学箴言报》和《德尔塔镜报》的记者。他们当天下午来到灯塔，却遭到了越来越暴力的对待。

《福帝科学箴言报》的记者躲在远远的安全距离之外，仍旧在揉着屁股。“愚昧的傻瓜！”他大喊，“你干吗不吃点唆麻？”

“滚开！”野蛮人晃了晃拳头。

其他人退后几步，又转过身来。“如果你吃几片唆麻，邪恶就不复存在。”

“抠哈克哇咿呀透克呀咿！”语气凶恶且满含讥讽。

“痛苦只是幻象。”

“哦，是吗？”野蛮人说，捡起一根粗粗的榛子木棍，大步走了过来。

《福帝科学箴言报》的记者朝着自己的直升机飞奔过去。

这之后的一段时间内，野蛮人的生活回归平静。几架直升机飞来，围着灯塔好奇地盘旋。他向飞得最近、最缠人的一架射出一箭，射穿了驾驶舱的铝制地板，只听一声尖叫，飞机火箭般地加速升空，使出了它的超级充电器所能提供的最大速度。随后，其他飞机就敬而远之了。野蛮人毫不理会那些恼人的嗡嗡声（在他的想象中，他将自己比喻成玛塔斯基少女的众多求婚者之一，不为那些长翅膀的毒虫所扰乱，坚毅而执着），继续挖他那个未来的菜园。过了片刻，很明显，毒虫厌倦了，飞走了。连续几个小时，他头顶的天空中空空如也，除了云雀的鸣叫外，寂静无声。

天气又闷又热，叫人透不过气来，空中传来滚滚雷声。他挖了一上午的地，正躺在地板上休息。突然，对列宁娜的思念似乎变成了一个真实的存在，裸露着，几乎可以触摸到，她在说：“亲爱的！”“抱紧我！”她穿着鞋子和袜子，喷了香水。不要脸的娼妇！可是，哦，哦，她的胳膊在搂着他的脖子，她的乳房抬起来了，她的嘴！永恒就在我们的唇间和双眼。列宁娜……不，不，不，不！他跳了起来，半裸着身体，跑出房子。在荒原边上，有一大簇灰白色的杜松，他冲入杜松丛。他拥抱的，不是他渴望的光滑肉体，而是一捧绿色的松针。尖利的松针，上千个针尖，刺着他。他竭力去想可怜的琳达，她喘不过气，说不出话，两手乱挠着，眼睛里充满无言的恐惧。可怜的琳达，他曾经发誓要牢记的琳达。可是，缠绕着他的依然是列宁娜，他发誓要忘记的列宁娜。尽管杜松的松针在刺着他，扎着他，但他畏缩的肉体感受到的，还是列宁娜，真实的、难以逃避的列宁娜。“亲爱的，亲爱的……如果你也想要我，你干吗不……”

鞭子就挂在门边的钉子上，记者们来时可以随手就拿起来。野蛮人一阵迷乱，他跑回房子，抓住鞭子，挥舞起来。打了结的绳子咬进了他的肉体。

“娼妇！娼妇！”每打一鞭，他就大喊一声，好像他打的是列宁娜（他没有意识到，他多么疯狂地希望打的真是列宁娜啊！），白花花的、温暖的、喷喷香的、无耻的列宁娜，他正这样鞭打着她。“娼妇！”然后，他绝望地说，“哦，列宁娜，宽恕我吧。宽恕我吧，上帝，我道德败坏，我邪恶。我……不，不，你这个娼妇，你这个娼妇！”

在三百米开外的树林里，达尔文·波拿巴藏在他精心建造的隐身处，目睹了刚才的整个过程，他是感官电影公司最高明的大型野兽摄像师。耐心和技巧终于得到了回报。他在一棵人工橡树的树洞里坐了三个白天，又花了三个晚上在石楠丛中爬来爬去，将麦克风安装到金雀花丛中，将电线埋进柔软的灰色沙地。在七十二个小时里，他饱尝艰辛，现在，伟大的时刻到来了，最伟大的时刻——达尔文·波拿巴一边在他的仪器中间走动着，一边在想，自从他拍摄了那著名的有关大猩猩交配的全号叫、立体感官电影之后，这是最伟大的时刻。“太精彩了，”当看到野蛮人开始那令人震惊的表演，他自言自语，“太精彩了！”他将望远式照相机小心翼翼地瞄准并固定在那移动着的目标上，调大功率，以获得那张疯狂扭曲的脸的特写（太棒了！）；又调换成半分钟的慢镜头（将产生巧妙的滑稽效果，他向自己保证）；同时，他聆听着那些正在往位于胶卷边沿的录音带中录入的鞭打声、呻吟声、狂野而疯癫的话语声，试了试将声音稍微放大的效果（是的，绝对更好）；在短暂的停歇之中，他很高兴地听到了云雀高亢尖锐的歌声；他真希望野蛮人能够扭过身去，让他给他后背上的鲜血来个特写，这时，几乎是立刻（多么令人吃惊的好运气！），那个与人为善的家伙真的转过身去了，他拍了个完美的特写。

“嗯，好极了！”拍完之后，他心里想，“真是好极了！”他擦了把脸。等他们在制作室里加入感官效果，这会是一部绝佳的影片。达尔文·波拿巴想，几乎和《抹香鲸的爱情生活》一样优秀——福帝！那可就说明问题了！

十二天后，《萨里郡的野蛮人》正式上映，在西欧的每个顶级感官电影院都可以看到、听到和触摸到。

达尔文·波拿巴的电影立即产生了巨大的轰动。晚上推出的电影，第二天下午，一大群直升机就突然飞临约翰头顶，打断了他的乡间独处生活。

他正在菜园里挖地，在他的脑海里，他也在挖着，费力地翻动着头脑中的思绪。死亡——他的铁锹落下去，一下，一下，再一下。我们所有的昨天，不过替傻子们照亮了到死亡的土壤中去的路。(2)一阵有说服力的雷声在那些词语之上訇然作响。他又抡起了一锹土。为什么琳达会死？为什么要让她逐渐变得不像人样，最后……他打了个冷战。可亲可吻的好腐肉。(3)他将脚放在铁锹上，狠狠地踩入坚硬的土地。天神掌握着我们的命运，正像顽童捉到苍蝇一样，为了戏弄的缘故而把我们杀害。又一声响雷。这些话宣告着自己的正确，甚至比真理本身还正确。可是，葛罗斯特却把他们叫作永远温柔的天神。(4)还有，睡眠是你所渴慕的最好的休息，死是永恒的宁静，你却对它心惊胆战。(5)睡眠，可能会做梦。(6)他的锹碰到了一块石头，他弯腰捡起来。可是，在那死亡的睡眠里，会做什么样的梦呢？(7)……

头顶上的嗡嗡声变成了轰鸣声，一片阴影突然遮住了他，有什么东西挡在了他和太阳之间。他停下挖掘，停下思考，抬头望去，吓了一跳。他迷茫不解地抬头去看，脑子还在比真理还正确的另一个世界里游荡，注意力仍然还停留在死亡与神祇的重大问题上。他抬头看去，看见了，那群盘旋着的直升机，离他的头顶那么近。它们就像蝗虫一样飞过来，悬停在半空，然后降落在他四周的荒原上。从这些巨大的蝗虫肚子里，走出了穿白色人造丝-法兰绒衣服的男人，穿黏胶-茧绸套装或者天鹅绒短裤和拉链半开的无袖汗衫的女人（天气很热）——从每架飞机中都走出一对男女。不一会儿，就走出来几十个人，他们围着灯塔，形成一个大圈子，盯着他看，嬉笑着，咔嚓咔嚓地照着相，向他扔花生（就像扔给一只猴子），扔一包包性荷尔蒙口香糖，扔泛腺体小奶油饼。每时每刻，他们的数量都在增加，此时，在野猪背的上空，飞机还在不断地蜂拥而来。如同在噩梦中一般，几十个人变成了上百个，上百个又变成了几百个。

野蛮人退回到隐蔽处。现在，他背靠灯塔的墙壁，姿势如同困兽一样，一张张脸地看过去，恐惧得说不出话来，像个疯子。

突然，一包瞄准精确的口香糖砸到了他的脸颊，把他从恍惚状态中惊醒，他意识到了眼前的现实。他痛苦地惊叫一声，他完全清醒了，清醒而怒火中烧。

“滚开！”他大喊。

猴子说话了，周围爆发出一阵大笑和鼓掌声。“好野蛮人！好哇，好哇！”他在这些杂乱的声音里听到有人在喊：“鞭子，鞭子，鞭子！”

这话提醒了他，他从门后的钉子上抓起那段打了结的绳子，对着折磨他的人晃了晃。

一阵讥讽的喝彩声和掌声。

他气势汹汹地走向他们。一个女人害怕地叫起来。队伍中离危险最近的人们犹豫了一下，然后又站直了，坚定地站在那里。这些观光者意识到自己在力量上具有压倒性的优势，因此勇气大增，这大大出乎野蛮人的意料。他吃了一惊，停住了脚步，向四处望望。

“你们为什么不让我一个人待着？”他的愤怒里几乎带着一种哀怨。

“吃点镁盐杏仁吧！”如果野蛮人继续向前，将第一个受到攻击的那个男人说，他递过来一包，“很好吃，你知道的，”他又说，讨好的笑容有些紧张，“镁盐会帮助你永葆青春。”

野蛮人没有理会他递过来的东西。“你们找我干什么？”他看着一张张傻笑的脸，问道，“你们找我干什么？”

“鞭子，”上百个声音乱糟糟地说，“表演一下那鞭子功夫，给我们看看鞭子功。”

然后，伴着缓慢沉重的节奏，他们一起喊起来：“我们——想看——鞭子。”队伍后边的一群人喊：“我们——想看——鞭子。”

其他人马上也跟着喊了起来，不断地重复着这句话，鹦鹉学舌一般，一遍又一遍，声音越来越大，喊到第七次或第八次的时候，就没有其他声音了，只剩下“我们——想看——鞭子”。

他们都在一起喊着。这声音，这团结，还有作为补偿的节奏感，都令他们陶醉，他们似乎可以连续喊叫几个小时，几乎可以无休无止地喊下去。可是，喊到大概第二十五次的时候，这喊叫被突如其来地打断了。又一架直升机飞过野猪背，悬停在人群上方，然后，在观光者和灯塔之间的空地上，在距离野蛮人几码远的地方降落了。螺旋桨的咆哮声暂时淹没了喊声。飞机落地了，马达关掉了。“我们——想看——鞭子，我们——想看——鞭子”的喊声再次爆发，同样响亮、同样急切的单调声音。

直升机门打开了，走出一个金发碧眼、脸色红润的年轻人，随后走出来的，是一个穿着绿色天鹅绒短裤和白衬衫、戴着骑士帽的年轻姑娘。

野蛮人一看到这个姑娘，吓得直往后退，脸色变得煞白。

那个姑娘站在那里，对他微笑着——不自信的、乞求的、几乎是低声下气的微笑。时间一秒秒地过去了，她的嘴唇翕动，她在说着什么，可是，她的声音被观光者们一次次的大喊遮盖住了。“我们——想看——鞭子！我们——想看——鞭子！”

姑娘将两只手紧紧地贴在自己身体的左侧，她那桃红色的、布娃娃般的明媚脸蛋上出现了极不协调的渴望和悲伤。她碧蓝的眼睛似乎变大了，更加明亮了。突然，两颗泪珠顺着她的脸颊滚落。她又说了什么听不见的话，然后，她突然动情地张开双臂，向着野蛮人走过来。

“我们——想看——鞭子！我们——想看……”

突然之间，他们看到了他们想看的。

“娼妇！”野蛮人像个疯子一样冲向她，“臭猫！”他像个疯子，要用那打结的鞭子抽打她。

她吓坏了，扭头就逃，绊了一下，摔倒在石楠丛中。“亨利！亨利！”她大喊，可是，那个红脸膛的年轻人已经逃到直升机后面，躲到安全之处了。

人群又兴奋又激动，大喊着，散开来，一窝蜂地向那个有磁力般的焦点簇拥过来。痛苦真是一种令人痴迷的恐怖。

“惩罚，好色，惩罚！(8)”迷乱之中，野蛮人再次挥起鞭子抽打起来。

人们饥渴地聚集在周围，像食槽周围的猪，乱哄哄地推搡着，拥挤着。

“哦，肉体！”野蛮人咬牙切齿。这一次，他抽打的是自己的肩膀，“杀死它！杀死它！”

人们着迷于这种痛苦的恐怖景象，又被合作的习惯以及那种寻求一致和补偿的欲望驱动（早年的条件训练已将这种欲望植根于他们的头脑，难以消除），他们开始模仿野蛮人那癫狂的举动，击打着彼此的身躯，同时，野蛮人正在鞭打他自己叛逆的肉体，或者鞭打着他脚下的石楠丛中那团蠕动着的丰满肉体，那个淫乱的化身。

“杀死它，杀死它，杀死……”野蛮人还在大喊。

突然，有人开始高唱“狂欢啊狂欢”，不一会儿，人们都唱开了，不断地重复着那个叠句，开始跳舞。狂欢啊，一圈又一圈，打着六八拍，击打着彼此。狂欢啊……

午夜过后，最后一架直升机起飞离开了。野蛮人正在石楠丛中沉睡，唆麻令他呆滞，长时间疯狂的肉欲放纵令他精疲力竭。他醒来时，太阳已经高照。他躺了片刻，像猫头鹰一样，对着阳光眨着不解的眼睛，突然，他想起来了，一切都想起来了。

“哦，我的上帝，我的上帝呀！”他用手蒙住了眼睛。

那天晚上，一群群嗡嗡叫着的直升机飞过野猪背，形成了绵延十公里的乌云。所有的报纸上都登载了对昨天晚上赎罪般的狂欢的描述。

“野蛮人！”最早到达的人们走下飞机，喊道，“野蛮人先生！”

没有回答。

灯塔的门虚掩着。他们推开门，步入百叶窗背后的昏暗。透过房间另一头的拱门，他们可以看到通往楼上的楼梯的底部。在圆拱的下方，悬挂着一双脚。

“野蛮人先生！”

那双脚，就像圆规的两条不慌不忙的腿，缓慢地，缓慢地转向右边，北，东北，东，东南，南，西南，然后停住了，悬停了几秒钟，接着又慢条斯理地转向左边，西南，南，东南，东……

————————————————————

(1) 《哈姆雷特》里哈姆雷特的叔叔、丹麦现任国王。

(2) 引自《麦克白》，麦克白在第五幕中关于人生和死亡的著名台词。

(3) 引自《哈姆雷特》，哈姆雷特装疯时的胡言乱语。

(4) 引自《李尔王》，葛罗斯特的话，他认为天神对待人类的态度就像男孩子们对待苍蝇一样轻率，可是，在下一句里，他又称天神是温柔的。

(5) 引自《一报还一报》，公爵对克劳迪奥说的话，问他为什么惧怕死亡，死亡不过是睡眠。不过是睡眠。

(6) 引自《哈姆雷特》，是哈姆雷特关于“To be or not to be”的著名独白段落中的话。

(7) 出处同上。

(8) 引自《特洛伊罗斯与克瑞西达》，特洛伊罗斯误会了克瑞西达，以为她是轻浮的女人。

译序

美国前总统约翰·肯尼迪曾经说过：“几乎没有哪个美国人比欧内斯特·海明威对美国人民的感情和态度产生的影响更大。”1961年7月2日，海明威由于肝硬化和高血压等多种疾病，给他身心造成极大的痛苦，没能再创作出很有影响力的作品。这使他精神抑郁，形成了消极悲观的情绪，于是饮弹自尽，结束了自己恢宏壮丽的一生。整个世界都为此震惊，人们纷纷为这位巨人叹息。美国人民更是悲悼这颗美国文坛巨星的陨落。他虽然走了，但给世界文坛留下了数百万字的优秀文学作品，每一部作品都字字珠玑，蕴含着深刻的思想，给人以激励和启迪。其中最广为人知的有《老人与海》《太阳照常升起》《永别了，武器》《乞力马扎罗的雪》和《没有女人的男人们》等。《老人与海》1952年出版，翌年海明威便因此书荣获普利策奖，1954年获得了诺贝尔文学奖。《没有女人的男人们》也是一部具有强大影响力、令读者痴迷的作品。日本当红作家村上春树是海明威的崇拜者，他创作了一部同名作品（《没有女人的男人们》），可能是为了表达自己对这部作品的喜爱吧。

海明威的这部短篇小说集共包含十四篇故事。第一篇《勇者不败》讲述的是斗牛士曼纽尔·加西亚的悲惨人生。他生活拮据，经常是吃了上顿没下顿，但他胸怀远大的人生理想，立志要当一名优秀的斗牛士，面对伤痛和窘迫的生活状况始终没有低头。本篇故事用很大的篇幅和细腻的笔法描述了斗牛场上惨烈的情景，其中有这样一个主人公与公牛殊死搏斗的场景：“ 一个撞震，他觉得自己被抛到了空中。趁着腾空而起的工夫，他把剑刺出去，那把剑从手里飞了出去。他重重地落在了地上，公牛就在他的上方。他躺在地上，用穿着便鞋的脚狠踹公牛的鼻子，踹了一脚又一脚。公牛用犄角顶他，但由于太兴奋，老是顶不着，于是就用头撞他，两只犄角插在沙子里。”海明威认为，对于斗牛士而言，斗牛纵使危险之极，但他们不能因为危险而退缩，这是他们世袭的职业，更是世袭的光荣，就像骑士为了荣誉而战而死一样；每一次危险而优雅的转身，每一次利剑直插牛心的快感，每一次惊险过后观众雷鸣般的掌声，或许这些就是斗牛士以生命追求的。第二篇《异国见闻》叙述的是海明威在意大利米兰疗伤时的见闻，详细描述了医院里的设备、医疗水平以及病人的情绪等，既有士兵对“勇敢”的看法，又有军官对“爱情”的迷惘。第三篇《似白象一般的山峦》其实是借题发挥，有点“王顾左右而言他”，完全谈论的是堕胎方面的话题，反映的是男女主人公对此事不同的心态。第四篇《杀手》反映的是社会上一些人对生命的淡漠，“杀手”谈笑风生，视杀人为游戏，而“被杀者”则对自己即将面临的厄运不动声色。第五篇《意大利拾趣》通过“我”在意大利的游历，讲述了法西斯统治下的人民生活如何困苦，年轻女孩不惜卖身以求生存，而法西斯军人囊中羞涩，有的出门要“搭便车”，有的则敲诈旅人挣零花钱。第六篇《五万元》描述的是拳击场上的诡谲风云，既有你死我活的搏斗，又有幕后的交易——“打黑拳”的现象屡见不鲜。第七篇《一次简单的调查》写的是一个军官对一个年轻士兵的询问，从中可以看出上级对部下颐指气使，随意拆看他们的信件，任意“践踏”他们的隐私的情况在军队里广泛存在。第八篇《十个印第安人》讲述的是一个白人男孩对一个印第安女孩的迷恋。男孩后来发现对方另有心上人，于是顿感心灰意冷。第九篇《金丝雀的故事》讲述的是“我”和妻子在前往巴黎办理分居手续的途中遇到的人和事——火车上的一个美国太太买了一只金丝雀准备送给她的爱女表示安慰（她的爱女不顾她的反对爱上了一个瑞士人，而她硬将他们拆散）。第十篇《阿尔卑斯田园曲》里，两个滑雪客来到一条山谷，听到了一些奇闻……一个农民在妻子死后，把她的尸体冻成“冰棍”放在柴火间里，夜里他到柴火间劈柴，竟将提灯挂在妻子的尸体上……第十一篇《自行车比赛》里的“比赛”只是个噱头，其实描述的是一个赛手迷惘和绝望的心理状态。第十二篇《今天是星期五》以耶稣被钉上十字架为故事背景，通过几个罗马士兵的谈论表达对此事的看法。第十三篇《平庸的故事》表达的是作者对人类生存的空间、英雄人物等问题的看法。第十四篇《睡不着的时候》讲述的是“我”睡不着觉时的遐想，有对往事的回忆，也有对现实的思索……

海明威的作品风格洗练、简洁、硬朗，独树一帜，在世界文坛引起了轰动，为广大文学家所推崇。正如英国作家赫·欧·贝茨所说，他那简约、有力的语言引起了一场文学革命，在许多欧美作家的身上留下了痕迹。海明威所信奉的是美国建筑师罗德维希的名言“越少，就越多”，使作品趋于精练，缩短了作品与读者之间的距离，他提出了“冰山原则”，只表现事物的八分之一，使作品充实、含蓄、耐人寻味。

海明威已逝世五十多年，而他的作品仍焕发着强大的生命力——海明威不死！如何翻译他的作品是摆在我们面前的一个重大课题。我们坚决反对“对号入座”式的字对字翻译，因为这样的译文完全是西语结构，甚至会出现文理不通的现象——每个字读者都是认识的，但就是不知道这些字连在一起表达的是什么意思，瞿秋白称其为“非驴非马的骡子文”。这样的译文恐怕连小学生的作文也不如，只能算作“信手涂鸦”，乍眼一看倒是做到了“移形”，却忽略了“传神”，看鼻子、眼和装束与原作并无差异，只是少了原作的精气神，像是原作的“木乃伊”，失去了原作的活力。我们建议重视和采用钱锺书的“化境”理论。所谓“化境”，不仅要求译者“移形”，还要“移意”和“移味”，也就是说应该做到“形神兼备”，让原作“投胎转世”，从“译出语”彻底融入“译入语”。其中最难的恐怕要算“移味”，也就是用译文反映作者的审美情趣、艺术风格以及人生观等重大却又微妙的因素。还有一种倾向也应该警惕，那就是“借景生情”“借题发挥”，只是一味展现自己的文采，全然不顾原作的内容，翻译出的作品只有“张三李四”的味，却缺少了海明威的味。鲁迅曾戏称这样的译文为“无源之水，无本之木”。瞿秋白当年批评这种不负责任的译者：“……是和城隍庙里演说西洋故事的，一鼻孔出气。这是自己懂得了外国文，看了些书报，就随便拿起笔来乱写几句所谓通顺的中国文。这明明是欺侮读者，信口开河地乱讲海外奇谈。”

翻译本身就很难，翻译海明威的作品更难。翻译得不好，作品中的艺术形象就没有了“英雄味”，而会变成一个个没精打采、胡言乱语的“小瘪三”——这样的情景是谁也不愿看到的。

我就是怀着这颗忐忑、警惕之心着手翻译这本《没有女人的男人们——海明威短篇小说集》的……

方华文作于苏州大学

2017.12.1

第二篇　异国见闻

秋天，战场上仍硝烟弥漫，但我们不再到那儿去了。米兰的秋天寒意袭人，天色很早就黑了。华灯初上，一边漫步于街头，一边浏览橱窗，很是惬意。野味店把许多野味挂在外面陈列。狐狸的皮毛上落满了雪花，尾巴迎风摇曳；鹿被掏空了内脏，沉甸甸、僵硬地挂在那儿；小鸟在风中一晃一晃的，羽毛被风吹得翻起。这个秋天很冷，寒风是从山里刮来的。

每天下午，我们都要到医院去。傍晚穿城而过，去医院有三条不同的路。其中的两条在运河边，只是太长，要从桥上走，跨过运河进入医院。有三座桥供你选择。其中的一座桥上有个女人在卖炒栗子。站在她的木炭炉火前，你会觉得身上暖洋洋的，炒栗子放进衣袋里热乎乎的。医院非常古老，也非常漂亮。走进一扇大门，穿过一座院落，从院落另一侧的一扇门出去。葬礼仪式通常是从这座院落开始的。这座古老医院的对面有几幢新建的康复病房，是清一色的砖房。我们每天下午在那儿相聚，见面时一团和气，关注彼此的病情，然后就坐在对我们十分要紧的器械上。

医生来到我坐的器械跟前，问我：“参战前，你最喜欢干什么？搞过什么体育运动吗？”

我说：“搞过。踢过足球。”

“很好，”他说，“你还能踢足球的，而且会踢得比以前更好。”

我的膝关节不能弯曲，由于没有了腿肚子，膝盖到脚腕都是直的。这台器械能叫我的膝关节打弯，让它能像骑自行车那样运动。可是我的膝关节就是无法弯曲，机器一到弯曲部位，就会突然倾斜。医生说：“一切都会过去的。你是个幸运的年轻人，将来还能重返足球场，像个冠军一样去踢球的。”

坐在我旁边的器械上的是个少校，一只手特别小，就跟初生婴儿的手那么大。医生过来检查他的手时，少校冲我挤挤眼，两条上下翻动的皮带不断地拍打着他夹在中间僵硬的手指。他问医生：“我的上尉医生，那么我也能重新踢球吗？”他曾经是一个优秀的击剑手，在战前的意大利可以说是最伟大的击剑手之一。

医生回到后厢房的办公室里，拿来了一张照片，上面是一只手，那只手治疗前萎缩得几乎跟少校的手一样小，治疗后则大了一些。少校用那只好手接过照片，十分仔细地看了看，然后问道：“是枪伤吗？”

“是意外工伤。”医生说。

“有意思，非常有意思。”少校说着，把照片还给了医生。

“你现在该有信心了吧？”

“没有。”少校回答。

还有三个小伙子也是每天来，跟我年龄差不多，都是米兰人，一个想当律师，一个想当画家，另一个立志要做职业军人。做完器械治疗，我们有时会一起走回去，一起到斯卡拉酒店隔壁的科沃咖啡馆去。由于四人结伴，我们敢于抄近路走共产主义者聚居区。那里的人痛恨军官，一次见我们走过，酒馆里有人高呼：“打倒军官！[17]”还有一个小伙子有时也和我们结伴，一行就成了五个人。他失去了鼻子，要做整容手术，脸上老蒙着一块黑颜色的丝手帕。他是从军校直接上的前线，刚上前线没出一个小时便挂了彩。他来自一个古老世家，鼻子很特殊，虽做了整容，但永远也无法使他的鼻子恢复原样了。他去过南美洲，在一家银行里干过。但那是很久以前的事了。谁都不知道以后会怎么样。我们仅仅知道战火一直没有熄灭，只是我们再也不用到那儿出生入死了。

除了那个脸上老蒙着一块黑颜色丝手帕的小伙子，我们几个都有军功章。他在前线待的时间太短，没来得及赢得军功章。那个脸色苍白、想当律师的高个子小伙子是“阿迪蒂”部队[18]的上尉，竟然赢得了三枚勋章，而我们每人只有一枚。他久经沙场，曾九死一生，对待人情世故有点儿淡漠。其实我们都有点儿淡漠，除了每天下午相逢于医院，没有什么能让我们相聚。不过，当我们穿过那个难缠的城区去科沃咖啡馆时，在黑暗中行走，酒馆里闪射出灯光，传来阵阵歌声，有时走上街头会碰见一些男女堵在人行道上，我们得推开他们才过得去——此时此刻，我们感到有一种共同的命运将我们紧紧连在了一起，而这是那些厌恶我们的人所无法理解的。

我们几个都很熟悉科沃咖啡馆，这儿富丽堂皇、温暖如春、灯光柔和，有的时候人声鼎沸、烟雾弥漫，桌边总有姑娘们坐着，壁架上老摆着几份带插图的杂志。来科沃咖啡馆的姑娘们都很爱国。我发现意大利最爱国的要数咖啡馆里的姑娘了——我相信，她们现在依然爱国。

起初，那几个小伙子因为我能获得军功章而对我彬彬有礼，问我建立了什么样的军功。我拿出奖状给他们看，上面净是些漂亮话，什么“手足情谊”[19]啦，“自我牺牲精神”[20]啦。将这些形容词去掉，其实只剩下了一句话——我是个美国人，所以获得了军功章。后来，虽然跟外人相比，我仍是他们的朋友，但他们对我的态度却有了变化。看了奖状上的评语，他们固然仍将我视为朋友，却不把我当作他们当中的一员了，因为我跟他们经历不同，跟他们获取军功章的途径截然两样。我负了伤，这是事实，但我们心里都有一本账，我负伤其实是一次事故造成的。不过，我从未因为自己获得勋章而感到惭愧。有时喝过鸡尾酒后还会产生幻想，觉得自己跟他们一样，是有功才受奖的。可是，当夜间回住所，寒风呼啸，街头空无一人，所有的商店都关门闭户，紧靠着有街灯的地方走时，我才明白自己是绝不敢像他们那样出生入死的，因为我非常怕死。夜间躺在床上，一想到死我就怕得要命，真不知叫我回到前线去，我会怎么样呢。

那三个荣获军功章的人就像勇猛的猎鹰。虽然在那些从未打过猎的人看来我也像一只雄鹰，其实并不然。他们三个心中有数，于是我们就疏远了。不过，那个一上前线就挂了彩的小伙子仍然和我是好友，因为他永远也不知道自己会变成什么样的人，说不定也会遭到排斥呢。我喜欢他，则是因为觉得他也许跟我一样也不是雄鹰。

曾经是叱咤风云的击剑手的少校并不相信勇敢，我们坐在器械上的时候，他抽出大量时间纠正我的语法错误。他夸奖过我的意大利语，说我的意大利语说得很流利，我们在一起聊起天来轻松自如。一天，我说我觉得意大利语简直太简单了，都无法产生浓厚的兴趣了。“哦，是这样的。”少校说，“你愿不愿意研究一下意大利语的语法呢？”于是，我们就一道研究起了意大利语的语法。我很快就觉得意大利语很棘手，每次跟他说话心里得先把语法弄明白，否则就不敢张口。

少校来医院总是很准时。尽管我敢肯定他压根就不相信这些机器的功效，但他照样来，恐怕一天也没耽误过。有一段时间，我们没有一个相信理疗器的疗效。一天，少校还说这种玩意儿都是胡折腾。这些机器当时刚问世，可能是拿我们当试验品了。这种试验很荒唐，他说：“只是个理论，像其他理论一样。”我的意大利语语法没学好，他就骂我是笨蛋，是无可救药的白痴，还说他自己傻，和我一起研究意大利语简直是自找麻烦。他是个小个子，总是在器械上坐得直直的，右手塞进机器，目光直呆呆看着墙壁，手指夹在皮带之间，由着皮带一上一下地揉搓他的手指。

“假如战争结束了，要是真的结束了，你战后打算做什么？”他问我，“说话时注意语法！”

“我打算回美国。”

“结婚了吗？”

“没有。但我希望能结婚。”

“那你就是个傻瓜。”他说道，语气似乎有点儿气冲冲的，“男人是绝对不该结婚的。”

“为什么，少校先生？”

“别叫我少校先生！”

“为什么男人绝对不该结婚？”

“不该就是不该。”他愤怒地说，“即便到了山穷水尽的地步，也不该陷入婚姻的窘境。陷入那种窘境，只会落个空。应该寻找不落空的东西才对。”

他显得极其愤怒和痛苦，说话时直视着前方。

“若说落空，此话怎讲？”

“反正到头来绝对是一场空。”少校望着墙壁，嘴里说道。随后，他低头看看机器，把他的那只小手从皮带间抽出来，用它狠狠拍了拍大腿。“反正到头来绝对是一场空。”他几乎喊了起来，“你别跟我争辩！”接着，他对那个操作机器的护理员吼道：“过来，把这臭玩意儿关掉！”

说完，他去另一个房间接受光疗和按摩了。我听见他问医生是否可以用电话，接着就关上了房门。待他返回时，我正坐在另一个机器上。只见他穿着披风，戴着帽子，径直走到了我跟前，把手搭在了我肩上。

“对不起，”他用那只完好的手拍拍我的肩头说，“我不该这么粗鲁。我的妻子刚去世。请你务必原谅我。”

“噢……”我心里为他感到难过，说道，“我很遗憾。”

他站在那儿，咬了咬下嘴唇。“真是太难了。”他说，“我都有点儿接受不了。”

他的目光越过我，飘向了窗外。接着他哭了，抽泣着说：“我接受不了，有点儿过不去这道坎了。”他潸然泪下，抬着头，目光茫然，腰板挺得直直的，不失军人之风，两颊热泪乱滚，紧咬双唇。最后，他从器械旁走过，出了房门。

医生告诉我说，少校的妻子非常年轻。他负伤从战场归来，二人才结的婚，谁知她竟患肺炎死了。她病了没几天，谁也想不到竟会一病而亡。少校连着三天没来医院。第四天，他按时来了，军服的袖子上戴着一圈黑纱。他回到医院，只见墙上挂满了照片，上面照的是各种伤病在理疗前后的对比。在少校坐的器械前挂着三幅照片，上面的手跟他的一样，但已完全康复。真不知这些照片医生是从哪儿搞来的。我一直以为我们是第一批使用这些器械的患者呢。不过，这些照片对少校没有产生多大影响，因为他不看照片，只看窗外。

第三篇　似白象一般的山峦

埃布罗河[21]河谷对面的山脉连绵不断，泛着白色。河谷的这边没有树木，没有阴凉地，火车站夹在两条铁轨之间，暴露在阳光下。紧靠车站的这头，是投下温热阴影的建筑物。那儿的酒吧敞着门，门道挂着一扇门帘挡苍蝇，门帘上的珠子是用竹子制成的。一个美国人和一个女孩坐在外边建筑物阴影里的桌子旁。天气热得要命。从巴塞罗那来的快车四十分钟内到站，在本站停两分钟，然后开往马德里。

“喝点儿什么吧？”女孩问。她已经摘下帽子放在了桌子上。“这鬼天气可真热呀。”美国男子说。

“那就喝啤酒吧。”

“来两杯啤酒！[22]”男子冲着门帘里面喊道。

“大杯的吗？”一个女人站在门口问。

“是的，两大杯。”

女人送来了两杯啤酒和两个毛毡杯垫，将杯垫和酒放在桌上，看了一眼美国男子和女孩。女孩正在眺望远处的山脉。艳阳下，山脉泛着白光，而田野却一片干涸，呈棕褐色。

“那山脉看上去就似一群白象。”女孩说。

“我从没见过白象。”男子喝了口啤酒说。

“是啊，你不会见到的。”

“也许我见过。”男子说，“光凭你一句话，说明不了什么问题。”

女孩望了望珠帘，“帘子上画了什么东西。”她说，“上面写了什么？”

“大茴香酒[23]。是一种饮品。”

“我们能尝一尝吗？”

男子冲着珠帘里面喊：“来人！”女人从酒吧里走出来。

“一共是四个雷阿尔[24]。”

“再来两杯大茴香酒。”

“加水吗？”

“你要加水吗？”

“我也不知道。”女孩说，“加了水好喝吗？”

“还可以吧。”

“两杯都要加水吗？”女人问。

“嗯，加水吧。”

“喝起来有股甘草味。”女孩说着放下酒杯。

“这儿所有的东西都有这种味道。”

“是啊，”女孩说，“样样东西都有甘草味。尤其你日思夜想的东西，比如苦艾酒。”

“罢了，这种话就不要再说了。”

“是你自己开的头，”女孩说，“刚才我还挺开心、挺享受的。”

“好吧，那咱们就试着开开心心享受吧。”

“好的。我正试着呢。我说那些山峦看上去好像白象。难道这样的话题不开心吗？”

“是挺叫人开心的。”

“我还想尝一尝这种新饮料。咱们就做了这些事，不就是——看看周围的东西，尝尝新饮料吗？”

“我想是的。”

女孩又眺望对面的山峦。

“多么美丽的大山啊！”她说，“看上去并不像白象。我刚才只是说透过树木看那些山的颜色是白的。”

“再来一杯怎么样？”

“好的。”

一阵热风把珠帘吹得蹭到了他们的桌子。

“啤酒味道真好，冰凉冰凉的。”男子说。

“是挺不错的。”女孩说。

“这种手术太简单了，吉格，”男人说，“其实算不上什么手术。”

女孩低头看了看桌子腿周围的地面。

“我知道你不会往心里去的，吉格。这只是小事一桩，只需吸点儿氧气就行了。”[25]

女孩没吱声。

“我会跟你去的，始终守在你身边。他们只是叫你吸点儿氧，这事再自然不过了。”

“那么，以后该怎么办呢？”

“以后一定会把日子过得顺风顺水的，一如以往。”

“你为何如此肯定？”

“因为咱们所苦恼的就这么一件事，正是这一件事弄得你我心情不畅。”

女孩看看珠帘，伸手抓起珠帘上的两串珠子。

“你觉得然后一定能平安无事，大家都开开心心的？”

“我知道一定会这样的，你不必担心。据我所知，许多人都做过这种手术。”

“这我也知道。”女孩说，“手术过后，男人们倒是挺开心的。”

“好吧，”男子说，“你要是不愿意做，就不做了。我绝不会强迫你干自己不愿意的事情。不过，话又说回来，这种手术的确简单极了。”

“这果真是你的意愿？”

“我觉得这是上上策。不过，假如你真的不想做，我也不愿勉强你。”

“如果我做这次手术，你就会高兴，一切都会跟以前一样，你还会爱我，对不对？”

“我现在就爱着你，这你心里清楚。”

“是的，我清楚。但如果我做了手术，一切恢复了正常，我要是说山峦像白象之类的话，你会喜欢吗？”

“会喜欢的，现在就很喜欢。只不过现在不能想那事。你知道我一旦心烦会怎么样。”

“我做手术，你就不心烦了。”

“我不为这个心烦，因为这种手术简单极了。”

“好吧，那我就做吧，因为我对自己是不在乎的。”

“你这是什么意思？”

“我是说我是不在乎自己的。”

“可是我在乎。”

“哦，是的。不过，我是不在乎我自己的。我去做就是了，那时就一好百好了。”

“假如这是你的感受，那我可不愿让你去做。”

女孩站起身，走到了车站的尽头。铁轨的另一侧可以看到埃布罗河的河岸上阡陌纵横、绿树成荫。河对岸的远处则是起伏的群山。云影在田野中穿行。她的目光透过树木瞥见了埃布罗河。

“你我原本是可以纵情享受这一切的，”她说道，“可以拥有一切美好的感受。而现在，这些一天天变得愈加不可能实现了。”

“你说什么来着？”

“我说你我原本是可以拥有一切美好感受的。”

“现在也可以呀。”

“现在不行了，一切都成了镜花水月。”

“你我可以拥有整个世界。”

“现在不行了，一切都成了镜花水月。”

“咱们可以到任何地方去，走遍天涯海角。”

“现在不行了，一切都成了镜花水月。这个世界不再是我们的了。”

“是我们的！”

“已经不是了。一旦失去，就不再拥有。”

“可是，还没有失去呀。”

“那就等着瞧吧。”

“快回来，到阴凉地来！”男子说，“你不该如此多愁善感。”

“我这不是多愁善感，”女孩说，“而是心中有数。”

“我可不想勉强你做自己不愿做的事情……”

“也不想勉强我做对我不利的事情。”女孩说，“这我清楚，再来杯啤酒怎么样？”

“好吧。你应该明白……”

“我明白。”女孩说，“这话能不能不说了？”

他们又在桌子旁坐下。女孩望着河谷对面那干涸土地上的山峦，而男子则看着她和桌面。

“你应该明白，”他说道，“如果你不想做，我是不愿意勉强你的。假如你觉得此事很重要，我十分情愿陪着你，一陪到底。”

“难道这对你不重要吗？我们是可以挺过这一关的。”

“当然重要。我心里没有别人，任何一个别的人都没有，只有你。我很清楚，这样的手术十分简单。”

“是呀，是呀，你很清楚这样的手术十分简单。”

“随你怎么说吧，反正我心里是有数的。”

“就眼下而言，你能不能为我做些事情？”

“我愿为你赴汤蹈火。”

“我一千遍一万遍地求求你不要再说了，好不好？”

他没再说什么，而是看了看靠在车站墙根的行李，上面有各家他们曾在那里度过了许多良宵的旅馆的标签。

“我是不会勉强你的，”他说道，“对此我是无所谓的。”

“我要大声喊叫了。”女孩说。

酒吧女子端着两杯酒从珠帘后走出来，把它们放在湿漉漉的毛毡杯垫上。“火车五分钟内就到。”她说。

“她说什么？”女孩问。

“火车五分钟内就到。”

女孩冲酒吧女子嫣然一笑以示谢意。

“我最好还是过去把行李拿到站台的另一边。”男子说。女孩对他笑了笑。

“好的。搬过行李你再回来，咱们把酒喝完。”

男子拎起两个沉甸甸的行李包，绕过站台，将它们放在了另一侧的铁轨旁。回来时穿过酒吧，见那儿有几位等火车的旅客在喝酒，他自己也在吧台要了杯茴香酒，边喝边打量着那几位旅客。他们都在心平气和地等待着列车的到来。喝完酒，他掀起珠帘走了出来。女孩在桌旁坐着，冲他莞尔一笑。

“现在感觉好些了吧？”他问。

“感觉很好。”女孩说，“我感觉很好，没有什么感觉不好的。”

第四篇　杀手

亨利快餐馆的房门被推开，两个男子走了进来，在柜台前坐下。

“二位吃什么？”乔治问。

“不知道。”其中的一个男子说，“你想吃什么，阿尔？”

“不知道，”阿尔说，“我也不知道自己想吃什么。”

天色渐渐黑了下来。窗外的街灯亮了。两个男子坐在柜台前看菜单。尼克·亚当斯坐在柜台的另一头仔细观察着他们。两个男子进来时，他正和乔治聊天。

“我要一份烤猪里脊，配苹果酱和土豆泥。”第一个男子说。

“这道菜还没做好呢。”

“那你为什么写在菜单上。”

“这是正餐的菜，”乔治解释道，“六点钟可以吃到。”

乔治看看柜台后挂在墙上的钟说。

“现在是五点钟。”

“指针明明指的是五点二十分。”第二个男子说。

“这钟快二十分钟。”

“哼，什么破烂钟。”第一个男子说，“那你这儿有什么可吃的？”

“各种三明治都有。”乔治说，“你可以点火腿鸡蛋、熏肉鸡蛋、猪肝熏肉或牛排。”

“给我来一份炸鸡肉饼，配青豆、奶油沙司和土豆泥。”

“这也是正餐的菜。”

“我们要吃的全都是正餐的菜，是不是？这是搞什么鬼！”

“二位可以点火腿鸡蛋、熏肉鸡蛋、猪肝……”

“我要份火腿鸡蛋。”那个叫阿尔的男子说。此人头戴礼帽，身穿黑大衣，大衣的胸口上缀着几枚扣子，一张脸又小又白，嘴唇紧绷，脖子上系着丝巾，手上戴着手套。

“给我来一份熏肉鸡蛋。”另一个男子说。他和阿尔身段差不多，长相各异，穿戴却一模一样，打扮得像一对双胞胎，大衣都紧紧绷在身上。二人坐在那儿，身体前倾，胳膊肘支在柜台上。

“有什么喝的吗？”阿尔问。

“有白啤酒、佐餐酒和姜汁汽水。”乔治说。

“我是问有什么可以‘喝’[26]的？”

“只有我刚才所说的。”

“这真是一个闹腾的城镇。”另一个男子说，“这儿叫什么来着？”

“萨米特镇[27]。”

“你听说过没有？”阿尔问他的朋友。

“没有。”他的朋友说。

“你们这儿晚上都干些什么？”阿尔问。

“吃饭呗，”他的朋友答道，“到这个餐馆来吃一顿大餐呗。”

“是这样的。”乔治说。

“你认为是这样的吗？”阿尔问乔治。

“一点儿不错。”

“你是个机灵鬼吧，对不对？”

“算得上吧。”乔治说。

“喂，你才不是机灵鬼呢。”另一个小个男子说，“他是个机灵鬼吗，阿尔？”

“他是个笨蛋。”阿尔说完，转向尼克问：“你叫什么名字？”“亚当斯。”

“又是个机灵鬼！”阿尔说，“难道他不是个机灵鬼吗，马克思？”

“这个小镇满世界都是机灵鬼。”马克思说。

乔治端来两盘菜放在柜台上，一盘火腿鸡蛋，一盘熏肉鸡蛋，然后又放下两盘作为配菜的炸土豆，关上了通向厨房的那扇小窗。

“哪一份是你的？”他问阿尔。

“你记不得了吗？”

“是火腿鸡蛋。”

“好一个机灵鬼！”马克思说。他身体前倾去拿火腿鸡蛋。两个男子吃饭时连手套也没有摘。乔治在一旁看着他们吃。

“你看什么呀？”马克思盯着乔治问。

“没看什么。”

“你这该死的。你是在看我。”

“也许这孩子跟你开玩笑呢，马克思。”阿尔说。

乔治哈哈大笑了起来。

“你用不着笑！”马克思对他说，“你根本不用笑，知道了吗？”

“好吧。”乔治说。

“他认为这样很好，”马克思对阿尔说，“他认为这样很好。多么高明的见解！”

“哦，他是个思想家嘛。”阿尔说。二人又吃了起来。

“柜台那头的那个机灵鬼叫什么名字来着？”阿尔问马克思。

“喂，机灵鬼，”马克思冲尼克说，“你和你的男朋友绕到柜台那边去。”

“什么意思？”尼克问。

“没什么意思。”

“你最好还是过去，机灵鬼。”阿尔说。尼克绕过去，走到了柜台后边。

“什么意思？”乔治问。

“你别瞎操心！”阿尔说，“谁在厨房里？”

“那个黑人。”

“你说那个黑人是什么意思？”

“就是掌勺的那个黑人。”

“叫他进来！”

“什么意思？”

“叫他进来。”

“你以为你们这是在什么地方？”

“我们非常清楚这是什么地方。”那个名字叫马克思的男子说。“难道我们看上去很蠢吗？”

“你说的话倒是挺蠢的。”阿尔对他说，“你跟这小子啰唆个啥劲。听着，”他转向乔治说，“快叫那个黑鬼出来，到这里来！”

“你们想把他怎么样？”

“不怎么样。动动你的脑筋，机灵鬼。我们会把一个黑人怎么样呢？”

乔治推开通向厨房的那扇小窗。“萨姆，”他喊道，“请你来一下！”

厨房的门开了，黑人走了过来。“什么事呀？”他问。柜台前的那两个男子打量着他。

“好啦，黑鬼，你站在那儿别动。”阿尔说。

黑人萨姆腰系着围裙站在那里，眼睛望着坐在柜台前的那两个男子。“好的，先生。”他说。阿尔离开了他的座位。

“我带这个黑鬼和这个机灵鬼到后边的厨房里去。”他吆喝道，“黑鬼，你回厨房里去！机灵鬼，你和他一起去！”尼克和厨子萨姆到厨房里去了，小个子阿尔跟在后边。厨房的门砰地关上了。马克思坐在柜台前面对着乔治，眼睛却不看对方，而是在看柜台后边的一面镜子。亨利快餐馆是从一个酒吧改建而来的。

“喂，机灵鬼，”马克思一边照镜子一边说道，“为什么不吭声呀？”

“这是在做什么呀？”

“听见了吧，阿尔，”马克思高声叫道，“机灵鬼想知道这是在做什么。”

“那你为什么不告诉他呀！”阿尔的声音从厨房飘了过来。

“你觉得这是在干什么？”

“不知道。”

“依你看呢？”

马克思说话时一直在照镜子。

“我说不上来。”

“喂，阿尔，机灵鬼声称他说不上来，不知道这是在做什么。”

“我听得见你说话，别喊了。”阿尔从厨房里说。他打开了递送碗碟的那扇窗户，用一个番茄酱瓶子撑着窗板。“你给我听着，机灵鬼！”他从厨房里对乔治说，“站得离柜台远一点儿。马克思，你向左靠一靠。”他俨然就像个摄影师在为顾客拍团体照。

“请你告诉我，机灵鬼，”马克思说，“依你看这儿会发生什么事情？”

乔治没吱声。

“我来告诉你吧，”马克思说，“我们打算干掉一个瑞典人。你认识一个叫奥利·安德森的大个子瑞典人吗？”

“认识。”

“他每天都来这儿吃晚餐，对不对？”

“有时候来。”

“他是六点钟来，对不对？”

“如果来，的确是在六点。”

“这些情况我们了如指掌，机灵鬼。”马克思说，“还是扯点儿别的吧。看过电影吗？”

“偶尔看看。”

“应该多去看看。看电影对你这样的机灵鬼大有好处。”

“你们为什么要杀奥利·安德森？他怎么得罪你们了？”

“我们连见也没见过他，他哪有机会得罪我们。”

“他见也只能见我们这一次。”阿尔在厨房里说。

“那你们为什么要杀他？”乔治问。

“是为一个朋友杀他。为朋友两肋插刀嘛，机灵鬼。”

“别信口开河了！”阿尔从厨房里说，“你他妈说得太多了。”

“哦，我这是让这机灵鬼开心开心。你说是不是，机灵鬼？”

“你他妈说得太多了。”阿尔说，“黑鬼和我的这位机灵鬼会自己寻开心的。我把他俩捆在一起，就像是修道院里的一对女朋友。”

“听这话，你肯定在修道院里待过。”

“无可奉告。”

“你肯定在哪个修道院里待过。一定如此！”

乔治抬头看了看时钟。

“如果有人来吃饭，你就说厨子出去了。假如他们不肯走，你就说你得亲自下厨，看他们走不走。听明白了吗，机灵鬼？”

“听明白了。”乔治说，“事情完了之后，你们把我们怎么办？”

“说不准，”马克思说，“这种事一时间说不好的。”

乔治抬头看了看钟表。六点过一刻。临街的门开了，一个电车司机走了进来。

“你好，乔治，”他说，“可以吃饭了吧？”

“萨姆出去了，”乔治说，“大约半个小时后回来。”

“那我就去街那头吧。”司机说。乔治看了看时钟。六点二十。

“干得好，机灵鬼。”马克思说，“你真是个规矩的小绅士。”

“他是怕我一枪崩掉他的脑袋。”阿尔在厨房里说。

“不，”马克思说，“情况并非如此。机灵鬼很机灵，表现得很不错。我喜欢他。”

到了六点五十五分的时候，乔治说：“他不会来了。”

这期间，有两个顾客来过快餐馆。一个顾客想买一份外卖，于是乔治就下厨给他做火腿鸡蛋三明治让他带走。在厨房里，他瞥见阿尔歪戴着帽子坐在小窗旁的一个凳子上，一支锯短了枪管的猎枪放在那里，枪口架在窗台上。尼克和厨子被背靠背捆在墙角，嘴里各塞了一条毛巾。乔治做好三明治，用油纸包好放入袋子，拿出来交给顾客，顾客付了钱就走了。

“机灵鬼是个百事通，”马克思说，“下厨做饭无所不能。你可以娶一个女孩做太太，训练她当贤妻良母，机灵鬼。”

“是吗？”乔治说，“你的朋友奥利·安德森今天不会来了。”

“再等他十分钟吧。”马克思说。

马克思一边照镜子，一边看大钟。大钟的时针指到了七点钟，接着便是七点五分。

“走吧，阿尔。”马克思说，“咱们还是走吧，那家伙不会来了。”

“最好再等五分钟。”阿尔在厨房里说。

就在这五分钟里又来了一个顾客。乔治说厨子生病了。

“你为什么不再找个厨子？”那人说，“这像开餐馆的吗？”顾客又走了。

“走吧，阿尔！”马克思催促道。

“这两个机灵鬼和黑鬼怎么办？”

“他们是没问题的。”

“你是这么想的？”

“当然喽。咱们到此为止。”

“我不喜欢这样，”阿尔说，“不利索。你话太多了。”

“嗬，得了吧，”马克思说，“大家总得有点儿话说，开开心心的，难道不好吗？”

“你老是说呀说的，废话太多。”阿尔说。他从厨房走了出来，由于大衣绷得太紧，别在腰间的锯短了枪管的猎枪顶得大衣鼓了个小包。他用戴着手套的手扯了扯大衣，把它扯平。

“再见，机灵鬼。”他对乔治说，“今天你运气不错。”

“此话不假，”马克思说，“你应该去赌赌赛马，机灵鬼。”

两人出了大门。乔治从窗口望着他们行走在弧光灯下，目送他们穿过马路。那两人身穿紧身大衣，头戴高帽子，像两个杂耍演员。之后，乔治推门走进厨房，为尼克和厨子松了绑。

“我可不愿让这样的事情再次发生，”厨子萨姆连声说，“我可不愿让这样的事情再次发生！”

尼克站起来。以前从来没有人往他的嘴里塞过毛巾。

“你说，”他说，“这到底是怎么回事呀？”他正在设法把毛巾甩掉。

“他们想干掉奥利·安德森，”乔治说，“打算趁他来吃饭时枪杀他。”

“奥利·安德森？”

“是的。”

厨子用拇指摸了摸嘴角。

“他们都走啦？”他问。

“是的，”乔治说，“都滚蛋了。”

“我不喜欢这样，”厨子说，“打心眼里不喜欢！”

“听着，”乔治对尼克说，“你最好去见见奥利·安德森。”

“好吧。”

“你们可不要掺和进去，”厨子萨姆说，“不要引火烧身。”

“你要是不愿去就别去了。”乔治说。

“掺和进去只会招来灾祸，”厨子说，“最好离得远远的。”

“我愿意去见奥利·安德森，”尼克对乔治说，“他住在哪里？”

厨子转身走了。

“不听老人言，吃亏在眼前。”他说。

“他住在赫希出租屋。”乔治对尼克说。

“我这就去。”

出了门，但见弧光灯的灯光透过光秃秃的树枝洒落在地面上。尼克在与电车轨道并行的那条大街上走，在下一盏弧光灯那儿拐上了一条小街道。小街道旁边的三幢房屋就是赫希出租屋。他走上两级台阶，按响了门铃。一个女人朝门口走来。

“奥利·安德森在这里住吗？”

“你要见他吗？”

“嗯，如果他在屋里的话。”

尼克跟在女人身后上了一段楼梯，朝后走到了甬道的尽头。女人敲了敲门。

“谁呀？”

“有个人想见你，安德森先生。”女人说。

“我叫尼克·亚当斯。”

“进来吧。”

尼克推门走进了房间。奥利·安德森和衣躺在床上。他曾经是重量级拳击手，个子太高，那张床都容不下他。他头枕两个摞在一起的枕头，对尼克看也不看。

“有何贵干？”他问。

“我是亨利快餐馆的。”尼克说，“两个家伙闯进快餐馆，把我和厨子捆起来，说是要杀你。”

他这话像天方夜谭。奥利·安德森听了什么也没说。

“他们把我们关在厨房里，”尼克继续说，“准备等你来吃饭时枪杀你。”

奥利·安德森眼睛望着墙壁，仍一声不吭。

“乔治觉得还是让我来告诉你一声好。”

“我也无可奈何。”奥利·安德森说。

“我可以告诉你他们长什么样子。”

“他们长什么样子我并不想知道。”奥利·安德森说，眼睛仍望着墙壁，“谢谢你过来告诉我。”

“没什么。”

尼克打量着躺在床上的那个大块头。

“要不要我去报警？”

“不用了，”奥利·安德森说，“报了也没用。”

“有没有什么需要我帮忙的？”

“没有。没有什么忙可帮的。”

“也许他们只不过是想吓唬吓唬你。”

“不。这不仅仅是吓唬。”

奥利·安德森转过身去面对着墙。

“只是，”他冲着墙壁说道，“我不知道该不该走出这个房间。我已经在这里躺了一天了。”

“难道你就不能远走高飞？”

“不能。”奥利·安德森说，“我已经受够了东躲西藏。”

他仍望着墙壁。

“现在我已无力回天了。”

“难道你就不能想个办法把问题解决掉？”

“不能。怪都怪我把事情搞砸了。”他仍用那种麻木的声音说道，“现在已无力回天了。过会儿，我要下决心出去走走。”

“我得回去看看乔治了。”尼克说。

“再见，”奥利·安德森说，看也没看尼克，“谢谢你跑来通知我。”

尼克走了，关门时最后看了奥利·安德森一眼，只见他和衣躺在床上，眼睛呆呆地望着墙壁。

“他在屋子里憋了一天了，”楼下的女管家说，“我想可能是不舒服吧。我对他说：‘安德森先生，这样的日子秋高气爽，你应该出去走走。’可是他不愿意出门。”

“他不想出去。”

“他不舒服，让我也觉得难过。”女管家说，“他是个大好人。要知道，他过去是个拳击手呢。”

“这我知道。”

“你不看他的脸，是看不出来的。”[28]女管家说，他们正站在临街的大门内，“他待人一团和气。”

“是呀。再见，赫希太太。”尼克说。

“我不是赫希太太，”女管家说，“她是房主。我只是替她照管。我是贝尔太太。”

“哦，再见，贝尔太太。”尼克说。

“再见。”女管家说。

尼克走上黑暗的街道，到了街拐角的弧光灯下拐弯，沿着电车轨道回亨利快餐馆。乔治正站在餐馆的柜台后。

“见到奥利了吧？”

“见到了。”尼克说，“他待在房间里，不愿出来。”

厨子听见尼克的声音，从厨房里面推开了门。

“这种事我连听都不想听。”他又把门关上了。

“你把情况告诉他了吗？”乔治问。

“当然告诉了。其实，他对所有的情况都很了解。”

“他打算采取什么措施？”

“什么措施也不采取。”

“他们可是要杀他呀。”

“我猜他们会的。”

“他一定是在芝加哥陷进了祸水里。”

“我想是这样的。”尼克说。

“这种事非常棘手。”

“的确非常棘手。”尼克说。

二人一时没再说什么。乔治伸手从柜台下拿出块抹布，用它擦柜台。

“不知道他究竟干了些什么？”尼克说。

“欺骗了什么人，才惹来了杀身之祸。”

“我要走了，远离这座城镇。”尼克说。

“嗯，”乔治说，“这样也好。”

“他明明知道有人要杀他，却还待在房间里等着人家上门。想想真叫人受不了！简直太可怕了！”

“唉，”乔治说，“这件事最好就不要再想了。”

第五篇　意大利拾趣[29]

隘口的路坚硬、平坦，清晨车辆少，尘土尚未扬起。脚下是连绵起伏的丘陵，上面满是橡树和栗树，远方则是大海。另一侧是白雪皑皑的巍峨大山。

我们离开隘口，穿过一片林区下山。路边堆着一袋一袋的木炭，透过树木看得见烧炭人的小屋。这天是星期天。路面起起伏伏，但我们离高处的隘口越来越远，一路向下行驶，穿过一片片的矮树丛和一座座村庄。

每座村庄的外围都有成片的葡萄园，葡萄藤又粗又密，使大地成了棕褐色。村子里，住房是白颜色的，街上有几个男人穿着体面的衣服在玩滚木球。有的人家种着些梨树，枝丫叉开，紧挨着白颜色的墙壁。梨树喷了杀虫剂，把白墙也弄脏了，留下了金属般的青绿色污痕。村子四周被小片小片的田地所环绕，种的有葡萄，也有各种树木。

在距离斯培西亚[30]二十公里的山上有一座村庄。进了村子，广场上聚集着一群人，一个年轻人拎着手提箱走到我们的车前请求搭车，让我们带他到斯培西亚去。

“车上只有两个位子，都有人坐。”我说。我们开的是一辆旧式的福特牌小轿车。

“我站在车门外就是了。”

“那样会很不舒服的。”

“舒服不舒服无所谓。我必须到斯培西亚去。”

“让他搭车吗？”我问盖伊。

“看来他非搭不可了。”盖伊说。年轻人把一个小包塞进了车窗。

“照看下这个。”他说。过来两个男子，把他的手提箱摞在车后我们的行李箱之上，用绳子捆牢。年轻人跟大家一一握手，对众人说他身为法西斯党员，又经常出门，这样乘车并没有什么不舒服的。说完，他踩到汽车左侧的踏板上，把右胳膊伸进开着的车窗，钩牢车身。

“可以开车啦！”他说。那群人向他挥手告别，他也频频挥动那只空着的手。

“他说什么来着？”盖伊问我。

“他说可以开车啦。”

“他站好了吗？”盖伊说。

我们沿着河岸迤逦前行。河对面是巍巍群山。太阳晒干了草叶上的白霜。天气晴朗而寒冷，阵阵寒风从敞开的窗户刮进了车里。

“你觉得他站在车外是什么滋味？”盖伊抬头望着前边的路面。我们的那个乘客挡住了他那一侧窗外的视线。那位年轻人站在车外，歪着身子，活像一尊船头雕像。他竖起衣领，压低帽檐，鼻子在寒风中看上去冻得不行。

“也许他快受不了了。”盖伊说，“他站的那侧的轮胎不好使。”

“哦，汽车一爆胎，他就会走掉的。”我说，“他肯定不愿帮着修车而弄脏他的那身出门的衣服。”

“我倒不介意他搭便车，”盖伊说，“只是怕他在转弯处斜着身子会有危险。”

过了林区，我们离开河岸开始爬坡。汽车的水箱开了锅。年轻人望着水箱里的蒸汽和带着一股锈味的水，神色气恼和疑虑。盖伊两脚发力，把油门踩到底，引擎嘎吱嘎吱直响，汽车往高处爬啊爬，退回来再往前爬，最后终于到了平路上。引擎不再嘎吱嘎吱响了，可是嘎吱声一停，却听见了水箱咕嘟咕嘟的声音，水箱里的水沸腾着，冒着气泡。这时我们正在斯培西亚和大海上方最后那段路的至高处。汽车开始下山，一路都是急转弯。转弯的时候，我们的这位乘客就吊在车上，几次都差点儿没把头重脚轻的汽车弄翻。

“你不好说他，”我对盖伊说，“他这是出于一种自我保护意识。”

“了不起的意大利式的自我保护意识。”

“最了不起的意大利式的自我保护意识。”

我们沿着盘山路蜿蜒下行，车轮碾在厚厚的尘土上，车后扬起的灰尘落在橄榄树上。山脚下就是斯培西亚，沿着海岸而建。到了城外，道路变得平坦了。我们的乘客把头探进车窗。

“我想要下车。”

“停车！”我对盖伊说。

汽车减速，停到了路边。年轻人下了车，走到车后解下自己的手提箱。

“我在这儿下车，是怕你们因为私自搭载乘客而遇到麻烦。”他说，“请把我的包递给我。”

我把包递给了他。他把手伸进衣袋去掏钱。

“需要给你们多少钱？”

“一分钱也不要。”

“为什么不要？”

“我不知道。”我说。

“那就谢谢喽。”年轻人说。他并没有说“谢谢你们”“非常感谢你们”或者“万分感谢你们”。过去在意大利，谁只要递给你一张时刻表，或者为你指指路，你都会这样说，可是这个年轻人仅用了最简单的“谢谢”。盖伊把车开走时，他还用狐疑的目光望着我们的背影。我冲他挥手告别，而他架子大得连理也不理。之后，我们继续驱车向着斯培西亚进发。

“那个年轻人在意大利还要走很长的路。”我对盖伊说。“哦，”盖伊说，“他搭乘咱们的车，走了有二十公里。”

斯培西亚就餐记

一开进斯培西亚，我们就找地方吃饭。这儿街道宽敞，房屋很高，漆成黄颜色。顺着电车车轨，我们把汽车开到了市中心。屋墙上随处可见墨索里尼鼓着一双金鱼眼的画像，手写的vivas[31]中两个V的墨汁顺着墙壁直流。那儿有几条偏街通往港口。天气晴朗，由于是星期天，人们纷纷走上了街头。铺石的路面上洒了水，尘土中仍有片片湿痕。我们紧靠街边行车，避开了电车。

“找个餐馆简单吃点儿吧。”盖伊说。

我们把车停在了两家餐馆的招牌对面，隔着街道站了会儿，我掏钱买了份报纸。那两家餐馆挨着。一家餐馆的门口站着个女子直冲着我们笑，于是我们就穿过马路进了那家餐馆。

里面黑黢黢的，房间的深处有三个女孩和一个老太婆守着一张桌子坐着。正对着我们有个水手坐在饭桌前，既没有吃饭也没有喝酒。再往后，有个身穿蓝西装的年轻人正伏在桌子上写字，头发油光锃亮，衣冠楚楚，仪表堂堂。

日光从门道和窗户照进来，窗户那儿有个陈列柜，柜子里陈列有蔬菜、水果、牛排和猪排。一个女孩走上前请我们点菜。另有一个女孩站到了门口，我们留意到她外边穿了件衣服，里面却什么也没有穿。正当我们看菜单的时候，请我们点菜的那个女孩伸出粉臂勾住了盖伊的脖子。一共有三个女孩，她们轮流出去在门口站着。坐在屋子深处的老太婆冲她们说了句什么，她们就都回到老太婆身边坐下了。

大堂里只有通向厨房的一扇门，门上挂着个帘子。那个请我们点菜的女孩从厨房端过来一些通心粉放在桌子上，还拎来了一瓶红酒，然后坐在了桌旁。

“瞧，”我对盖伊说，“你本来是想找地方简单吃点儿的。”

“这顿饭并不简单，而是很复杂。”

“你们在说什么呀？”女孩问，“你们是德国人吧？”

“是南德人。”我说，“南德人温柔体贴，很讨人喜欢哟。”

“我听不懂你说的话。”女孩说。

“这地方怎么回事？”盖伊问，“非得让她用胳膊搂我的脖子吗？”

“当然喽。”我说，“墨索里尼取缔了妓院，并没有取缔这样的餐馆嘛。”

女孩穿着件连衣裙，身体前倾靠在桌上，两手捂住酥胸，笑吟吟的。她笑的时候，一边脸比较好看，另一边不太好看，于是她便把好看的那一边冲着我们。与此同时，不知什么使她的那一侧鼻翼如同温热的蜡被用刀抹平了一样光滑，这使得她这半边脸魅力倍增。不过，她的鼻子看上去毕竟不像是温热的蜡，显得冰冷、坚毅，只是稍微显得光滑一些罢了。“你喜欢我吗？”她问盖伊。

“他喜欢极了。”我说，“遗憾的是他不会说意大利语。”

“那我就说德语喽。”[32]她用手捋着盖伊的头发说。

“你就用你的母语跟这个女孩说吧，盖伊。”我说。

“你是从哪里来的？”女孩问。

“波茨坦[33]。”

“你们打算在这里待一阵子吧？”

“你是指在斯培西亚这块风水宝地？”我问。

“你告诉她，就说咱们必须走，”盖伊对我说，“就说咱们身上有病，口袋里没钱。”

“我的朋友不喜欢女人，”我说，“他是个老派德国人，不喜欢女人。”

“你告诉他，就说我爱他。”女孩说。

我把女孩的话翻译给了盖伊听。

“你能不能闭上你的嘴，咱们离开这里？”盖伊说。

女孩的另一条胳膊也搂住了他的脖子。“告诉他，就说他属于我。”只听她说。我把这话翻译了过去。

“你能不能让我们赶快离开这里？”盖伊说。

“你们在拌嘴，”女孩说，“看来你们之间并不友好。”

“我们是德国人，”我不无自豪地说，“我们是老派的南德人。”

“你跟他说，他是个漂亮的男孩子。”女孩说。盖伊都三十八岁了，想不到在这里竟被当成了法国流动推销员那样的潇洒人物受到女性青睐，这叫他不由产生了几分自豪感。“你是个漂亮的男孩子。”我对他说。

“这是谁的话，”盖伊问，“你的还是她的？”

“这是她说的，我只不过充当你们的翻译罢了。这趟旅行，这不就是你想让我担任的角色吗？”

“很高兴这是她的话。”盖伊说，“我可不想在这里跟你各奔东西。”

“我不知道。斯培西亚是块风水宝地呀。”

“斯培西亚？”女孩说，“你在说斯培西亚？”

“风水宝地呀。”我对她说。

“这儿是我的家乡，”她说，“斯培西亚是我的故乡，而意大利是我的祖国。”

“她说意大利是她的祖国。”

“告诉她，意大利一看就像是她的祖国。”盖伊说。

“你们有什么甜点？”我问。

“有水果。”女孩说，“我们这里有香蕉。”

“香蕉很好，”盖伊说，“香蕉有皮。”

“哦，他喜欢吃香蕉！”女孩说着，又搂紧了盖伊。

“她说什么？”盖伊把脸扭开，问道。

“你喜欢吃香蕉，这叫她很高兴。”

“告诉她，我不喜欢吃香蕉。”

“这位先生不喜欢吃香蕉。”

“哦，”女孩顿时像霜打的茄子一样蔫了下来，说道，“原来他不喜欢吃呀。”

“告诉她，我每天早晨洗冷水澡。”盖伊说。

“这位先生每天早晨洗冷水澡。”

“这叫人不可理解。”女孩说。

这期间，我们对面坐的那个水手动也不动，活像个摆设。餐馆里的人谁也没去注意他。

“我们要结账了。”我说道。

“别急，你们还是留下来吧。”

“听我说，”那个伏在桌上写字的仪表堂堂的年轻男子说道，“让他们走吧。不值得在他俩身上花时间。”

女孩拉住我的手。“难道你们就不肯留下？你就不能叫他留下来吗？”

“我们必须走了。”我说，“我们要到比萨[34]去，如果可能的话，还要连夜赶到佛罗伦萨[35]去。到了晚上，我们要在那些城市里娱乐放松一下。现在是白天，趁着天亮我们还要赶路呢。”

“哪怕再待一会儿也好嘛。”

“趁白天赶路要紧。”

“听我说，”那个仪表堂堂的年轻男子说，“别跟他俩啰唆了。我不是说了不值得在他俩身上花时间吗。我心里是有数的。”

“请把我们的账单拿来吧！”我说。女孩去老太婆那儿拿来了账单，然后又回到桌边坐下。另一个女孩从厨房里出来，穿过大堂，站在了门口。

“别跟他俩费口舌了，”仪表堂堂的年轻男子厌烦地说，“你们来吃饭吧。不值得在他们身上花时间。”

我们付了饭钱，站起了身。那几个女孩和那个老太婆，以及那个仪表堂堂的年轻男子坐下来吃饭。那个摆设一般的水手两手抱头坐着，我们进餐的时候没人跟他说过一句话。老太婆把应该找的零钱交给那个女孩，她把钱送过来后又回到了他们的餐桌旁。我们在桌子上留了些小费，走出了餐馆。当我们上了车准备动身时，那个女孩来到了门口。汽车启动了，我向她挥手告别。她没有挥手，只是呆呆地站在那儿目送我们。

雨后

车开到热那亚[36]的郊区时，天降大雨。尽管我们跟在电车和卡车后面把车开得很慢，但还是把泥水溅到了人行道上，行人见我们过来就急忙躲进门里去了。热那亚市郊工业区的圣皮埃尔竞技场那儿路宽，是个双车道，我们就驾车在马路中间行驶，避免把泥水溅到下班回家的人身上。马路的左边就是地中海，辽阔的大海波涛汹涌，海风将浪花都吹到了我们的车身上。我们进入意大利时，国境线那儿有条河，河道很宽，河床干涸，满是鹅卵石。那条河到了这里，河水满得都快漫上岸了，很混浊。混浊的河水流进大海，使海水都变了颜色。海水冲上岸，化为碎小的浪花时，才变淡变清。光线透进混浊的水里，一阵风吹来，就会有发黄的海水和细浪冲到马路上。

一辆大型轿车疾驰而过，把许多泥水溅在了我们的挡风玻璃和引擎盖上。自动挡风玻璃刷子来回摆动，把那泥水抹得满玻璃都是。我们停了车在塞斯特里餐馆吃饭。餐馆里没有暖气，我们吃饭时没摘帽子，也没脱外套。透过窗户可以看见外边我们的汽车，见车身上溅满了泥浆，旁边有几艘被拖上岸以避风浪的小船。在餐馆里，你还可以看见你自己呼出的热气。

意大利通心粉味道很好。葡萄酒里有一股白矾味，我们往里掺了些水。吃过面，侍者端来了牛排和炸土豆。远处那头坐着一男一女。男的已入中年，女的年轻，穿一身黑衣。吃饭时，女的老是对着又潮又冷的空气呼热气，男的见了直摇头。二人吃东西时一言不发，男的伸手在桌下拉着女孩的手。她长得很好看，二人满面愁容，旁边放着他们的旅行包。

我们随身带着报纸，于是我就把有关上海战况的报道念给盖伊听。饭后，他留下来向侍者询问一个餐馆里根本没有的地方。我用一块抹布把挡风玻璃、车灯以及车牌擦干净。盖伊回来后，我们把车倒出车位，起程上路了。刚才侍者领他穿过马路，走进一幢旧房子。那里的人起了疑心，于是侍者就和他一道留下，让那儿的人看看，并没有什么东西被偷。

“我也不知道是怎么回事，也许因为我不是管道工吧，他们就怀疑我偷东西。”盖伊说。

出了城，我们到了一个海岬，那儿的风大，差点儿没把我们的车刮翻。

“幸亏这风是从海上往陆地上吹的。”盖伊说。

“哦，”我说，“雪莱[37]就是在这里附近什么地方遇到大风才船毁人亡的。”

“他出事的地点在维亚雷焦那边。”盖伊说，“你还记得咱们来这个地区的初衷吗？”

“记得，”我说，“可是咱们并没有如愿。”

“今晚就要开出这块地方了。”

“但愿能平平安安开过文蒂米利亚[38]。”

“看情况吧。在海边行车时，我不喜欢走夜路。”这时中午刚过，太阳出来了。下面，海水一片湛蓝，白白的浪潮翻滚着涌向萨沃纳[39]。后面，在岬角那儿，混浊的河水和湛蓝的海水交汇在一起。前面，有一艘远洋货轮正向岸边驶来。

“你还能看见热那亚吗？”盖伊问。

“还能，还看得见。”

“一过前边的大岬角就看不见了。”

“我们还能看见它好一会儿，现在连它后边的波托菲诺海角都还看得见。”

最后，终于看不见热那亚了。当热那亚从视野中消失时，回首望去，只能看得见茫茫的大海，看得见海湾里和海岸线边停泊的渔船，看得见山腰上的一个小镇以及远处几个傍海矗立的海岬。

“现在看不见了。”我对盖伊说。“哦，早就看不见了。”

“等我们找到出路离开了才能肯定。”

前边有一个路标，上面有S形弯道的标志以及“弯道危险”[40]的提示。绕过海岬，海风从挡风玻璃的裂口直向车里灌。海岬下面则是一片狭长的平地，紧靠着海边。海风把这儿的泥浆吹干，车轮碾过时扬起一股尘云。在平坦的公路上行驶时我们同一个骑自行车的法西斯分子擦身而过。那家伙身挎一支带枪套的沉甸甸的左轮手枪，骑车时霸住路中央，我们只好走外道躲他。我们从旁边驶过时，他抬头看了我们一眼。前方有个铁路闸口，我们往那儿开时闸口的栏杆却放下了。

我们等着放行，那个法西斯分子骑车赶了过来。火车过去后，盖伊发动了汽车。

“等一等，”那家伙从后边喊了一声，“你们的车牌脏了。”

我拿着抹布下了车。吃午饭时刚擦过车牌。

“可以看得清呀。”我说。

“你这么认为？”

“看啊。”

“车牌是脏的。反正我看不清。”

我用抹布擦了擦。

“现在怎么样？”

“罚款二十五里拉。”

“什么？”我说，“明明可以看得清呀。只是路况不好，才脏了一点儿罢了。”

“你不喜欢意大利的道路？”

“这儿的路的确很脏。”

“那就罚五十里拉。”他朝地上啐了一口说，“你们的车脏，你们的人也脏。”

“好吧。给我张收据，签上你的名字。”

他掏出收据本，一式两份，中间打着眼的那种，一份给被罚款人，一份填写后留作存根。被罚款人的收据上写有什么，存根上却不留底。

“给我五十里拉。”

他用消不掉笔迹的铅笔填写了收据，撕下来交给我。我看了看。

“这是二十五里拉的收据。”

“写错了。”他说完把二十五里拉改写成了五十里拉。

“另一份也应该一样。你留的存根上也应该写五十里拉。”

他堆起一脸意大利式的迷人的微笑，在存根上写了些什么，遮遮掩掩地拿在手里，让我看不清楚。

“快走吧，”他说，“趁你的号牌没有再次弄脏。”

天黑后我们又赶了两个小时的路，当晚在蒙托内[41]住宿。旅馆的环境非常惬意、干净、舒适，叫人心情舒畅。随后，我们去了文蒂米利亚，再从那儿驱车前往比萨和佛罗伦萨，经罗马涅[42]到里米尼[43]，拐回头相继经过弗利[44]、伊莫拉[45]、博洛尼亚[46]、帕尔马[47]、皮亚琴察[48]和热那亚，又返回到文蒂米利亚。这趟旅行，全程只用了十天。这么短的时间，我们自然无缘了解各地的风土人情以及百姓的生活状况。

第六篇　五万元

“你的情况怎么样，杰克？”我问他。

“你见过这个沃尔科特没有？”他问。

“只是在健身房见过。”

“是吗？”杰克说，“跟这家伙过招，我得碰上好运气才行。”

“他打不过你的，杰克。”士兵说。

“真希望如此。”

“他打的那套鸟拳是无法击倒你的。”

“鸟拳不鸟拳关系倒是不大，”杰克说，“他的拳路我是不会在意的。”

“打败他好像并不难。”我说。

“这一点是肯定的，”杰克说，“他撑不了多久。他不会跟你我一样能坚持太长时间的，杰瑞。不过，就目前而言，他能打的牌还很多。”

“你用左拳都能把他揍个半死。”

“也许吧。”杰克说，“当然，我有机会试试。”

“你可以打他个落花流水，就像你痛打小屁孩刘易斯那样。”

“小屁孩刘易斯，”杰克说，“那个犹太佬算不上什么！”

我们三个，杰克·布伦南、士兵巴特利特和我正在汉德利酒馆喝酒。旁边的桌子旁坐着两个妓女，也在喝酒。

“你说这话是什么意思，犹太佬？”其中一个妓女说，“你说这话是什么意思，犹太佬，你这个大块头爱尔兰佬？”

“没错，”杰克说，“说得对。”

“犹太佬！”那妓女仍在不依不饶地说着，“这几个大个子爱尔兰佬张口闭口就说犹太佬。你说这话是什么意思，犹太佬？”

“走吧，咱们离开这里。”

“犹太佬！”那妓女连珠炮似的说个不停，“谁见过你给别人买过一杯酒？每天上午来，你老婆都把你的钱袋子扎得紧紧的。这些爱尔兰佬动辄便说别人是犹太佬！特德·刘易斯都能把你揍得屁滚尿流！”

“当然，”杰克说，“你是不是把你那东西也白白送给别人了？”

我们走出了酒馆。杰克就是这样的人，口无遮拦，不分场合，想说什么就说什么。

目前，他来到泽西，在丹尼·霍根的健身中心进行训练。这儿的条件很好，但他还是不怎么喜欢。远离老婆孩子，他变得脾气暴躁，动不动就发无名之火。他喜欢我，我们俩相处得很好。他也喜欢霍根。至于士兵巴特利特，没过多久便叫他有点儿受不了了。如果营地里某个喜欢开玩笑的人讲的笑话有点儿惹人厌，他就会变得叫人害怕。士兵老拿杰克开玩笑，时时刻刻拿他开涮。他开的玩笑并不十分幽默，也不讨人喜欢，这就触痛了杰克的神经。反正就是这类玩笑。杰克有时会停止举重和打沙袋，戴上拳击手套。

“想过几招吗？”他会对士兵说。

“没问题。怎么个过法？”士兵会问，“是不是想让我像跟沃尔科特那样对你毫不留情，把你打翻在地？”

“是这样的。”杰克会说，其实心里并不喜欢对方开玩笑的话。

一天上午，我们几个到公路上活动，跑了很远的路，然后往回拐。一路上，我们快跑三分钟，再慢走一分钟，接着又快跑三分钟。杰克可不是那种你可以称之为短跑爱好者的人。在拳击场上，如果有必要，他可以跑得快如闪电，但在公路上跑得就不快了。我们一路走，士兵一路开他的玩笑。我们开始爬通往健身场营房的小山。

“喂，”杰克说，“你最好还是回到城里去吧，士兵。”

“你这是什么意思？”

“你最好回到城里，就待在那儿吧。”

“怎么啦？”

“一听你说话我就心烦。”

“是吗？”士兵说。

“是的。”杰克说。

“等沃尔科特打败你，你会更加心烦的。”

“是的，”杰克说，“也许会是这样的。但我知道叫我心烦的是你！”

于是，当天上午士兵就乘火车回城了。我送他上车时，见他窝了一肚子的火。

“我只不过跟他开了个玩笑，”我们在月台上等车的时候他说，“他不该翻脸不认人，杰瑞。”

“他精神紧张，脾气有点儿暴躁。”我说，“他是个好人，士兵。”

“狗屁好人！这算什么狗屁好人！”

“嗯，”我说，“再见啦，士兵！”

火车进站了。他拎着包登上了车。

“再见，杰瑞，”他说，“大赛前你回城里吗？”

“恐怕回不去。”

“那到时候再见吧。”

他说完进了车厢。列车员跳上车。火车开走了。我搭乘一辆运货马车回到了健身中心。杰克正在游廊上给妻子写信。送邮件的已经来过，我拿着送来的报纸到游廊的另一头，找地方坐下看了起来。霍根出了房门，走到我跟前。

“杰克是不是和士兵闹翻了？”

“没闹翻，”我说，“他只是叫士兵回城里待着。”

“我早就知道会出现这种情况。”霍根说，“他一直都不太喜欢士兵。”

“是呀。许多人他都不喜欢。”

“他对人十分冷淡。”霍根说。

“这个嘛，他对我一向很好。”

“对我也很好。”霍根说，“我对他没什么成见，只是觉得他待人比较冷淡。”

霍根拉开纱门进屋去了。我坐在游廊上继续看报。此时正值初秋，健身中心位于泽西的山间，风光旖旎。我看完报，就坐在那儿远眺乡间景色，眺望山下树林旁边车来车往的公路，一有车经过，就会扬起一片尘云。天气晴好，景色迷人！霍根又来到了门口，我说：“喂，霍根，这地方有没有什么猎物可打的？”

“没有，”霍根说，“这地方只有麻雀。”

“看报了吗？”我问他。

“有什么新闻？”

“桑德昨天赢了三场。”

“昨晚我从电话里听说了。”

“你在密切地跟踪他们的情况，霍根？”我问。

“哦，我跟他们保持着联系。”霍根说。

“杰克怎么样？”我问，“他还在玩那些东西吗？”

“他？”霍根说，“你能看到他在干这个吗？”

就在这时杰克从拐弯处走了过来，手里拿着写好的信，上穿毛衣，下穿一条旧裤子，足蹬拳击鞋。

“有邮票吗，霍根？”他问道。

“把信给我，”霍根说，“我替你寄。”

“喂，杰克，”我说，“你以前是不是常去赌赛马？”

“当然喽。”

“这我是知道的，我以前常在西普海德赛马场见到你来着。”

“那你为什么不赌了？”霍根问。

“因为老输钱呗。”

杰克来到游廊上，在我身边坐了下来，背靠着柱子，冲着阳光闭上了眼睛。

“需要拿把椅子来吗？”霍根问。

“不了，”杰克说，“这样挺好。”

“天不错，”我说，“乡间景色迷人呀。”

“我倒情愿回城里和妻子待在一起。”

“在这儿只不过再待一个星期嘛。”

“是的，”杰克说，“是这么回事。”

我们俩继续坐在游廊上，而霍根到办公室里去了。

“你觉得我的状态怎么样？”杰克问我。

“现在还难说。”我说，“你还有一个星期可以恢复恢复。”

“说话别拐弯抹角。”

“好吧，”我说，“你状态不佳。”

“我老是睡不着觉。”杰克说。

“过两天就会好的。”

“好不了，”杰克说，“我得了失眠症。”

“你有什么心事？”

“想老婆。”

“把她接来就是了。”

“不行，我年岁大了，应付不来。”

“咱们先徒步走一段长路，然后你再折回来，这样你会感觉不错，又很累。”

“累！”杰克说，“我一直都感到很累。”

他一整个星期都是这种状态，晚上睡不着觉，早晨起来便带着那种感觉，你知道，就是拳头握都握不起来那种感觉。

“他毫无生气，就像救济院里的糕饼，”霍根说，“根本上不了场了。”

“我没见过沃尔科特的拳路。”我说。

“沃尔科特会打死他的，”霍根说，“会把他撕成两半的。”

“但是，”我说，“任何人都会有状态不佳的时候。”

“再不佳也不会像他那样，”霍根说，“让人觉得他从没有经过训练似的，使得健身中心也跟着丢人现眼。”

“你听到过记者是怎么评价他的吗？”

“当然听到过！他们说他状态极差，绝对不该叫他打比赛。”

“哦，”我说道，“他们的话往往是不靠谱的，对不对？”

“那倒也是，”霍根说，“但这次他们说得有理。”

“他们怎么知道一个拳击手的状态好不好？”

“当然，”霍根说，“他们一点儿都不傻。”

“当年在托莱多[49]举行大赛，他们就对威拉德[50]横挑鼻子竖挑眼。那个拉德纳[51]现在可聪明啦，你可以问问他当年在托莱多是怎么挑剔威拉德的。”

“噢，拉德纳没有报道那次比赛，”霍根说，“他只报道大型比赛。”

“我才不管报道人是何人呢。”我说，“他们到底懂什么？也许可以耍耍笔杆子，但恐怕狗屁都不懂！”

“你难道不觉得杰克状态很差吗？”霍根问。

“差是差，正处于低谷。他需要的无非就是让科比特来挑他的刺，让他无路可退赢一回。”

“哦，科比特会刺激他的。”霍根说。

“当然，科比特会那么做的。”

那天夜里杰克又失眠了。次日便是大赛前的最后一天了。早饭后，我们又来到了游廊上。

“你睡不着觉的时候，心里都想些什么，杰克？”我问。

“唉，我在担心，”杰克说，“担心我在布朗克斯的产业，也担心佛罗里达的产业。担心完孩子，又担心老婆。有时也想打比赛的事。一想到那个犹太佬特德·刘易斯，就觉得窝火。再者，我有些股票，这也叫我担心。真是愁了这个又愁那个！”

“嗯，”我说，“明天晚上一切都会过去的。”

“那是自然的，”杰克说，“这个总是管用，是不是？事情一过，所有的问题便迎刃而解了。这是肯定的。”

那一整天，他怒气冲冲，什么也没干，只是四处转悠想让自己放松下来。他练了几趟空拳，就连空拳似乎也打不好。后来他跳了一会儿绳，可是汗都没有出。

“他这样子最好什么也别干了。”霍根说。我们站着看他跳绳。“跳绳怎么连汗也跳不出来？”

“他是出不了汗。”

“你看他是不是有症结？在体重方面他从没出过问题，对不对？”

“他没有症结，他就是心里是空的，什么都没有。”

“他应该出点儿汗才对。”

杰克跳着绳到了我们跟前，在我们面前一上一下、一前一后地跳，每跳三下交叉一次胳膊。

“喂，”他说道，“你们俩鬼鬼祟祟在说什么？”

“我看你就不要再练了，”霍根说，“越练越糟。”

“那岂不是完蛋啦？”杰克敷衍了一句便跳着绳躲开了，把绳子甩得噼啪响。

那天下午，约翰·柯林斯来到了健身中心。当时，杰克在楼上他自己的寝室里。约翰是坐汽车从城里赶来的，还带来了两个朋友。车一停，他们就全都下了车。

“杰克呢？”约翰问我。

“在他的房间里躺着呢。”

“躺着？”

“是的。”我说。

“他怎么啦？”

我看了看和他一起来的那两个人。

“他们是杰克的朋友。”约翰说。

“他的状态十分糟糕。”我说。

“怎么回事？”

“他睡不着觉。”

“见鬼，”约翰说，“那个爱尔兰小子一向觉不好。”

“他有点儿不对劲。”我说。

“见鬼，”约翰说，“他从来就没对劲过。我和他交往十年了，他还从没对劲过。”

跟他一起来的那两个人听了哈哈大笑。

“请允许我介绍一下。这两位是摩根先生和斯坦菲尔特先生。”约翰说，“这位是负责训练杰克的道尔先生。”

“很高兴见到二位。”我说道。

“咱们一道去看看那个伙计吧。”那个叫摩根的人说。

“走，去看看他。”斯坦菲尔特说。

我们一起上了楼。

“霍根在哪里？”约翰问。

“他在健身房陪两个顾客。”我说。

“现在来这里的人多不多？”约翰问。

“只有两个。”

“这里倒是挺安静的，是不是？”摩根说。

“是的，是很安静。”我说。

我们来到杰克寝室的门外。约翰敲了敲门，可是无人应答。

“他也许睡着了。”我说。

“大白天睡什么觉呀？”

约翰一扭门柄，我们进了房间。杰克正脸朝下趴在枕头上呼呼大睡，两条胳膊搂着枕头。

“喂，杰克！”约翰冲着他叫了一声。

杰克那趴在枕头上的脑袋动了动。“杰克！”约翰俯下身又叫了一声。杰克把脸在枕头上埋得更深了些。约翰用手碰了碰他的肩膀。杰克坐起来看了看我们。他没刮脸，穿着件旧毛衣。

“上帝呀！为什么你就不能让我睡一会儿呢？”他对约翰说。

“别生气呀，”约翰说，“我又不是有意非得把你叫醒。”

“哦，算啦，”杰克说，“你当然不是有意的。”

“摩根和斯坦菲尔特你是认识的。”约翰说。

“很高兴见到二位。”杰克说。

“你感觉如何，杰克？”摩根问。

“很好。”杰克说，“我能感觉怎样呢？”

“你看上去气色不错。”斯坦菲尔特说。

“是呀，是不错。”杰克说。随后，他冲着约翰说道：“你是我的经理，分成拿的钱不少。记者纠缠不休的时候，你为什么不出来见他们？难道你想让我和杰瑞面对他们吗？”

“当时我陪刘在费城打比赛。”约翰说。

“那关我屁事！”杰克说，“你是我的经理，分钱分得不少，对不对？你到费城该不是为我赚钱吧？我需要你的时候，你为什么不在我的身边？”

“霍根在这儿嘛。”

“霍根？”杰克说，“霍根和我一样是个哑巴。”

“士兵巴特利特是不是在这里陪练过一阵子？”斯坦菲尔特问道，意在转换话题。

“是的，他在这里待过。”杰克说，“他是在这里待过一阵子。”

“喂，杰瑞，”约翰对我说，“你能不能去找一下霍根，就说我们想在大约半个小时后见见他？”

“当然可以。”我说。

“为什么不能叫他待在这里呢？”杰克说，“待在这里，杰瑞。”

摩根和斯坦菲尔特面面相觑。

“安静点儿，杰克。”约翰对他说道。

“我还是去找霍根吧。”我说。

“好吧，你愿去你就去吧，”杰克说，“不过，这里没一个人想打发你走。”

“我愿去找霍根。”我说。

霍根在健身中心的健身房里，正在和两个戴着拳击手套的顾客切磋技艺。那两人都不愿出手打对方，生怕对方反击扑上来打自己。

“好啦，就这样啦。”霍根见我进来，便对那两人说道，“你俩可以停止厮杀了，去冲个澡，让布鲁斯给你们按摩按摩。”

那两人跨出绳圈。霍根走到了我跟前。

“约翰·柯林斯带着两个朋友来看杰克了。”我说。

“他们从汽车里出来时我看见了。”

“跟约翰一起来的那两人是何方神圣？”

“他们就是所谓的聪明人。”霍根说，“你不认识他俩？”

“不认识。”我说。

“他们一个叫哈皮·斯坦菲尔特，一个叫刘·摩根，合开了一个赌场。”

“我很长时间都没到赌场去过了。”

“当然。”霍根说，“那个哈皮·斯坦菲尔特是个大骗子。”

“我有所耳闻。”我说。

“他是个非常圆滑的家伙。”霍根说，“他们俩沆瀣一气，是一对奸商。”

“哦，”我说，“他们想在半小时后跟咱们见面。”

“你是说他们要在半个小时后才愿意见咱们？”

“是的。”

“咱们先到办公室坐坐去。”霍根说，“让那些奸商见鬼去吧。”

大约半个小时后，我和霍根上楼敲响了杰克寝室的门。他们正在里面说话。

“请先等一等！”房间里有个人说。

“搞什么鬼名堂！”霍根说，“啥时候你们要见我，我在办公室恭候！”

我们听见里面有开锁的声音。接着，斯坦菲尔特把房门打开了。

“请进，霍根，”他说，“咱们干上一杯。”

“好，”霍根说，“那就干上一杯吧。”

我们进了屋。杰克坐在床上。约翰和摩根各坐了一把椅子。斯坦菲尔特站着。

“你们几个可真够神秘的。”霍根说。

“你好，戴尼！”约翰说。

“你好，戴尼！”摩根说着和他握了手。

杰克一言不发，默默地坐在床上，似乎很不合群，显得非常孤独。他穿着旧的蓝色运动衣裤和拳击鞋，脸也没有刮。斯坦菲尔特和摩根都衣冠楚楚，约翰也衣帽光鲜。杰克坐在那里就像个粗俗的爱尔兰乡巴佬。

斯坦菲尔特拿出一瓶酒来，摩根取过几个杯子。每人喝了酒。我和杰克只喝了一杯，其他人则各喝了两三杯。

“最好留下一点儿回去的路上喝。”霍根说。

“别担心。酒还多着呢。”摩根说。

杰克喝了一杯就再不喝了。他站起来，眼睛望着那几个人。摩根一屁股坐在了床上，就坐在杰克刚才坐过的地方。

“再来一杯，杰克！”约翰一边说，一边把酒杯和酒瓶递给他。

“不了，”杰克说，“我历来都不喜欢去喝下葬酒[52]。”

大家都笑了。杰克却没有笑。

几位客人离开时都感觉不错。他们上车时，杰克站在游廊那儿目送他们。他们冲他挥了挥手。

“再见！”杰克说。

晚饭时，除了“把这个递给我”或“把那个递给我”之类的话，杰克别的什么也不说。健身中心的那两个顾客也跟我们同桌吃饭。他们俩都是相当不错的人。饭后，我们去了游廊。天色早早就黑了。

“想出去走走吗，杰瑞？”杰克问。

“当然。”我说。

我们穿上外套出了门。到大路上得走很长一段路。到了那儿，我们沿着大路走了大约有一英里半。路上车来车往，我们只好躲到路边让车过去。杰克一句话也不说。后来，一辆大轿车开过来，害得我们踏进矮树丛里躲它。杰克这才说：“这是散的他妈什么步呀！还是回霍根的健身中心去吧！”我们选了条小路，爬过山丘，穿过田野，返回霍根住的地方。可以看见位于小山顶上的那幢房屋的灯光。我们走到房屋前，只见霍根正站在门道口。

“散步散得还开心吧？”霍根问。

“挺好的。”杰克说，“喂，霍根，有酒喝吗？”

“当然有。”霍根说，“怎么啦？”

“麻烦你把酒送到我的寝室来，”杰克说，“今晚我要好好睡一觉。”

“你倒成了医生啦。”霍根说。

“到我房间坐坐，杰瑞。”杰克对我说。

上了楼，杰克坐到床上，两手抱头。

“这算过的什么日子！”

霍根送来了一夸脱白酒和两个酒杯。

“还想来点儿姜汁饮料吗？”

“你觉得我想要吗？想喝得反胃吗？”

“我只是随便问问。”霍根说。

“来一杯？”杰克说。

“不了，谢谢。”霍根说完就出去了。

“你怎么样，杰瑞？”

“我陪你喝一杯。”我说。

杰克倒了两杯酒。“现在，”他说，“我要慢慢喝，轻轻松松地喝。”

“还是加点儿水吧。”我说。

“好的，”杰克说，“我想加点儿水更好一些。”

我们默默地喝完了这两杯酒，什么也没说。杰克又要给我斟酒。

“不用了，”我说，“我已经喝够了。”

“那好吧。”杰克说。他给自己又倒了一大口，并加了水，情绪也有所好转。

“今天下午这儿来了一伙衣着光鲜的家伙，”他说，“他们一点儿风险都不愿意冒，那两个家伙。”

过了一小会儿他又说：“其实他们是对的。冒风险对他们有什么好处？”

“你真的不想再来一杯吗，杰瑞？”他说，“来吧，就算陪我喝。”

“我不想喝了，杰克。”我说，“我现在感觉不错。”

“只喝一杯。”杰克说。酒劲已经让他变柔和了。

“那我就舍命陪君子喽。”我说。

杰克为我倒了一杯，又为他自己倒了一大杯。

“你知道，”他说，“我嗜酒如命。要不是打拳击，一定会喝很多酒的。”

“当然。”我说。

“你知道，”他说，“为了打拳击，我失去了很多东西。”

“可你赚钱赚得盆满钵满。”

“这当然喽，我图的就是这个。可你知道我也失去了很多东西，杰瑞。”

“此话怎讲？”

“譬如，”他说，“老是离开家门，不能跟老婆在一起，对女儿也没有任何好处。‘你爸爸是谁？’在社交场合不少小伙子会问她们。她们只好说：‘我爸爸是杰克·布伦南。’这对她们没有任何好处。”

“得啦，”我说，“她们手里要是没有钱那可就不同了。”

“这个嘛，”杰克说，“钱我倒是为她们挣了不少。”

他又为自己倒了杯酒。酒瓶已经快空了。

“往酒里加点儿水。”我说。杰克倒了点儿水进去。

“你知道，”他说，“你都想象不出我是多么想我老婆。”

“当然喽。”

“你根本无法想象，想象不出这是一种什么滋味。”

“在乡下应该比在城里舒服些呀。”

“对我而言，”杰克说，“在哪里都无所谓。离开老婆的滋味你是体会不来的。”

“再来一杯吧。”

“我喝醉了吗？是不是说什么糊涂话了？”

“你没喝醉，很正常。”

“你没法想象那是一种什么滋味。没人想象得出那是什么滋味。”

“除了你老婆。”我说。

“不错，”杰克说，“她的确是知道的。她知道，她绝对知道。”

“再加点儿水吧。”我说。

“杰瑞呀，”杰克说，“你无法想象这是一种什么滋味。”

他状态不错，已喝得大醉，痴呆呆地望着我，目光迷离。

“你会睡个好觉的。”我说。

“喂，杰瑞，”杰克说，“你想弄点儿钱花花吗？可以在沃尔科特身上弄点儿钱。”

“是吗？”

“听着，杰瑞，”杰克放下酒杯说，“我没有喝醉，明白吗？知道我在他身上押了多少赌注吗？五万元！”

“这可不是一笔小数目。”

“整整五万元！”杰克说，“二一添作五，我可以拿到手两万五。你也可以在他身上押些赌注，杰瑞。”

“听上去不错嘛。”我说。

“我怎么能叫他输呢？”杰克说，“这算不上玩阴谋诡计。我怎么能叫他输呢？有钱为什么不赚？”

“再加点儿水吧。”我说。

“赛完这一场我就洗手不干了。”杰克说，“这一场之后，我的拳击生涯彻底结束。这次我必须吃败仗。放着钱为什么不搂它一把？”

“当然啦。”

“一星期来，我睡也睡不着，”杰克说，“彻夜躺在那里发愁，不知怎样才能如愿以偿。我睡也睡不着呀，杰瑞。你都想象不来睡不着觉的滋味是多么难受。”

“当然啦。”

“睡不着觉，这就是症结所在！再怎么也睡不着！这些年对自己的身体千注意万注意，睡不着觉岂不是白搭？”

“是挺糟糕的。”

“你都想象不来睡不着觉的滋味是多么难受，杰瑞。”

“再加点儿水吧。”我说。

大约折腾到十一点钟，杰克终于撑不住了。我扶他上床。他老是睡不着觉，最后还是撑不住了。我帮他脱掉衣服，让他躺到被窝里。

“你会睡个好觉的。”我说。

“当然，”杰克说，“我现在可以睡着了。”

“晚安，杰克。”我说。

“晚安，杰瑞，”杰克说，“你是我唯一的朋友。”

“别说啦！”我说。

“你是我唯一的朋友，”杰克说，“是我唯一的朋友。”

“睡觉吧！”我说。

“我会睡的。”杰克说。

我下楼时，霍根在办公室里，正坐在桌前看报。他抬起头。“喂，你的男朋友睡着了吧？”他问。

“他醉得一塌糊涂。”

“这总比睡不着觉强。”霍根说。

“当然啦。”

“至于那些新闻记者，你得花许多口舌跟他们解释情况了。”霍根说。

“哦，我也得睡觉了。”我说。

“晚安。”霍根说。

次日清晨，我八点钟左右下楼吃了早餐。霍根和他的顾客去健身房练习了。我走过去，看着他们。

“一！二！三！四！”霍根在为顾客计数。“你好，杰瑞！杰克起来了吗？”

“没有，还睡着呢。”

我回到自己的房间，收拾行装准备进城。九点半左右，我听见了隔壁杰克起床的声音，接着便听见他下了楼，就跟了下去。他坐在早餐桌旁，霍根也在那里，站在桌子跟前。

“感觉怎么样，杰克？”我问他。

“还不赖。”

“睡得好吗？”霍根问。

“睡得还好。”杰克说，“昨晚喝酒喝得舌头有点儿不听使唤，但大脑还是清醒的。”

“这就好，”霍根说，“那是好酒。”

“记在我的账上吧。”杰克说。

“打算什么时候进城？”霍根问。

“午饭前吧，”杰克说，“赶十一点的那趟车。”

“你请坐，杰瑞。”杰克对我说。霍根走了出去。

我在桌旁坐下。杰克在吃葡萄柚，吃到核便吐在勺子里，然后倒在盘子上。

“昨晚我恐怕醉得不轻。”他开始说话。

“你喝了点儿白酒。”

“恐怕说了不少胡话。”

“没那么糟。”

“当时霍根在哪里？”他问。这时他已经把葡萄柚吃完了。

“他在前边的办公室里。”

“关于比赛下注的事情，我都说了些什么？”杰克一边问，一边拿勺子随意拨弄着葡萄柚的皮。

女仆端来一盘火腿和鸡蛋，把葡萄柚皮收走。

“再给我来杯牛奶。”杰克对女仆说。后者走出了房间。

“你说你在沃尔科特身上下了五万元的赌注。”我说。

“此话不假。”杰克说。

“这笔钱可不是个小数目。”

“对这件事我感觉不是很好。”杰克说。

“天有不测风云呀。”

“没什么，”杰克说，“他想当冠军想得要命。他们会跟他谈妥的。”

“谁都不知道会出什么事。”

“不会出事的。他想当冠军，这对他而言值很多钱。”

“五万元可不是笔小数目。”我说。

“这是在做交易，”杰克说，“我反正是赢不了的。你知道我无论如何都赢不了。”

“你只要进去那里，就有赢的机会。”

“赢不了，”杰克说，“我已经完蛋了。这是笔交易。”

“你现在感觉怎样？”

“感觉很好。”杰克说，“我所需要的就是睡这么一大觉。”

“你也许会有精彩的表现。”

“我会展现一场精彩的表演。”杰克说。

早饭后，他一头钻进电话亭里给妻子打长途电话。

“自从来到这里，他这是第一次给老婆打电话。”霍根说。

“他每天都给她写信呢。”

“当然啦，”霍根说，“一封信才花两分钱。”

之后，霍根和我们道别。黑人按摩师布鲁斯驾驶货车送我们去车站。

“再见，布伦南先生，”到车站时，布鲁斯说道，“衷心希望你把他打得落花流水。”

“再见。”杰克说完，给了布鲁斯两块钱，因为布鲁斯为他干了不少活儿。后者手里拿着那两块钱，显得很失望。杰克看到我在望着布鲁斯手里的两块钱。

“所有的收费都上了账单。”他说，“霍根已经向我收过按摩费了。”

在开往城里的火车上，杰克默默无语地坐在座位的角落里，车票插在帽圈里，眼睛望着窗外。后来，他把脸扭过来跟我说话。

“我告诉我老婆，说我今晚在谢尔比旅馆订了个房间。”他说，“那儿离公园不远，拐个弯就到。明天早晨我可以回家一趟。”

“这想法不错。”我说，“你老婆看过你比赛吗，杰克？”

“没有，”杰克说，“她从不看我打比赛。”

我觉得他选择赛前回家，而不是在赛后，一定是想着自己会被揍得很惨。到了城里，我们乘出租车去了谢尔比旅馆。一个杂役走出来接过我们的包。我们去前台办理手续。

“房租要多少？”杰克问。

“我们只有双人房。”服务员说，“可以给你一个舒适的双人房，只收十块钱。”

“太贵了。”

“那就给你一个七块钱的双人房。”

“有浴室吗？”

“当然有。”

“你跟我一道住在这里算啦，杰瑞。”杰克说。

“噢，”我说，“我还是到我内弟家住吧。”

“我可没有特意为你花钱的意思。”杰克说，“我只是想让我的钱花得不冤枉。”

“请登记一下好吗？”服务员看了看登记簿说，“238号房间，布伦南先生。”

我们乘电梯上了楼。这是一个非常宽敞的房间，有两张床，有扇门通向浴室。

“这儿挺不错的。”杰克说。

引我们上楼的杂役拉开窗帘，再将我们的旅行包拎进来。杰克没有任何表示，于是我就给了杂役两角五分钱的小费。我们各洗了一把脸，杰克建议出去找个地方吃饭。

我们到吉米·汉德利餐馆吃午餐。那儿有很多吃客。我们的饭差不多吃到一半的时候，约翰进来了，在我们旁边坐下。杰克话说得不多。

“你的体重怎么样，杰克？”约翰问。杰克正吃着可口的午餐。

“就是穿着衣服也不会超重的。”杰克说。他从不为减不减体重而发愁。他天生就是次中量级拳击手的料，从不超重。在霍根那儿，他的体重还有所下降。

“这一点，你可是从不用发愁哟。”约翰说。

“就这一点。”杰克说。

饭后，我们到公园去称体重。根据比赛规则，两个选手的体重在下午三点时不得超过一百四十七磅。杰克腰间围了条毛巾站到了磅秤上。秤杆动也没动。沃尔科特刚称过，还站在那里，四周围了一圈人。

“咱们来看看你的体重，杰克。”沃尔科特的经纪人弗里德曼说。

“没问题。称完我，再称他。”杰克朝沃尔科特那儿努努嘴说。

“请把毛巾取下来。”弗里德曼说。

“重量是多少？”杰克问那个管磅秤的人。

“一百四十三磅。”那个管磅秤的胖子说。

“你的体重下降了，杰克。”弗里德曼说。

“该称他了。”杰克说。

沃尔科特走了过来。他一头金发，膀大腰圆，看上去像重量级选手。他的腿很短，杰克差不多比他高半个头。

“你好，杰克。”他打了个招呼。他的脸上有许多疤痕。

“你好。”杰克说，“感觉怎么样？”

“感觉很好。”沃尔科特说着，从腰间取下毛巾，站到了磅秤上。他的肩膀和脊背之宽，你怕是见都没有见过。

“一百四十六磅十二盎司。”

沃尔科特下了磅秤，冲杰克咧嘴笑了笑。

“嗯，”约翰对他说，“杰克比你轻了大约有四磅。”

“我刚来时，还不止这个数呢，伙计。”沃尔科特说，“失陪，我要去吃饭了。”

我们回去，杰克穿上了衣服。“沃尔科特看上去身体挺棒的。”杰克对我说道。

“他好像吃过不少败仗。”

“哦，是呀，”杰克说，“打败他并不难。”

“你准备到哪儿去？”杰克穿戴停当后，约翰问道。

“回旅馆，”杰克说，“你什么都要操心吗？”

“是的，”约翰说，“事事都要操心。”

“我回去躺一会儿。”杰克说。

“我七点十五左右去找你们，咱们一起去吃饭。”

“好吧。”

回到旅馆，杰克脱下鞋和外套，躺在了床上。我则写信，中间回头看了他几次，发现他并没有睡着，只是静静地躺着，每过一会儿眼睛就睁一睁。最后，他索性坐了起来。

“想玩会儿纸牌吗，杰瑞？”他问。

“当然可以。”我说。

他走到行李箱那儿，取出纸牌和记分板。我们玩了起来，结果他赢了我三块钱。玩着玩着，约翰敲门走了进来。

“想玩纸牌吗，约翰？”杰克问他。

约翰把帽子放在了桌子上。他的帽子湿漉漉的，外套也湿透了。

“下雨啦？”杰克问。

“在下暴雨。”约翰说，“雨大，堵车，我坐的那辆出租车动不了了。我下了车，是一路走来的。”

“来，玩会儿纸牌吧。”杰克说。

“你该去吃东西了。”

“不，”杰克说，“我现在还不想吃。”

于是，他们俩就玩起了纸牌，玩了大约有半个小时。杰克赢了他一块五毛钱。

“好吧，我看咱们该去吃饭了。”杰克说。他说完走到窗前朝外看了看。

“还在下雨吗？”

“是的。”

“那就在旅馆里吃吧。”约翰说。

“好吧。”杰克说，“你我再玩一把，看谁买单。”

一小会儿后，杰克站起身，说：“这顿饭你买单，约翰。”我们下了楼，在旅馆宽敞的餐厅里吃了一顿。

吃完饭我们就上了楼，杰克又跟约翰玩起纸牌来。杰克又赢了约翰两块五毛钱，心里乐开了花。约翰随身带来了一个提包，他的东西全装在里面。杰克脱下衬衫和假领子，换上运动衫和毛衣，免得出去着凉，把拳击服和一件浴衣放在一个提包里。

“准备好了吗？”约翰问他，“我打电话给前台，让他们叫辆出租车。”

前台很快就回了电话，说出租车已在门外等了。

我们乘电梯下楼，穿过门厅出去上了出租车，拐个弯向公园驶去。雨下得很大，但街面上人很多。公园的门票已经售罄。进了公园，在向更衣室走的路上，但见人头攒动，到处都是人。通向拳击场的那段路很长，似乎有半英里。四周一片漆黑，只有拳击场上方悬着大灯。

“下这场雨反而成了好事，这样他们就没有把这场比赛安排在棒球场。”约翰说。

“来观战的人可真不少哟。”杰克说。

“这场比赛吸引来的人公园都承受不了了。”

“谁都说不准老天爷什么时候下雨。”杰克说。

过了一会儿，约翰带着两个帮手来到更衣室的门前，把脑袋探进屋里张望。杰克穿着浴衣坐在更衣室里，两条胳膊交叉，眼睛盯着地面。那两个帮手从约翰的肩头也在往屋里望。杰克抬头看着。

“他来了吗？”他问。

“刚到不久。”约翰说。

我们向场内走去。沃尔科特正在入场，观众欢声雷动。他钻过绳圈，登上拳击台，两个拳头合在一起，微微含笑，晃动拳头先是向一侧的观众致意，接着是另一侧，然后坐了下来。杰克从人群中走过时，受到了人们的夹道欢迎。他是爱尔兰人，而爱尔兰人总是很受人们的拥戴。在纽约，爱尔兰人虽然不像犹太人或意大利人那般吸引人的眼球，但一直都深得人心。杰克登上台，低头去钻绳圈。沃尔科特跑过来，把下面的绳子压低让他钻过。观众很喜欢这一举动。沃尔科特把手搭在杰克的肩上，他们在那儿站了有一秒钟。

“看来你要当走红的冠军了。”杰克对他说，“把你那讨厌的手从我的肩上拿开！”

“你自然一些就是了。”沃尔科特说。

观众觉得他们俩深明大义，开打前表现得很有绅士风度，竟然互祝对方交上好运！

杰克在用绷带包扎手的时候，索利·弗里德曼来到了我们的这个角落，而约翰去了沃尔科特的那个角落。杰克把大拇指从绷带的缝隙伸出来，将手包得既结实又平展，我用胶带在他的手腕和指关节上缠了两圈。

“喂，”弗里德曼说，“胶带是从哪儿弄来的？”

“你摸摸好啦，”杰克说，“是软的，对不对？别大惊小怪的！”

杰克包扎另一只手时，弗里德曼一直站在跟前。杰克的一个助手把手套拿了过来，我给杰克戴上，系紧绳子。

“喂，弗里德曼，”杰克说，“沃尔科特是哪国人？”

“不清楚，”索利说，“好像是丹麦人吧。”

“他是波西米亚人。”那个送手套过来的助手说。

裁判员叫选手到台子中央去。杰克走了过去。沃尔科特过来时面带微笑。二人走到了一起。裁判员把两条胳膊搭在他们各自的肩上。

“喂，你会出尽风头的！”杰克对沃尔科特说。

“你自然一些就是了。”

“你为什么起‘沃尔科特’这个名字？”杰克说，“你不知道这是黑人的名字吗？”

“听着！”裁判说，接着便重复了一遍拳击场上的老规矩。中间，沃尔科特还打断了他一次，抓住杰克的胳膊说：“假如他用手这样抓住我，我能用拳头揍他吗？”

“把你的手拿开，”杰克说，“这又不是拍电影。”

他们回到各自的角落里。我拿掉披在杰克身上的浴衣。他趴在绳子上活动了几下膝关节，把鞋底在防打滑的松香里蹭了蹭。一声锣响，他猛地转回身，走出了角落。沃尔科特迎了上来。二人的手套碰了碰。沃尔科特刚把手放下，杰克就以迅雷不及掩耳之势给他的脸上来了两记左勾拳。他的拳法是无与伦比的。沃尔科特紧追过来，向前冲时下巴始终抵在胸口上。他惯于打勾拳，所以总是把手放得很低。他的战术是打近战，贴近了打。可是每次到了跟前，他的脸上就会挨一记杰克的左勾拳，杰克的左手好像是个自动运行装置。杰克老是用左勾拳，一次次打在沃尔科特的脸上。有三四次，杰克用右拳发难，沃尔科特一躲，那拳头就会落在沃尔科特的肩上或头上。后者跟所有的勾拳手别无两样，最怕的是和自己同一类型的拳手。凡是要害部位，他都防护有方，并不在乎脸上挨左勾拳。

四个回合之后，杰克打得他血肉模糊，一张脸被打得处处是伤。不过，他一旦靠近杰克，就会出重拳，打得杰克肋骨下左右两侧出现了两大块红肿。每次他一接近，杰克就缠紧他，腾出一只手从上面揍他。可是他只要摆脱纠缠，双拳就会重重地落在杰克的身上，声音之大恐怕外边街上的行人都能听得见。他可是一个拳头很重的人！

就这样，他们又打了三个回合，谁都不说话，只是埋头混战。中间休息的时候，我们就围着杰克忙碌。他看上去状态不好，但在场上从不过度主动。他从不过度移动，而左手拳简直就是自动装置，似乎跟沃尔科特的脸是连在一起的，每次杰克想打中便能打中。一旦二人贴在一起，杰克总是很冷静，从不浪费精力。他对近战非常熟悉，会使出许多招式。一次，他们俩厮打到了我们的角落，我看见他缠住沃尔科特，然后腾出右手，向上一挥，让拳击手套的后部砸在了沃尔科特的鼻子上，砸得对方的鼻子鲜血迸溅。沃尔科特把鼻子靠在他的肩上，想回敬他一拳。而他猛地把肩膀朝上一抬，撞在了沃尔科特的鼻子上，接着挥起右拳，又是重重一击。

沃尔科特怒不可遏。此时二人已打了五个回合，他对杰克恨之入骨。杰克却不惊不怒。他历来临危不惊，此刻也同样淡定。凡是跟他交过手的拳击手对他的打法都恨之入骨。小屁孩刘易斯是个例外，没有被他打乱阵脚，于是他倒对小屁孩恨恨不已。小屁孩刘易斯有三四个阴招很新鲜，是他无法做到的。在比赛场上，杰克只要身体不出问题，历来都稳如泰山，此时当然在狠狠地对付沃尔科特。有趣的是，他看上去就像是一个地地道道的传统拳击手，这是因为他对传统的打法同样全都了然于胸。

第七回合之后，杰克说：“我的左手有点儿发沉了。”

随之，他便开始被动挨打了。起初，这种颓势表现得还不太明显。但掌握主动权的不再是他，而是由沃尔科特控制局面了。这一来，他不再稳如泰山，而是麻烦不断。此时，他已不再能用左手化解对方的招数了。表面看局面没变，但沃尔科特的拳头不再落空，而是一拳拳击打在他身上，打得他惨不忍睹。

“现在是第几回合啦？”杰克问。

“第十一回合。”

“我撑不住了。”杰克说，“我的腿不行了。”

沃尔科特狠狠地揍他，揍了很长时间，就像是一个垒球手击球，发出砰砰的声音。此后，沃尔科特步步为营，稳扎稳打，宛若一台精通拳击的机器。杰克只有招架之功，哪有还手之力，真不知挨了多少狠拳。中间休息时，我给他揉腿，稍微一碰，他腿上的肌肉就发抖。他的状态糟得不能再糟了。

“你觉得局势怎么样？”他扭过头问约翰，整张脸都肿了。

“他掌控了局面。”

“我恐怕撑不住了。”杰克说，“但我不甘心败在这个波西米亚人手下。”

情况的发展果然不出他所料。他情知自己已无法击败沃尔科特，他已经没那么壮实了。不过，他不会有事。他的钱也不会有问题，现在他只想按自己的心愿打完这场比赛。他不认输，绝不想失败！

锣声响了。我们把他推了出去。他慢慢地走上场。沃尔科特扑了上来。杰克左拳一挥砸在了他的脸上，沃尔科特挨了一拳，却趁势逼近猛揍杰克的身体。杰克企图缠住他，可那无异于怀抱一个电锯，于是急忙向后一闪，避开了右拳。沃尔科特一个左勾拳，将他打翻在地。杰克倒了下去，两手和膝盖撑住身子，望了我们一眼。裁判开始数数。杰克眼睛盯着我们，摇了摇头。裁判数到八的时候，约翰冲他打了个手势。观众席上人声鼎沸，说话的声音杰克是听不见的。杰克倏地站了起来。裁判一边报数一边用胳膊将沃尔科特挡住。

杰克站稳后，沃尔科特逼了过来。

“当心点儿，吉米！”我听见索利·弗里德曼冲他喊了一声。

沃尔科特走到杰克跟前逼视着他。杰克挥左拳打来，而沃尔科特只是摇了摇头，逼得杰克背靠在绳子上，打量着他。随后一个左勾拳轻轻落在杰克脑袋的一侧，再拼尽全力挥起右拳，尽量把拳头压低，猛击杰克的下部。拳头一定是落在了腰带以下五英寸的地方。这一拳打得杰克眼珠子恐怕都快掉出来了，只见他眼珠外凸，嘴巴大张。

裁判一把拉住了沃尔科特。杰克走上前去。如果他此时倒下，那五万元就泡汤了。他脚步踉跄，仿佛五脏六腑都快要掉出来了。“那一拳打得不算低，”[53]他说，“只不过是个意外。”

观众大喊大叫，什么都听不见。

“我没事。”杰克站在我们面前说。裁判看看约翰，摇了摇头。

“来呀，你这个波兰杂种！”杰克对沃尔科特说。

约翰趴在绳子上，手里拿着毛巾，准备把它扔进去。杰克就站在离绳索不远的地方。他跨前一步，我看得见他脸上在冒汗，而那汗珠就像是从皮肤里挤出来的一样，其中有一滴很大的汗珠顺着他的鼻梁朝下淌。

“来打呀！”杰克对沃尔科特说。

裁判看看约翰，摆手让沃尔科特上去。

“过去吧，你这个傻小子。”他说。

沃尔科特走上前去，不知怎样出手才好。他没想到杰克竟然能挺过来，踌躇间脸上挨了一拳。观众的叫喊声山呼海啸，似开了锅一般。两个拳击手就在我们面前较量。沃尔科特把两记重拳砸在了杰克身上，杰克的脸都变了形，是我所见过的最惨的一张脸——简直惨不忍睹！他在努力坚持着，不让自己倒下去，这些情形都流露在了脸上。他自始至终都在默默下决心，硬挺着伤痕累累的身体。

后来，他开始绝地反击，脸上一副恶狠狠的表情，两手出拳时压得很低，直取沃尔科特的下三路。沃尔科特遮挡时，他又向对方的头部发起猛攻。接着，他一个左勾拳击中了沃尔科特的腹股沟，又一记右拳砸在了对方腰带以下的那个部位，也就是对方刚才击中他的地方。那位置比腰带低多了。沃尔科特倒了下去，疼得在地上直打滚，两手乱抓，身子扭来扭去。

裁判拽住了杰克，把他推到了他的角落里。约翰跳进了绳圈。观众又喊又叫。裁判跟评判员商量了一下，接着就见报分员拿着扩音器跳到了拳击台上宣布：“沃尔科特因对手犯规而获胜！”

裁判在和约翰交谈时解释说：“我有什么办法呢？杰克不愿意接受被犯规打败，可他毕竟糊里糊涂犯了规。”

“再怎么他也是输了。”约翰说。

杰克坐在椅子上。我为他摘掉手套，见他用双手捂住下部，硬是在坚持着，捂了一会儿脸色就不那么难看了。

“你过去说声对不起，”约翰附在他耳边说，“这样会好看些！”

杰克站起来，脸上汗珠乱滴。我把浴衣披在他身上，他用一只手在浴衣下撑着自己，穿过拳击台走了过去。沃尔科特已经被扶起，有人在照料他。他的那个角落里挤满了人，没人搭理杰克。杰克弯腰凑近沃尔科特。

“对不起，”杰克说，“我并不是有意犯规打你的。”

沃尔科特什么也没说，疼得脸色极其难看。

“噢，你现在是冠军了，”杰克对他说，“希望你为此而感到高兴。”

“让他单独待一会儿。”索利·弗里德曼说。

“你好，索利。”杰克说，“对不起，我犯规打了你的人。”

弗里德曼只是瞪了他一眼。

杰克回他的角落时一瘸一拐的，样子很滑稽。我们扶他钻过绳圈，经过记者席到了甬道。许多观众都想用拳头擂他的后背。他披着浴衣穿过愤怒的人群走到了更衣室。沃尔科特获胜在大多数人的意料之中，来公园看比赛的观众基本把赌注都押在了他身上。

一进更衣室，杰克便躺下来，闭上了眼睛。

“应该回旅馆，请医生看看。”约翰说。

“我的身子里面伤得不轻。”杰克说。

“我非常抱歉，杰克。”约翰说。

“没什么。”杰克说。

他双目紧闭躺在那里。

“他们搞了一场双重骗局[54]。”约翰说。

“都是你的朋友摩根和斯坦菲尔特搞的鬼。”杰克说，“看你交的好朋友！”

他躺在那儿，眼睛却睁开了，脸上仍是那种疼痛难忍、惨不忍睹的表情。

“滑稽的是，一想到有大笔的钱可赚，你的思维就会变得异常敏捷。”杰克说。

“你是好样的，杰克。”约翰说。

“没什么，”杰克说，“这算不上什么。”

第七篇　一次简单的调查

外边的积雪比窗台都高。一缕阳光透过窗户玻璃照在了小屋松木板壁所挂的地图上。日升中天，阳光是从雪堆顶上射进来的。小屋旁边的空地上挖了条战壕，遇到天晴日朗，阳光照在墙上，而热气则会反射到雪堆上，使得冰雪覆盖的战壕变宽。这是三月末。少校坐在靠墙的一张桌子旁，他的副官坐在另一张桌子旁。

少校眼睛的四周有两个白圈，那是因为戴防止雪地太阳紫外线照射的雪镜而留下的。除了这两处，脸上别的部位都已受到了紫外线照射，被晒黑，然后被灼伤。他的鼻子有点儿发肿，脸上曾经被灼出水疱的地方皮肤已经松弛。此时他正在处理文件，一边把左手指探进盛着油的碟子里，将油抹在整张脸上，再用指尖轻轻地揉匀。他非常小心地把手指在碟子边蹭一蹭，蹭掉多余的油脂，只留下薄薄的一层。揉完了额头和脸颊，他又揉鼻子，将鼻子夹在两个手指间极其小心地揉。抹完油脂，他拿起碟子走进一个睡觉用的小房间。“我小憩一会儿。”他对副官说，“你把这些文件处理一下。”在这支部队里，副官不属于正式任命的军官。“遵命，马乔里先生。”副官应了一声。他把身子朝椅背上一靠，打了个哈欠，从外套口袋里掏出一本平装书，翻开摊在桌子上，点上烟斗。随后，他一边趴在桌子上看书，一边抽着烟斗。后来他合上书，将其放回口袋。要处理的文件堆积如山，不干完活儿，哪有闲情看书！外边，太阳落到了山后，屋里墙上的光线不见了踪影。一个士兵走进来，把一些砍得长短不一的松枝塞进炉子里。“轻一点儿，皮宁，”副官对他说，“少校在睡觉。”

皮宁是少校的勤务兵，脸膛黝黑。他捅了捅炉子，轻手轻脚添了些松木进去，关好门，又回到后屋去了。副官继续处理文件。

“托纳尼！”只听少校叫道。

“有何吩咐，马乔里先生？”

“叫皮宁来见我！”

“皮宁！”副官喊了一声。皮宁应声跑进房间。“少校要见你。”副官说。

皮宁穿过大厅走到少校的门前，敲了敲虚掩着的门，说：“马乔里先生？”

“请进，”副官听见少校说道，“把门关上！”

屋里，少校躺在床上。皮宁站到了床前。少校头枕帆布背包，背包里塞了些换洗衣服充当枕头。他抬起那张被阳光灼伤、涂着油的脸打量着皮宁，两手放在毯子上。

“十九岁了吧？”少校问。

“是的，马乔里先生。”

“谈过恋爱吗？”

“什么意思，马乔里先生？”

“和女孩子相处过吗？”

“和一些女孩子相处过。”

“我问的不是这个。我是问你爱过哪个女孩子吗？”

“爱过，马乔里先生。”

“现在还爱这个女孩吗？反正你是不给她写信的，因为你所有的信件我都看过。”

“我爱她，”皮宁说，“但的确不写信。”

“你敢肯定吗？”

“敢肯定。”

“托纳尼，”少校以同样的声调说，“你能听见我说话吗？”

隔壁没有人回答。

“他听不见，”少校说，“你百分之百肯定自己爱上了一个女孩？”

“是这样的。”

“那么，”少校飞快地瞥了皮宁一眼，“你敢肯定自己没有因此而变坏？”

“变坏？我不明白你的意思。”

“得了吧，”少校说，“你不必觉得自己多了不起。”

皮宁低下头望着地面。少校则看看他那张黝黑的脸，上上下下打量，再瞧瞧他的手，然后面无笑容地接着说道：“难道你真的不想……”少校把话说了半截就打住了。皮宁仍望着地面。“难道你真的没有那种欲望……”皮宁仍望着地面。少校把头又枕到了背包上，露出微笑。他真正释然了。部队里的生活太复杂呀！“你是个好孩子，”少校说，“你是个好孩子，皮宁。但是，但是别觉得自己多了不起。小心另有人来取代了你的位置。”

皮宁一动不动地站在床跟前。

“别害怕。”少校说。他两手交叉放在毯子上。“我又不会动你。你要是愿意，可以回到连队里打仗去。不过，你还是留下当我的勤务兵好，这样送命的概率会小一些。”

“还有什么吩咐吗，马乔里先生？”

“没有了，”少校说，“你可以下去了，该干什么就干什么吧。出去时别关门。”

皮宁走出少校寝室时没有关门。副官抬头看着他窘迫地穿过大厅到了外边。皮宁满脸通红，走路的步子也跟刚才送柴火进来时不一样了。副官望望他的背影，笑了笑。皮宁又抱进来一些柴火。少校躺在床上，望着挂在墙壁钉子上的带布罩的钢盔以及那个雪镜，听着他在屋里走动的脚步声，心想：“这小鬼头！不知他对我撒谎了没有？”

第八篇　十个印第安人

有一年，七月四日[55]庆典之后，天色已晚，尼克和乔·盖默一家赶着大篷车从城里回家，路上遇见了九个喝得烂醉的印第安人。他记得是九个，因为正在苍茫暮色里赶车的乔·盖默见有个印第安人脸朝下趴在满是沙子的车辙上睡着了，便勒住马，跳下车，把他拖开，拖到路边的矮树丛里，然后又回到了驭手座上。

“从城外到这里，”乔说，“都遇见九个了。”

“这些印第安人呀！”盖默太太说。

尼克和盖默家的两个男孩坐在后座上。乔把那个印第安人拖到路边时，尼克一直在后座那儿望着印第安人。

“那人是比利·泰伯肖吗？”卡尔问。

“不是。”

“看他穿的裤子倒是很像比利。”

“印第安人穿的裤子全都一样。”

“我压根就没有看到。”弗兰克说，“爸爸跳下车，很快就又回来了，弄得我什么也没看清。我还以为他下车是去打蛇呢。”

“今天晚上，恐怕很多印第安人出动‘打蛇’哩。”乔·盖默打趣道。

“这些印第安人呀！”盖默太太说。

他们继续驾车前行，后来离开通衢大道上了盘山路。马拉车上山很吃力，于是几个男孩子便跳下车步行。路面上全是沙子。到了学校旁的小山顶上，尼克回头望去，但见佩托斯基[56]灯火辉煌，目光掠过小特拉弗斯湾，对面的哈伯斯普林斯小镇也是一片灯海。下山时，他们又回到了车上。

“刚才那段路，应该铺碎石。”乔·盖默说。大篷车沿着车道进了林子。乔和他的妻子盖默太太并排坐在前排。尼克坐在他家的两个男孩之间。马车出了林子，来到了一片空地上。

“就是在这儿爸爸赶车轧死了一只臭鼬。”

“是再往前一点儿的地方。”

“在哪儿轧死都是一样的，”乔头也没回地说，“在这儿轧死和在那儿轧死没什么两样。”

“昨晚我看见了两只臭鼬。”尼克说。

“哪儿看见的？”

“在湖边。它们正在湖岸上找死鱼吃呢。”

“大概是浣熊吧。”卡尔说。

“是臭鼬。臭鼬我想我还是认识的。”

“你应该认识。”卡尔说，“你有个印第安女朋友嘛。”

“别说这种话，卡尔。”盖默太太说。

“他们的嗅觉差不多同样灵敏。”[57]

乔·盖默听了哈哈大笑。

“别笑啦，乔。”盖默太太说，“我不许卡尔说这种话。”

“你是不是有个印第安女友，尼基[58]？”乔问。

“没有。”

“他是有的，爸爸。”弗兰克说，“普鲁登斯·米切尔就是他的女友。”

“不是的。”

“他每天都去见她。”

“没有的事。”黑暗中尼克坐在两个男孩之间，心里感到空落落的，但听见别人说普鲁登斯·米切尔是他的女友，内心也有几分高兴。“她不是我的女友！”他说。

“听他说？！”卡尔说，“我亲眼看见他俩天天约会来着。”

“卡尔自己找不到女友嘛，”他母亲抢白道，“印第安女友也找不到嘛。”

卡尔不作声了。

“卡尔在交女友方面是个门外汉。”弗兰克说。

“你闭嘴。”

“不沾女色是对的，卡尔。”乔·盖默说，“好色之徒一无所成。要学就学你老爹。”

“啧，看你油嘴滑舌的。”大篷车颠了一下，盖默太太趁势靠在了丈夫身上，“想当初，你还不是交了一大堆女朋友。”

“我敢打赌，爸爸绝不会交印第安女友。”

“你可别想这个，”乔说，“你最好盯牢普鲁蒂[59]，尼克。”

乔说完，他妻子低声对他耳语了些什么，他听后哈哈大笑。

“你在笑什么？”弗兰克问。

“别告诉他，盖默。”他妻子警告道。乔又是一阵大笑。

“尼基可以有普鲁登斯做女友，”乔·盖默接下来说道，“我嘛，有你这么个好姑娘做太太。”

“这样说话才像回事。”盖默太太说。

马拉着车在沙路上吃力地前行。乔在黑暗中扬着鞭子。

“拉呀，用劲拉！明天还有更重的活儿要干呢！”

马加快了步伐，在长长的下山的路上小跑起来，马车一颠一颠的。到家后，大伙儿下了车。盖默太太开了门锁，摸黑进了屋，拿出来了一盏灯。卡尔和尼克把车尾装的东西卸了下来。弗兰克坐上驭手座，将大篷车赶到牲口棚里，给马卸了套。尼克走上台阶，推开厨房的门。盖默太太正在生炉子，往木柴上浇煤油，听见门响便转过了头。

“再见，盖默太太，”尼克说，“谢谢你们让我搭车回来。”

“别见外，尼基。”

“今天玩得很高兴。”

“有你我们也很高兴。你不留下来吃饭吗？”

“不了，我还是走吧。爸爸等我恐怕都等急了。”

“好吧，那就不留你了。你去把卡尔喊来，好吗？”

“好的。”

“再见，尼基。”

“再见，盖默太太。”

尼克出了房门，去了牲口棚。乔和弗兰克正在那儿挤牛奶。

“再见，”尼克说，“今天我过得很愉快。”

“再见，尼克。”乔·盖默大声回答道，“你不留下来吃饭吗？”

“不了，我不能待着了。你能不能告诉卡尔，就说他妈妈叫他呢？”

“没问题。再见，尼基。”

尼克光着脚沿着小路走了，穿过牲口棚旁边的那片草地。小路平展，赤脚踩在露水上凉丝丝的。到了草地的尽头，他翻过栅栏，经过一条水沟，踩在泥浆里，脚上满是泥。随后，他爬上坡，进了干燥的山毛榉林子直往前走，远远望见了自家的灯光。他翻过栅栏，绕到前门跟前。透过窗户，他瞧见爸爸正坐在桌前，借着那盏大灯的灯光在看书，于是便推开门走了进去。

“回来啦，尼基？”他的父亲说，“玩得高兴吧？”

“简直棒极了，爸爸。今年的国庆庆典非常隆重。”

“饿了吧？”

“那还用说。”

“你的鞋怎么啦？”

“我把鞋忘在盖默家的马车上了。”

“来，到厨房里来。”

尼克的父亲端起灯走在前边，到了冰柜那儿停下来，揭开冰柜的盖。尼克径自进了厨房。他的父亲端来一盘冷鸡肉和一罐牛奶，放在尼克面前的桌子上，把手里的灯也放下了。

“还有点儿馅饼呢。”他说，“要吃吗？”

“棒极啦。”

父亲傍着那张铺着油布的桌子在椅子上坐下，巨大的身影投射在厨房的墙壁上。

“球赛是谁赢了？”

“佩托斯基队五比三获胜。”

父亲看着尼克吃饭，把罐子里的牛奶倒进他的杯子里。尼克喝了奶，用餐巾擦擦嘴。父亲从架子上取来馅饼，给尼克切了一大块。那是越橘馅饼。

“你今天干什么啦，爸爸？”

“上午去钓了会儿鱼。”

“钓到什么鱼啦？”

“只不过几条鲈鱼。”

父亲坐在那儿看着尼克吃馅饼。

“下午干什么了？”尼克问。

“到印第安人的营地那儿转了转。”

“见到什么人了吗？”

“印第安人全跑到城里酗酒去了。”

“一个人也没见到吗？”

“倒是见到你的朋友普鲁蒂了。”

“在哪里见到的？”

“她和弗兰克·沃什伯恩在林子里。我是在那儿碰见他们的。他们玩得挺高兴的。”

父亲不再看他。

“他们在干什么？”

“我没停下来仔细看。”

“告诉我，他们在干什么？”

“不知道，”父亲说，“只听见他们跑动的声音。”

“你怎么知道是他们？”

“我看见他们了。”

“我还以为你说没看见他们呢。”

“哦，对，我看见他们了。”

“究竟是谁和她在一起？”尼克问。

“弗兰克·沃什伯恩。”

“他们是不是……是不是……”

“是不是什么？”

“他们是不是玩得很开心？”

“我想是的。“

父亲从桌旁站起身，拉开厨房的纱门出去了，回来时见尼克在望着盘子发呆，眼泪汪汪的。

“再吃点儿吧？”父亲拿起刀子为他切馅饼。

“不吃了。”尼克说。

“还是再吃一块吧。”

“不吃了，一口也不想吃了。”

父亲把餐桌收拾干净了。

“他们在林子里的哪块地方？”尼克问。

“营地后边。”尼克呆呆地望着自己的盘子。父亲说：“你还是睡觉去吧，尼克。”

“好的。”

尼克回到自己的寝室，脱掉衣服，上了床。他听见父亲在客厅里走来走去的声音。他趴在床上，把脸埋在枕头里。

“我的心碎了。”他想，“假如过于伤心，我的心一定会碎的。”

过了一会儿，他听见父亲吹灭了灯，回房间去了。林子里风声呼啸，一阵风从纱窗刮进来，带来了丝丝的凉意。他把脸埋在枕头上趴了很长时间。后来，他忘掉了一切，不再去想普鲁登斯，最终进入了梦乡。半夜醒来，他听见铁杉树林间风声呼呼作响，湖里起了浪，在拍打着湖岸，听着听着就又睡着了。次日早晨，狂风大作，湖水波翻浪涌，漫到了岸上来。他躺在床上，躺了很长时间才记起自己的心已经碎了。

第九篇　金丝雀的故事

火车风驰电掣，从一长排红颜色的石头房子旁边疾驰而过。那儿有个花园和四株粗壮的棕榈树，树荫下摆着几张桌子。车厢的另一侧是茫茫的大海。红色的岩石和泥土间有道裂缝，只能偶尔瞥得见大海，而且只能看到低处紧靠岩石的部分。

“这只鸟是我在巴勒莫[60]买的。”美国太太说，“那是个星期天的早晨。我们在岸上只停留一个小时。卖鸟人让我付美元，于是我就给了他一块五毛钱的美元。这只鸟唱歌唱得简直好听极了。”

火车上闷热闷热的，卧铺车厢里热得像个蒸笼。车窗开着，但没有一丝风进来。美国太太拉上遮光帘，这样也就看不见大海了，甚至连瞥一眼也不能够了。另一边是隔挡玻璃，外边则是甬道，甬道那儿的窗户开着，看得见落满尘土的树木、油光发亮的公路和成片成片的葡萄园，再往远处则是灰蒙蒙的石山。

到了马赛时，只见有许多高高的烟囱冒着黑烟。火车减速，穿过蜘蛛网一样的铁轨徐徐开进车站。火车在马赛站停二十五分钟，美国太太下车买了份《每日邮报》和半瓶依云天然矿泉水[61]。她在月台上走了走，但就待在离车门的踏板不远的地方。因为在戛纳火车停了十二分钟，开车时没鸣笛就启动了，她差点儿没来得及上车。她耳朵聋，生怕火车发出了开车信号，自己却听不见。

火车驶离了马赛站，不仅把调车场以及工厂的滚滚浓烟甩在了后边，回头望去，还把马赛城、背靠石山的港口以及那水面上落日的余晖，统统都甩在了后边。天快黑时，火车在野外疾驰，只见那儿有一幢农舍着了火。路上停了许多车辆，屋子里搬出来的被褥等物品被摊放在外边的地上。火场那儿的围观者很多。天黑后，火车开到了阿维尼翁[62]，旅客上上下下的。几个法国人准备回巴黎，跑到报摊那儿买当天的法国报纸。月台上有一些黑人士兵，穿着黄褐色的军服，个子都高高的，灯光下一张张脸闪着亮光。他们的面孔非常黑，个子高得没法凝视。火车驶离了阿维尼翁站，黑人士兵还在那儿站着，有个矮小的白人军官和他们站在一起。

乘务员来到我们的卧铺车厢，把靠在墙上的三张床拉下来，准备让旅客睡觉。夜间，美国太太躺着睡不着，因为本趟车是快车，速度非常快，夜里开快车叫她担惊受怕。她的铺位紧挨窗户。从巴勒莫买的那只金丝雀，笼子上罩着块布，挂在去洗手间的甬道里背风的地方。车厢外亮着盏蓝灯。火车一整夜都风驰电掣，而美国太太一整夜都醒着，时刻担心会撞车。

次日晨，火车离巴黎已经不远了。美国太太从洗手间出来，尽管彻夜未眠，气色却很好，一位中年妇女，美国味十足。她揭开鸟笼上的罩布，把笼子挂在有阳光的地方，然后就到餐车里去吃早饭了。待她返回我们的车厢，床已经收起靠在了墙上，变成了几个座位。窗户开着，阳光从窗户射进来，金丝雀在阳光下抖动着羽毛。火车离巴黎更近了。

“它喜欢阳光，”美国太太说，“马上就会歌唱的。”

金丝雀抖动着羽毛，用鸟喙梳理着。“我一直都很喜欢小鸟，”美国太太说，“这只鸟我要带给我的小女儿。瞧，它现在开始唱了！”

金丝雀叽叽喳喳唱了一阵子，竖起脖子上的羽毛，随后就又埋头用鸟喙梳理身上的羽毛了。火车驶过一条河，穿过一片精心护理过的林子，掠过巴黎郊外星罗棋布的小镇。可以看见那些小镇上有电车，迎向火车的墙上挂着“美丽的花园”、杜本内开胃酒和绿茴香酒[63]几类名酒的巨幅广告。火车好像是在早饭前经过这里的。美国太太一直在跟我妻子说话，有一阵子我没有细听。

“你丈夫也是美国人吧？”那位太太问。

“是的，”我妻子说，“我们俩都是美国人。”

“我原先还以为你们是英国人呢。”

“哦，不是的。”

“也许这是因为我用‘背带’这个词的缘故吧。”我解释说。我原想说“吊带”这个词，可话到嘴边却说成了“背带”，这样更具英国特色[64]。美国太太没有听见我的话，因为她耳朵聋得厉害，只能靠看别人的唇型来理解意思，而我说话时是背过脸的，眼睛望着窗外。她继续跟我妻子说话。

“很高兴你们是美国人。美国男人是天下最好的丈夫，”美国太太说，“要知道，这就是我们离开欧洲大陆的原因。我的女儿在沃韦[65]爱上了一个欧洲人。”她说到这里停顿了一下，“他们俩爱得死去活来。”她又停顿了一下，“当然，我只好带她一走了之。”

“她死心了吗？”我妻子问。

“恐怕死不了心。”美国太太说，“她茶不思饭不想，连觉也不肯睡。我把所有的办法都用尽了，可她对什么都不感兴趣，对什么都不闻不问。反正我决不能叫她嫁给一个外国人。”她又停顿了一下，“我的一个心腹之交曾经告诉我：‘外国男人给美国女孩当丈夫，是当不好的。’”

“是的，”我妻子说，“我想是这样的。”

美国太太对我妻子的旅行装颇为欣赏（这套行头是在圣奥诺雷街的一家时装屋买的）。原来，美国太太的衣服也是在那儿买，都有二十年之久了。那家店里留有她的尺码，有个店员熟悉她，了解她的品位，常常为她选衣服寄到美国去。衣服寄到纽约上城区她家附近的邮局，关税历来都不很高。因为邮局拆封验货，看到的只是样式极其朴素的衣服，既不镶金边也没有装饰物，不像是贵重物品。以前为她寄衣服的店员叫阿梅利亚，现在的这个叫泰蕾兹，二十年来就这么两个人。为她做衣服的始终是同一个裁缝，但价钱却涨了。不过，由于汇率的变化，还能保持平衡。现在，那家店里也有她女儿的尺码——女儿已长大，尺码不大可能变了。

火车正在驶入巴黎车站。防御工事已夷为平地，但空地上还未长出草来。铁轨上停放着许多节车厢，有棕色的木头餐车车厢，也有棕色的木头卧铺车厢。如果那列车还在五点钟出发，这些车厢就都要在这个时间被拉到意大利去。这些车厢上都标有“巴黎—罗马”字样。除此之外，铁轨上还停放着一些定点来往于市区和郊区的区间车，车顶上有座位，车厢里和车顶上到处是旅客，过去如此，现在仍如此。这时，我们的车正在经过一堵堵白墙和一扇扇窗户。没什么早餐可吃。

“美国男人是天下最好的丈夫。”美国太太在跟我妻子说话。我正在从行李架上往下拿行李。“在这个世界上，只有美国男人才值得你去嫁。”

“你离开沃韦多久啦？”我妻子问。

“到今年秋天就两年了。要知道这只金丝雀就是带给小女的。”

“你女儿爱的那个男子是瑞士人吧？”

“是的，”美国太太说，“他出身于沃韦的一个很好的家族，将来准备当工程师。他们是在沃韦认识的，二人经常到很远的地方散步。”

“我熟悉沃韦，”我妻子说，“因为我们在那儿度的蜜月。”

“真的吗？那太好啦！我当时万万没想到她竟然会爱上他。”

“那个地方非常漂亮。”我妻子说。

“是啊，”美国太太说，“很漂亮？你们住在哪里呀？”

“我们住在特罗伊古罗奈酒店。”我妻子说。

“那是家非常舒适的老店。”美国太太说。

“是呀。”我妻子说，“我们住的房间非常舒适，外边秋高气爽、风光旖旎。”

“你们是秋天去的？”

“是的。”我妻子说。

这时，火车正经过三节被撞坏的车厢。车厢皮被撞得稀巴烂，顶部都凹陷了。

“快看，”我说，“撞车啦。”

美国太太向窗外望去，看到的是最后一节车厢。“我整夜提心吊胆，怕的就是这个。”她说，“有时候，我心里会产生不祥的预感。从今往后，夜间我绝不会再乘坐快车了。舒适的火车一定会有的，没必要坐跑得这么快的车。”

火车开进黑黢黢的巴黎里昂站[66]停了下来。几个行李员来到车窗前，我把行李从窗口递出去，随后我们就下车来到了昏暗的月台上。美国太太见有库克旅行社[67]的三个人在那儿，就叫其中的一个来拿自己的行李。那人说：“请等一等，夫人，容我查一下你的名字。”

行李员推来一辆小车，把我们的行李放在车上，我和妻子跟那位美国太太告了别。库克旅行社的那个人在一沓打印纸上找到了她的名字，然后把打印纸放回了衣袋里。

行李员推着行李车，我们俩跟在后边，紧挨着火车往前走，穿过长长的月台。月台的尽头有扇门，那儿有个检票员收了我们的车票。

我们俩这次回巴黎是要办理分居手续的。

第十篇　阿尔卑斯田园曲

即便清晨走进山谷，也会感到浑身发热。太阳把我们滑雪板上的残雪晒得融化了，把滑雪板也晒干了。虽然还只是春天，山谷里的太阳却火辣辣的。我们拿着滑雪板，背着帆布包，沿着大路走进了加尔蒂[68]。经过教堂墓地时，一场葬礼刚刚结束。牧师出了墓地，从我们身边走过，我对他说了声：“愿上帝保佑你！”他冲我躬了躬身子。

“奇怪的是，牧师从不跟人讲话。”约翰说。

“你以为他们喜欢说‘愿上帝保佑你’这样的话？”

“反正他们从不搭腔。”约翰说。

我们停下脚步，站在路上观看教堂司事在铲新土。一个留着黑胡子的农民穿着高腰皮靴守在旁边。教堂司事停下手里的活儿，直起腰来，穿高腰皮靴的农民便从他手中接过铲子，继续往墓坑里填土——他把土撒得很匀，就像在菜园里撒肥料一样。在这么一个阳光灿烂的五月份的上午埋死人显得很不真实。我简直想象不出来这样的时候会死人。

“这样的日子埋死人，你能想象得出来吗？”我对约翰说。

“我不喜欢这样。”

“还好，”我说，“咱们不必干这种倒霉的事。”

我们继续行路，从镇上鳞次栉比的人家门前走过，径直到了客栈。在锡尔夫雷塔[69]待了一个月，此时来到这条山谷，我们感觉很好。在锡尔夫雷塔滑雪固然很棒，但到了春天，那儿的雪只适合早晚滑，其他的时间段，雪都叫太阳给糟蹋了。我们俩都讨厌上了太阳，唯恐躲避不及。在阳光下，只有巉岩和小木屋（那座小木屋建在冰川旁的岩石后，以岩石作掩护）才会投下些许阴影。躲到阴影里，你内衣上的汗水就会结成冰。你不戴墨镜，根本无法坐在小屋外面。把皮肤晒黑本来是件挺开心的事，可是太阳实在太令人讨厌了。你没法在太阳下面休息。能够下山，远离那片滑雪场，我感到心情舒畅。春天去锡尔夫雷塔，未免有点儿太迟了。我都有点儿讨厌滑雪了。我们在那儿待的时间太长，靠着喝小木屋铁皮屋顶上融化的雪水度日，现在嘴里还有一股雪水味。这股味道，也是我们对滑雪的感受的一部分；幸好除了滑雪，还可以干别的有趣的事情，这叫我心里有了一些喜悦。我很高兴能下山，远离高山上那反常的春天，来到这条山谷里，享受这融融的五月晨光。

客栈老板正坐在门廊那儿，椅子向后翘起，抵在墙上。厨子则坐在他身旁。

“嗨，滑雪的！”客栈老板说。

“嗨！”我们一边打招呼，一边把滑雪板靠在墙上，卸下背包。

“山上怎么样？”客栈老板问。

“还好。就是太阳有点儿太毒了。”

“是的。每年的这个时候太阳都特别毒。”

厨子坐在椅子上没动，而客栈老板把我们迎进屋去，打开办公室，取出我们的邮件——一捆信和几份报纸。

“咱们喝点儿啤酒吧。”约翰说。

“好。到里面去喝吧。”

老板送来两瓶酒，我们一边喝酒一边看信。

“最好再来点儿啤酒。”约翰说。这次送酒来的是个女孩。她开瓶时笑了笑。

“好多信哟！”她说。

“是的，是很多。”

“祝你们一切如意！”[70]她说完，拿着空酒瓶子走了出去。

“我都忘了啤酒是什么味道了。”

“我没忘，”约翰说，“因为我在山上的小屋里老想来着。”

“啊，”我说，“现在总算喝到啦。”

“什么事情都不能干的时间太长。”

“是啊。咱们在山上待的时间太长了。”

“长得简直不得了。”约翰说，“凡事时间过长，就没有好结果。”

阳光从敞开的窗户射进来，透过啤酒瓶，照在桌子上。酒瓶里的酒剩下了一半，里面有一点儿泡沫，但因为天气寒冷，泡沫并不很多。把酒倒进高脚杯里，泡沫就堆积了起来。从敞开的窗户望出去，可以看见那条白颜色的大路，路边的树木落满了灰尘。再往远看则是绿油油的田野和一条小溪，溪边树木成行，还有一个磨坊，磨坊里有个水轮。磨坊的一侧是敞开的，可以看见有个大锯在一上一下地锯一根长长的原木，似乎没有人在跟前操作。四只乌鸦在绿野里走来走去，另有一只在树上观看。坐在门廊那儿的厨子离开了椅子，走进了通往后边厨房的门厅。屋内，阳光透过空玻璃杯，射在桌子上。约翰趴在桌子上，把脸埋在两条胳膊上。

从窗户望出去，我看见有两个人走上门前台阶，接着来到了酒吧间里。他们当中的一个就是那个穿高腰皮靴的留黑胡子的农民，另一位是教堂司事。他们在靠窗户的桌子旁落座。那个女孩进来，站在他们的桌子跟前。农民似乎跟没看见她一样，两只手放在桌上，呆坐着。他穿一身旧军装，胳膊肘上缀着补丁。

“要什么酒？”教堂司事问。农民没有理会。

“想喝什么酒？”

“来点儿烈酒吧。”农民说。

“我要四分之一升红葡萄酒。”教堂司事对女孩说。

女孩拿来了酒。农民把烈酒喝了，眼睛望着窗外。教堂司事则在观察他。约翰脸伏在桌子上，已经睡着了。

客栈老板走进来，到了他们的桌子跟前，用方言说了句什么，教堂司事应答着。农民仍在望着窗外。老板出去了。农民站起来，从皮夹子里取出一张叠在一起的一万克朗[71]钞票，把它展开。女孩走上前去。

“一起算？”女孩问。

“一起算。”农民回答。

“红酒的钱我出。”教堂司事说。

“一起算。”农民把刚才的话又对女孩重复了一遍。女孩把手伸进围裙口袋里，掏出一把硬币，数出了应该找的钱。农民走了。他前脚走，客栈老板后脚就进来了，在教堂司事的桌旁坐下，跟他说起了话。他们谈话时，都操方言。教堂司事乐呵呵的，而客栈老板则是一脸的厌恶。教堂司事是个小个子，留着小胡子。只见他从桌旁站起，把脑袋探出窗户，朝大路那儿望了望。

“他进去了。”教堂司事说。

“进洛温旅馆啦？”

“是的。”

他们又说了一会儿话。后来，客栈老板来到了我们桌子跟前。这位客栈老板是个老头，个子高高的。他看了看正在呼呼大睡的约翰。

“他累坏了。”

“是的。我们今天起床起得早。”

“想不想马上吃饭？”

“什么时候都可以。”我说，“有什么菜？”

“随你点了。女孩会把菜单拿来的。”

女孩把菜单送来时，约翰也醒了。菜单用墨水写在卡片上，再将卡片嵌入一个木框。

“菜单来了。”我对约翰说。他仍在发困，睡眼惺忪地看了看菜单。

“想跟我们喝杯酒吗？”我问客栈老板。

客栈老板坐了下来。“那些农民简直就是畜生。”客栈老板说。

“我们来小镇的路上看见刚才的那位在办葬礼。”

“死的是他的妻子。”

“噢。”

“那家伙是个畜生。那些农民全都是畜生。”

“此话怎讲？”

“说出来你也不相信。他干的事情令人难以置信。”

“说说看。”

“你是绝对不会相信的。”客栈老板说完，冲着教堂司事喊了一声：“弗朗兹，你过来！”教堂司事拿着他那一小瓶葡萄酒和酒杯走了过来。

“这两位先生刚从威斯巴登小屋那儿过来。”客栈老板介绍道。我们相互握了手。

“你喝什么酒？”我问。

“什么酒也不喝了。”弗朗兹摆了摆手说。

“再来四分之一升红酒怎么样？”

“那好吧。”

“你懂我们的地方话？”客栈老板问。

“不懂。”

“你在搞什么名堂？”约翰问。

“咱们来镇上，半路不是见到一个农民在埋死人吗，听他讲一讲那个农民的情况。”

“讲了我也听不明白的。”约翰说，“事情发生得太快了。”

“那个农民，”老板说，“今天才把他的妻子下葬，而他的妻子去年十一月就死了。”

“是十二月。”教堂司事说。

“这没什么关系。就算是去年十二月死的吧。当时他把死讯告诉了教区。”

“是在十二月十八号告诉的。”教堂司事说。

“不管怎样吧，反正当时不能送死者去墓地安葬，得等雪化之后才行。”

“他住在帕斯农山谷的另一侧，”教堂司事说，“但他属于这个教区。”

“难道不能想办法把死者送过来吗？”

“不行。得等到雪化之后，才能从他住的地方用雪橇送过来，所以今天才送来下葬。牧师看了看死者的脸，不愿为她主持葬礼。接下来的情况，你来讲吧。”老板对教堂司事说，“你用德语介绍，别说地方话。”

“牧师觉得这件事十分蹊跷。”教堂司事说，“那个农民在报告死讯时，说他的妻子死于心脏病。我们知道她心脏有毛病，有时候来教堂做礼拜还有昏厥的现象。有好长一段时间她都没有来过了，因为没有力气爬山。牧师揭开她脸上的毯子时问奥尔兹：‘你老婆死得很痛苦吧？’‘不痛苦。’奥尔兹说，‘我一进家门，就见她躺在床上与世长辞了。’

“牧师看了看死者。他并不愿意看。

“‘她的脸怎么弄成这个样子啦？’

“‘我不清楚。’奥尔兹回答说。

“‘那你最好搞清楚再说。’牧师说着又把毯子盖上了。奥尔兹一声不吭。牧师望着他，他也望着牧师，说道：‘你真的想知道吗？’

“‘我必须知道。’牧师说。”

“接下来就是谜底，”客栈老板说，“你们注意听。弗朗兹，你继续讲吧。”

“‘哦，’奥尔兹说，‘她死后，我向教区报告了死讯，接着就把她的尸体放在了柴火间里的一截粗大的木头上。后来我要用那截木头，而她已僵硬，于是我就把她靠墙放，让她立在那儿。她的嘴大张着。夜里我到柴火间要劈开那截木头，就把提灯挂在她的嘴上。’

“‘你为什么要那样做？’牧师问。

“‘我也不知道。’奥尔兹说。

“‘这样的事你干了很多次？’

“‘每次夜里去柴火间干活儿，我都这样做。’

“‘真是罪过。’牧师说，‘你爱你的老婆吗？’

“‘爱，我爱她，’奥尔兹说，‘非常爱她。’”

“你们都听明白了吗？”客栈老板问，“关于他妻子的情况你们都听明白了吗？”

“听明白了。”

“该吃饭了吧？”约翰问。

“你点菜吧。”我说。“你觉得这事是真的吗？”我问客栈老板。

“千真万确。”他说，“这些农民都是畜生。”

“他刚才到哪儿去了？”

“到我的同行洛温旅馆那儿喝酒去了呗！”

“他不愿跟我一起喝酒。”教堂司事说。

“弗朗兹了解了他妻子的情况，他就不愿在这里喝酒了。”客栈老板说。

“喂，”约翰说，“该吃饭了吧？”

“好吧。”我说。

第十一篇　自行车比赛

在匹兹堡[72]，威廉·坎贝尔开始跟一个杂耍班子进行骑车比赛。举行这样的自行车比赛，选手们出发时，彼此间前后的间距是同等的。由于赛程短，选手们骑得都非常快，如果车速慢，其他保持车速的车手就会把出发时的差距追平。一个选手一旦被赶上和超过，就得退赛，灰溜溜地下车，离开赛道。假如赶超的现象没有发生，间距拉得最长的选手就是冠军。如果只有两个选手参赛，大多数情况下，骑不到六英里，其中的一个选手就会被另一个选手赶上。杂耍班子的选手就是在堪萨斯城[73]赶上威廉·坎贝尔的。

威廉·坎贝尔原计划只要稍稍领先于杂耍班子即可，到了太平洋岸边再说。反正只要领先于杂耍班子，在杂耍班子之前到达就可以拿到奖金。谁知竟让杂耍班子赶了上来，而这时的他已上床睡觉了。杂耍班子的经理进入他的房间时，他正躺在床上。经理走后，他决定仍躺在床上，堪萨斯城太冷，他才不急着往外跑呢。他不喜欢这座城市。他伸手从床下取出一瓶酒喝了几口，胃里感到舒服了些。刚才请杂耍班子的经理特纳先生喝酒，对方谢绝了。

威廉·坎贝尔刚才和特纳先生的会面，场景有点儿怪怪的。特纳先生敲了敲门，坎贝尔说：“请进！”特纳先生走进屋，见椅子上堆着衣服，行李箱敞着盖，床边的一把椅子上放着一瓶酒，一个人躺在床上，用被子把自己从头到脚捂得严严实实的。

“坎贝尔先生！”特纳先生叫了一声。

“你不能解雇我！”威廉·坎贝尔躲在被窝里说，被子白白的，暖暖和和的，把他裹得严严实实。“你不能因为我被赶上，下了车子，就把我一脚踢开。”

“你喝醉了。”特纳先生说。

“对，是喝醉了。”威廉·坎贝尔说话时，脸紧贴着被子，嘴唇摩擦着布料。

“你是个傻瓜。”特纳先生说着，关掉了屋里的灯。那盏灯已经亮了一夜，此时已是上午十点了。“你是个喝醉了的傻瓜。你是什么时候来到这座城市的？”

“昨天晚上来的。”威廉·坎贝尔隔着被子回答道，他发现自己喜欢隔着被子跟人说话，“你有没有隔着被子跟人说过话？”

“别犯傻了。你这样并不幽默。”

“我并不是犯傻，只不过隔着被子说说话而已。”

“好一个隔着被子说说话而已。”

“你可以走啦，特纳先生。”坎贝尔说，“我不再为你效力了。”

“你总算知道了。”

“我知道的事情多着呢。”威廉·坎贝尔说。他把被子朝下一扯，盯着特纳先生。“就因为我知道的事情太多，所以看都不想看见你了。想听听我知道什么吗？”

“不想。”

“不听也罢，”威廉·坎贝尔说，“其实我什么也不知道，只不过是随便说说而已。”他把被子一拉，又捂在了脸上。“我喜欢捂在被窝里。”他说。特纳先生是个中年人，大腹便便，秃头，正站在床跟前。其实他有许多事情要做。“你应该在这儿歇一歇，比利[74]，疗养一下身体。”他说，“如果你有这个意愿，我会作出安排。”

“我才不想疗养呢，”威廉·坎贝尔说，“我完全没有这个意愿。我现在感觉很好。我这辈子感觉一直很好。”

“你这样子有多长时间啦？”

“这算是什么问题呀！”威廉·坎贝尔隔着被子喘着气。

“你酗酒有多长时间啦，比利？”

“难道耽误工作了吗？”

“那倒没耽误。我只是问你酗酒有多长时间了，比利。”

“说不清。但我的狼[75]的确回来了。”他用舌头舔了舔被子说，“它回来有一个星期了。”

“胡扯什么！”

“啊，是这样的。我亲爱的狼回来啦。我每次喝酒，它就在屋外。它是受不了酒精味的。可怜的小乖乖。”威廉·坎贝尔边说，边用舌头在被子上舔来舔去。“它是只可爱的狼，总是那样的可爱。”他说完，闭上眼睛，深深吸了口气。

“看来你必须疗养疗养了，比利。”特纳先生说，“基利疗养院[76]你一定会喜欢的。那家疗养院挺不错的。”

“基利吗？”威廉·坎贝尔说，“离伦敦不太远。”他闭上眼睛，然后又睁开，眼睫毛来回蹭着被子。“我就喜欢躺在被窝里。”他说着，抬起眼看了看特纳先生。

“喂，你以为我喝醉啦？”

“你的确是喝醉了。”

“不，我没喝醉。”

“你喝醉了，你得了震颤性谵妄症。”

“没有的事。”威廉·坎贝尔说着，拿被子裹住脑袋，“亲爱的被子啊！”他说。他温柔地贴着被单呼吸着。“美丽的被子啊，你是爱我的，对不对，被子？这都包括在了房租里，就跟在日本一样[77]。不，”他说，“你听我说，比利，亲爱的滑头比利，我有件意外的事情要告诉你：我虽然看上去像喝醉了，但其实没醉。”

“胡言乱语！”特纳先生说。

“你瞧这个！”威廉·坎贝尔在被窝里拉起睡衣右边的袖子，伸出了右胳膊，“你瞧瞧好啦！”他的小臂上，从手腕到胳膊肘之间满都是深蓝色的小针眼，每个针眼周围都有一个小蓝圈，密密麻麻，一个挨着一个[78]。“这可是一种新情况。我有时喝点儿酒嘛，就是要把这只狼赶出屋外。”

“他们有妙方，可以治疗这种病。”“滑头比利”特纳说。

“不行，”威廉·坎贝尔说，“他们什么病都治不了。”

“你可不能自暴自弃，比利。”特纳说着，一屁股坐到了床上。

“小心我的被子！”威廉·坎贝尔说。

“你这么年轻，可不能自暴自弃，不能一遇到点儿困难就灌黄汤。”

“难道这犯法吗？你是说这犯法吗？”

“我不是那意思。我是说你应该和困难斗争到底。”

威廉·坎贝尔用嘴唇和舌头把被子又是吻又是舔。“亲爱的被子啊，”他说，“我吻你，同时可以透过你观察人间百态。”

“别胡扯什么被子啦。劝你不要迷上那东西，比利。”

威廉·坎贝尔闭上眼睛，开始觉得有点儿恶心。他知道没有什么遏制它，使它缓解，这种恶心感就会不断加剧。正是在这个节骨眼上，他请特纳先生喝酒，而特纳先生谢绝了。他自己拎起酒瓶喝了几口，恶心感暂时压了下去。特纳先生在一旁看着他。特纳先生不应该在这个房间待这么长时间，他手头还有许多事情需要处理。他虽然天天和吸毒人员打交道，对毒品却还是怀有恐惧。他非常喜欢威廉·坎贝尔，不愿丢下他不管。他为威廉·坎贝尔感到十分难过，觉得治疗治疗也许可以帮他恢复正常。他知道在堪萨斯城就有些非常好的疗养机构。但此刻他必须走了，于是就站了起来。

“喂，比利，”威廉·坎贝尔说，“我想告诉你：你才是‘滑头比利’，因为善于耍滑头嘛。至于我，只能叫比利，因为我压根就不会耍滑头。滑头我是不会耍的，比利。我不会耍滑头。这行不通呀！每次我试着耍滑头，都是行不通的。”他闭上了眼睛，“行不通呀，比利。一旦行不通，结果就很糟糕。”

“是啊。”“滑头比利”特纳说。

“是什么呀？”威廉·坎贝尔望着他。

“就是你刚才说的那样呀。”

“我没说什么，”威廉·坎贝尔说，“你一定听岔了。”

“你说滑头什么来着。”

“我不可能说滑头什么来着。不过，你仔细听着，我要告诉你一个秘密。你到我的被窝跟前来，比利。劝你远离女人和马，另外还……”他停顿了一下，“另外还要远离老鹰，比利。假如你喜欢马，最终得到的是马粪；喜欢老鹰，得到的则是鹰屎。”他打住了话头，把脸又遮在了被子下。

“我得走啦。”“滑头比利”特纳说。

“假如你喜欢女人，就会染上花柳病。”威廉·坎贝尔说，“假如你喜欢马……”

“得啦，这话你刚才已经说过了。”

“说过什么啦？”

“说过喜欢马和老鹰会导致什么样的后果。”

“噢，是这样的。假如你喜欢被子……”他嘴对被子吸了口气，用鼻子在上面蹭了蹭说。“其实我对被子并不了解，”他说，“只是现在开始有点儿喜欢罢了。”

“我得走了，”特纳先生说，“手里有许多事情要做呢。”

“那好吧，”威廉·坎贝尔说，“人人都有事忙着要走。”

“我还是走吧。”

“好，你走吧。”

“你没事吧，比利？”

“我一生从来都没有这么高兴过。”

“你真的没事？”

“我很好。你走你的。我再躺一会儿，中午的时候起来。”

可中午时分特纳先生来到威廉·坎贝尔的房间，见他仍在睡觉。特纳先生是个知趣的人，知道生活中什么东西最宝贵，于是就没有叫醒他。

第十二篇　今天是星期五[79]

晚上十一点钟，三个罗马士兵在酒馆里喝酒。酒馆的墙根放着几大桶酒。木质柜台后坐着个卖酒的希伯来人[80]。三个罗马士兵都喝得有点儿眼睛发呆。

士兵甲：尝尝红酒吧？

士兵乙：不了，我就不尝了。

士兵甲：你还是尝尝吧。

士兵乙：那好吧，乔治，我们就喝上一巡红酒吧。

卖酒人：各位先生，酒来啦。你们会喜欢的。（他把一个陶制酒壶放在了他们的桌子上，里面盛着从酒桶里倒出来的酒。）这可是佳酿美酒呀。

士兵甲：来，你也喝上一杯！（他对靠在酒桶上的士兵丙说。）你怎么啦？

士兵丙：我肚子疼。

士兵乙：你一直在喝水。

士兵甲：还是尝几口红酒吧。

士兵丙：这玩意儿我喝不成，一喝胃里就泛酸。

士兵甲：你出来待的时间太长了。

士兵丙：见鬼，我还不知道这个？

士兵甲：喂，乔治，你能不能给这位先生来点儿什么，治治他的肚子疼？

卖酒人：我这儿有灵丹妙药呢。

（士兵丙尝了尝卖酒人为他调制的“灵丹妙药”。）

士兵丙：喂，你在里面放了什么？骆驼粪吗？

卖酒人：你喝下去就是了，包你能好，长官。

士兵丙：唉，我觉得难受极了。

士兵甲：你就试一试嘛。那天我不舒服，乔治就把我治好了。

卖酒人：你的情况很不妙，长官。对于治肚子疼，我还是有把握的。

（士兵丙把药酒喝了下去。）

士兵丙：耶稣基督啊！（他做了个鬼脸。）

士兵乙：真是虚惊一场！

士兵甲：说到耶稣，实在叫人搞不懂。今天他在那儿状态很好！

士兵乙：他为什么就不愿从十字架上下来呢？

士兵甲：他就不愿从十字架上下来，因为那不是他的玩法。

士兵乙：你告诉我，有谁愿意待在十字架上而不肯下来！

士兵甲：得了吧，这种事情你一点儿都不懂。你问问乔治。他想从十字架上下来吗，乔治？

卖酒人：各位先生，恕我直言。我没有到现场去，因为这种事情我丝毫不感兴趣。

士兵乙：这种人我见得多啦，不但在这儿见了，别的许多地方也见过。不管什么时候，你只要指给我看，看哪个人在时辰到了的时候（我指的是时辰来到之际）不愿意从十字架上下来，那我就爬上十字架陪他！

士兵甲：我觉得他今天在那儿的状态挺好的。

士兵丙：是挺好的。

士兵乙：你们俩根本不知道我在说什么。我没说他状态好不好，而是说时辰来到之际会怎么样。刚开始钉他的时候，即便有人能够阻止，也不会出面干涉的。

士兵甲：你听明白了吗，乔治？

卖酒人：不明白。我对这种事丝毫不感兴趣，长官。

士兵甲：他的行为举止叫人觉得惊讶。

士兵丙：我所不喜欢的是把人钉在十字架上。要知道，那是非常痛的。

士兵乙：刚开始把人吊起来的时候，还不算特别痛。（他双手合在一起，做了一个吊人的姿势。）一旦身体下沉，疼痛就加剧了。

士兵丙：有些人痛得死去活来。

士兵甲：难道我没见过吗？十字架钉人的事情我见得多了。我只是说他今天在那儿的状态挺好的。

（士兵乙冲着卖酒人笑了笑。）

士兵乙：你可真是个死脑筋，大个子。

士兵甲：说得是，接着逗他吧。不过，容我告诉你一句：今天他在那儿状态挺好的。

士兵乙：再来杯酒怎么样？

（卖酒人抬起头，投来期待的目光。士兵乙耷拉着脑袋，脸色看上去不太好。）

士兵丙：我不想再喝了。

士兵乙：那就来两杯吧，乔治。

（卖酒人端出一壶酒，酒壶比刚才的那个小一点儿，然后身子前倾趴在木质柜台上。）

士兵甲：你见他的女友了吧？[81]

士兵乙：我不就站在她身边吗？

士兵甲：她长得挺漂亮。

士兵乙：我在他之前就认识她了。（他说着，冲卖酒人挤了挤眼。）

士兵甲：我在城里常见到她。

士兵乙：她原来生意还是很好的。他从来就没有给她带来过好运。

士兵甲：哦，他自己就不走运嘛。不过，我看他今天在那儿的状态挺好的。

士兵乙：他的追随者哪里去了？

士兵甲：哦，全都溜掉了，只剩下了一帮女人守在他身边。

士兵乙：那些人都是胆小鬼，一见他被钉上十字架，就吓得不敢跟他有牵连了。

士兵甲：那些女人倒是紧紧跟随着他。

士兵乙：不错，她们一直守在他身边。

士兵甲：你见我把铁矛刺进他的身体了吗？

士兵乙：你那样做总有一天会惹祸的。

士兵甲：我只能为他做这么一点儿事情了[82]。说真的，他今天在那儿的状态挺好的。

卖酒人：各位先生，对不起，我要关门了。

士兵甲：让我们再喝上一巡吧。

士兵乙：还喝什么呀？光喝酒解不了心中的愁。得啦，咱们走吧。

士兵甲：只喝上一巡就走。

士兵丙：（起身离开酒桶。）不喝了。走吧，咱们走！今天晚上我觉得难受极了。

士兵甲：就一巡么。

士兵乙：不喝了。走吧，咱们走！再见，乔治，把酒钱记在账上。

卖酒人：再见，先生们。（他脸上露出了些许愁容。）能不能先付一点儿酒钱呢，长官？

士兵乙：见鬼，乔治！星期三才是我们的发饷日。

卖酒人：那好吧，长官。再见，先生们！

（三个士兵走出酒馆，来到了大街上。）

（在酒馆外面的大街上。）

士兵乙：乔治是犹太佬，跟那些家伙是一路人。

士兵甲：哦，乔治是个好人。

士兵乙：今晚在你看来，个个都是好人。

士兵丙：走吧，快回到军营里去吧。今晚我难受死啦。

士兵乙：你是因为在外边待的时间太长了。

士兵丙：不，这并不是原因。反正我难受得要死。

士兵乙：你在外边待的时间太长了。就是这么回事。

（幕落）

第十三篇　平庸的故事

他在吃橘子，不慌不忙地把核吐出来。外边，雪转成了雨。屋里的电炉子似乎没有热气，于是他从写字台前站起，走过去坐在了火炉旁。啊，好舒服呀！生活就应该这样子！

他又拿了一个橘子。在遥远的巴黎，马斯卡特在第二个回合就把那个菜鸟丹尼·弗拉斯揍趴下了。在遥远的美索不达米亚[83]，下的雪有二十一英尺厚。而远在地球南端的澳大利亚，英国板球手正秣马厉兵，加强训练，颇具浪漫情调。

他读到，文学艺术的赞助人已经发现了《论坛》这个刊物。此刊物具有指导意义，哲理性强，堪为少数喜欢思索的人之友，登载的都是些获奖的短篇小说——这些作家将来能写出畅销书吗？

你可以欣赏到温馨、朴实的美国故事，看到有关空旷的牧场、拥挤的出租屋或舒适人家真实生活的点点滴滴，处处透露出健康、幽默的情趣。

他心想：我一定要读一读这些作品。

他继续看了下去。我们的子孙后代……他们将会怎样？将会成为什么样的人？要在太阳下争取到生存空间，就必须寻找新的途径。是需要诉诸战争，还是可以用和平的方式办到？

要不然就移居到加拿大去？

我们最深厚的信念……它们会不会受到科学的颠覆？我们的现代文明……它是不是还不如原来旧的社会体系？

就在这个时候，遥远的尤卡坦半岛[84]的雨林里正回响着橡胶采集者的伐木声。

我们需要大人物吗？或者说我们需要有文化教养的大人物吗？不妨想一想乔伊斯[85]，抑或柯立芝总统[86]！我们的大学生想当哪一类的明星人物？想当杰克·布里顿[87]那样的人，还是亨利·范戴克博士[88]那样的人？这两种类型的人能不能中和一下？扬·斯特里布林[89]那样的人怎么样？

我们的女儿必须亲自探索人生。她们将会怎样呢？南希·霍桑就深入人生的海洋中进行了探索，勇敢、理智地面对每一个十八岁女孩都会遇到的问题。

这真是一本非常棒的刊物！

你是个十八岁的女孩吗？你不妨想一想圣女贞德[90]的事迹吧！想一想萧伯纳[91]以及贝琪·罗斯[92]的事迹吧！

不妨想一想1925年发生的那些事吧……清教徒的历史上是否有过伤风败俗的一页？波卡洪塔斯[93]有两面性吗？她是否还有第四维[94]？

现代绘画和现代诗歌算不算艺术？说算也不算。不妨想一想毕加索[95]吧！

流浪汉有没有行为准则？你就让你的想象驰骋吧！

这个刊物充满了浪漫的情调，作者诙谐幽默、妙语连珠，句句切中要害，绝不忸怩做作、拖泥带水。

要活就应该活得思想充实，受新思想的激励，为非同寻常的浪漫情怀而陶醉！想到这里，他放下了手中的小册子。

就在这时，曼努埃尔·加西亚·梅拉[96]正仰面八叉躺在特里纳[97]的一个黑屋子里，因患肺炎肺里积水，两叶肺里都插着导管。安达卢西亚亚[98]的所有报纸都为他的去世预留出了特别增刊，人们预计他要死已经有好几天了。无论成年人还是孩子，纷纷争购他的全身彩色画像纪念他。看着他的平版印刷画像，人们反而淡忘了他那保留在大家记忆中的勃勃英姿。他的死倒是叫斗牛士们松了口气，因为他在斗牛场上总是绝技频出，而这样的绝技其他的斗牛士只能偶然为之。有一百四十七位斗牛士为他送葬，冒雨跟在他的灵车后把他送往墓园，将他埋葬在何赛利托[99]坟茔的旁边。葬礼过后，大家都跑进了咖啡馆躲雨，那儿卖掉了许多梅拉的彩色画像，买家把画像卷起来放进兜里。

第十四篇　睡不着的时候

那天夜里，我们是躺在屋里的地板上睡的。我睡不着，就侧耳倾听蚕吃桑叶的声音。桑叶放在架子上，蚕就在那儿大吃大嚼，一整夜都能听得见，还能听见蚕粪掉在桑叶上的声音。其实我并不想进入梦乡，长期以来，我一直有一种想法：在黑暗中闭上眼睛，昏昏睡去，我的灵魂就会出窍。自从一天夜里被炮弹炸了一次之后，这种现象存在已有好长时间了，我老觉得自己的灵魂会出窍，会离开我，最终又返回我的体内。我尽量不去想它，可是夜里每当快睡着的时候，这种现象就会出现，非得使出全身的解数才能制止它重演。现在我倒是确信灵魂不会真的出窍，但那年夏天我却并不愿意做这种试验。

夜里醒着的时候，我有种种办法排遣时间。我会想小时候格外认真地循着整条小溪钓鱼的情形，有时小心翼翼地钓浮木底下的鱼，有时钓溪水转弯处的鱼，有时则在深潭和清澈的浅滩处钓，有时会钓到鳟鱼，有时让它们跑了。中午的时候，我就放下钓竿吃饭，有时在小溪的独木桥上吃，有时则在高高的河岸上躲在树下吃，每次吃饭都细嚼慢咽，边吃边观看脚下的溪水。出发的时候，我往往只在烟草铁盒里装十条蚯蚓当鱼饵，结果常常不够用。一旦鱼饵用尽，就得去找新的鱼饵。岸上，由于雪松遮住了阳光，结果寸草不生，只有潮湿的泥土，在这样的地方挖蚯蚓往往是很难的，常常一条蚯蚓也找不到。遇到这种情况，我就找其他种类的鱼饵。然而有一次在沼泽地里，由于任何鱼饵都找不到，我只好把钓到的一条鳟鱼切碎充当鱼饵。

有时在沼泽地的草窝里、荒草间或羊齿植物的根部下找到些昆虫，我就用这些昆虫当鱼饵。这其中有甲虫，有腿像草茎一样的昆虫，也有藏在朽木里的金龟甲幼虫。这种幼虫，白白的身子，脑袋是棕色的，尖尖的，在鱼钩上挂不住，一到冰冷的溪水里就不见了踪影。还有躲在原木下的蜱虫。有时会有蚯蚓藏在原木下，可一掀开原木，它们就会钻进土里。一次，我在一根朽木下找到一只蝾螈，就用它当鱼饵。那只蝾螈很小，轻巧灵活，颜色很好看，用小小的爪子紧紧抓住钓钩。这之后，虽然常常还能找到蝾螈，但我再也不用它们当鱼饵了。我也不用蟋蟀当鱼饵，因为它们在鱼钩上胡蹦乱跳。

有的时候，小溪会流过一片开阔的草地。我会在干草丛里抓蚱蜢，用蚱蜢当鱼饵。有时，我抓住蚱蜢，就把它们扔进溪水里，看着它们漂浮在水面顺流而下，流水冲上来时它就在水面上打转转，直至一条鳟鱼跃起才不见了踪影。有时，我会在一个晚上去四五条小溪边钓鱼，尽量从源头开始，然后溯流而下，一路甩钩垂钓。有时由于钓鱼钓得过分匆忙，时间又来得及，我就在这条小溪上再钓一遍，从溪水入湖处开始往上游边走边钓，试图把漏掉的鳟鱼钓上岸。有时在夜间，我还会幻想出几条小溪，其中一些极其有趣，而且非常生动，宛在眼前。有的我至今记忆犹新，以为自己真的在那些溪水里钓过鱼。那些溪水和我真正了解的溪水混在一起，难以区分。我还给那些溪水起了一个个名字，而且还会坐火车去寻找它们，有时还会步行走很远的路去寻觅它们的踪影。

有时夜间无法钓鱼，清醒极了，于是我就念祈祷词，念了一遍又一遍，试图为所有我认识的人祈祷。这要花相当长的时间。如果你想回忆起所有你认识的人，就得追溯你记忆中最早的往事。对我而言，就得回忆回忆我出生的那个阁楼。阁楼的椽子上挂着一个铁皮盒子，里面保存着我父母的结婚蛋糕；阁楼里放着几个瓶子，里面有父亲小时候收集的蛇的标本，以及其他的一些动物的标本，浸泡在酒精里，但由于酒精的蒸发，一些蛇和其他动物标本的脊背露出来，都发白了。追溯这么远的往事，你肯定能回忆起许多人。如果为每个人念一遍“万福马利亚”和“天父保佑”，那也得花好长时间，念到天亮也念不完。如果在一个大白天还容你睡觉的地方，你可以补上一大觉。

在那些夜晚，我竭力想回忆起自己经历过的诸多事情，从上战场之前开始，一件件回忆，但我发现最早只能回忆起祖父家阁楼里出现过的场景。于是我就以那儿为起点往后回忆，一直回忆到参战时。

我回忆起祖父死后，我们一家离开祖屋，搬到了一幢由母亲设计建造的新房屋里。许多搬不走的东西被拿到后院付之一炬。记得阁楼里的那几个标本瓶子扔进火堆时，砰地爆裂开来，酒精燃烧，火焰冲天。我至今仍记得蛇的标本在后院的火堆里熊熊燃烧的情景。不过后院没人，全都是东西。我甚至记不得是什么人在烧那些东西。我就绞尽脑汁想啊想，直至想起了是什么人在烧东西才罢休，接下来就为他们祈祷。

记得到了新家，母亲老是清理东西，收拾得干净整洁。一次，父亲出门打猎，她就钻进地下室来了个大清扫，把她认为不该放在那里的东西全都扔进火里烧了。父亲打猎归来，下了马车，拴了马，余火仍在房屋旁的道路上燃烧。我跑上前迎接他，他把手里的猎枪递给我，看了看火堆。“这是怎么回事？”他问。

“我在清理地下室呢，亲爱的。”母亲来到门廊迎接他，站在那儿笑吟吟地说。父亲望望火堆的灰烬，用脚踢了踢。踢到了一样东西，于是弯腰把那样东西捡起，对我说：“把耙子拿来，尼克！”我跑到地下室取来了耙子，父亲用耙子在灰堆里细心地耙来耙去，扒出了一些石斧、剥兽皮用的石刀和制作箭头用的工具，还有一些陶器碎片以及许多箭头。这些物件已被大火烧黑，残破不全了。父亲轻手轻脚把东西扒出来后，摊开放在路边的草地上。带皮套的猎枪和狩猎袋也在草地上放着，那是他下马车时丢在那儿的。

“把枪和袋子拿到屋里去，尼克，再给我拿张纸来！”他对我说。此时母亲已进了屋。我拿起猎枪和两个狩猎袋拔腿就往屋里走，猎枪沉得不得了，老碰我的腿。“一次拿一件东西，”父亲说，“别一次拿那么多！”我把两个狩猎袋放下，将猎枪送进了屋，然后到父亲的办公室，从报纸堆里取来一张报纸。父亲把那些烧黑了的、残破不全的石器放在报纸上裹起来。“最好的箭头全都成了碎渣渣。”他说完就拿着那包残破的石器进屋了，而我仍留在屋外的草地上守着那两个狩猎袋。过了一会儿，我把它们拿进了屋。回忆这段往事时只能想起这两个人，于是我就为他俩念祈祷文。

有几个夜晚，我连祈祷文都记不起来了，只能记起一句“在人间如同置身于天堂”，于是只好从头来，结果还是在这里卡壳，其他内容一概记不起来。这种情况下我只好认输，承认自己记不起来，当天晚上就不再念祈祷文，而是思索别的事情。所以，有那么几个夜晚，我绞尽脑汁想回忆世上所有动物的名称，回忆飞禽和鱼类的名称，然后试着回忆国家、城市以及各种食物的名称，接着搜索枯肠回忆芝加哥各街道的名称。待到什么都回忆不起来时，我就竖起耳朵倾听动静。我记不得自己哪天夜里会听不见任何声音。夜间，只要有亮光，我就不怕睡觉，因为我知道我的灵魂只有在黑暗中才会出窍。所以，好多夜晚我当然会躺到有亮光的地方安然入睡，这时的我十有八九已精疲力竭，经常困得不得了。也有许多次我是不知不觉睡着的，这一点我敢肯定。但凡有知觉的夜晚，我便睡不着，这时我就听蚕的动静。更深人静时，蚕吃桑叶的声音你可以听得一清二楚。于是我睁大眼睛躺着，侧耳静听。

那天夜里，屋里另有一人，他也醒着。听得出来他是醒着的，很长时间。他不能像我一样静静地躺着，也许是因为没有我这么多睡不着觉的经验吧。我们睡在稻草上，身下铺着毯子，他稍微一动，稻草就窸窣作响。不过，不管我们弄出什么样的响动都不会吓着蚕，它们照样吃它们的桑叶。我们距离前线七公里，夜里外边会有一些响动，但那种响动跟黑屋子里这种细小的声音是不同的。屋里另外的那个人竭力想安安静静地躺着，可后来又动了下身子。我也动了动，好叫他知道我也醒着。他在芝加哥居住过十年，1914年回家探亲，却被抓了壮丁。他被分配给我当勤务兵，因为他会说英语。这时我情知他在听，于是躺在毯子上又动了动身子。

“你睡不着吗，中尉先生？”他问。

“是的。”

“我也睡不着。”

“怎么回事？”

“不知道。反正就是睡不着。”

“你的身体还好吧？”

“还好，身体没毛病。可就是睡不着。”

“想说会儿话吗？”我问。

“好呀，但在这鬼地方有什么可说的呢？”

“这地方挺好呀。”我说。

“是挺好，”他说，“还可以吧。”

“把你在芝加哥的经历跟我讲讲好吗？”我说。

“这个嘛，”他说，“我都跟你讲过了。”

“那就说说你结婚的经过吧。”

“这个也跟你说过了。”

“你星期一收到的那封信……是你老婆的吗？”

“当然是喽。她一直在给我写信。她在家里赚钱赚得盆满钵满。”

“那你解甲归田时就有一个安乐窝了。”

“当然喽。她能挣大钱，把家打理得很好。”

“咱俩说话，你觉得会不会把别人吵醒？”我问。

“不会的。他们听不见，一个个睡得像死猪。我却不一样，”他说，“神经很紧张。”

“说话小声点儿。”我说，“想抽烟吗？”

在黑暗中，我们老练地抽起了烟。

“你抽烟抽得不多，中尉先生。”

“是的。我快要戒掉了。”

“是呀，”他说，“抽烟是没有好处的。一旦戒掉，恐怕你就不再想它了。你听说过一个故事没有，说的是一个瞎子抽烟时看不见烟，于是就不想抽了？”

“我才不信呢。”

“我也知道这是无稽之谈。”他说，“我只是在哪个地方随便听人说说而已。你知道这是街头巷尾的闲谈。”

随后，我们俩都不作声了。我静静听着蚕吃桑叶的声音。

“你听见那些该死的蚕的声音了吗？”他问，“你可以听见它们在大嚼大咽！”

“怪有意思的。”我说。

“我说，中尉先生，你睡不着觉是不是心里有什么事情？从没见你睡着过。自从我来到你身边，夜里就没见你睡过觉。”

“说不清呀，约翰。”我说，“今年一开春我的状态就不好，一到夜里就心烦。”

“跟我一样。”他说，“我就不该卷入这场战争，神经紧张得要命。”

“也许以后会好的。”

“我说，中尉先生，你参加这场战争到底是为了什么？”

“我也不清楚，约翰。反正我当时就是想参战。”

“想参战？”他说，“这算什么原因呀！”

“咱们说话别声音太大。”我说。

“没事，他们睡得像死猪。”他说，“就是听见，他们也不懂英语。他们一个个狗屁不通！战争结束后回国，你打算干什么？”

“我要到报社谋个差事。”

“芝加哥的报社？”

“也许吧。”

“那个叫布里斯班[100]的人写的东西你看过吗？我老婆特意把他的文章从报上剪下来寄给我看。”

“当然看过。”

“你认识他吗？”

“不认识。但我见过他。”

“我很想认识认识那个人。他是个出类拔萃的作家。我老婆看不懂英语，但她就像我在家时一样照样订报，把社论和体育版剪下来寄给我。”

“你的孩子怎么样？”

“都挺好的。一个女儿现在念小学四年级了。实话说，中尉先生，我要不是因为有孩子，就当不成你的勤务兵，而必须留在前线打仗。”

“很高兴你有孩子。”

“我也是的。她们都很棒，但我想要个儿子。三个女儿，却没有一个儿子，真是怪事！”

“你何不试一试，睡上一觉？”

“不行，我现在睡不着，一点儿睡意都没有，中尉先生。说实话，我倒是为你睡不着觉而担心哩。”

“没事的，约翰。”

“你这么个年轻人却睡不着觉，简直匪夷所思。”

“没事的。这只不过是暂时的。”

“觉是一定要睡的。一个人不睡觉那怎么成！你是不是有什么犯愁的事？心里是不是有什么疙瘩？”

“没有，约翰。我想是没有的。”

“你应该结婚，中尉先生。结了婚就没有犯愁的事了。”

“谁知道呢。”

“婚是应该结的。何不挑一个模样好又有钱的意大利女孩娶过来？你年轻英俊，获得过勋章，还光荣地负过两次伤，女孩子任你挑，想要哪一个就要哪一个。”

“意大利语我说得不够好。”

“你说得挺好的。会不会说意大利语狗屁都不算。你不必跟她们说话，娶过来就是了。”

“让我考虑考虑吧。”

“你还是认识几个女孩的，对不对？”

“当然喽。”

“那就挑一个最有钱的娶过来得啦。就凭着她们在这儿受的教养，个个都可以成为贤妻良母。”

“让我考虑考虑吧。”

“别优柔寡断，中尉先生。应该当机立断！”

“好吧。”

“男大当婚嘛。你不会后悔的。一个人总要结婚的。”

“好吧。”我说，“咱们争取睡上一会儿吧？”

“好吧，中尉先生。我就再试试吧。不过，你可要记住我说的话。”

“我会记住的。”我说，“咱们都睡上一会儿吧，约翰。”

“好的，”他说，“希望这次你能睡着，中尉先生。”

我听见他在铺在稻草窝里的毯子上辗转反侧，后来安静了下来，发出了均匀的呼吸声，又过了一会儿便打起了呼噜。我听他打呼噜听了很长时间，才转而去听蚕虫进食的声音。那些蚕虫吃啊吃的，边吃边把蚕屎拉在桑叶上。这时我有新鲜事可想了，于是就睁着眼躺在黑暗中把我认识的女孩子在脑海里全过了一遍，看她们是否能成为贤妻良母。思索这样的事情是非常有趣的，一时间使得我不再去想钓鳟鱼的事，同时干扰了我的祈祷。不过，我最终还是把思路转回到了钓鳟鱼上，因为我发现自己能记得起所有钓过鱼的小溪，总有新东西可供回味，而女孩子则不然，想一会儿就印象模糊了，就记不起来了。最后，她们的嘴脸全都变得朦朦胧胧，成了一个模样，于是我干脆就不再去想她们了。而祈祷文，我则坚持在念，夜里常常为约翰祈祷。在十月攻势开始之前，他和他的战友已经退役，不再参战了。很高兴他离开了前线，要不然我会很为他担心的。几个月后我到米兰的医院养伤，他来看我，发现我还没有结婚，不由大失所望。直至今日，我仍未结婚，要是叫他知道了，肯定会为我感到难过的。当时他准备回美国，对于婚姻有着坚定的信念，认为结了婚就会事事如意。

The Undefeated

MANUEL GARCIA climbed the stairs to Don Miguel Retana's offce.He set down his suitcase and knocked on the door.There was no answer.Manuel, standing in the hallway, felt there was someone in the room.He felt it through the door.

“Retana，”he said, listening.

There was no answer.

He's there, all right, Manuel thought.

“Retana，”he said and banged the door.

“Who's there?”said someone in the offce.

“Me, Manolo，”Manuel said.

“What do you want?”asked the voice.

“I want to work，”Manuel said.

Something in the door clicked several times and it swung open.Manuel went in, carrying his suitcase.

A little man sat behind a desk at the far side of the room.Over his head was a bull's head, stuffed by a Madrid taxidermist；on the walls were framed photographs and bullfght posters.

The little man sat looking at Manuel.

“I thought they'd killed you，”he said.

Manuel knocked with his knuckles on the desk.The little man satlooking at him across the desk.

“How many corridas you had this year?”Retana asked.

“One，”he answered.

“Just that one?”the little man asked.

“That's all.”

“I read about it in the papers，”Retana said.He leaned back in the chair and looked at Manuel.

Manuel looked up at the stuffed bull.He had seen it often before.He felt a certain family interest in it.It had killed his brother, the promising one, about nine years ago.Manuel remembered the day.There was a brass plate on the oak shield the bull's head was mounted on.Manuel could not read it, but he imagined it was in memory of his brother.Well, he had been a good kid.

The plate said：“The Bull‘Mariposa'of the Duke of Veragua, which accepted 9 varas for 7 caballos, and caused the death of Antonio Garcia, Novillero, April 27，1909.”

Retana saw him looking at the stuffed bull's head.

“The lot the Duke sent me for Sunday will make a scandal，”he said.“They're all bad in the legs.What do they say about them at the Café?”

“I don't know，”Manuel said.“I just got in.”

“Yes，”Retana said.“You still have your bag.”

He looked at Manuel, leaning back behind the big desk.

“Sit down，”he said.“Take off your cap.”

Manuel sat down；his cap off, his face was changed.He looked pale, and his coleta pinned forward on his head, so that it would not show under the cap, gave him a strange look.

“You don't look well，”Retana said.

“I just got out of hospital，”Manuel said.

“I heard they'd cut your leg off，”Retana said.

“No，”said Manuel.“It got all right.”

Retana leaned forward across the desk and pushed a wooden box of cigarettes toward Manuel.

“Have a cigarette，”he said.

“Thanks.”

Manuel lit it.

“Smoke?”he said, offering the match to Retana.

“No，”Retana waved his hand.“I never smoke.”

Retana watched him smoking.

“Why don't you get a job and go to work?”he said.

“I don't want to work，”Manuel said.“I am a bullfghter.”

“There aren't any bullfghters any more，”Retana said.

“I'm a bullfghter，”Manuel said.

“Yes, while you're in there，”Retana said.

Manuel laughed.

Retana sat, saying nothing and looking at Manuel.

“I'll put you in a nocturnal if you want，”Retana offered.

“When?”Manuel asked.

“Tomorrow night.”

“I don't like to substitute for anybody，”Manuel said.That was the way they all got killed.That was the way Salvador got killed.He tapped with his knuckles on the table.

“It's all I've got，”Retana said.

“Why don't you put me on next week?”Manuel suggested.

“You wouldn't draw，”Retana said.“All they want is Litri and Rubito and La Torre.Those kids are good.”

“They'd come to see me get it，”Manuel said, hopefully.

“No, they wouldn't.They don't know who you are any more.”

“I've got a lot of stuff，”Manuel said.

“I'm offering to put you on tomorrow night，”Retana said.“You can work with young Hernandez and kill two novillos after the Charlots.”

“Whose novillos?”Manuel asked.

“I don't know.Whatever stuff they've got in the corrals.What the veterinaries won't pass in the daytime.”

“I don't like to substitute，”Manuel said.

“You can take it or leave it，”Retana said.He leaned forward over the papers.He was no longer interested.The appeal that Manuel had made to him for a moment when he thought of the old days was gone.He would like to get him to substitute for Larita because he could get him cheaply.He could get others cheaply too.He would like to help him though.Still he had given him the chance.It was up to him.

“How much do I get?”Manuel asked.He was still playing with the idea of refusing.But he knew he could not refuse.

“Two hundred and ffty pesetas，”Retana said.He had thought of fve hundred, but when he opened his mouth it said two hundred and ffty.

“You pay Villalta seven thousand，”Manuel said.

“You're not Villalta，”Retana said.

“I know it，”Manuel said.

“He draws it, Manolo，”Retana said in explanation.

“Sure，”said Manuel.He stood up.“Give me three hundred, Retana.”

“All right，”Retana agreed.He reached in the drawer for a paper.

“Can I have ffty now?”Manuel asked.

“Sure，”said Retana.He took a fifty-peseta note out of his pocket-book and laid it, spread out fat, on the table.

Manuel picked it up and put it in his pocket.

“What about a cuadrilla?”he asked.

“There's the boys that always work for me nights，”Retana said.“They're all right.”

“How about picadors?”Manuel asked.

“They're not much，”Retana admitted.

“I've got to have one good pic，”Manuel said.

“Get him then，”Retana said.“Go and get him.”

“Not out of this，”Manuel said.“I'm not paying for any cuadrilla out of sixty duros.”

Retana said nothing but looked at Manuel across the big desk.

“You know I've got to have one good pic，”Manuel said.

Retana said nothing but looked at Manuel from a long way off.

“It isn't right，”Manuel said.

Retana was still considering him, leaning back in his chair, considering him from a long way away.

“There're the regular pics，”he offered.

“I know，”Manuel said.“I know your regular pics.”

Retana did not smile.Manuel knew it was over.

“All I want is an even break，”Manuel said reasoningly.“When I go out there I want to be able to call my shots on the bull.It only takes onegood picador.”

He was talking to a man who was no longer listening.

“If you want something extra，”Retana said，“go and get it.There will be a regular cuadrilla out there.Bring as many of your own pics as you want.The charlotada is over by ten-thirty.”

“All right，”Manuel said.“If that's the way you feel about it.”

“That's the way，”Retana said.

“I'll see you tomorrow night，”Manuel said.

“I'll be out there，”Retana said.

Manuel picked up his suitcase and went out.

“Shut the door，”Retana called.

Manuel looked back.Retana was sitting forward looking at some papers.Manuel pulled the door tight until it clicked.

He went down the stairs and out of the door into the hot brightness of the street.It was very hot in the street and the light on the white buildings was sudden and hard on his eyes.He walked down the shady side of the steep street toward the Puerta del Sol.The shade felt solid and cool as running water.The heat came suddenly as he crossed the intersecting streets.Manuel saw no one he knew in all the people he passed.

Just before the Puerta del Sol he turned into a café.

It was quiet in the café.There were a few men sitting at tables against the wall.At one table four men played cards.Most of the men sat against the wall smoking, empty coffee-cups and liqueur-glasses before them on the tables.Manuel went through the long room to a small room in back.A man sat at a table in the corner asleep.Manuel sat down at one of the tables.

A waiter came in and stood beside Manuel's table.

“Have you seen Zurito?”Manuel asked him.

“He was in before lunch，”the waiter answered.“He won't be back before fve o'clock.”

“Bring me some coffee and milk and a shot of the ordinary，”Manuel said.

The waiter came back into the room carrying a tray with a big coffee-glass and a liqueur-glass on it.In his left hand he held a bottle of brandy.He swung these down to the table and a boy who had followed him poured coffee and milk into the glass from two shiny, spouted pots with long handles.

Manuel took off his cap and the waiter noticed his pigtail pinned forward on his head.He winked at the coffee-boy as he poured out the brandy into the little glass beside Manuel's coffee.The coffee-boy looked at Manuel's pale face curiously.

“You fghting here?”asked the waiter, corking up the bottle.

“Yes，”Manuel said.“Tomorrow.”

The waiter stood there, holding the bottle on one hip.

“You in the Charlie Chaplin's?”he asked.

The coffee-boy looked away, embarrassed.

“No.In the ordinary.”

“I thought they were going to have Chaves and Hernandez，”the waiter said.

“No.Me and another.”

“Who?Chaves or Hernandez?”

“Hernandez, I think.”

“What's the matter with Chaves?”

“He got hurt.”

“Where did you hear that?”

“Retana.”

“Hey, Looie，”the waiter called to the next room，“Chaves got cogida.”

Manuel had taken the wrapper off the lumps of sugar and dropped them into his coffee.He stirred it and drank it down, sweet, hot, and warming in his empty stomach.He drank off the brandy.

“Give me another shot of that，”he said to the waiter.

The waiter uncorked the bottle and poured the glass full, slopping another drink into the saucer.Another waiter had come up in front of the table.The coffee-boy was gone.

“Is Chaves hurt bad?”the second waiter asked Manuel.

“I don't know，”Manuel said.“Retana didn't say.”

“A hell of a lot he cares，”the tall waiter said.Manuel had not seen him before.He must have just come up.

“If you stand in with Retana in this town, you're a made man，”the tall waiter said.“If you aren't in with him, you might just as well go out and shoot yourself.”

“You said it，”the other waiter who had come in said.“You said it then.”

“You're right I said it，”said the tall waiter.“I know what I'm talking about when I talk about that bird.”

“Look what he's done for Villalta，”the frst waiter said.

“And that ain't all，”the tall waiter said.“Look what he's done forMarcial Lalanda.Look what he's done for Nacional.”

“You said it, kid，”agreed the short waiter.

Manuel looked at them, standing talking in front of his table.He had drunk his second brandy.They had forgotten about him.They were not interested in him.

“Look at that bunch of camels，”the tall waiter went on.“Did you ever see this Nacional II?”

“I seen him last Sunday, didn't I?”the original waiter said.

“He's a giraffe，”the short waiter said.

“What did I tell you?”the tall waiter said.“Those are Retana's boys.”

“Say, give me another shot of that，”Manuel said.He had poured the brandy the waiter had slopped over in the saucer into his glass and drank it while they were talking.

The original waiter poured his glass full mechanically, and the three of them went out of the room talking.

In the far corner the man was still asleep, snoring slightly on the intaking breath, his head back against the wall.

Manuel drank his brandy.He felt sleepy himself.It was too hot to go out into the town.Besides there was nothing to do.He wanted to see Zurito.He would go to sleep while he waited.He kicked his suitcase under the table to be sure it was there.Perhaps it would be better to put it back under the seat, against the wall.He leaned down and shoved it under.Then he leaned forward on the table and went to sleep.

When he woke there was someone sitting across the table from him.It was a big man with a heavy brown face like an Indian.He had been sitting there some time.He had waved the waiter away and sat reading thepaper and occasionally looking down at Manuel, asleep, his head on the table.He read the paper laboriously, forming the words with his lips as he read.When it tired him he looked at Manuel.He sat heavily in the chair, his black Cordoba hat tipped forward.

Manuel sat up and looked at him.

“Hullo, Zurito，”he said.

“Hello, kid，”the big man said.

“I've been asleep.”Manuel rubbed his forehead with the back of his fst.

“I thought maybe you were.”

“How's everything?”

“Good.How is everything with you?”

“Not so good.”

They were both silent.Zurito, the picador, looked at Manuel's white face.Manuel looked down at the picador's enormous hands folding the paper to put away in his pocket.

“I got a favor to ask you, Manos，”Manuel said.

Manosduros was Zurito's nickname.He never heard it without thinking of his huge hands.He put them forward on the table self-consciously.

“Let's have a drink，”he said.

“Sure，”said Manuel.

The waiter came and went and came again.He went out of the room looking back at the two men at the table.

“What's the matter, Manolo?”Zurito set down his glass.

“Would you pic two bulls for me tomorrow night?”Manuel asked, looking at Zurito across the table.

“No，”said Zurito.“I'm not pic-ing.”

Manuel looked down at his glass.He had expected that answer；now he had it.Well, he had it.

“I'm sorry, Manolo, but I'm not pic-ing.”Zurito looked at his hands.

“That's all right，”Manuel said.

“I'm too old，”Zurito said.

“I just asked you，”Manuel said.

“Is it the nocturnal tomorrow?”

“That's it.I fgured if I had just one good pic, I could get away with it.”

“How much are you getting?”

“Three hundred pesetas.”

“I get more than that for pic-ing.”

“I know，”said Manuel.“I didn't have any right to ask you.”

“What do you keep on doing it for?”Zurito asked.“Why don't you cut off your coleta, Manolo?”

“I don't know，”Manuel said.

“You're pretty near as old as I am，”Zurito said.

“I don't know，”Manuel said.“I got to do it.If I can fx it so that I get an even break, that's all I want.I got to stick with it, Manos.”

“No you don't.”

“Yes, I do.I've tried keeping away from it.”

“I know how you feel.But it isn't right.You ought to get out and stay out.”

“I can't do it.Besides, I've been going good lately.”

Zurito looked at his face.

“You've been in the hospital.”

“But I was going great when I got hurt.”

Zurito said nothing.He tipped the cognac out of his saucer into his glass.

“The papers said they never saw a better faena，”Manuel said.

Zurito looked at him.

“You know when I get going I'm good，”Manuel said.

“You're too old，”the picador said.

“No，”said Manuel.“You're ten years older than I am.”

“With me it's different.”

“I'm not too old，”Manuel said.

They sat silent, Manuel watching the picador's face.

“I was going great till I got hurt，”Manuel offered.

“You ought to have seen me, Manos，”Manuel said, reproachfully.

“I don't want to see you，”Zurito said.“It makes me nervous.”

“You haven't seen me lately.”

“I've seen you plenty.”

Zurito looked at Manuel, avoiding his eyes.

“You ought to quit it, Manolo.”

“I can't，”Manuel said.“I'm going good now, I tell you.”

Zurito leaned forward, his hands on the table.

“Listen.I'll pic for you and if you don't go big tomorrow night, you'll quit.See?Will you do that?”

“Sure.”

Zurito leaned back, relieved.

“You got to quit，”he said.“No monkey business.You got to cut the coleta.”

“I won't have to quit，”Manuel said.“You watch me.I've got the stuff.”

Zurito stood up.He felt tired from arguing.

“You got to quit，”he said.“I'll cut your coleta myself.”

“No, you won't，”Manuel said.“You won't have a chance.”

Zurito called the waiter.

“Come on，”said Zurito.“Come on up to the house.”

Manuel reached under the seat for his suitcase.He was happy.He knew Zurito would pic for him.He was the best picador living.It was all simple now.

“Come on up to the house and we'll eat，”Zurito said.

***

Manuel stood in the patio de caballos waiting for the Charlie Chaplins to be over.Zurito stood beside him.Where they stood it was dark.The high door that led into the bull-ring was shut.Above them they heard a shout, then another shout of laughter.Then there was silence.Manuel liked the smell of the stables about the patio de caballos.It smelt good in the dark.There was another roar from the arena and then applause, prolonged applause, going on and on.

“You ever seen these fellows?”Zurito asked, big and looming beside Manuel in the dark.

“No，”Manuel said.

“They're pretty funny，”Zurito said.He smiled to himself in the dark.

The high, double, tight-ftting door into the bull-ring swung open and Manuel saw the ring in the hard light of the arc-lights, the plaza, dark all the way around, rising high；around the edge of the ring were running and bowing two men dressed like tramps, followed by a third in the uniform of a hotel-boy who stooped and picked up the hats and canes thrown down on to the sand and tossed them back up into the darkness.

The electric light went on in the patio.

“I'll climb onto one of those ponies while you collect the kids，”Zurito said.

Behind them came the jingle of the mules, coming out to go into the arena and be hitched onto the dead bull.

The members of the cuadrilla, who had been watching the burlesque from the runway between the barrera and the seats, came walking back and stood in a group talking, under the electric light in the patio.A good-looking lad in a silver-and-orange suit came up to Manuel and smiled.

“I'm Hernandez，”he said and put out his hand.

Manuel shook it.

“They're regular elephants we've got tonight，”the boy said cheerfully.

“They're big ones with horns，”Manuel agreed.

“You drew the worst lot，”the boy said.

“That's all right，”Manuel said.“The bigger they are, the more meat for the poor.”

“Where did you get that one?”Hernandez grinned.

“That's an old one，”Manuel said.“You line up your cuadrilla, so Ican see what I've got.”

“You've got some good kids，”Hernandez said.He was very cheerful.He had been on twice before in nocturnals and was beginning to get a following in Madrid.He was happy the fght would start in a few minutes.

“Where are the pics?”Manuel asked.

“They're back in the corrals fighting about who gets the beautiful horses，”Hernandez grinned.

The mules came through the gate in a rush, the whips snapping, bells jangling, and the young bull plowing a furrow of sand.

They formed up for the paseo as soon as the bull had gone through.

Manuel and Hernandez stood in front.The youths of the cuadrillas were behind, their heavy capes furled over their arms.In black, the four picadors, mounted, holding their steel-tipped push-poles erect in the half-dark of the corral.

“It's a wonder Retana wouldn't give us enough light to see the horses by，”one picador said.

“He knows we'll be happier if we don't get too good a look at these skins，”another pic answered.

“This thing I'm on barely keeps me off the ground，”the frst picador said.

“Well, they're horses.”

“Sure, they're horses.”

They talked, sitting their gaunt horses in the dark.

Zurito said nothing.He had the only steady horse of the lot.He had tried him, wheeling him in the corrals and he responded to the bit and the spurs.He had taken the bandage off his right eye and cut the strings wherethey had tied his ears tight shut at the base.He was a good, solid horse, solid on his legs.That was all he needed.He intended to ride him all through the corrida.He had already, since he had mounted sitting in the half-dark in the big, quilted saddle, waiting for the paseo, pic-ed through the whole corrida in his mind.The other picadors went on talking on both sides of him.He did not hear them.

The two matadors stood together in front of their three peones, their capes furled over their left arms in the same fashion.Manuel was thinking about the three lads in back of him.They were all three Madrileños, like Hernandez, boys about nineteen.One of them, a gypsy, serious, aloof, and dark faced, he liked the look of.He turned.

“What's your name, kid?”he asked the gypsy.

“Fuentes，”the gypsy said.

“That's a good name，”Manuel said.

The gypsy smiled, showing his teeth.

“You take the bull and give him a little run when he comes out，”Manuel said.

“All right，”the gypsy said.His face was serious.He began to think about just what he would do.

“Here she goes，”Manuel said to Hernandez.

“All right.We'll go.”

Heads up, swinging with the music, their right arms swinging free, they stepped out, crossing the sanded arena under the arc-lights, the cuadrillas opening out behind, the picadors riding after, behind came the bull-ring servants and the jingling mules.The crowd applauded Hernandez as they marched across the arena.Arrogant, swinging, they looked straightahead as they marched.

They bowed before the president, and the procession broke up into its component parts.The bullfghters went over to the barrera and changed their heavy mantles for the light fghting capes.The mules went out.The picadors galloped jerkily around the ring, and two rode out the gate they had come in by.The servants swept the sand smooth.

Manuel drank a glass of water poured for him by one of Retana's deputies, who was acting as his manager and sword-handler.Hernandez came over from speaking with his own manager.

“You got a good hand, kid，”Manuel complimented him.

“They like me，”Hernandez said happily.

“How did the paseo go?”Manuel asked Retana's man.

“Like a wedding，”said the handler.“Fine.You came out like Joselito and Belmonte.”

Zurito rode by, a bulky equestrian statue.He wheeled his horse and faced him toward the toril on the far side of the ring where the bull would come out.It was strange under the arc-light.He pic-ed in the hot afternoon sun for big money.He didn't like this arc-light business.He wished they would get started.

Manuel went up to him.

“Pic him, Manos，”he said.“Cut him down to size for me.”

“I'll pic him, kid，”Zurito spat on the sand.“I'll make him jump out of the ring.”

“Lean on him, Manos，”Manuel said.

“I'll lean on him，”Zurito said.“What's holding it up?”

“He's coming now，”Manuel said.

Zurito sat there, his feet in the box-stirrups, his great legs in the buckskin-covered armor gripping the horse, the reins in his left hand, the long pic held in his right hand, his broad hat well down over his eyes to shade them from the lights, watching the distant door of the toril.His horse's ears quivered.Zurito patted him with his left hand.

The red door of the toril swung back and for a moment Zurito looked into the empty passage-way far across the arena.Then the bull came out in a rush, skidding on his four legs as he came out under the lights, then charging in a gallop, moving softly in a fast gallop, silent except as he woofed through wide nostrils as he charged, glad to be free after the dark pen.

In the frst row of seats, slightly bored, leaning forward to write on the cement wall in front of his knees, the substitute bullfght critic of El Heraldo scribbled：“Campagnero, Negro，42，came out at 90 miles an hour with plenty of gas—”

Manuel, leaning against the barrera, watching the bull, waved his hand and the gypsy ran out, trailing his cape.The bull, in full gallop, pivoted and charged the cape, his head down, his tail rising.The gypsy moved in a zigzag, and as he passed, the bull caught sight of him and abandoned the cape to charge the man.The gyp sprinted and vaulted the red fence of the barrera as the bull struck it with his horns.He tossed into it twice with his horns, banging into the wood blindly.

The critic of El Heraldo lit a cigarette and tossed the match at the bull, then wrote in his notebook，“large and with enough horns to satisfy the cash customers, Campagnero showed a tendency to cut into the terrain of the bullfghters.”

Manuel stepped out on the hard sand as the bull banged into the fence.Out of the corner of his eye he saw Zurito sitting the white horse close to the barrera, about a quarter of the way around the ring to the left.Manuel held the cape close in front of him, a fold in each hand, and shouted at the bull.“Huh！Huh！”The bull turned, seemed to brace against the fence as he charged in a scramble, driving into the cape as Manuel side-stepped, pivoted on his heels with the charge of the bull, and swung the cape just ahead of the horns.At the end of the swing he was facing the bull again and held the cape in the same position close in front of his body, and pivoted again as the bull recharged.Each time, as he swung, the crowd shouted.

Four times he swung with the bull, lifting the cape so it billowed full, and each time bringing the bull around to charge again.Then, at the end of the ffth swing, he held the cape against his hip and pivoted, so the cape swung out like a ballet dancer's skirt and wound the bull around himself like a belt, to step clear, leaving the bull facing Zurito on the white horse, come up and planted frm, the horse facing the bull, its ears forward, its lips nervous, Zurito, his hat over his eyes, leaning forward, the long pole sticking out before and behind in a sharp angle under his right arm, held half-way down, the triangular iron point facing the bull.

El Heraldo's second-string critic, drawing on his cigarette, his eyes on the bull, wrote：“the veteran Manolo designed a series of acceptable veronicas, ending in a very Belmontistic recorte that earned applause from the regulars, and we entered the tercio of the cavalry.”

Zurito sat his horse, measuring the distance between the bull and the end of the pic.As he looked, the bull gathered himself together andcharged, his eyes on the horse's chest.As he lowered his head to hook, Zurito sunk the point of the pic in the swelling hump of muscle above the bull's shoulder, leaned all his weight on the shaft, and with his left hand pulled the white horse into the air, front hoofs pawing, and swung him to the right as he pushed the bull under and through so that the horns passed safely under the horse's belly and the horse came down, quivering, the bull's tail brushing his chest as he charged the cape Hernandez offered him.

Hernandez ran sideways, taking the bull out and away with the cape, toward the other picador.He fxed him with a swing of the cape, squarely facing the horse and rider, and stepped back.As the bull saw the horse he charged.The picador's lance slid along his back, and as the shock of the charge lifted the horse, the picador was already half-way out of the saddle, lifting his right leg clear as he missed with the lance and falling to the left side to keep the horse between him and the bull.The horse, lifted and gored, crashed over with the bull driving into him, the picador gave a shove with his boots against the horse and lay clear, waiting to be lifted and hauled away and put on his feet.

Manuel let the bull drive into the fallen horse；he was in no hurry, the picador was safe；besides, it did a picador like that good to worry.He'd stay on longer next time.Lousy pics！He looked across the sand at Zurito a little way out from the barrera, his horse rigid, waiting.

“Huh！”he called to the bull，“Tomar！”holding the cape in both hands so it would catch his eye.The bull detached himself from the horse and charged the cape, and Manuel, running sideways and holding the cape spread wide, stopped, swung on his heels, and brought the bull sharplyaround facing Zurito.

“Campagnero accepted a pair of varas for the death of one rosinante, with Hernandez and Manolo at the quites，”El Heraldo's critic wrote.“He pressed on the iron and clearly showed he was no horse-lover.The veteran Zurito resurrected some of his old stuff with the pike-pole, notably the suerte—”

“Olé！Olé！”the man sitting beside him shouted.The shout was lost in the roar of the crowd, and he slapped the critic on the back.The critic looked up to see Zurito, directly below him, leaning far out over his horse, the length of the pic rising in a sharp angle under his armpit, holding the pic almost by the point, bearing down with all his weight, holding the bull off, the bull pushing and driving to get at the horse, and Zurito, far out, on top of him, holding him, holding him, and slowly pivoting the horse against the pressure, so that at last he was clear.Zurito felt the moment when the horse was clear and the bull could come past, and relaxed the absolute steel lock of his resistance, and the triangular steel point of the pic ripped in the bull’s hump of shoulder muscle as he tore loose to fnd Hernandez’s cape before his muzzle.He charged blindly into the cape and the boy took him out into the open arena.

Zurito sat patting his horse and looking at the bull charging the cape that Hernandez swung for him under the bright light while the crowd shouted.

“You see that one?”he said to Manuel.

“It was a wonder，”Manuel said.

“I got him that time，”Zurito said.“Look at him now.”

At the conclusion of a closely turned pass of the cape the bull slidto his knees.He was up at once, but far out across the sand Manuel and Zurito saw the shine of the pumping flow of blood, smooth against the black of the bull's shoulder.

“I got him that time，”Zurito said.

“He's a good bull，”Manuel said.

“If they gave me another shot at him, I'd kill him，”Zurito said.

“They'll change the thirds on us，”Manuel said.

“Look at him now，”Zurito said.

“I got to go over there，”Manuel said, and started on a run for the other side of the ring, where the monos were leading a horse out by the bridle toward the bull, whacking him on the legs with rods and all, in a procession, trying to get him toward the bull, who stood, dropping his head, pawing, unable to make up his mind to charge.

Zurito, sitting his horse, walking him toward the scene, not missing any detail, scowled.

Finally the bull charged, the horse leaders ran for the barrera, the picador hit too far back, and the bull got under the horse, lifted him, threw him onto his back.

Zurito watched.The monos, in their red shirts, running out to drag the picador clear.The picador, now on his feet, swearing and fopping his arms.Manuel and Hernandez standing ready with their capes.And the bull, the great black bull, with a horse on his back, hooves dangling, the bridle caught in the horns.Black bull with a horse on his back, staggering short-legged, then arching his neck and lifting, thrusting, charging to slide the horse off, horse sliding down.Then the bull into a lunging charge at the cape Manuel spread for him.

The bull was slower now, Manuel felt.He was bleeding badly.There was a sheen of blood all down his fank.

Manuel offered him the cape again.There he came, eyes open, ugly, watching the cape.Manuel stepped to the side and raised his arms, tightening the cape ahead of the bull for the veronica.

Now he was facing the bull.Yes, his head was going down a little.He was carrying it lower.That was Zurito.

Manuel fopped the cape；there he comes；he side-stepped and swung in another veronica.He's shooting awfully accurately, he thought.He's had enough fght, so he's watching now.He's hunting now.Got his eye on me.But I always give him the cape.

He shook the cape at the bull；there he comes；he sidestepped.Awful close that time.I don't want to work that close to him.

The edge of the cape was wet with blood where it had swept along the bull's back as he went by.

All right, here's the last one.

Manuel, facing the bull, having turned with him each charge, offered the cape with his two hands.The bull looked at him.Eyes watching, horns straight forward, the bull looked at him, watching.

“Huh！”Manuel said，“Toro！”and leaning back, swung the cape forward.Here he comes.He side-stepped, swung the cape in back of him, and pivoted, so the bull followed a swirl of cape and then was left with nothing, fxed by the pass, dominated by the cape.Manuel swung the cape under his muzzle with one hand, to show the bull was fxed, and walked away.

There was no applause.

Manuel walked across the sand toward the barrera, while Zurito rode out of the ring.The trumpet had blown to change the act to the planting of the banderillos while Manuel had been working with the bull.He had not consciously noticed it.The monos were spreading canvas over the two dead horses and sprinkling sawdust around them.

Manuel came up to the barrera for a drink of water.Retana's man handed him the heavy porous jug.

Fuentes, the tall gypsy, was standing holding a pair of banderillos, holding them together, slim, red sticks, fshhook points out.He looked at Manuel.

“Go on out there，”Manuel said.

The gypsy trotted out.Manuel set down the jug and watched.He wiped his face with his handkerchief.

The critic of El Heraldo reached for the bottle of warm champagne that stood between his feet, he took a drink, and fnished his paragraph.

“—the aged Manolo rated no applause for a vulgar series of lances with the cape and we entered the third of the palings.”

Alone in the centre of the ring the bull stood, still fixed.Fuentes, tall, fat-backed, walking toward him arrogantly, his arms spread out, the two slim, red sticks, one in each hand, held by the fngers, points straight forward.Fuentes walked forward.Back of him and to one side was a peon with a cape.The bull looked at him and was no longer fxed.

His eyes watched Fuentes, now standing still.Now he leaned back, calling to him.Fuentes twitched the two banderillos and the light on the steel points caught the bull's eye.

His tail went up and he charged.

He came straight, his eyes on the man.Fuentes stood still, leaning back, the banderillos pointing forward.As the bull lowered his head to hook, Fuentes leaned backward, his arms came together and rose, his two hands, touching, the banderillos two descending red lines, and leaning forward drove the points into the bull's shoulder, leaning far in over the bull's horns and pivoting on the two upright sticks, his legs tight together, his body, curving to one side to let the bull pass.

“Olé！”from the crowd.

The bull was hooking wildly, jumping like a trout, all four feet off the ground.The red shafts of the banderillos tossed as he jumped.

Manuel, standing at the barrera, noticed that he hooked always to the right.

“Tell him to drop the next pair on the right，”he said to the kid who started to run out to Fuentes with the new banderillos.

A heavy hand fell on his shoulder.It was Zurito.

“How do you feel, kid?”he asked.

Manuel was watching the bull.

Zurito leaned forward on the barrera, leaning the weight of his body on his arms.Manuel turned to him.

“You're going good，”Zurito said.

Manuel shook his head.He had nothing to do now until the next third.The gypsy was very good with the banderillos.The bull would come to him in the next third in good shape.He was a good bull.It had all been easy up to now.The fnal stuff with the sword was all he worried over.He did not really worry.He did not even think about it.But standing there he had a heavy sense of apprehension.He looked out at the bull, planning hisfaena, his work with the red cloth that was to reduce the bull, to make him manageable.

The gypsy was walking out toward the bull again, walking heel-and-toe, insultingly, like a ballroom dancer, the red shafts of the banderillos, twitching with his walk.The bull watched him, not fixed now, hunting him, but waiting to get close enough so he could be sure of getting him, getting the horns into him.

As Fuentes walked forward the bull charged.Fuentes ran across the quarter of a circle as the bull charged and, as he passed running backwards, stopped, swung forward, rose on his toes, arms straight out, and sunk the banderillos straight down into the tight of the big shoulder muscles as the bull missed him.

The crowd were wild about it.

“That kid won't stay in this night stuff long，”Retana's man said to Zurito.

“He's good，”Zurito said.

“Watch him now.”

They watched.

Fuentes was standing with his back against the barrera.Two of the cuadrilla were back of him, with their capes ready to fop over the fence to distract the bull.

The bull, with his tongue out, his barrel heaving, was watching the gypsy.He thought he had him now.Back against the red planks.Only a short charge away.The bull watched him.

The gypsy bent back, drew back his arms, the banderillos pointing at the bull.He called to the bull, stamped one foot.The bull was suspicious.He wanted the man.No more barbs in the shoulder.

Fuentes walked a little closer to the bull.Bent back.Called again.Somebody in the crowd shouted a warning.

“He's too damn close，”Zurito said.

“Watch him，”Retana's man said.

Leaning back, inciting the bull with the banderillos, Fuentes jumped, both feet off the ground.As he jumped the bull's tail rose and he charged.Fuentes came down on his toes, arms straight out, whole body arching forward, and drove the shafts straight down as he swung his body clear of the right horn.

The bull crashed into the barrera where the flopping capes had attracted his eye as he lost the man.

The gypsy came running along the barrera toward Manuel, taking the applause of the crowd.His vest was ripped where he had not quite cleared the point of the horn.He was happy about it, showing it to the spectators.He made a tour of the ring.Zurito saw him go by, smiling, pointing to his vest.He smiled.

Somebody else was planting the last pair of banderillos.Nobody was paying any attention.

Retana's man tucked a baton inside the red cloth of a muleta, folded the cloth over it, and handed it over the barrera to Manuel.He reached in the leather sword-case, took out a sword, and holding it by its leather scabbard, reached it over the fence to Manuel.Manuel pulled the blade out by the red hilt and the scabbard fell limp.

He looked at Zurito.The big man saw he was sweating.

“Now you get him, kid，”Zurito said.

Manuel nodded.

“He's in good shape，”Zurito said.

“Just like you want him，”Retana's man assured him.

Manuel nodded.

The trumpeter, up under the roof, blew for the fnal act, and Manuel walked across the arena toward where, up in the dark boxes, the president must be.

In the front row seats the substitute bullfght critic of El Heraldo took a long drink of warm champagne.He had decided it was not worthwhile to write a running story and would write up the corrida back in the offce.What the hell was it anyway?Only a nocturnal.If he missed anything he would get it out of the morning papers.He took another drink of the champagne.He had a date at Maxim's at twelve.Who were these bullfghters anyway?Kids and bums.A bunch of bums.He put his pad of paper in his pocket and looked over toward Manuel, standing very much alone in the ring, gesturing with his hat in a salute toward a box he could not see high up in the dark plaza.Out in the ring the bull stood quiet, looking at nothing.

“I dedicate this bull to you, Mr.President, and to the public of Madrid, the most intelligent and generous in the world，”was what Manuel was saying.It was a formula.He said it all.It was a little too long for nocturnal use.

He bowed at the dark, straightened, tossed his hat over his shoulder, and carrying the muleta in his left hand and the sword in his right, walked out toward the bull.

Manuel walked toward the bull.The bull looked at him；his eyeswere quick.Manuel noticed the way the banderillos hung down on his left shoulder and the steady sheen of blood from Zurito's pic-ing.He noticed the way the bull's feet were.As he walked forward, holding the muleta in his left hand and the sword in his right, he watched the bull's feet.The bull could not charge without gathering his feet together.Now he stood square on them, dully.

Manuel walked toward him, watching his feet.This was all right.He could do this.He must work to get the bull's head down, so he could go in past the horns and kill him.He did not think about the sword, not about killing the bull.He thought about one thing at a time.The coming things oppressed him, though.Walking forward, watching the bull's feet, he saw successively his eyes, his wet muzzle and the wide, forward-pointing spread of his horns.The bull had light circles about his eyes.His eyes watched Manuel.He felt he was going to get this little one with the white face.

Standing still now and spreading the red cloth of the muleta with the sword, pricking the point into the cloth so that the sword, now held in his left hand, spread the red fannel like the jib of a boat, Manuel noticed the points of the bull's horns.One of them was splintered from banging against the barrera.The other was sharp as a porcupine quill.Manuel noticed while spreading the muleta that the white base of the horn was stained red.While he noticed these things he did not lose sight of the bull's feet.The bull watched Manuel steadily.

He's on the defensive now, Manuel thought.He's reserving himself.I've got to bring him out of that and get his head down.Always get his head down.Zurito had his head down once, but he's come back.He'llbleed when I start him going and that will bring it down.

Holding the muleta, with the sword in his left hand widening it in front of him, he called to the bull.

The bull looked at him.

He leaned back insultingly and shook the widespread fannel.

The bull saw the muleta.It was a bright scarlet under the arc-light.The bull's legs tightened.

Here he comes.Whoosh！Manuel turned as the bull came and raised the muleta so that it passed over the bull's horns and swept down his broad back from head to tail.The bull had gone clean up in the air with the charge.Manuel had not moved.

At the end of the pass the bull turned like a cat coming around a corner and faced Manuel.

He was on the offensive again.His heaviness was gone.Manuel noted the fresh blood shining down the black shoulder and dripping down the bull's leg.He drew the sword out of the muleta and held it in his right hand.The muleta held low down in his left hand, leaning toward the left, he called to the bull.The bull's legs tightened, his eyes on the muleta.Here he comes, Manuel thought.Yuh！

He swung with the charge, sweeping the muleta ahead of the bull, his feet frm, the sword following the curve, a point of light under the arcs.

The bull recharged as the pase natural finished and Manuel raised the muleta for a pase de pecho.Firmly planted, the bull came by his chest under the raised muleta.Manuel leaned his head back to avoid the clattering banderillo shafts.The hot, black bull body touched his chest as it passed.

Too damn close, Manuel thought.Zurito, leaning on the barrera, spoke rapidly to the gypsym who trotted out toward Manuel with a cape.Zurito pulled his hat down low and looked out across the arena at Manuel.

Manuel was facing the bull again, the muleta held low and to the left.The bull's head was down as he watched the muleta.

“If it was Belmonte doing that stuff, they'd go crazy，”Retana's man said.

Zurito said nothing.He was watching Manuel out in the centre of the arena.

“Where did the boss dig this fellow up?”Retana's man asked.

“Out of the hospital，”Zurito said.

“That's where he's going damn quick，”Retana's man said.Zurito turned on him.

“Knock on that，”he said, pointing to the barrera.

“I was just kidding, man，”Retana's man said.

“Knock on that wood.”

Retana's man leaned forward and knocked three times on the barrera.

“Watch the faena，”Zurito said.

Out in the centre of the ring, under the lights, Manuel was kneeling, facing the bull, and as he raised the muleta in both hands the bull charged, tail up.

Manuel swung his body clear and, as the bull recharged, brought around the muleta in a half-circle that pulled the bull to his knees.

“Why, that one's a great bullfghter，”Retana's man said.

“No, he's not，”said Zurito.

Manuel stood up and, the muleta in his left hand, the sword in hisright, acknowledged the applause from the dark plaza.

The bull had humped himself up from his knees and stood waiting, his head hung low.

Zurito spoke to two of the other lads of the cuadrilla and they ran out to stand back of Manuel with their capes.There were four men back of him now.Hernandez had followed him since he frst came out with the muleta.Fuentes stood watching, his cape held against his body, tall, in repose, watching lazy-eyed.Now the two came up.Hernandez motioned them to stand one at each side.Manuel stood alone, facing the bull.

Manuel waved back the men with the capes.Stepping back cautiously, they saw his face was white and sweating.

Didn't they know enough to keep back?Did they want to catch the bull's eye with the capes after he was fxed and ready?He had enough to worry about without that kind of thing.

The bull was standing, his four feet square, looking at the muleta.Manuel furled the muleta in his left hand.The bull's eyes watched it.His body was heavy on his feet.He carried his head low, but not too low.

Manuel lifted the muleta at him.The bull did not move.Only his eyes watched.

He's all lead, Manuel thought.He's all square.He's framed right.He'll take it.

He thought in bullfight terms.Sometimes he had a thought and a particular piece of slang would not come into his mind and he could not realize the thought.His instincts and knowledge worked automatically, and his brain worked slowly and in words.He knew all about bulls.He did not have to think about them.He just did the right thing.His eyesnoted things and his body performed the necessary measures without thought.If he thought about it, he would be gone.

Now, facing the bull, he was conscious of many things at the same time.There were the horns, the one splintered, the other smoothly sharp, the need to profle himself toward the left horn, lance himself short and straight, lower the muleta so the bull would follow it, and, going in over the horns, put the sword all the way into a little spot about as big as a fve-peseta piece straight in back of the neck, between the sharp pitch of the bull's shoulders.He must do all this and must then come out from between the horns.He was conscious he must do all this, but his only thought was in words：“Corto y derecho.”

“Corto y derecho，”he thought, furling the muleta.Short and straight.Corto y derecho, he drew the sword out of the muleta, profiled on the splintered left horn, dropped the muleta across his body, so his right hand with the sword on the level with his eye made the sign of the cross, and, rising on his toes, sighted along the dipping blade of the sword at the spot high up between the bull's shoulders.

Corto y derecho he lanced himself on the bull.

There was a shock, and he felt himself go up in the air.He pushed on the sword as he went up and over, and it few out of his hand.He hit the ground and the bull was on him.Manuel, lying on the ground, kicked at the bull's muzzle with his splippered feet.Kicking, kicking, the bull after him, missing him in his excitement, bumping him with his head, driving the horns into the sand.Kicking like a man keeping a ball in the air, Manuel kept the bull from getting a clean thrust at him.

Manuel felt the wind on his back from the capes fopping at the bull, and then the bull was gone, gone over him in a rush.Dark, as his belly went over.Not even stepped on.

Manuel stood up and picked up the muleta.Fuentes handed him the sword.It was bent where it had struck the shoulder-blade.Manuel straightened it on his knee and ran toward the bull, standing now beside one of the dead horses.As he ran, his jacket fopped where it had been ripped under the armpit.

“Get him out of there，”Manuel shouted to the gypsy.The bull had smelled the blood of the dead horse and ripped into the canvas cover with his horns.He charged Fuentes's cape, with the canvas hanging from his splintered horn, and the crowd laughed.Out in the ring, he tossed his head to rid himself of the canvas.Hernandez, running up from behind him, grabbed the end of the canvas and neatly lifted it off the horn.

The bull followed it in a half-charge and stopped still.He was on the defensive again.Manuel was walking toward him with the sword and muleta.Manuel swung the muleta before him.The bull would not charge.

Manuel profled toward the bull, sighting along the dipping blade of the sword.The bull was motionless, seemingly dead on his feet, incapable of another charge.

Manuel rose to his toes, sighting along the steel, and charged.

Again there was the shock and he felt himself being borne back in a rush, to strike hard on the sand.There was no chance of kicking this time.The bull was on top of him.Manuel lay as though dead, his head on his arms, and the bull bumped him.Bumped his back, bumped his face in the sand.He felt the horn go into the sand between his folded arms.The bull hit him in the small of the back.His face drove into the sand.The horndrove through one of his sleeves and the bull ripped it off.Manuel was tossed clear and the bull followed the capes.

Manuel got up, found the sword and muleta, tried the point of the sword with his thumb, and then ran toward the barrera for a new sword.

Retana's man handed him the sword over the edge of the barrera.

“Wipe off your face，”he said.

Manuel, running again toward the bull, wiped his bloody face with his handkerchief.He had not seen Zurito.Where was Zurito?

The cuadrilla had stepped away from the bull and waited with their capes.The bull stood, heavy and dull again after the action.

Manuel walked toward him with the muleta.He stopped and shook it.The bull did not respond.He passed it right and left, left and right before the bull's muzzle.The bull's eyes watched it and turned with the swing, but he would not charge.He was waiting for Manuel.

Manuel was worried.There was nothing to do but go in.Corto y derecho.He profled close to the bull, crossed the muleta in front of his body and charged.As he pushed in the sword, he jerked his body to the left to clear the horn.The bull passed him and the sword shot up in the air, twinkling under the arc-lights, to fall red-hilted on the sand.

Manuel ran over and picked it up.It was bent and he straightened it over his knee.

As he came running toward the bull, fixed again now, he passed Hernandez standing with his cape.

“He's all bone，”the boy said encouragingly.

Manuel nodded, wiping his face.He put the bloody handkerchief in his pocket.

There was the bull.He was close to the barrera now.Damn him.Maybe he was all bone.Maybe there was not any place for the sword to go in.The hell there wasn't！He'd show them.

He tried a pass with the muleta and the bull did not move.Manuel chopped the muleta back and forth in front of the bull.Nothing doing.

He furled the muleta, drew the sword out, profled and drove in on the bull.He felt the sword buckle as he shoved it in, leaning his weight on it, and then it shot high in the air, end-over-ending into the crowd.Manuel had jerked clear as the sword jumped.

The first cushions thrown down out of the dark missed him.Then one hit him in the face, his bloody face looking toward the crowd.They were coming down fast.Spotting the sand.Somebody threw an empty champagne-bottle from close range.It hit Manuel on the foot.He stood there watching the dark where the things were coming from.Then something whished through the air and struck by him.Manuel leaned over and picked it up.It was his sword.He straightened it over his knee and gestured with it to the crowd.

“Thank you，”he said.“Thank you.”

Oh, the dirty bastards！Dirty bastards！Oh, the lousy, dirty bastards！He kicked into a cushion as he ran.

There was the bull.The same as ever.All right, you dirty, lousy bastard！

Manuel passed the muleta in front of the bull's black muzzle.

Nothing doing.

You won't.All right.He stepped close and jammed the sharp peak of the muleta into the bull's damp muzzle.

The bull was on him as he jumped back and as he tripped on a cushion he felt the horn go into him, into his side.He grabbed the horn with his two hands and rode backward, holding tight on to the place.The bull tossed him and he was clear.He lay still.It was all right.The bull was gone.

He got up coughing and feeling broken and gone.The dirty bastards！

“Give me the sword，”he shouted.“Give me the stuff.”

Fuentes came up with the muleta and the sword.

Hernandez put his arm around him.

“Go on to the infrmary, man，”he said.“Don't be a damn fool.”

“Get away from me，”Manuel said.“Get to hell away from me.”

He twisted free.Hernandez shrugged his shoulders.Manuel ran toward the bull.

There was the bull standing, heavy, frmly planted.

All right, you bastard！Manuel drew the sword out of the muleta, sighted with the same movement, and fung himself onto the bull.He felt the sword go in all the way.Right up to the guard.Four fngers and his thumb into the bull.The blood was hot on his knuckles, and he was on top of the bull.

The bull lurched with him as he lay on, and seemed to sink；then he was standing clear.He looked at the bull going down slowly over on his side, then suddenly four feet in the air.

Then he gestured at the crowd, his hand warm from the bull blood.

All right, you bastards！He wanted to say something, but he started to cough.It was hot and choking.He looked down for the muleta.He must go over and salute the president.President hell！He was sitting downlooking at something.It was the bull.His four feet up.Thick tongue out.Things crawling around on his belly and under his legs.Crawling where the hair was thin.Dead bull.To hell with the bull！To hell with them all！He started to get to his feet and commenced to cough.He sat down again, coughing.Somebody came and pushed him up.

They carried him across the ring to the infrmary, running with him across the sand, standing blocked at the gate as the mules came in, then around under the dark passage-way, men grunting as they took him up the stairway, and then laid him down.

The doctor and two men in white were waiting for him.They laid him out on the table.They were cutting away his shirt.Manuel felt tired.His whole chest felt scalding inside.He started to cough and they held something to his mouth.Everybody was very busy.

There was an electric light in his eyes.He shut his eyes.

He heard someone coming very heavily up the stairs.Then he did not hear it.Then he heard a noise far off.That was the crowd.Well, somebody would have to kill his other bull.They had cut away all his shirt.The doctor smiled at him.There was Retana.

“Hello, Retana！”Manuel said.He could not hear his voice.Retana smiled at him and said something.Manuel could not hear it.

Zurito stood beside the table, bending over where the doctor was working.He was in his picador clothes, without his hat.

Zurito said something to him.Manuel could not hear it.

Zurito was speaking to Retana.One of the men in white smiled and handed Retana a pair of scissors.Retana gave them to Zurito.Zurito said something to Manuel.He could not hear it.

To hell with this operating-table！He'd been on plenty of operating-tables before.He was not going to die.There would be a priest if he was going to die.

Zurito was saying something to him.Holding up the scissors.

That was it.They were going to cut off his coleta.They were going to cut off his pigtail.

Manuel sat up on the operating-table.The doctor stepped back, angry.Someone grabbed him and held him.

“You couldn't do a thing like that, Manos，”he said.

He heard suddenly, clearly, Zurito's voice.

“That's all right，”Zurito said.“I won't do it.I was joking.”

“I was going good，”Manuel said.“I didn't have any luck.That was all.”

Manuel lay back.They had put something over his face.It was all familiar.He inhaled deeply.He felt very tired.He was very, very tired.They took the thing away from his face.

“I was going good，”Manuel said weakly.“I was going great.”

Retana looked at Zurito and started for the door.

“I'll stay here with him，”Zurito said.

Retana shrugged his shoulders.

Manuel opened his eyes and looked at Zurito.

“Wasn't I going good, Manos?”he asked, for confrmation.

“Sure，”said Zurito.“You were going great.”

The doctor's assistant put the cone over Manuel's face and he inhaled deeply.Zurito stood awkwardly, watching.

Hills Like White Elephants

THE hills across the valley of the Ebro were long and white.On this side there was no shade and no trees and the station was between two lines of rails in the sun.Close against the side of the station there was the warm shadow of the building and a curtain, made of strings of bamboo beads, hung across the open door into the bar, to keep out fies.The American and the girl with him sat at a table in the shade, outside the building.It was very hot and the express from Barcelona would come in forty minutes.It stopped at this junction for two minutes and went on to Madrid.

“What should we drink?”the girl asked.She had taken off her hat and put it on the table.

“It's pretty hot，”the man said.

“Let's drink beer.”

“Dos cervezas，”the man said into the curtain.

“Big ones?”a woman asked from the doorway.

“Yes.Two big ones.”

The woman brought two glasses of beer and two felt pads.She put the felt pads and the beer glasses on the table and looked at the man and the girl.The girl was looking off at the line of hills.They were white in the sun and the country was brown and dry.

“They look like white elephants，”she said.

“I've never seen one.”The man drank his beer.

“No, you wouldn't have.”

“I might have，”the man said.“Just because you say I wouldn't have doesn't prove anything.”

The girl looked at the bead curtain.“They've painted something on it，”she said.“What does it say?”

“Anis del Toro.It's a drink.”

“Could we try it?”

The man called“Listen”through the curtain.The woman came out from the bar.

“Four reales.”

“We want two Anis del Toros.”

“With water?”

“Do you want it with water?”

“I don't know，”the girl said.“Is it good with water?”

“It's all right.”

“You want them with water?”asked the woman.

“Yes, with water.”

“It tastes like liquorice，”the girl said and put the glass down.

“That's the way with everything.”

“Yes，”said the girl.“Everything tastes of liquorice.Especially all the things you've waited so long for, like absinthe.”

“Oh, cut it out.”

“You started it，”the girl said.“I was being amused.I was having a fne time.”

“Well, let's try and have a fne time.”

“All right.I was trying.I said the mountains looked like white elephants.Wasn't that bright?”

“That was bright.”

“I wanted to try this new drink.That's all we do, isn't it—look at things and try new drinks?”

“I guess so.”

The girl looked across at the hills.

“They're lovely hills，”she said.“They don't really look like white elephants.I just meant the coloring of their skin through the trees.”

“Should we have another drink?”

“All right.”

The warm wind blew the bead curtain against the table.

“The beer's nice and cool，”the man said.

“It's lovely，”the girl said.

“It's really an awfully simple operation, Jig，”the man said.“It's not really an operation at all.”

The girl looked at the ground the table legs rested on.

“I know you wouldn't mind it, Jig.It's really not anything.It's just to let the air in.”

The girl did not say anything.

“I'll go with you and I'll stay with you all the time.They just let the air in and then it's all perfectly natural.”

“Then what will we do afterwards?”

“We'll be fne afterwards.Just like we were before.”

“What makes you think so?”

“That's the only thing that bothers us.It's the only thing that's made us unhappy.”

The girl looked at the bead curtain, put her hand out and took hold of two of the strings of beads.

“And you think then we'll be all right and be happy.”

“I know we will.You don't have to be afraid.I've known lots of people that have done it.”

“So have I，”said the girl.“And afterward they were all so happy.”

“Well，”the man said，“if you don't want to you don't have to.I wouldn't have you do it if you didn't want to.But I know it's perfectly simple.”

“And you really want to?”

“I think it's the best thing to do.But I don't want you to do it if you don't really want to.”

“And if I do it you'll be happy and things will be like they were and you'll love me?”

“I love you now.You know I love you.”

“I know.But if I do it, then it will be nice again if I say things are like white elephants, and you'll like it?”

“I'll love it.I love it now but I just can't think about it.You know how I get when I worry.”

“If I do it you won't ever worry?”

“I won't worry about that because it's perfectly simple.”

“Then I'll do it.Because I don't care about me.”

“What do you mean?”

“I don't care about me.”

“Well, I care about you.”

“Oh, yes.But I don't care about me.And I'll do it and then everything will be fne.”

“I don't want you to do it if you feel that way.”

The girl stood up and walked to the end of the station.Across, on the other side, were felds of grain and trees along the banks of the Ebro.Far away, beyond the river, were mountains.The shadow of a cloud moved across the feld of grain and she saw the river through the trees.

“And we could have all this，”she said.“And we could have everything and every day we make it more impossible.”

“What did you say?”

“I said we could have everything.”

“We can have everything.”

“No, we can't.”

“We can have the whole world.”

“No, we can't.”

“We can go everywhere.”

“No, we can't.It isn't ours any more.”

“It's ours.”

“No, it isn't.And once they take it away, you never get it back.”

“But they haven't taken it away.”

“We'll wait and see.”

“Come on back in the shade，”he said.“You mustn't feel that way.”

“I don't feel any way，”the girl said.“I just know things.”

“I don't want you to do anything that you don't want to do—”

“Nor that isn't good for me，”she said.“I know.Could we haveanother beer?”

“All right.But you've got to realize—”

“I realize，”the girl said.“Can't we maybe stop talking?”

They sat down at the table and the girl looked across at the hills on the dry side of the valley and the man looked at her and at the table.

“You've got to realize，”he said，“that I don't want you to do it if you don't want to.I'm perfectly willing to go through with it if it means anything to you.”

“Doesn't it mean anything to you?We could get along.”

“Of course it does.But I don't want anybody but you.I don't want anyone else.And I know it's perfectly simple.”

“Yes, you know it's perfectly simple.”

“It's all right for you to say that, but I do know it.”

“Would you do something for me now?”

“I'd do anything for you.”

“Would you please please please please please please please stop talking?”

He did not say anything but looked at the bags against the wall of the station.There were labels on them from all the hotels where they had spent nights.

“But I don't want you to，”he said，“I don't care anything about it.”

“I'll scream，”the girl said.

The woman came out through the curtains with two glasses of beer and put them down on the damp felt pads.“The train comes in fve minutes，”she said.

“What did she say?”asked the girl.

“That the train is coming in fve minutes.”

The girl smiled brightly at the woman, to thank her.

“I'd better take the bags over to the other side of the station，”the man said.She smiled at him.

“All right.Then come back and we'll fnish the beer.”

He picked up the two heavy bags and carried them around the station to the other tracks.Coming back, he walked through the bar-room, where people waiting for the train were drinking.He drank an Anis at the bar and looked at the people.They were all waiting reasonably for the train.He went out through the bead curtain.She was sitting at the table and smiled at him.

“Do you feel better?”he asked.

“I feel fne，”she said.“There's nothing wrong with me.I feel fne.”

The Killers

THE door of Henry's lunch-room opened and two men came in.They sat down at the counter.

“What's yours?”George asked them.

“I don't know，”one of the men said.“What do you want to eat, Al?”

“I don't know，”said Al.“I don't know what I want to eat.”

Outside it was getting dark.The street-light came on outside the window.The two men at the counter read the menu.From the other end of the counter Nick Adams watched them.He had been talking to George when they came in.

“I'll have a roast pork tenderloin with apple sauce and mashed potatoes，”the frst man said.

“It isn't ready yet.”

“What the hell do you put it on the card for?”

“That's the dinner，”George explained.“You can get that at six o'clock.”

George looked at the clock on the wall behind the counter.

“It's fve o'clock.”

“The clock says twenty minutes past fve，”the second man said.

“It's twenty minutes fast.”

“Oh, to hell with the clock，”the frst man said.“What have you gotto eat?”

“I can give you any kind of sandwiches，”George said.“You can have ham and eggs, bacon and eggs, liver and bacon, or a steak.”

“Give me chicken croquettes with green peas and cream sauce and mashed potatoes.”

“That's the dinner.”

“Everything we want's the dinner, eh?That's the way you work it.”

“I can give you ham and eggs, bacon and eggs, liver—”

“I'll take ham and eggs，”the man called Al said.He wore a derby hat and a black overcoat buttoned across the chest.His face was small and white and he had tight lips.He wore a silk muffer and gloves.

“Give me bacon and eggs，”said the other man.He was about the same size as Al.Their faces were different, but they were dressed like twins.Both wore overcoats too tight for them.They sat leaning forward, their elbows on the counter.

“Got anything to drink?”Al asked.

“Silver beer, bevo, ginger-ale，”George said.

“I mean you got anything to drink?”

“Just those I said.”

“This is a hot town，”said the other.“What do they call it?”

“Summit.”

“Ever hear of it?”Al asked his friend.

“No，”said the friend.

“What do you do here nights?”Al asked.

“They eat the dinner，”his friend said.“They all come here and eat the big dinner.”

“That's right，”George said.

“So you think that's right?”Al asked George.

“Sure.”

“You're a pretty bright boy, aren't you?”

“Sure，”said George.

“Well, you're not，”said the other little man.“Is he, Al?”

“He's dumb，”said Al.He turned to Nick.“What's your name?”

“Adams.”

“Another bright boy，”Al said.“Ain't he a bright boy, Max?”

“The town's full of bright boys，”Max said.

George put the two platters, one of ham and eggs, the other of bacon and eggs, on the counter.He set down two side dishes of fried potatoes and closed the wicket into the kitchen.

“Which is yours?”he asked Al.

“Don't you remember?”

“Ham and eggs.”

“Just a bright boy，”Max said.He leaned forward and took the ham and eggs.Both men ate with their gloves on.George watched them eat.

“What are you looking at?”Max looked at George.

“Nothing.”

“The hell you were.You were looking at me.”

“Maybe the boy meant it for a joke Max，”Al said.

George laughed.

“You don't have to laugh，”Max said to him.“You don't have to laugh at all, see?”

“All right，”said George.

“So he thinks it's all right，”Max turned to Al.“He thinks it's all right.That's a good one.”

“Oh, he's a thinker，”Al said.They went on eating.

“What's the bright boy's name down the counter?”Al asked Max.

“Hey, bright boy，”Max said to Nick.“You go around on the other side of the counter with your boy friend.”

“What's the idea?”Nick asked.

“There isn't any idea.”

“You better go around, bright boy，”Al said.Nick went around behind the counter.

“What's the idea?”George asked.

“None of your damn business，”Al said.“Who's out in the kitchen?”

“The nigger.”

“What do you mean the nigger?”

“The nigger that cooks.”

“Tell him to come in.”

“What's the idea?”

“Tell him to come in.”

“Where do you think you are?”

“We know damn well where we are，”the man called Max said.“Do we look silly?”

“You talk silly，”Al said to him.“What the hell do you argue with this kid for?Listen，”he said to George，“tell the nigger to come out here.”

“What are you going to do to him?”

“Nothing.Use your head, bright boy.What would we do to a nigger?”

George opened the slit that opened back into the kitchen.“Sam，”he called.“Come in here a minute.”

The door of the kitchen opened and the nigger came in.“What was it?”he asked.The two men at the counter took a look at him.

“All right, nigger.You stand right there，”Al said.

Sam, the nigger, standing in his apron, looked at the two men sitting at the counter.“Yes, sir，”he said.Al got down from his stool.

“I'm going back to the kitchen with the nigger and bright boy，”he said.“Go on back to the kitchen, nigger.You go with him, bright boy.”The little man walked after Nick and Sam, the cook, back into the kitchen.The door shut after them.The man called Max sat at the counter opposite George.He didn't look at George but looked in the mirror that ran along back of the counter.Henry's had been made over from a saloon into a lunch-counter.

“Well, bright boy，”Max said, looking into the mirror，“why don't you say something?”

“What's it all about?”

“Hey, Al，”Max called，“bright boy wants to know what it's all about.”

“Why don't you tell him?”Al's voice came from the kitchen.

“What do you think it's all about?”

“I don't know.”

“What do you think?”

Max looked into the mirror all the time he was talking.

“I wouldn't say.”

“Hey, Al, bright boy says he wouldn't say what he thinks it's all about.”“I can hear you, all right，”Al said from the kitchen.He had propped open the slit that dishes passed through into the kitchen with a catsup bottle.“Listen, bright boy，”he said from the kitchen to George.“Stand a little further along the bar.You move a little to the left, Max.”He was like a photographer arranging for a group picture.

“Talk to me, bright boy，”Max said.“What do you think's going to happen?”

George did not say anything.

“I'll tell you，”Max said.“We're going to kill a Swede.Do you know a big Swede named Ole Andreson?”

“Yes.”

“He comes here to eat every night, don't he?”

“Sometimes he comes here.”

“He comes here at six o'clock, don't he?”

“If he comes.”

“We know all that, bright boy，”Max said.“Talk about something else.Ever go to the movies?”

“Once in a while.”

“You ought to go to the movies more.The movies are fine for a bright boy like you.”

“What are you going to kill Ole Andreson for?What did he ever do to you?”

“He never had a chance to do anything to us.He never even seen us.”

“And he's only going to see us once，”Al said from the kitchen.

“What are you going to kill him for, then?”George asked.

“We're killing him for a friend.Just to oblige a friend, bright boy.”

“Shut up，”said Al from the kitchen.“You talk too goddam much.”

“Well, I got to keep bright boy amused.Don't I, bright boy?”

“You talk too damn much，”Al said.“The nigger and my bright boy are amused by themselves.I got them tied up like a couple of girl friends in the convent.”

“I suppose you were in a convent.”

“You never know.”

“You were in a kosher convent.That's where you were.”

George looked up at the clock.

“If anybody comes in you tell them the cook is off, and if they keep after it, you tell them you'll go back and cook yourself.Do you get that, bright boy?”

“All right，”George said.“What you going to do with us afterwards?”

“That'll depend，”Max said.“That's one of those things you never know at the time.”

George looked up at the clock.It was a quarter past six.The door from the street opened.A street-car motorman came in.

“Hello, George，”he said.“Can I get supper?”

“Sam's gone out，”George said.“He'll be back in about half an hour.”

“I'd better go up the street，”the motorman said.George looked at the clock.It was twenty minutes past six.

“That was nice, bright boy，”Max said.“You're a regular little gentleman.”

“He knew I'd blow his head off.”Al said from the kitchen.

“No，”said Max.“It ain't that.Bright boy is nice.He's a nice boy.I like him.”

At six ffty-fve George said：“He's not coming.”

Two other people had been in the lunch-room.Once George had gone out to the kitchen and made a ham-and-egg sandwich“to go”that a man wanted to take with him.Inside the kitchen he saw Al, his derby hat tilted back, sitting on a stool beside the wicket with the muzzle of a sawed-off shotgun resting on the ledge.Nick and the cook were back to back in the corner, a towel tied in each of their mouths.George had cooked the sandwich, wrapped it up in oiled paper, put it in a bag, brought it in, and the man had paid for it and gone out.

“Bright boy can do everything，”Max said.“He can cook and everything.You'd make some girl a nice wife, bright boy.”

“Yes?”George said.“Your friend, Ole Andreson, isn't going to come.”

“We'll give him ten minutes，”Max said.

Max watched the mirror and the clock.The hands of the clock marked seven o'clock, and then fve minutes past seven.

“Come on, Al，”said Max.“We better go.He's not coming.”

“Better give him fve minutes，”Al said from the kitchen.

In the five minutes a man came in, and George explained that the cook was sick.

“Why the hell don't you get another cook?”the man asked.“Aren't you running a lunchcounter?”He went out.

“Come on, Al，”Max said.

“What about the two bright boys and the nigger?”

“They're all right.”

“You think so?”

“Sure.We're through with it.”

“I don't like it，”said Al.“It's sloppy.You talk too much.”

“Oh, what the hell，”said Max.“We got to keep amused, haven't we?”

“You talk too much, all the same，”Al said.He came out from the kitchen.The cut-off barrels of the shotgun made a slight bulge under the waist of his too tight-fitting overcoat.He straightened his coat with his gloved hands.

“So long, bright boy，”he said to George.“You got a lot of luck.”

“That's the truth，”Max said.“You ought to play the races, bright boy.”

The two of them went out of the door.George watched them, through the window, pass under the arc-light and cross the street.In their tight overcoats and derby hats they looked like a vaudeville team.George went back through the swinging-door into the kitchen and untied Nick and the cook.

“I don't want any more of that，”said Sam, the cook.“I don't want any more of that.”

Nick stood up.He had never had a towel in his mouth before.

“Say，”he said.“What the hell?”He was trying to swagger it off.

“They were going to kill Ole Andreson，”George said.“They were going to shoot him when he came in to eat.”

“Ole Andreson?”

“Sure.”

The cook felt the corners of his mouth with his thumbs.

“They all gone?”he asked.

“Yeah，”said George.“They're gone now.”

“I don't like it，”said the cook.“I don't like any of it at all.”

“Listen，”George said to Nick.“You better go see Ole Andreson.”

“All right.”

“You better not have anything to do with it at all，”Sam, the cook, said.“You better stay way out of it.”

“Don't go if you don't want to，”George said.

“Mixing up in this ain't going to get you anywhere，”the cook said.“You stay out of it.”

“I'll go see him，”Nick said to George.“Where does he live?”

The cook turned away.

“Little boys always know what they want to do，”he said.

“He lives up at Hirsch's rooming-house，”George said to Nick.

“I'll go up there.”

Outside the arc-light shone through the bare branches of a tree.Nick walked up the street beside the car-tracks and turned at the next arc-light down a side-street.Three houses up the street was Hirsch's rooming-house.Nick walked up the two steps and pushed the bell.A woman came to the door.

“Is Ole Andreson here?”

“Do you want to see him?”

“Yes, if he's in.”

Nick followed the woman up a fight of stairs and back to the end of the corridor.She knocked on the door.

“Who is it?”

“It's somebody to see you, Mr.Andreson，”the woman said.

“It's Nick Adams.”

“Come in.”

Nick opened the door and went into the room.Ole Andreson was lying on the bed with all his clothes on.He had been a heavyweight prize-fighter and he was too long for the bed.He lay with his head on two pillows.He did not look at Nick.

“What was it?”he asked.

“I was up at Henry's，”Nick said，“and two fellows came in and tied up me and the cook, and they said they were going to kill you.”

It sounded silly when he said it.Ole Andreson said nothing.

“They put us out in the kitchen，”Nick went on.“They were going to shoot you when you came in to supper.”

Ole Andresen looked at the wall and did not say anything.

“George thought I'd better come and tell you about it.”

“There isn't anything I can do about it，”Ole Andreson said.

“I'll tell you what they were like.”

“I don't want to know what they were like，”Ole Andreson said.He looked at the wall.“Thanks for coming to tell me about it.”

“That's all right.”

Nick looked at the big man lying on the bed.

“Don't you want me to go and see the police?”

“No，”Ole Andresen said.“That wouldn't do any good.”

“Isn't there something I could do?”

“No.There ain't anything to do.”

“Maybe it was just a bluff.”

“No.It ain't just a bluff.”

Ole Andresen rolled over toward the wall.

“The only thing is，”he said, talking toward the wall，“I just can't make up my mind to go out.I been in here all day.”

“Couldn't you get out of town?”

“No，”Ole Andresen said.“I'm through with all that running around.”

He looked at the wall.

“There ain't anything to do now.”

“Couldn't you fx it up some way?”

“No.I got in wrong.”He talked in the same fat voice.“There ain't anything to do.After a while I'll make up my mind to go out.”

“I better go back and see George，”Nick said.

“So long，”said Ole Andreson.He did not look toward Nick.“Thanks for coming around.”

Nick went out.As he shut the door he saw Ole Andreson with all his clothes on, lying on the bed looking at the wall.

“He's been in his room all day，”the landlady said downstairs.“I guess he don't feel well.I said to him：‘Mr.Andreson, you ought to go out and take a walk on a nice fall day like this，'but he didn't feel like it.”

“He doesn't want to go out.”

“I'm sorry he don't feel well，”the woman said.“He's an awfully nice man.He was in the ring, you know.”

“I know it.”

“You'd never know it except for the way his face is，”the woman said.They stood talking just inside the street door.“He's just as gentle.”

“Well, good night, Mrs.Hirsch，”Nick said.

“I'm not Mrs.Hirsch”the woman said.“She owns the place.I just look after it for her, I'm Mrs.Bell.”

“Well, good night, Mrs.Bell，”Nick said.

“Good night，”the woman said.

Nick walked up the dark street to the corner under the arc-light, and then along the car-tracks to Henry's eating-house.George was inside, back of the counter.

“Did you see Ole?”

“Yes，”said Nick.“He's in his room and he won't go out.”

The cook opened the door from the kitchen when he heard Nick's voice.

“I don't even listen to it，”he said and shut the door.

“Did you tell him about it?”George asked.

“Sure.I told him, but he knows what it's all about.”

“What's he going to do?”

“Nothing.”

“They'll kill him.”

“I guess they will.”

“He must have got mixed up in something in Chicago.”

“I guess so，”said Nick.

“It's a hell of a thing.”

“It's an awful thing，”Nick said.

They did not say anything.George reached down for a towel and wiped the counter.

“I wonder what he did?”Nick said.

“Double-crossed somebody.That's what they kill them for.”

“I'm going to get out of this town，”Nick said.

“Yes，”said George.“That's a good thing to do.”

“I can't stand to think about him waiting in the room and knowing he's going to get it.It's too damned awful.”

“Well，”said George，“you better not think about it.”

Che Ti Dice La Patria

THE road of the pass was hard and smooth and not yet dusty in the early morning.Below were the hills with oak and chestnut trees, and far away below was the sea.On the other side were snowy mountains.

We came down from the pass through wooded country.There were bags of charcoal piled beside the road, and through the trees we saw charcoal-burners'huts.It was Sunday and the road, rising and falling, but always dropping away from the altitude of the pass, went through the scrub woods and through villages.

Outside the villages there were fields with vines.The fields were brown and the vines coarse and thick.The houses were white, and in the streets the men, in their Sunday clothes, were playing bowls.Against the walls of some of the houses there were pear trees, their branches candelabraed against the white walls.The pear trees had been sprayed, and the walls of the houses were stained a metallic blue-green by the spray vapor.There were small clearings around the villages where the vines grew, and then the woods.

In a village, twenty kilometers above Spezia, there was a crowd in the square, and a young man carrying a suitcase came up to the car and asked us to take him in to Spezia.

“There are only two places, and they are occupied，”I said.We hadan old Ford coupé.

“I will ride on the outside.”

“You will be uncomfortable.”

“That makes nothing, I must go to Spezia.”

“Should we take him?”I asked Guy.

“He seems to be going anyway，”Guy said.The young man handed in a parcel through the window.

“Look after this，”he said.Two men tied his suitcase on the back of the car, above our suitcases.He shook hands with everyone, explained that to a Fascist and a man as used to traveling as himself there was no discomfort, and climbed up on the running-board on the left-hand side of the car, holding on inside, his right arm through the open window.

“You can start，”he said.The crowd waved.He waved with his free hand.

“What did he say?”Guy asked me.

“That we could start.”

“Isn't he nice?”Guy said.

The road followed a river.Across the river were mountains.The sun was taking the frost out of the grass.It was bright and cold and the air came through the open windshield.

“How do you think he likes it out there?”Guy was looking up the road.His view out of his side of the car was blocked by our guest.The young man projected from the side of the car like the fgurehead of a ship.He had turned his coat collar up and pulled his hat down and his nose looked cold in the wind.

“Maybe he'll get enough of it，”Guy said.“That's the side our bumtire's on.”

“Oh, he'd leave us if we blew out，”I said.“He wouldn't get his traveling clothes dirty.”

“Well, I don't mind him，”Guy said—“except the way he leans out on the turns.”

The woods were gone；the road had left the river to climb；the radiator was boiling；the young man looked annoyedly and suspiciously at the steam and rusty water；the engine was grinding, with both Guy's feet on the frst-speed pedal, up and up, back and forth and up, and fnally, out level.The grinding stopped, and in the new quiet there was a great churning bubbling in the radiator.We were at the top of the last range above Spezia and the sea.The road descended with short, barely rounded turns.Our guest hung out on the turns and nearly pulled the top-heavy car over.

“You can't tell him not to，”I said to Guy.“It's his sense of self-preservation.”

“The great Italian sense.”

“The greatest Italian sense.”

We came down around curves, through deep dust, the dust powdering the olive trees.Spezia spread below along the sea.The road flattened outside the town.Our guest put his head in the window.

“I want to stop.”

“Stop it，”I said to Guy.

We slowed up, at the side of the road.The young man got down, went to the back of the car and untied the suitcase.

“I stop here, so you won't get into trouble carrying passengers，”hesaid.“My package.”

I handed him the package.He reached in his pocket.

“How much do I owe you?”

“Nothing.”

“Why not?”

“I don't know，”I said.

“Then thanks，”the young man said, not“thank you，”or“thank you very much，”or“thank you a thousand times，”all of which you formerly said in Italy to a man when he handed you a time-table or explained about a direction.The young man uttered the lowest form of the word“thanks”and looked after us suspiciously as Guy started the car.I waved my hand at him.He was too dignifed to reply.We went on into Spezia.

“That's a young man that will go a long way in Italy，”I said to Guy.

“Well，”said Guy，“he went twenty kilometers with us.”

A MEAL IN SPEZIA

We came into Spezia looking for a place to eat.The street was wide and the houses high and yellow.We followed the tram-track into the centre of town.On the walls of the houses were stenciled eye-bugging portraits of Mussolini, with hand-painted“vivas”，the double V in black paint with drippings of paint down the wall.Side-streets went down to the harbor.It was bright and the people were all out for Sunday.The stone paving had been sprinkled and there were damp stretches in the dust.We went close to the curb to avoid a train.

“Let's eat somewhere simple，”Guy said.

We stopped opposite two restaurant signs.We were standing across the street and I was buying the papers.The two restaurants were side by side.A woman standing in the doorway of one smiled at us and we crossed the street and went in.

It was dark inside and at the back of the room three girls were sitting at a table with an old woman.Across from us, at another table, sat a sailor.He sat there neither eating nor drinking.Further back, a young man in a blue suit was writing at a table.His hair was pomaded and shining and he was very smartly dressed and clean-cut looking.

The light came through the doorway, and through the window where vegetables, fruit, steaks, and chops were arranged in a show-case.A girl came and took our order and another girl stood in the doorway.We noticed that she wore nothing under her house dress.The girl who took our order put her arm around Guy's neck while we were looking at the menu.There were three girls in all, and they all took turns going and standing in the doorway.The old woman at the table in the back of the room spoke to them and they sat down again with her.

There was no doorway leading from the room except into the kitchen.A curtain hung over it.The girl who had taken our order came in from the kitchen with spaghetti.She put it on the table and brought a bottle of red wine and sat down at the table.

“Well，”I said to Guy，“you wanted to eat at some place simple.”

“This isn't simple, this is complicated.”

“What do you say?”asked the girl.“Are you Germans?”

“South Germans，”I said.“The South Germans are a gentle, lovable people.”

“Don't understand，”she said.

“What's the mechanics of this place?”Guy asked.“Do I have to let her put her arm around my neck?”

“Certainly，”I said.“Mussolini has abolished brothels.This is a restaurant.”

The girl wore a one-piece dress.She leaned forward against the table and put her hands on her breasts and smiled.She smiled better on one side than on the other and turned the good side toward us.The charm of the good side had been enhanced by some event which had smoothed the other side of her nose in, as warm wax can be smoothed.Her nose, however, did not look like warm wax.It was very cold and frmed, only smoothed in.“You like me?”she asked Guy.

“He adores you，”I said.“But he doesn't speak Italian.”

“Ich spreche Deutsch，”she said, and stroked Guy's hair.

“Speak to the lady in your native tongue, Guy.”

“Where do you come from?”asked the lady.

“Potsdam.”

“And you will stay here now for a little while?”

“In this so dear Spezia?”I asked.

“Tell her we have to go，”said Guy.“Tell her we are very ill, and have no money.”

“My friend is a misogynist，”I said，“an old German misogynist.”

“Tell him I love him.”

I told him.

“Will you shut your mouth and get us out of here?”Guy said.The lady had placed another arm around his neck.“Tell him he is mine，”shesaid.I told him.

“Will you get us out of here?”

“You are quarreling，”the lady said.“You do not love one another.”

“We are Germans，”I said proudly，“old South Germans.”

“Tell him he is a beautiful boy，”the lady said.Guy is thirty-eight and takes some pride in the fact that he is taken for a traveling salesman in France.“You are a beautiful boy，”I said.

“Who says so?”Guy asked，“you or her?”

“She does.I'm just your interpreter.Isn't that what you got me in on this trip for?”

“I'm glad it's her，”said Guy.“I don't want to have to leave you here too.”

“I don't know.Spezia's a lovely place.”

“Spezia，”the lady said.“You are talking about Spezia.”

“Lovely place，”I said.

“It is my country，”she said.“Spezia is my home and Italy is my country.”

“She says that Italy is her country.”

“Tell her it looks like her country，”Guy said.

“What have you for dessert?”I asked.

“Fruit，”she said.“We have bananas.”

“Bananas are all right，”Guy said.“They've got skins on.”

“Oh, he takes bananas，”the lady said.She embraced Guy.

“What does she say?”he asked, keeping his face out of the way.

“She is pleased because you take bananas.”

“Tell her I don't take bananas.”

“The signor does not take bananas.”

“Ah，”said the lady, crestfallen，“he doesn't take bananas.”

“Tell her I take a cold bath every morning，”Guy said.

“The signor takes a cold bath every morning.”

“No understand，”the lady said.

Across from us, the property sailor had not moved.No one in the place paid any attention to him.

“We want the bill，”I said.

“Oh, no.You must stay.”

“Listen，”the clean-cut young man said from the table where he was writing，“let them go.These two are worth nothing.”

The lady took my hand.“You won't stay?You won't ask him to stay?”

“We have to go，”I said.“We have to get to Pisa, or if possible, Firenze, tonight.We can amuse ourselves in those cities at the end of the day.It is now the day.In the day we must cover distance.”

“To stay a little while is nice.”

“To travel is necessary during the light of day.”

“Listen，”the clean-cut young man said.“Don't bother to talk with these two.I tell you they are worth nothing and I know.”

“Bring us the bill，”I said.She brought the bill from the old woman and went back and sat at the table.Another girl came in from the kitchen.She walked the length of the room and stood in the doorway.

“Don't bother with these two，”the clean-cut young man said in a wearied voice.“Come and eat.They are worth nothing.”

We paid the bill and stood up.All the girls, the old woman, and theclean-cut young man sat down at the table together.The property sailor sat with his head in his hands.No one had spoken to him all the time we were at lunch.The girl brought us our change that the old woman counted out for her and went back to her place at the table.We left a tip on the table and went out.When we were seated in the car ready to start, the girl came out and stood in the door.We started and I waved to her.She did not wave, but stood there looking after us.

AFTER THE RAIN

It was raining hard when we passed through the suburbs of Genoa and, even going very slowly behind the tram-cars and the motor trucks, liquid mud splashed onto the sidewalks, so that people stepped into the doorways as they saw us coming.In San Pier d'Arena, the industrial suburb outside of Genoa, there is a wide street with two car-tracks and we drove down the centre to avoid sending the mud on to the men going home from work.On our left was the Mediterranean.There was a big sea running and waves broke and the wind blew the spray against the car.A riverbed that, when we had passed, going into Italy, had been wide, stony and dry, was running brown and up to the banks.The brown water discolored the sea and as the waves thinned and cleared in breaking, the light came through the yellow water and the crests, detached by the wind, blew across the road.

A big car passed us, going fast, and a sheet of muddy water rose up and over our wind-shield and radiator.The automatic wind-shield cleaner moved back and forth, spreading the flm over the glass.We stopped andate lunch at Sestri.There was no heat in the restaurant and we kept our hats and coats on.We could see the car outside, through the window.It was covered with mud and was stopped beside some boats that had been pulled up beyond the waves.In the restaurant you could see your breath.

The pasta asciutta was good；the wine tasted of alum, and we poured water into it.Afterward the waiter brought beefsteak and fried potatoes.A man and a woman sat at the far end of the restaurant.He was middle-aged and she was young and wore black.All during the meal she would blow out her breath in the cold damp air.The man would look at it and shake his head.They ate without talking and the man held her hand under the table.She was good-looking and they seemed very sad.They had a traveling-bag with them.

We had the papers and I read the account of the Shanghai fghting aloud to Guy.After the meal, he left with the waiter in search for a place which did not exist in the restaurant, and I cleaned off the wind-shield, the lights and the license plates with a rag.Guy came back and we backed the car out and started.The waiter had taken him across the road and into an old house.The people in the house were suspicious and the waiter had remained with Guy to see nothing was stolen.

“Although I don't know how, me not being a plumber, they expected me to steal anything，”Guy said.

As we came up on a headland beyond the town, the wind struck the car and nearly tipped it over.

“It's good, it blows us away from the sea，”Guy said.

“Well，”I said，“they drowned Shelley somewhere along here.”

“That was down by Viareggio，”Guy said.“Do you remember whatwe came to this country for?”

“Yes，”I said，“but we didn't get it.”

“We'll be out of it tonight.”

“If we can get past Ventimiglia.”

“We'll see.I don't like to drive this coast at night.”It was early afternoon and the sun was out.Below, the sea was blue with whitecaps running toward Savona.Back, beyond the cape, the brown and blue waters joined.Out ahead of us, a tramp steamer was going up the coast.

“Can you still see Genoa?”Guy asked.

“Oh, yes.”

“That next big cape ought to put it out of sight.”

“We'll see it a long time yet.I can still see Portofno Cape behind it.”

Finally we could not see Genoa.I looked back as we came out and there was only the sea, and below, in the bay, a line of beach with fshing-boats and above, on the side of the hill, a town and then capes far down the coast.

“It's gone now，”I said to Guy.

“Oh, it's been gone a long time now.”

“But we couldn't be sure till we got way out.”

There was a sign with a picture of an S-turn and Svolta Pericolosa.The road curved around the headland and the wind blew through the crack in the wind-shield.Below the cape was a fat stretch beside the sea.The wind had dried the mud and the wheels were beginning to lift dust.On the fat road we passed a Fascist riding a bicycle, a heavy revolver in a holster on his back.He held the middle of the road on his bicycle and we turned out for him.He looked up at us as we passed.Ahead there was a railwaycrossing, and as we came toward it the gates went down.

As we waited, the Fascist came up on his bicycle.The train went by and Guy started the engine.

“Wait，”the bicycle man shouted from behind the car.“Your number's dirty.”

I got out with a rag.The number had been cleaned at lunch.

“You can read it，”I said.

“You think so?”

“Read it.”

“I cannot read it.It is dirty.”

I wiped it off with the rag.

“How's that?”

“Twenty-fve lire.”

“What?”I said.“You could have read it.It's only dirty from the state of the roads.”

“You don't like Italian roads?”

“They are dirty.”

“Fifty lire.”He spat in the road.“Your car is dirty and you are dirty too.”

“Good.And give me a receipt with your name.”

He took out a receipt book, made in duplicate, and perforated, so one side could be given to the customer, and the other side flled in and kept as a stub.There was no carbon to record what the customer's ticket said.

“Give me ffty lire.”

He wrote in indelible pencil, tore out the slip and handed it to me.I read it.

“This is for twenty-fve lire.”

“A mistake，”he said, and changed the twenty-fve to ffty.

“And now the other side.Make it ffty in the part you keep.”

He smiled a beautiful Italian smile and wrote something on the receipt stub, holding it so I could not see.

“Go on，”he said，“before your number gets dirty again.”

We drove for two hours after it was dark and slept in Mentone that night.It seemed very cheerful and clean and sane and lovely.We had driven from Ventimiglia to Pisa and Florence, across the Romagna to Rimini, back through Forlì，Imola, Bologna, Parma, Piacenza and Genoa, to Ventimiglia again.The whole trip had only taken ten days.Naturally, in such a short trip, we had no opportunity to see how things were with the country or the people.

Fifty Grand

“How are you going yourself Jack?”I asked him.

“You seen this Walcott ?”he says.

“Just in the gym.”

“Well，”Jack says，“I'm going to need a lot of luck with that boy.”

“He can't hit you, Jack，”Soldier said.

“I wish to hell he couldn't.”

“He couldn't hit you with a handful of bird-shot.”

“Bird-shot'd be all right，”Jack says.“I wouldn't mind bird-shot any.”

“He looks easy to hit，”I said.

“Sure，”Jack says，“he ain't going to last long.He ain't going to last like you and me, Jerry.But right now he's got everything.”

“You'll left-hand him to death.”

“Maybe，”Jack says.“Sure.I got a chance to.”

“Handle him like you handled Kid Lewis”

“Kid Lewis，”Jack said.“That kike！”

The three of us, Jack Brennan, Soldier Bartlett, and I were in Handley's.There were a couple of broads sitting at the next table to us.They had been drinking.

“What do you mean, kike?”one of the broads says.“What do youmean, kike, you big Irish bum?”

“Sure，”Jack says.“That's it.”

“Kikes，”this broad goes on.“They're always talking about kikes, these big Irishmen.What do you mean, kikes?”

“Come on.Let's get out of here.”

“Kikes，”this broad goes on.“Whoever saw you ever buy a drink?Your wife sews your pockets up every morning.These Irishmen and their kikes?Ted Lewis could lick you too.”

“Sure，”Jack says.“And you give away a lot of things free too, don't you?”

We went out.That was Jack.He could say what he wanted to when he wanted to say it.

Jack started training out at Danny Hogan's health farm over in Jersey.It was nice out there but Jack didn't like it much.He didn't like being away from his wife and the kids, and he was sore and grouchy most of the time.He liked me and we got along fne together；and he liked Hogan, but after a while Soldier Bartlett commenced to get on his nerves.A kidder gets to be an awful thing around a camp if his stuff goes sort of sour.Soldier was always kidding Jack, just sort of kidding him all the time.It wasn't very funny and it wasn't very good, and it began to get to Jack.It was sort of stuff like this.Jack would fnish up with the weights and the bag and pull on the gloves.

“You want to work?”he'd say to Soldier.

“Sure.How you want me to work?”Soldier would ask.“Want me to treat you rough like Walcott?Want me to knock you down a few times?”

“That's it，”Jack would say.He didn't like it any, though.

One morning we were all out on the road.We'd been out quite a way and now we were coming back.We'd go along fast for three minutes and then walk a minute, and then go fast for three minutes again.Jack wasn't ever what you would call a sprinter.He'd move around fast enough in the ring if he had to, but he wasn't any too fast on the road.All the time we were walking Soldier was kidding him.We came up the hill to the farmhouse.

“Well，”says Jack，“you better go back to town, Soldier.”

“What do you mean?”

“You better go back to town and stay there.”

“What's the matter?”

“I'm sick of hearing you talk.”

“Yes?”says Soldier.

“Yes，”says Jack.

“You'll be a damn sight sicker when Walcott gets through with you.”

“Sure，”says Jack，“maybe I will.But I know I'm sick of you.”

So Soldier went off on the train to town that same morning.I went with him to the train.He was good and sore.

“I was just kidding him，”he said.We were waiting on the platform.“He can't pull that stuff with me, Jerry.”

“He's nervous and crabby，”I said.“He's a good fellow, Soldier.”

“The hell he is.The hell he's ever been a good fellow.”

“Well，”I said，“so long, Soldier.”

The train had come in.He climbed up with his bag.

“So long, Jerry，”he says.“You be in town before the fght?”

“I don't think so.”

“See you then.”

He went in and the conductor swung up and the train went out.I rode back to the farm in the cart.Jack was on the porch writing a letter to his wife.The mail had come and I got the papers and went over on the other side of the porch and sat down to read.Hogan came out the door and walked over to me.

“Did he have a jam with Soldier?”

“Not a jam，”I said.“He just told him to go back to town.”

“I could see it coming，”Hogan said.“He never liked Soldier much.”

“No.He don't like many people.”

“He's a pretty cold one，”Hogan said.

“Well, he's always been fne to me.”

“Me too，”Hogan said.“I got no kick on him.He's a cold one, though.”

Hogan went in through the screen door and I sat there on the porch and read the papers.It was just starting to get fall weather and it's nice country there in Jersey, up in the hills, and after I read the paper through I sat there and looked out at the country and the road down below against the woods with cars going along it, lifting the dust up.It was fne weather and pretty nice-looking country.Hogan came to the door and I said，“Say, Hogan, haven't you got anything to shoot here?”

“No，”Hogan said.“Only sparrows.”

“Seen the paper?”I said to Hogan.

“What's in it?”

“Sande booted three of them in yesterday.”

“I got that on the telephone last night.”

“You follow them pretty close, Hogan?”I asked.

“Oh, I keep in touch with them，”Hogan said.

“How about Jack?”I said.“Does he still play them?”

“Him?”said Hogan.“Can you see him doing it?”

Just then Jack came around the corner with the letter in his hand.He's wearing a sweater and an old pair of pants and boxing shoes.

“Got a stamp, Hogan?”he asks.

“Give me that letter，”Hogan said.“I'll mail it for you.”

“Say, Jack，”I said，“didn't you used to play the ponies?”

“Sure.”

“I knew you did.I knew I used to see you out at Sheepshead.”

“What did you lay off them for?”Hogan asked.

“Lost money.”

Jack sat down on the porch by me.He leaned back against a post.He shut his eyes in the sun.

“Want a chair?”Hogan asked.

“No，”said Jack.“This is fne.”

“It's a nice day，”I said.“It's pretty nice out in the country.”

“I'd a damn sight rather be in town with the wife.”

“Well, you only got another week.”

“Yes，”Jack says.“That's so.”

We sat there on the porch.Hogan was inside at the offce.

“What do you think about the shape I'm in?”Jack asked me.

“Well, you can't tell，”I said.“You got a week to get around into form.”

“Don't stall me.”

“Well，”I said，“you're not right.”

“I'm not sleeping，”Jack said.

“You'll be all right in a couple of days.”

“No，”said Jack，“I got the insomnia.”

“What's on your mind?”

“I miss the wife.”

“Have her come out.”

“No.I'm too old for that.”

“We'll take a long walk before you turn in and get you good and tired.”

“Tired！”Jack says.“I'm tired all the time.”

He was that way all week.He wouldn't sleep at night and he'd get up in the morning feeling that way, you know, when you can't shut your hands.

“He's stale as poorhouse cake，”Hogan said.“He's nothing.”

“I never seen Walcott，”I said.

“He'll kill him，”said Hogan.“He'll tear him in two.”

“Well，”I said，“everybody's got to get it sometime.”

“Not like this, though，”Hogan said.“They'll think he never trained.It gives the farm a black eye.”

“You hear what the reporters said about him?”

“Didn't I！They said he was awful.They said they oughtn't to let him fght.”

“Well，”I said，“they're always wrong, ain't they?”

“Yes，”said Hogan.“But this time they're right.”

“What the hell do they know about whether a man's right or not?”

“Well，”said Hogan，“they're not such fools.”

“All they did was pick Willard at Toledo.This Lardner he's so wise now, ask him about when he picked Willard at Toledo.”

“Aw, he wasn't out，”Hogan said.“He only writes the big fghts.”

“I don't care who they are，”I said.“What the hell do they know?They can write maybe, but what the hell do they know?”

“You don't think Jack's in any shape, do you?”Hogan asked.

“No.He's through.All he needs is to have Corbett pick him to win for it to be all over.”

“Well, Corbett'll pick him，”Hogan says.

“Sure.He'll pick him.”

That night Jack didn't sleep any either.The next morning was the last day before the fght.After breakfast we were out on the porch again.

“What do you think about, Jack, when you can't sleep?”I said.

“Oh, I worry，”Jack says.“I worry about property I got up in the Bronx, I worry about property I got in Florida.I worry about the kids.I worry about the wife.Sometimes I think about fghts.I think about that kike Ted Lewis and I get sore.I got some stocks and I worry about them.What the hell don't I think about?”

“Well，”I said，“tomorrow night it'll all be over.”

“Sure，”said Jack.“That always helps a lot, don't it?That just fxes everything all up, I suppose.Sure.”

He was sore all day.We didn't do any work.Jack just moved around a little to loosen up.He shadow-boxed a few rounds.He didn't even look good doing that.He skipped the rope a little while.He couldn't sweat.

“He'd be better not to do any work at all，”Hogan said.We werestanding watching him skip rope.“Don't he ever sweat at all any more?”

“He can't sweat.”

“Do you suppose he's got the con?He never had any trouble making weight, did he?”

“No, he hasn't got any con.He just hasn't got anything inside any more.”

“He ought to sweat，”said Hogan.

Jack came over, skipping the rope.He was skipping up and down in front of us, forward and back, crossing his arms every third time.

“Well，”he says.“What are you buzzards talking about?”

“I don't think you ought to work any more，”Hogan says.“You'll be stale.”

“Wouldn't that be awful?”Jack says and skips away down the foor, slapping the rope hard.

That afternoon John Collins showed up out at the farm.Jack was up in his room.John came out in a car from town.He had a couple of friends with him.The car stopped and they all got out.

“Where's Jack?”John asked me.

“Up in his room, lying down.”

“Lying down?”

“Yes，”I said.

“How is he?”

I looked at the two fellows that were with John.

“They're friends of his，”John said.

“He's pretty bad，”I said.

“What's the matter with him?”

“He don't sleep.”

“Hell，”said John.“That Irishman could never sleep.”

“He isn't right，”I said.

“Hell，”John said.“He's never right.I've had him for ten years and he's never been right yet.”

The fellows who were with him laughed.

“I want you to shake hands with Mr.Morgan and Mr.Steinfelt，”John said.“This is Mr.Doyle.He's been training Jack.”

“Glad to meet you，”I said.

“Let's go up and see the boy，”the fellow called Morgan said.

“Let's have a look at him，”Steinfelt said.

We all went upstairs.

“Where's Hogan?”John asked.

“He's out in the barn with a couple of his customers，”I said.

“He got many people out here now?”John asked.

“Just two.”

“Pretty quiet, ain't it?”Morgan said.

“Yes，”I said.“It's pretty quiet.”

We were outside Jack's room.John knocked on the door.There wasn't an answer.

“Maybe he's asleep，”I said.

“What the hell's he sleeping in the daytime for?”

John turned the handle and we all went in.Jack was lying asleep on the bed.He was face down and his face was in the pillow.Both his arms were around the pillow.

“Hey, Jack！”John said to him.

Jack's head moved a little on the pillow.“Jack！”John says, leaning over him.Jack just dug a little deeper in the pillow.John touched him on the shoulder.Jack sat up and looked at us.He hadn't shaved and he was wearing an old sweater.

“Christ！Why can't you let me sleep?”he says to John.

“Don't be sore，”John says.“I didn't mean to wake you up.”

“Oh no，”Jack says.“Of course not.”

“You know Morgan and Steinfelt，”John said.

“Glad to see you，”Jack says.

“How do you feel, Jack?”Morgan asks him.

“Fine，”Jack says.“How the hell would I feel?”

“You look fne，”Steinfelt says.

“Yes, don't I，”says Jack.“Say，”he says to John.“You're my manager.You get a big enough cut.Why the hell don't you come out here when the reporters was out！You want Jerry and me to talk to them?”

“I had Lew fghting in Philadelphia，”John said.

“What the hell's that to me?”Jack says.“You're my manager.You get a big enough cut, don't you?You aren't making me any money in Philadelphia, are you?Why the hell aren't you out here when I ought to have you?”

“Hogan was here.”

“Hogan，”Jack says.“Hogan's as dumb as I am.”

“Soldier Bartlett was out here working with you for a while, wasn't he?”Steinfelt said to change the subject.

“Yes, he was out here，”Jack says.“He was out here all right.”

“Say, Jerry，”John said to me.“Would you go and fnd Hogan and tellhim we want to see him in about half an hour?”

“Sure，”I said.

“Why the hell can't he stick around?”Jack says.“Stick around, Jerry.”

Morgan and Steinfelt looked at each other.

“Quiet down, Jack，”John said to him.

“I better go fnd Hogan，”I said.

“All right, if you want to go，”Jack says.“None of these guys are going to send you away, though.”

“I'll go fnd Hogan，”I said.

Hogan was out in the gym in the barn.He had a couple of his health-farm patients with the gloves on.They neither one wanted to hit the other, for fear the other would come back and hit him.

“That'll do，”Hogan said when he saw me come in.“You can stop the slaughter.You gentlemen take a shower and Bruce will rub you down.”

They climbed out through the ropes and Hogan came over to me.

“John Collins is out with a couple of friends to see Jack，”I said.

“I saw them come up in the car.”

“Who are the two fellows with John?”

“They're what you call wise boys，”Hogan said.“Don't you know them two?”

“No，”I said.

That's Happy Steinfelt and Lew Morgan.They got a pool-room.”

“I been away a long time，”I said.

“Sure，”said Hogan.“That Happy Steinfelt's a big operator.”

“I've heard his name，”I said.

“He's a pretty smooth boy，”Hogan said.“They're a couple of sharpshooters.”

“Well，”I said.“They want to see us in half an hour.”

“You mean they don't want to see us until half an hour?”

“That's it.”

“Come on in the office，”Hogan said.“To hell with those sharpshooters.”

After about thirty minutes or so Hogan and I went upstairs.We knocked on Jack's door.They were talking inside the room.

“Wait a minute，”somebody said.

“To hell with that stuff，”Hogan said.“When you want me I'm down in the offce.”

We heard the door unlock.Steinfelt opened it.

“Come on in, Hogan，”he says.“We're all going to have a drink.”

“Well，”says Hogan.“That's something.”

We went in.Jack was sitting on the bed.John and Morgan were sitting on a couple of chairs.Steinfelt was standing up.

“You're a pretty mysterious lot of boys，”Hogan said.

“Hello, Danny，”John says.

“Hello, Danny，”Morgan says and shakes hands.

Jack doesn't say anything.He just sits there on the bed.He ain't with the others.He's all by himself.He was wearing an old blue jersey and pants and had on boxing shoes.He needed a shave.Steinfelt and Morgan were dressers.John was quite a dresser too.Jack sat there looking Irish and tough.

Steinfelt brought out a bottle and Hogan brought in some glasses andeverybody had a drink.Jack and I took one and the rest of them went on and had two or three each.

“Better save some for your ride back，”Hogan said.

“Don't you worry.We got plenty，”Morgan said.

Jack hadn't drunk anything since the one drink.He was standing up and looking at them.Morgan was sitting on the bed where Jack had sat.

“Have a drink, Jack，”John said and handed him the glass and the bottle.

“No，”Jack said，“I never liked to go to these wakes.”

They all laughed.Jack didn't laugh.

They were all feeling pretty good when they left.Jack stood on the porch when they got into the car.They waved to him.

“So long，”Jack said.

We had supper.Jack didn't say anything all during the meal except，“Will you pass me this?”or“Will you pass me that?”The two health-farm patients ate at the same table with us.They were pretty nice fellows.After we fnished eating we went out on the porch.It was dark early.

“Like to take a walk, Jerry?”Jack said.

“Sure，”I said.

We put on our coats and started out.It was quite a way down to the main road and then we walked along the main road about a mile and a half.Cars kept going by and we would pull out to one side until they were past.Jack didn't say anything.After we had stepped out into the bushes to let a big car go by Jack said，“To hell with this walking.Come on back to Hogan's”.We went along a side road that cut up over the hill and cut across the felds back to Hogan's.We could see the lights of the house upon the hill.We came around to the front of the house and there standing in the doorway was Hogan.

“Have a good walk?”Hogan asked.

“Oh, fne，”Jack said.“Listen, Hogan.Have you got any liquor?”

“Sure，”says Hogan.“What's the idea?”

“Send it up to the room，”Jack says.“I'm going to sleep tonight.”

“You're the doctor，”Hogan says.

“Come on up to the room, Jerry，”Jack says.

Upstairs Jack sat on the bed with his head in his hands.

“Ain't it a life?”Jack says.

Hogan brought in a quart of liquor and two glasses.

“Want some ginger ale?”

“What do you think I want to do, get sick?”

“I just asked you，”said Hogan.

“Have a drink?”said Jack.

“No, thanks，”said Hogan.He went out.

“How about it, Jerry?”

“I'll have one with you，”I said.

Jack poured out a couple of drinks.“Now，”he said，“I want to take it slow and easy.”

“Put some water in it，”I said.

“Yes，”Jack said.“I guess that's better.”

We had a couple of drinks without saying anything.Jack started to pour me another.

“No，”I said，“that's all I want.”

“All right，”Jack said.He poured himself out another big shot and putwater in it.He was lighting up a little.

“That was a fne bunch out here this afternoon，”he said.“They don't take any chances, those two.”

Then a little later，“Well，”he says，“they're right.What the hell's the good in taking chances?”

“Don't you want another, Jerry?”he said.“Come on, drink along with me.”

“I don't need it, Jack，”I said.“I feel all right.”

“Just have one more，”Jack said.It was softening him up.

“All right，”I said.

Jack poured one for me and another big one for himself.

“You know，”he said，“I like liquor pretty well.If I hadn't been boxing I would have drunk quite a lot.”

“Sure，”I said.

“You know，”he said，“I missed a lot, boxing.”

“You made plenty of money.”

“Sure, that's what I'm after.You know I miss a lot, Jerry.”

“How do you mean?”

“Well，”he says，“like about the wife.And being away from home so much.It don't do my girls any good.‘Whose your old man?'some of those society kids'll say to them.‘My old man's Jack Brennan.'That don’t do them any good.”

“Hell，”I said，“all that makes a difference is if they got dough.”

“Well，”says Jack，“I got the dough for them all right.”

He poured out another drink.The bottle was about empty.

“Put some water in it，”I said.Jack poured in some water.

“You know，”he says，“you ain't got any idea how I miss the wife.”

“Sure.”

“You ain't got any idea.You can't have an idea what it's like.”

“It ought to be better out in the country than in town.”

“With me now，”Jack said，“it don't make any difference where I am.You can't have an idea what it's like.”

“Have another drink.”

“Am I getting soused?Do I talk funny?”

“You're coming on all right.”

“You can't have an idea what it's like.They ain't anybody can have an idea what it's like.”

“Except the wife，”I said.

“She knows，”Jack said.“She knows all right.She knows.You bet she knows.”

“Put some water in that，”I said.

“Jerry，”says Jack，“you can't have an idea what it gets to be like.”

He was good and drunk.He was looking at me steady.His eyes were sort of too steady.

“You'll sleep all right，”I said.

“Listen, Jerry，”Jack says.“You want to make some money?Get some money down on Walcott.”

“Yes?”

“Listen, Jerry.”Jack put down the glass.“I'm not drunk now, see?You know what I'm betting on him?Fifty grand.”

“That's a lot of dough.”

“Fifty grand，”Jack says，“at two to one.I'll get twenty-fve thousandbucks.Get some money on him, Jerry.”

“It sounds good，”I said.

“How can I beat him?”Jack says.“It ain't crooked.How can I beat him?Why not make money on it?”

“Put some water in that，”I said.

“I'm through after this fght，”Jack says.“I'm through with it.I got to take a beating.Why shouldn't I make money on it?”

“Sure.”

“I ain't slept for a week，”Jack says.“All night I lay awake and worry my can off.I can't sleep, Jerry.You ain't got an idea what it's like when you can't sleep.”

“Sure.”

“I can't sleep.That's all.I just can't sleep.What's the use of taking care of yourself all these years when you can't sleep?”

“It's bad.”

“You ain't got an idea what it's like, Jerry, when you can't sleep.”

“Put some water in that，”I said.

Well, about eleven o'clock Jack passes out and I put him to bed.Finally he's so he can't keep from sleeping.I helped him get his clothes off and got him into bed.

“You'll sleep all right, Jack，”I said.

“Sure，”Jack says.“I'll sleep now.”

“Good night, Jack，”I said.

“Good night, Jerry，”Jack says.“You're the only friend I got.”

“Oh, hell，”I said.

“You're the only friend I got，”Jack says，“the only friend I got.”

“Go to sleep，”I said.

“I'll sleep，”Jack says.

Downstairs Hogan was sitting at the desk in the office reading the papers.He looked up.“Well, you get your boy friend to sleep?”he asks.

“He's off.”

“It's better for him than not sleeping，”Hogan said.

“Sure.”

“You'd have a hell of a time explaining that to these sports writers though，”Hogan said.

“Well, I'm going to bed myself，”I said.

“Good night，”said Hogan.

In the morning I came downstairs about eight o'clock and got some breakfast.Hogan had his customers out in the barn doing exercises.I went out and watched them.

“One！Two！Three！Four！”Hogan was counting for them.“Hello, Jerry，”he said.“Is Jack up yet?”

“No.He's still sleeping.”

I went back to my room and packed up to go to town.About nine-thirty I heard Jack getting up in the next room.When I heard him go downstairs I went down after him.Jack was sitting at the breakfast table.Hogan had come in and was standing beside the table.

“How do you feel, Jack?”I asked him.

“Not so bad.”

“Sleep well?”Hogan asked.

“I slept all right，”Jack said.“I got a thick tongue but I ain't got a head.”

“Good，”said Hogan.“That was good liquor.”

“Put it on the bill，”Jack says.

“What time you want to go into town?”Hogan asked.

“Before lunch，”Jack says.“The eleven o'clock train.”

“Sit down, Jerry，”Jack says.Hogan went out.

I sat down at the table.Jack was eating a grapefruit.When he'd fnd a seed he'd spit it out in the spoon and dump it on the plate.

“I guess I was pretty stewed last night，”he started.

“You drank some liquor.”

“I guess I said a lot of fool things.”

“You weren't bad.”

“Where's Hogan?”he asked.He was through with the grapefruit.

“He's out in front in the offce.”

“What did I say about betting on the fight?”Jack asked.He was holding the spoon and sort of poking at the grapefruit with it.

The girl came in with some ham and eggs and took away the grapefruit.

“Bring me another glass of milk，”Jack said to her.She went out.

“You said you had ffty grand on Walcott，”I said.

“That's right，”Jack said.

“That's a lot of money.”

“I don't feel too good about it，”Jack said.

“Something might happen.”

“No，”Jack said.“He wants the title bad.They'll be shooting with him all right.”

“You can't ever tell.”

“No.He wants the title.It's worth a lot of money to him.”

“Fifty grand is a lot of money，”I said.

“It's business，”said Jack.“I can't win.You know I can't win anyway.”

“As long as you're in there you got a chance.”

“No，”Jack says.“I'm all through.It's just business.”

“How do you feel?”

“Pretty good，”Jack said.“The sleep was what I needed.”

“You might go good.”

“I'll give them a good show，”Jack said.

After breakfast Jack called up his wife on the long-distance.He was inside the booth telephoning.

“That's the frst time he's called her up since he's out here，”Hogan said.

“He writes her every day.”

“Sure，”Hogan says，“a letter only costs two cents.”

Hogan said good-bye to us and Bruce, the nigger rubber, drove us down to the train in the cart.

“Good-bye, Mr.Brennan，”Bruce said at the train，“I sure hope you knock his can off.”

“So long，”Jack said.He gave Bruce two dollars.Bruce had worked on him a lot.He looked kind of disappointed.Jack saw me looking at Bruce holding the two dollars.

“It's all in the bill，”he said.“Hogan charged me for the rubbing.”

On the train going to town Jack didn't talk.He sat in the corner of the seat with his ticket in his hat-band and looked out of the window.Once heturned and spoke to me.

“I told the wife I'd take a room at the Shelby tonight，”he said.“It's just around the corner from the Garden.I can go up to the house tomorrow morning.”

“That's a good idea，”I said.“Your wife ever see you fght, Jack?”

“No，”Jack says.“She never seen me fght.”

I thought he must be fguring on taking an awful beating if he doesn't want to go home afterwards.In town we took a taxi up to the Shelby.A boy came out and took our bags and we went to the desk.

“How much are the rooms?”Jack asked.

“We only have double rooms，”the clerk says.“I can give you a nice double room for ten dollars.”

“That's too steep.”

“I can give you a double room for seven dollars.”

“With a bath?”

“Certainly.”

“You might as well bunk with me, Jerry，”Jack says.

“Oh，”I said.“I'll sleep down at my brother-in-law's.”

“I don't mean for you to pay it，”Jack says.“I just want to get my money's worth.”

“Will you register, please?”the clerk says.He looked at the names.“Number 238，Mister Brennan.”

We went up in the elevator.It was a nice big room with two beds and a door opening into a bathroom.

“This is pretty good，”Jack says.

The boy who brought us up pulled up the curtains and brought in ourbags.Jack didn't make any move, so I gave the boy a quarter.We washed up and Jack said we better go out and get something to eat.

We ate a lunch at Jimmy Handley's place.Quite a lot of the boys were there.When we were about half through eating, John came in and sat down with us.Jack didn't talk much.

“How are you on the weight, Jack?”John asked him.Jack was putting away a pretty good lunch.

“I could make it with my clothes on，”Jack said.He never had to worry about taking off weight.He was a natural welter weight and he'd never gotten fat.He'd lost weight out at Hogan's.

“Well, that's one thing you never had to worry about.”John said.

“That's one thing，”Jack says.

We went around to the Garden to weigh in after lunch.The match was made at a hundred forty-seven pounds at three o'clock.Jack stepped on the scales with a towel around him.The bar didn't move.Walcott had just weighed and was standing with a lot of people around him.

“Let's see what you weigh, Jack，”Freedman, Walcott's manager, said.

“All right, weigh him then，”Jack jerked his head toward Walcott.

“Drop the towel，”Freedman said.

“What do you make it?”Jack asked the fellows who were weighing.

“One hundred and forty-three pounds，”the fat man who was weighing said.

“You're down fne, Jack，”Freedman says.

“Weigh him，”Jack says.

Walcott came over.He was blond with wide shoulders and arms likea heavyweight.He didn't have much legs.Jack stood about half a head taller than he did.

“Hello, Jack，”he said.His face was plenty marked up.

“Hello，”said Jack.“How do you feel?”

“Good，”Walcott says.He dropped the towel from around his waist and stood on the scales.He had the widest shoulders and back you ever saw.

“One hundred and forty-six pounds and twelve ounces.”

Walcott stepped off and grinned at Jack.

“Well，”John says to him，“Jack's spotting you about four pounds.”

“More than that when I come in, kid，”Walcott says.“I'm going to go and eat now.”

We went back and Jack got dressed.“He's a pretty tough-looking boy，”Jack says to me.

“He looks as though he'd been hit plenty of times.”

“Oh, yes，”Jack says.“He ain't hard to hit.”

“Where are you going?”John asked when Jack was dressed.

“Back to the hotel，”Jack says.“You looked after everything?”

“Yes，”John says.“It's all looked after.”

“I'm going to lie down for a while，”Jack says.

“I'll come around for you about a quarter to seven and we'll go and eat.”

“All right.”

Up at the hotel Jack took off his shoes and his coat and lay down for a while.I wrote a letter.I looked over a couple of times and Jack wasn't sleeping.He was lying perfectly still but every once in a while his eyeswould open.Finally he sits up.

“Want to play some cribbage, Jerry?”he says.

“Sure，”I said.

He went over to his suitcase and got out the cards and the cribbage board.We played cribbage and he won three dollars off me.John knocked at the door and came in.

“You want to play some cribbage, John?”Jack asked him.

John put his hat down on the table.It was all wet.His coat was wet too.

“Is it raining?”Jack asks.

“It's pouring，”John says.“The taxi I had got tied up in the traffc and I got out and walked.”

“Come on, play some cribbage，”Jack says.

“You ought to go and eat.”

“No，”says Jack.“I don't want to eat yet.”

So they played cribbage for about half an hour and Jack won a dollar and a half off him.

“Well, I suppose we got to go eat，”Jack says.He went to the window and looked out.

“Is it still raining?”

“Yes.”

“Let's eat in the hotel，”John says.

“All right，”Jack says，“I'll play you once more to see who pays for the meal.”

After a little while Jack gets up and says，“You buy the meal, John，”and we went downstairs and ate in the big dining-room.

After we ate we went upstairs and Jack played cribbage with John again and won two dollars and a half off him.Jack was feeling pretty good.John had a bag with him with all his stuff in it.Jack took off his shirt and collar and put on a jersey and a sweater, so he wouldn't catch cold when he came out, and put his ring clothes and bathrobe in a bag.

“You all ready?”John asks him.“I'll call up and have them get a taxi.”

Pretty soon the telephone rang and they said the taxi was waiting.

We rode down in the elevator and went out through the lobby, and got in a taxi and rode around to the Garden.It was raining hard but there was a lot of people outside on the streets.The Garden was sold out.As we came in on our way to the dressing-room I saw how full it was.It looked like half a mile down to the ring.It was all dark.Just the lights over the ring.

“It's a good thing, with this rain, they didn't try and pull this fght in the ball park，”John said.

“They got a good crowd，”Jack says.

“This is a fight that would draw a lot more than the Garden could hold.”

“You can't tell about the weather，”Jack says.

John came to the door of the dressing-room and poked his head in.Jack was sitting there with his bathrobe on, he had his arms folded and was looking at the foor.John had a couple of handlers with him.They looked over his shoulder.Jack looked up.

“Is he in?”he asked.

“He's just gone down，”John said.

We started down.Walcott was just getting into the ring.The crowd gave him a big hand.He climbed through between the ropes and put his two fsts together and smiled, and shook them at the crowd, frst at one side of the ring, then at the other, and then sat down.Jack got a good hand coming down through the crowd.Jack is Irish and the Irish always get a pretty good hand.An Irishman don't draw in New York like a Jew or an Italian but they always get a good hand.Jack climbed up and bent down to go through the ropes and Walcott came over from his corner and pushed the rope down for Jack to go through.The crowd thought that was wonderful.Walcott put his hand on Jack's shoulder and they stood there just for a second.

“So you're going to be one of these popular champions，”Jack says to him.“Take your goddam hand off my shoulder.”

“Be yourself，”Walcott says.

This is all great for the crowd.How gentlemanly the boys are before the fght！How they wish each other luck！

Solly Freedman came over to our corner while Jack is bandaging his hands and John is over in Walcott's corner.Jack put his thumb through the slit in the bandage and then wrapped his hand nice and smooth.I taped it around the wrist and twice across the knuckles.

“Hey，”Freedman says.“Where do you get all that tape?”

“Feel of it，”Jack says.“It's soft, ain't it?Don't be a hick.”

Freedman stands there all the time while Jack bandages the other hand and one of the boys that's going to handle him brings the gloves and I pull them on and work them around.

“Say, Freedman，”Jack asks，“what nationality is this Walcott?”

“I don't know，”Solly says.“He's some sort of a Dane.”

“He's a Bohemian，”the lad who brought the gloves said.

The referee called them out to the centre of the ring and Jack walks out.Walcott comes out smiling.They met and the referee put his arm on each of their shoulders.

“Hello, popularity，”Jack says to Walcott.

“Be yourself.”

“What do you call yourself‘Walcott'for?”Jack says.“Didn't you know he was a nigger?”

“Listen—”says the referee, and he gives them the same old line.Once Walcott interrupts him.He grabs Jack's arm, and says，“Can I hit when he's got me like this?”

“Keep your hands off me，”Jack says.“There ain't no moving-pictures of this.”

They went back to their corners.I lifted the bathrobe off Jack and he leaned on the ropes and fexed his knees a couple of times and scuffed his shoes in the rosin.The gong rang and Jack turned quick and went out.Walcott came toward him and they touched gloves and as soon as Walcott dropped his hands Jack jumped his left into his face twice.There wasn't anybody ever boxed better than Jack.Walcott was after him, going forward all the time with his chin on his chest.He's a hooker and he carries his hands pretty low.All he knows is to get in there and sock.But every time he gets in there close, Jack has the left hand in his face.It's just as though it's automatic.Jack just raises the left hand up and it's in Walcott’s face.Three or four times Jack brings the right over but Walcott gets it on the shoulder or high up on the head.He’s just like all thesehookers.The only thing he’s afraid of is another one of the same kind.He’s covered everywhere you can hurt him.He don’t care about a left hand in his face.

After about four rounds Jack has him bleeding bad and his face all cut up, but every time Walcott's got in close he's socked so hard he's got two big red patches on both sides just below Jack's ribs.Every time he gets in close, Jack ties him up, then gets one hand loose and uppercuts him, but when Walcott gets his hands loose he socks Jack in the body so they can hear it outside in the street.He's a socker.

It goes along like that for three rounds more.They don't talk any.They're working all the time.We worked over Jack plenty too, in between the rounds.He don't look good at all but he never does much work in the ring.He don't move around much and the left hand is just automatic.It's just like it was connected with Walcott’s face and Jack just had to wish it in every time.Jack is always calm in close and he doesn’t waste any juice.He knows everything about working in close too and he’s getting away with a lot of stuff.While they were in our corner I watched him tie Walcott up, get his right hand loose, turn it and come up with an uppercut that got Walcott’s nose with the heel of the glove.Walcott was bleeding bad and leaned his nose on Jack’s shoulder so as to give Jack some of it too, and Jack sort of lifted his shoulder sharp and caught him against the nose, and then brought down the right hand and did the same thing again.

Walcott was sore as hell.By the time they'd gone five rounds he hated Jack's guts.Jack wasn't sore；that is, he wasn't any sorer than he always was.He certainly did used to make the fellows he fought hate boxing.That was why he hated Kid Lewis so.He never got Kid's goat.Kid Lewis always had about three new dirty things Jack couldn’t do.Jack was as safe as a church all the time he was in there, as long as he was strong.He certainly was treating Walcott rough.The funny thing was it looked as though Jack was an open classic boxer.That was because he had all that stuff too.

After the seventh round Jack says，“My left's getting heavy.”

From then he started to take a beating.It didn't show at first.But instead of him running the fght it was Walcott was running it, instead of being safe all the time now he was in trouble.He couldn't keep him out with the left hand now.It looked as though it was the same as ever, only now instead of Walcott's punches just missing him they were just hitting him.He took an awful beating in the body.

“What's the round?”Jack asked.

“The eleventh.”

“I can't stay，”Jack says.“My legs are going bad.”

Walcott had been hitting him for a long time.It was like a baseball catcher pulls the ball and takes some of the shock off.From now on Walcott commenced to land solid.He certainly was a socking-machine.Jack was just trying to block everything now.It didn't show what an awful beating he was taking.In between the rounds I worked on his legs.The muscles would futter under my hands all the time I was rubbing them.He was sick as hell.

“How's it go?”he asked John, turning around, his face all swollen.

“It's his fght.”

“I think I can last，”Jack says.“I don't want this bohunk to stop me.”

It was going just the way he thought it would.He knew he couldn't beat Walcott.He wasn't strong any more.He was all right though.His money was all right and now he wanted to finish it off right to please himself.He didn't want to be knocked out.

The gong rang and we pushed him out.He went out slow.Walcott came right out after him.Jack put the left in his face and Walcott took it, came in under it and started working on Jack's body.Jack tried to tie him up and it was just like trying to hold on to a buzz-saw.Jack broke away from it and missed with the right.Walcott clipped him with a left hook and Jack went down.He went down on his hands and knees and looked at us.The referee started counting.Jack was watching us and shaking his head.At eight John motioned to him.You couldn't hear on account of the crowd.Jack got up.The referee had been holding Walcott back with one arm while he counted.

When Jack was on his feet Walcott started toward him.

“Watch yourself, Jimmy，”I heard Solly Freedman yell to him.

Walcott came up to Jack looking at him.Jack stuck the left hand at him.Walcott just shook his head.He backed Jack up against the ropes, measured him and then hooked the left very light to the side of Jack's head and socked the right into the body as hard as he could sock, just as low as he could get it.He must have hit him fve inches below the belt.I thought the eyes would come out of Jack's head.They stuck way out.His mouth came open.

The referee grabbed Walcott.Jack stepped forward.If he went down there went ffty thousand bucks.He walked as though all his insides were going to fall out.

“It wasn't low，”he said.“It was an accident.”

The crowd were yelling so you couldn't hear anything.

“I'm all right，”Jack says.They were right in front of us.The referee looks at John and then he shakes his head.

“Come on, you polak son-of-a-bitch，”Jack says to Walcott.

John was hanging on to the ropes.He had the towel ready to chuck in.Jack was standing just a little way out from the ropes.He took a step forward.I saw the sweat come out on his face like somebody had squeezed it and a big drop went down his nose.

“Come on and fght，”Jack says to Walcott.

The referee looked at John and waved Walcott on.

“Go in there, you slob，”he says.

Walcott went in.He didn't know what to do either.He never thought Jack could have stood it.Jack put the left in his face.There was such a hell of a lot of yelling going on.They were right in front of us.Walcott hit him twice.Jack's face was the worst thing I ever saw—the look on it！He was holding himself and all his body together and it all showed on his face.All the time he was thinking and holding his body in where it was busted.

Then he started to sock.His face looked awful all the time.He started to sock with his hands low down by his side, swinging at Walcott.Walcott covered up and Jack was swinging wild at Walcott's head.Then he swung the left and it hit Walcott in the groin and the right hit Walcott right bang where he'd hit Jack.Way low below the belt.Walcott went down and grabbed himself there and rolled and twisted around.

The referee grabbed Jack and pushed him toward his corner.John jumps into the ring.There was all this yelling going on.The referee wastalking with the judges and then the announcer got into the ring with the megaphone and says，“Walcott on a foul.”

The referee is talking to John and he says，“What could I do?Jack wouldn't take the foul.Then when he's groggy he fouls him.”

“He'd lost it anyway，”John says.

Jack's sitting on the chair.I've got his gloves off and he's holding himself in down there with both hands.When he's got something supporting it his face doesn't look so bad.

“Go over and say you're sorry，”John says into his ear.“It'll look good.”

Jack stands up and the sweat comes out all over his face.I put the bathrobe around him and he holds himself with one hand under the bathrobe and goes across the ring.They've picked Walcott up and they're working on him.There're a lot of people in Walcott's corner.Nobody speaks to Jack.He leans over Walcott.

“I'm sorry，”Jack says.“I didn't mean to foul you.”

Walcott doesn't say anything.He looks too damned sick.

“Well, you're the champion now，”Jack says to him.“I hope you get a hell of a lot of fun out of it.”

“Leave the kid alone，”Solly Freedman says.

“Hello, Solly，”Jack says.“I'm sorry I fouled your boy.”

Freedman just looks at him.

Jack went to his corner walking that funny jerky way and we got him down through the ropes and through the reporters'tables and out down the aisle.A lot of people want to slap Jack on the back.He goes out through all that mob in his bathrobe to the dressing-room.It's a popular win forWalcott.That's the way the money was bet in the Garden.

Once we got inside the dressing-room, Jack lay down and shut his eyes.

“We want to get to the hotel and get a doctor，”John says.

“I'm all busted inside，”Jack says.

“I'm sorry as hell, Jack，”John says.

“It's all right，”Jack says.

He lies there with his eyes shut.

“They certainly tried a nice double-cross，”John said.

“Your friends Morgan and Steinfelt，”Jack said.“You got nice friends.”

He lies there, his eyes are open now.His face has still got that awful drawn look.

“It's funny how fast you can think when it means that much money，”Jack says.

“You're some boy, Jack，”John says.

“No，”Jack says.“It was nothing.”

Ten Indians

AFTER one Fourth of July, Nick, driving home late from town in the big wagon with Joe Garner and his family, passed nine drunken Indians along the road.He remembered there were nine because Joe Garner, driving along in the dusk, pulled up the horses, jumped down into the road and dragged an Indian out of the wheel rut.The Indian had been asleep face down in the sand.Joe dragged him into the bushes and got back up on the wagon-box.

“That makes nine of them，”Joe said，“just between here and the edge of town.”

“Them Indians，”said Mrs.Garner.

Nick was on the back seat with the two Garner boys.He was looking out from the back seat to see the Indian where Joe had dragged him alongside of the road.

“Was it Billy Tableshaw?”Carl asked.

“No.”

“His pants looked mighty like Billy.”

“All Indians wear the same kind of pants.”

“I didn't see him at all，”Frank said.“Pa was down into the road and back up again before I seen a thing.I thought he was killing a snake.”

“Plenty of Indians'll kill snakes tonight, I guess，”Joe Garner said.

“Them Indians，”said Mrs.Garner.

They drove along.The road turned off from the main highway and went up into the hills.It was hard pulling for the horses and the boys got down and walked.The road was sandy.Nick looked back from the top of the hill by the school house.He saw the lights of Petoskey and, off across Little Traverse Bay, the lights of Harbor Springs.They climbed back into the wagon again.

“They ought to put some gravel on that stretch，”Joe Garner said.The wagon went along the road through the woods.Joe and Mrs.Garner sat close together on the front seat.Nick sat between the two boys.The road came out into a clearing.

“Right here was where Pa ran over the skunk.”

“It was further on.”

“It don't make no difference where it was，”Joe said without turning his head.“One place is just as good as another to run over a skunk.”

“I saw two skunks last night，”Nick said.

“Where?”

“Down by the lake.They were looking for dead fish along the beach.”

“They were coons probably，”Carl said.

“They were skunks.I guess I know skunks.”

“You ought to，”Carl said.“You got an Indian girl.”

“Stop talking that way, Carl，”said Mrs.Garner.

“Well, they smell about the same.”

Joe Garner laughed.

“You stop laughing, Joe，”Mrs.Garner said.“I won't have Carl talkthat way.”

“Have you got an Indian girl, Nickie?”Joe asked.

“No.”

“He has too, Pa，”Frank said.“Prudence Mitchell's his girl.”

“She's not.”

“He goes to see her every day.”

“I don't.”Nick, sitting between the two boys in the dark felt hollow and happy inside himself to be teased about Prudence Mitchell.“She ain't my girl，”he said.

“Listen to him，”said Carl.“I see them together every day.”

“Carl can't get a girl，”his mother said，“not even a squaw.”

Carl was quiet.

“Carl ain't no good with girls，”Frank said.

“You shut up.”

“You're all right, Carl，”Joe Garner said.“Girls never got a man anywhere.Look at your pa.”

“Yes, that's what you would say.”Mrs.Garner moved close to Joe as the wagon jolted.“Well, you had plenty of girls in your time.”

“I'll bet pa wouldn't ever have had a squaw for a girl.”

“Don't you think it，”Joe said.“You better watch out to keep Prudie, Nick.”

His wife whispered to him and Joe laughed.

“What you laughing at?”asked Frank.

“Don't you say it, Garner，”his wife warned.Joe laughed again.

“Nickie can have Prudence，”Joe Garner said.“I got a good girl.”

“That's the way to talk，”Mrs.Garner said.

The horses were pulling heavily in the sand.Joe reached out in the dark with the whip.

“Come on, pull into it.You'll have to pull harder than this tomorrow.”

They trotted down the long hill, the wagon jolting.At the farmhouse everybody got down.Mrs.Garner unlocked the door, went inside, and came out with a lamp in her hand.Carl and Nick unloaded the things from the back of the wagon.Frank sat on the front seat to drive to the barn and put up the horses.Nick went up the steps and opened the kitchen door.Mrs.Garner was building a fire in the stove.She turned from pouring kerosene on the wood.

“Good-bye, Mrs.Garner，”Nick said.“Thanks for taking me.”

“Oh shucks, Nickie.”

“I had a wonderful time.”

“We like to have you.Won't you stay and eat some supper?”

“I better go.I think Dad probably waited for me.”

“Well, get along then.Send Carl up to the house, will you?”

“All right.”

“Good night, Nickie！”

“Good night, Mrs.Garner.”

Nick went out the farmyard and down to the barn.Joe and Frank were milking.

“Good night，”Nick said.“I had a swell time.”

“Good night, Nick，”Joe Garner called.“Aren't you going to stay and eat?”

“No, I can't.Will you tell Carl his mother wants him?”

“All right.Good night, Nickie.”

Nick walked barefooted along the path through the meadow below the barn.The path was smooth and the dew was cool on his bare feet.He climbed a fence at the end of the meadow, went down through a ravine, his feet wet in the swamp mud, and climbed up through the dry beech woods until he saw the lights of the cottage.He climbed over the fence and walked around to the front porch.Through the window he saw his father sitting by the table, reading in the light from the big lamp.Nick opened the door and went in.

“Well, Nickie，”his father said，“was it a good day?”

“I had a swell time, Dad.It was a swell Fourth of July.”

“Are you hungry?”

“You bet.”

“What did you do with your shoes?”

“I left them in the wagon at Garner's.”

“Come on out to the kitchen.”

Nick's father went ahead with the lamp.He stopped and lifted the lid of the ice-box.Nick went on into the kitchen.His father brought out a piece of cold chicken on a plate and a pitcher of milk and put them on the table before Nick.He put down the lamp.

“There's some pie too，”he said.“Will that hold you?”

“It's grand.”

His father sat down in a chair beside the oilcloth-covered table.He made a big shadow on the kitchen wall.

“Who won the ball game?”

“Petoskey.Five to three.”

His father sat watching him eat and filled his glass from the milk-pitcher.Nick drank and wiped his mouth on his napkin.His father reached over to the shelf for the pie.He cut Nick a big piece.It was huckleberry pie.

“What did you do, Dad?”

“I went out fshing in the morning.”

“What did you get?”

“Only perch.”

His father sat watching Nick eat the pie.

“What did you do this afternoon?”Nick asked.

“I went for a walk up by the Indian camp.”

“Did you see anybody?”

“The Indians were all in town getting drunk.”

“Didn't you see anybody at all?”

“I saw your friend, Prudie.”

“Where was she?”

“She was in the woods with Frank Washburn.I ran onto them.They were having quite a time.”

His father was not looking at him.

“What were they doing?”

“I didn't stay to fnd out.”

“Tell me what they were doing.”

“I don't know，”his father said.“I just heard them threshing around.”

“How did you know it was them?”

“I saw them.”

“I thought you said you didn't see them.”

“Oh, yes, I saw them.”

“Who was it with her?”Nick asked.

“Frank Washburn.”

“Were they—were they—”

“Were they what?”

“Were they happy?”

“I guess so.”

His father got up from the table and went out of the kitchen screen door.When he came back Nick was looking at his plate.He had been crying.

“Have some more?”His father picked up the knife to cut the pie.

“No，”said Nick.

“You better have another piece.”

“No, I don't want any.”

His father cleared off the table.

“Where were they in the woods?”asked Nick.

“Up back of the camp.”Nick looked at his plate.His father said，“You better go to bed, Nick.”

“All right.”

Nick went into his room, undressed, and got into bed.He heard his father moving around in the living room.Nick lay in the bed with his face in the pillow.

“My heart's broken，”he thought.“If I feel this way my heart must be broken.”

After a while he heard his father blow out the lamp and go into his own room.He heard a wind come up in the trees outside and felt it comein cool through the screen.He lay for a long time with his face in the pillow, and after a while he forgot to think about Prudence and finally he went to sleep.When he awoke in the night he heard the wind in the hemlock trees outside the cottage and the waves of the lake coming in on the shore, and he went back to sleep.In the morning there was a big wind blowing and the waves were running high up on the beach and he was awake a long time before he remembered that his heart was broken.

Today is Friday

Three Roman soldiers are in a drinking-place at eleven o'clock at night.There are barrels around the wall.Behind the wooden counter is a Hebrew wine-seller.The three Roman soldiers are a little cock-eyed.

1st Roman Soldier—You tried the red?

2nd Soldier—No, I ain't tried it.

1st Soldier—You better try it.

2nd Soldier—All right, George, we'll have a round of the red.

Hebrew Wine-seller—Here you are, gentlemen.You'll like that.[He sets down an earthenware pitcher that he has flled from one of the casks.]That's a nice little wine.

1st Soldier—Have a drink of it yourself.[He turns to the third Roman soldier who is leaning on a barrel.]What's the matter with you?

3rd Soldier—I got a gut-ache.

2nd Soldier—You've been drinking water.

1st Soldier—Try some of the red.

3rd Soldier—I can't drink the damn stuff.It makes my gut sour.

1st Soldier—You been out here too long.

3rd Soldier—Hell, don't I know it?”

1st Soldier—Say, George, can't you give this gentleman somethingto fx his stomach?

Hebrew Wine-seller—I got it right here.

[The third Roman soldier tastes the cup that the wine-seller has mixed for him.]

3rd Soldier—Hey, what you put in that, camel chips?

Wine-seller—You drink that right down, Lootenant.That'll fx you up right.

3rd Soldier—Well, I couldn't feel any worse.

1st Soldier—Take a chance on it.George fxed me up fne the other day.

Hebrew Wine-seller—You were in bad shape, Lootenant.I know what fxes up a bad stomach.

[The third Roman soldier drinks the cup down.]

3rd Soldier—Jesus Christ.[He makes a face.]

2nd Soldier—That false alarm！

1st Soldier—Oh, I don't know.He was pretty good in there today.

2nd Soldier—Why didn't he come down off the cross?

1st Soldier—He didn't want to come down off the cross.That's not his play.

2nd Soldier—Show me a guy that doesn't want to come down off the cross.

1st Soldier—Aw, hell, you don't know anything about it.Ask George there.Did he want to come down off the cross, George?

Wine-seller—I'll tell you, gentlemen, I wasn't out there.It's a thing I haven't taken any interest in.

2nd Soldier—Listen, I seen a lot of them—here and plenty of otherplaces.Any time you show me one that doesn't want to get down off the cross when the time comes—when the time comes, I mean—I'll climb right up with him.

1st Soldier—I thought he was pretty good in there today.

3rd Soldier—He was all right.

2nd Soldier—You guys don't know what I'm talking about.I'm not saying whether he was good or not.What I mean is, when the time comes.When they frst start nailing him, there isn't none of them wouldn't stop it if they could.

1st Soldier—Didn't you follow it, George?

Wine-seller—No, I didn't take any interest in it, Lootenant.

1st Soldier—I was surprised how he acted.

3rd Soldier—The part I don't like is the nailing them on.You know, that must get you pretty bad.

2nd Soldier—It isn't that that's so bad, as when they frst lift 'em up [He makes a lifting gesture with his two palms together.]When the weight starts to pull on 'em.That's when it gets ’em.

3rd Soldier—It takes some of them pretty bad.

1st Soldier—Ain't I seen 'em?I seen plenty of them.I tell you, he was pretty good in there today.

[The second Roman soldier smiles at the Hebrew wine-seller.]

2nd Soldier—You're a regular Christer, big boy.

1st Soldier—Sure, go on and kid him.But listen while I tell you something.He was pretty good in there today.

2nd Soldier—What about some more wine?

[The wine-seller looks up expectantly.The third soldier is sittingwith his head down.He does not look well.]

3rd Soldier—I don't want any more.

2nd Soldier—Just for two, George.

[The wine-seller puts out a pitcher of wine, a size smaller than the last one.He leans forward on the wooden counter.]

1st Soldier—You see his girl?

2nd Soldier—Wasn't I standing right by her?

1st Soldier—She's a nice looker.

2nd Soldier—I knew her before he did.[He winks at the wine-seller.]

1st Soldier—I used to see her around the town.

2nd Soldier—She used to have a lot of stuff.He never brought her no good luck.

1st Soldier—Oh, he ain't lucky.But he looked pretty good to me in there today.

2nd Soldier—What became of his gang?

1st Soldier—Oh, they faded out.Just the women stuck by him.

2nd Soldier—They were a pretty yellow crowd.When they seen him go up there they didn't want any of it.

1st Soldier—The women stuck all right.

2nd Soldier—Sure, they stuck all right.

1st Soldier—You see me slip the old spear into him?

2nd Soldier—You'll get into trouble doing that some day.

1st Soldier—It was the least I could do for him.I'll tell you he looked pretty good to me in there today.

Hebrew wine-seller—Gentlemen, you know I got to close.

1st Soldier—We'll have one more round.

2nd Soldier—What's the use?This stuff don't get you anywhere.Come on, let's go.

1st Soldier—Just another round.

3rd Soldier—[Getting up from the barrel]No, come on.Let's go.I feel like hell tonight.

1st Soldier—Just one more.

2nd Soldier—No, come on.We're going to go.Good night, George.Put it on the bill.

Hebrew Wine-seller—Good night gentlemen.[He looks a little worried.]You couldn't let me have a little something on account, Lootenant?

2nd Soldier—What the hell, George！Wednesday's payday.

Wine-seller—It's all right, Lootenant.Good night, gentlemen.

[The three Roman soldiers go out the door into the street.]

[Outside in the street.]

2nd Soldier—George is a kike just like all the rest of them.

1st Soldier—Oh, George is a nice fella.

2nd Soldier—Everybody's a nice fella to you tonight.

3rd Soldier—Come on, let's go up to the barracks.I feel like hell tonight.

2nd Soldier—You been out here too long.

3rd Soldier—No, it ain't that.I feel like hell.

2nd Soldier—You been out here too long.That's all.

CURTAIN

Banal Story

SO he ate an orange, slowly spitting out the seeds.Outside, the snow was turning to rain.Inside, the electric stove seemed to give no heat and rising from his writing-table, he sat down upon the stove.How good it felt！Here, at last, was life.

He reached for another orange.Far away in Paris, Mascart had knocked Danny Frush cuckoo in the second round.Far off in Mesopotamia, twenty-one feet of snow had fallen.Across the world in distant Australia, the English cricketers were sharpening up their wickets.There was Romance.

Patrons of the arts and letters have discovered The Forum, he read.It is the guide, philosopher, and friend of the thinking minority.Prize short-stories—will their authors write our best-sellers of tomorrow?

You will enjoy these warm, homespun, American tales, bits of real life on the open ranch, in crowded tenement or comfortable home, and all with a healthy undercurrent of humor.

I must read them, he thought.

He read on.Our children's children—what of them?Who of them?New means must be discovered to fnd room for us under the sun.Shall this be done by war or can it be done by peaceful methods?

Or will we all have to move to Canada?

Our deepest convictions—will Science upset them?Our civilization—is it inferior to older orders of things?

And meanwhile, in the far-off dripping jungles of Yucatán, sounded the chopping of the axes of the gum-choppers.

Do we want big men—or do we want them cultured?Take Joyce.Take President Coolidge.What star must our college students aim at?There is Jack Britton.There is Dr.Henry Van Dyke.Can we reconcile the two?Take the case of Young Stribling.

And what of our daughters who must take their own Soundings?Nancy Hawthorne is obliged to make her own Soundings in the sea of life.Bravely and sensibly she faces the problems which come to every girl of eighteen.

It was a splendid booklet.

Are you a girl of eighteen?Take the case of a Joan of Arc.Take the case of Bernard Shaw.Take the case of Betsy Ross.

Think of these things in 1925—Was there a risqué page in Puritan history?Were there two sides to Pocahontas?Did she have a fourth dimension?

Are modern paintings—and poetry—Art?Yes and No.Take Picasso.

Have tramps codes of conduct?Send your mind adventuring.

There is Romance everywhere.Forum writers talk to the point, are possessed of humor and wit.But they do not try to be smart and are never long-winded.

Live the full life of the mind, exhilarated by new ideas, intoxicated by the Romance of the unusual.He laid down the booklet.

And meanwhile, stretched flat on a bed in a darkened room in the house in Triana, Manuel Garcia Maera lay with a tube in each lung, drowning with the pneumonia.All the papers in Andalucia devoted special supplements to his death, which had been expected for some days.Men and boys bought full-length colored pictures of him to remember him by, and lost the picture they had of him in their memories by looking at the lithographs.Bullfghters were very relieved he was dead, because he did always in the bull-ring the things they could only do sometimes.They all marched in the rain behind his coffn and there were one hundred and forty-seven bullfghters followed him out to the cemetery, where they buried him in the tomb next to Joselito.After the funeral every one sat in the cafés out of the rain, and many colored pictures of Maera were sold to men who rolled them up and put them away in their pockets.

译序

这本书是海明威的遗稿，是他死后在他家的故纸堆里发现的。书中记载了他作为“巴漂族”[1]的一员，为了理想坚持不懈努力奋斗的坎坷历程。那时候国际上流传着一种说法：要想成为国际性的大腕，无论是文学方面的巨擘还是艺术领域的佼佼者，就应该到巴黎去“混一混”，因为那儿是文学艺术之都。于是，海明威夹裹在滚滚人流中横渡大西洋来到了这个让他魂牵梦萦的大都市。在这个族群里，有已经小有所成的西班牙画家毕加索，有《了不起的盖茨比》的作者司各特·菲茨杰拉德、《尤利西斯》的作者詹姆斯·乔伊斯和意象派诗歌运动的代表人物庞德等。他们怀揣梦想，极其美好的梦想，但现实却是那般“骨感”——即便前程似锦，可是眼下却要为生存着恼（有地方住吗？有饭吃吗？），正是括号里的这两点往往令英雄们泪湿衣襟。不过，他们抱团取暖，相互勉励，陆续在自己的领域干出了大事业——画画的画出了《格尔尼卡》那样的惊世之作，写作的写出了《太阳照常升起》这般万古流芳的传世之作。如今，我们欣赏这些名画、阅读这些佳作时，心里不禁会问：20世纪20年代那些在巴黎漂泊的毛头小伙子是怎么将自己历练成了大师的？看完这本书，你心里可能会有一个答案。

海明威和成千上万“巴漂族”的成员一样，经济极其拮据，只好蜗居在贫民区，过着食不果腹的穷日子。他不是没有才华，而是太有才华了，于是就产生了野心，毅然放弃了原先衣食无忧的新闻记者的工作，宁肯饿得“前胸贴后背”也要一圆自己当小说家的梦。在巴黎，他靠出售短篇小说为生。一旦小说卖不出去，他就得饿肚子。在腹中无食的情况下，他最怕的就是食物的诱惑，于是他出门就捡没有饭馆的街道走，因为饭馆里飘出的饭菜香味实在让他受不了。他有着重量级拳击手的体格，饭量大，吃进肚子里的东西却少得可怜！为了解决这个难题，他就拼命写作，越写越“狂”，质量越来越好，最终……

是的，他成功了，他的伙伴们也功成名就，否则老天就太不公平了。

海明威写的短篇小说极多，内容极为丰富。在长篇小说创作方面，他也业绩辉煌，除了《太阳照常升起》，另外还有《永别了，武器！》《有的和没有的》《丧钟为谁而鸣》和《过河入林》等。但真正使他留名世界文学史的是他的中篇小说《老人与海》。《老人与海》1952年出版，翌年他便荣获普利策奖，1954年获得了诺贝尔文学奖。

海明威的长篇小说并不多，但他的小说思想性强，令人回味无穷，赢得了成千上万的读者。美国著名史学家威德勒·索普曾在《二十世纪美国文学》中写道：“尽管海明威的小说要隔很长时间才出版一本，但是一本新小说在出版之前的几个月就已经引起了人们的争论，并且这种争论在小说出版后的几个月还在继续进行。”海明威的作品大受欢迎，除了“写实”之外，还有一个原因，就是其中充溢着美国人所喜欢的“阳刚之气”。他以高超的艺术手段塑造了一个个敢作敢为的英雄好汉。正如我国学者于冬云在评论文章中所言：“所谓海明威的文体风格，即赫·欧·贝茨所称道的简洁、干净、含蓄、凝练。这是一种‘绝不矫饰’‘平易粗放、街头硬汉般的文风’。他尤其擅长用‘那种公牛般的、出于本能的、缺少思想的语言’来陈述他故事中的那些猎人、渔夫、斗牛士、士兵、拳击者的思想和行为。福柯认为，影响和控制话语运动的最根本因素是权力。现代社会语言学研究也发现男性语体和女性语体是有区别的，男性语体是一种有力语体，女性语体则是一种无力语体。以此标准来重新审视贝茨一再称颂的海明威的文体风格，便不难发现在这种简洁粗硬的文风下掩盖的是男性权力特征。从早期创作开始，海明威就有意识地选择了这样一种叙事文体，并坚持使用了一生。因此，我们完全有理由说海明威的叙事文体是一种典型的男性话语方式。”

获奖后的海明威患有多种疾病，给他的身心带来了极大的痛苦，他没能再创作出很有影响的作品，这使他精神抑郁，形成了消极悲观的情绪。1961年7月2日，蜚声世界文坛的海明威用猎枪结束了自己的生命。整个世界都为此震惊，人们纷纷叹息这位巨人的悲剧。美国人民更是悲悼这颗美国文坛巨星的陨落。在这个总统死了都不会举国哀痛的国家，海明威何以能令全国上下“沉浸在哀痛之中”？就凭他独特的作品，就凭他那硬汉精神！海明威本人及其笔下的人物影响了整整一代甚至几代美国人，人们争相仿效他和他作品中的人物。他就是美国精神的化身。人们在为这种精神哭泣。

方华文

注释：

[1]　指在巴黎苦苦挣扎和奋斗的群体。

第三章

于人而言，吃一堑长一智需要花费大量时间。谁都知道事物具有两面性，可股市却始终只有一面。不是多头的一面，也不是空头的一面，而是正确的一面。真正记住这条通则所花费的时间，远远超过股票投机游戏中很多技术层次的东西。

据说有人能模拟操作股市，证明自己有多厉害。这些玄幻的赌徒有时的确能赚很多钱，这样很容易让人成为大赌特赌的赌徒，就像老故事里说的那样，某人第二天要与人决斗。

助手问他：“你能行吗？”

决斗的人说：“当然，我能在二十步之外射中酒杯脚。”他还一副很谦虚的样子。

“厉害啊。”助手没任何反应，“可酒杯上若有个手枪对着你的心脏，而且已经上膛了，你还能行吗？”

我觉得，必须要拥有实际赚到的钱才能证明自己的观点正确。我过去栽的跟头让我明白：只有百分百坚信不会后退，才可以开始前进。如果不能前进，那就蛰伏待动。我的意思并非说人犯错了不要去止损。他就该那样做，不过最好不要把自己培养成优柔寡断的人。我这辈子总在犯错，不过我会吸取教训，也总结了一些很实用的经验。有那么几次，我的亏损很大，但是我的亏损从来都不是彻底的亏损。不然的话，我现在也就不是我了。我总是相信自己还有机会，我不会在同一条道上摔两次。我相信自己。

如果谁要靠这种游戏过活的话，就必须要自信，只有自信才不至于盲目相信各种乱七八糟的内幕消息。如果按照史密斯的内幕消息去买进卖出，那他就成了我的心理依靠，他一旦外出度假，又恰逢交易的好机会来了，那该怎么办？不能这样啊，先生，可不能靠别人教我们怎么去赚钱。以我的经验来看，只有靠自己的判断才能赚更多钱，不管谁提供的消息都比不上这个，我用五年时间才学会了怎么聪明地玩这个游戏，足以让我在自己正确时赚大钱。

我身上没有多少你认为的那种有趣经历。我的意思是，学习怎么样去投机股票，这个历程没有什么趣味性。我有好多令人不爽的失败经历，跟华尔街上的那些人一模一样。投机是一件非常耗人的艰难事情，玩的人一定要紧盯着不能松懈，不然的话随时都可能会失业。

本来，我要做的事情也不难，在受到富勒顿公司的打击后我就应该知道了：换个角度去看待投机。但我没有很快认识到，其实很多东西在对赌行都没办法学到。我觉得在投机过程中已经能手到擒来了，其实只不过是在对赌行有点小小战绩而已。而在对赌行的那些日子的确让我的分析判断能力有所提升，尤其是训练了记忆力。这两点我学得很好。身为交易人士，我起先的那些成功经历都源于这两点，而并不是我有多么聪明或者多么博学，我没受过头脑训练，是很无知的。在玩这个游戏的过程中我学会了操作，而且这个游戏也在教导我的同时很冷血地鞭打我。

直到现在我都记得初到纽约那天的情形。我提到过对赌行不跟我做生意，所以我只能去找名号响亮的经纪人。我原来有个同事在纽交所会员企业哈丁兄弟公司工作，我早上到纽约后，中午一点前就在那家公司开好了股票账户，准备交易。

我没有跟你解释过。我是多么自然而然地就玩起对赌行那一套，瞅准股价走势，伺机捕捉一小段一定会出现的价格变化。没人对我说这与原来有何不同，要是有人告诉我这样是不行的，那我也一定会去验证一番。只有赔钱才让我相信我错了，只要能赚钱就是正确之道。这就是投机的实质。

那段时日，股市活跃，股民们轻松快活，很让人兴奋，我一下子就如鱼得水。熟悉的股市行情公告就在我的眼前，大家谈的话我15岁以前就学会了。有个男孩干着我刚开始做事时干的那些活，股民们一动不动地看着股市行情公告牌，大喊着股价数字，讨论着行情。机器跟我熟悉的机器显然完全一样。空气和我在伯灵顿赚到第一笔钱（就是那3.12美元）以来所呼吸的空气一样。行情还是那样的行情，股民还是那种股民，游戏也还是那个游戏。不要忘记，这时候我才22岁，我觉得自己已经完全掌握了这个游戏规则，难道不是这样吗？

我专心观察着股市行情公告牌，看准了想买的股票，它的形势不错，84美元，我买了100股，没到半个小时，我就以85美元抛掉。紧接着，我又瞅准了另一只股票，然后用相同手法行事，在很短的时间里净赚3/4个点。初试身手就旗开得胜，不是吗？

请注意，在这家名气很响的地方，光在头一天只花了两个小时，我就买卖了1100股，抢进抢出。但是那天的结果是，我赔掉了1100美元，意思是我在纽交所第一次出手就损失了一半资金。请记住，有赚钱的时候，但最后赔掉了1100美元。

我没有在意，因为我根本不知道哪里出错了。我的每一步都稳稳当当，如果在之前的对赌行，肯定是稳赚不赔的。失去的那1100美元很清楚地告诉我，机器没有以正常的方式对待我，可只要机器操作人员没有问题，就没什么可担心的。22岁年轻人的懵懂不是什么大弱点。

过了几天，我告诉自己：“在这里这样交易可不行，这里出来的信息没有多大的参考价值。”不过这也就是一闪念的事，我没深想，继续按照老路子玩，有赚有赔，一直赔到一文不剩，我就去跟老富勒顿借了500美元。后来我带着从对赌行赚到的那些钱，再次由圣路易斯跑到纽约。

我学得更加谨慎，有一阵子还玩得比较顺手。手头一宽裕，我就尽力让生活惬意点。我认识了一些新朋友，日子过得还不错。不要忘记，我才不到23岁，一个人能闯荡纽约，口袋里也有挣来的钱，我心中坚信我已经开始了解新的股价机器了。

我开始考虑我的单子下到证券交易所大厅后实际的执行情况，行动变得特别谨慎，不过我还是相信来自纸上的那些信息，没有在意普遍性的规则。我一直不转变方式，就看不出自己操作上的真正问题。

1901年，经济开始进入大增长时期，我挣了很多钱——对一个年轻人来说——是很多钱。你还记得那些日子吗？国家经济繁荣，工业兼并和资本重组来势汹汹，股市被疯狂地托举起来。我听说以前日子红火时，华尔街号称日成交量达到了25万股，一天能倒腾2500万美元的股票。到1901年，股民们制造了日成交量300万股的创世纪录，每个人都在赚钱。那些挥金如土的钢铁巨头也进来了，都是些百万富翁，能让他们感到满意的游戏就是闯荡股市。我们曾遇到过这样的大人物：约翰·盖茨和他的一群朋友，他们常挂在嘴边的一句话就是“赌个100万”，比如约翰·德里克、罗伊尔·史密斯这些里德-利兹-摩尔集团的人，他们把钢铁公司的股份卖掉，然后在股市把罗德岛系统的一大半股份买进手里。还有施瓦布、弗里克、菲甫斯和匹斯堡集团，更别提很多很多在这场金钱易主的游戏中亏了本，但在其他行当里都被奉为大作手的人了。你可以买卖所有的股票。凯恩炒热了美国钢铁公司的股票。一个经纪人几分钟就能卖掉10万股，多美好的时代啊，多令人艳羡的巨头啊，而且人们不用为卖掉股票纳税，简直就是一派没有终点的祥和气氛。

没多久，我听到了熊市要来的流言。老手们都说，除了他们，其他人都是疯子。可事实却是除了他们外，其他人都赚到了钱。我自然知道，牛市总有到头的时候，见股票就收入囊中的疯劲儿也有终止的一天——我做好了面对熊市的心理准备。可我每次卖出后都在亏，如果不是我出手快，可能会赔更多。我梦想着股市暴跌，但我也小心翼翼地操作。我买进的股票赚了钱，抛掉的又赔本了，一直没赚什么大钱，虽然你们会因为我出手豪爽而觉得我赚了不少。

有一只股票我一直没放空，就是北太平洋铁路的股票。我以往具有的那些能力有了用武之地，通过分析后我觉得大多数股票都已经被人买到久盘不动了，而北太平洋的走势却很好，可能还会上涨。我们现在都清楚，当时不管是普通股还是优先股，都被库恩-罗布-哈里曼集团收入囊中。我手里握着北太平洋1000普通股，没有被其他人的意见左右，一直牢牢抓住不放。当它涨到110美元的时候，已经上涨了30个点，我立马伺机卖掉，赚了将近5万美元，这是那时候我赚得最多的一笔钱。对于几个月前在同一个地方还赔得吐血的人来说，这种成绩就算非常难得了。

你可能记得，哈里曼集团那时候通知摩根集团和希尔集团说，他们要取代摩根在北太平洋铁路公司的地位，然后摩根集团事先让操盘的凯恩买进5万股北太平洋，设法保住他们对公司的控股权。据说，凯恩让银行家罗伯特·培根做好了买15万股的准备，罗伯特照办了。总之，凯恩派了他的经纪人艾迪·诺顿去买北太平洋的10万股。我觉得，他们接下来又买了5万股，然后演变成一场著名的收购大战。1901年5月8日闭市后，谁都知道有两家金融巨鳄的战争正在持续。这个国家从未出现过规模如此庞大的巨头资本之战，哈里曼对战摩根，真正的棋逢对手啊。

5月9日早上，我拿着5万美元现金，没有一只股票。我说过，我做好了迎接熊市的准备，现在机会来了。我知道接下来要发生的事情：从暴跌开始，接着很多价格低廉的股票充斥股市，用不了多久又马上反弹，然后那些低价买进的股民们就会大赚。这都不用他福尔摩斯来推理我也能判断出这一点。我们即将有机会在股价一涨一跌之间稳稳当当地获取巨大利润。

所有事情都在我的预料之中，可是我却赔尽了钱。我没有料到会有一些意外出现。如果人们不遇到突发事件，大家就不会有什么差别，生活该是多么无趣，炒股也就只是乏味的增减，而股民也只是思维僵化的记账员而已。恰恰就是预测让人脑洞大开。你只要想想要猜得正确你必须做什么，就知道这一点。

就像我预测的那样，股市又变得疯狂了，巨额的成交量，变幻无常的股价。我下了一大堆卖单。我看到想做的股票开盘价不是太好，心里一阵兴奋。经纪人为我忙着，他们与其他经纪人一样兢兢业业，可等到他们执行我的单子时，价格已经跌了20多个点。成交量太大了，报价纸带上的数字远远落在市况之后。当我按报价纸带显示的股价，比如100美元，下单卖出股票时，经纪人却以80美元替我卖掉，比前一天的收盘价还低三四十美元，这好像是我花钱让股价跌落到我想买的低价了。不过股价不会一直这样下跌，所以我马上决定平了空头，掉转方向做多头。

经纪人按照交易所接到单子时候的那个股价买进股票，并不能按照能让我有利可图的那个股价买，而是他们的场内人员拿到我的委托单时，证券交易所的市价。他们付出的价格比我预估的高出15点，谁能受得了一天之内就损失35点呢。

我被滞后的信息完全损伤了，根据报价机信息判断行情的习惯耍了我，纸上显示的股价和真实的股价不符让我遭受了大损失。我被曾经让我失败过的东西再次打倒。如此看来，光靠那些滞后的信息，而不顾经纪人是怎么操作的会吃大亏。我特别吃惊，为什么早没有搞明白这点而找到应对措施呢。

我的行为比看不出来还糟糕，我继续交易，继续抢进抢出，也没考虑经纪人的操作规律。你知道，我没做过限价交易，我要抓住机会，打败股市而不是股价。我一旦觉得可以卖就赶紧卖掉，觉得股价会涨就赶紧买进，坚守投机的这一条通则挽救了我。在对赌行里的那一套——简单地玩限价交易——在股票交易所里也可以使用。倘若不是吃了亏，我就学不到实打实的投机玩法，只能按照粗浅的经验一直冒险。

为了减少纸带机滞后于股市的不利影响，我每次都尝试玩限价买卖，但股市一直飞速变化，我只好放弃这样的做法。我都不知道为什么会有这样的改变，耗了那么多年，我才知道不能赌随后几档的小小起伏，而应该赌预期即将出现的大波动。

5月9日赔了以后，我就改变了做法，不过还是有漏洞。要不是偶尔会赚点钱，我可能会更快地学到市场中的智慧。但我赚到的钱也够我舒服地生活，开心地享受生活。那年夏天，我跟其他富裕发达的华尔街人一样，到新泽西海滨去避暑，只是赚的钱不足以支撑我的亏损和生活开销。

我继续那样交易，不是因为我顽固不化，而是我不知道问题出在哪里，更别说如何解决了。我不厌其烦地说这些，只是想让你知道，天将降大任于我，必会先让我吃些苦。在对付大型动物时，我的那杆老猎枪与高超的来复枪相比，劣势太明显了。

这年秋天，我一方面输掉了全部的资金，另一方面对屡败屡战的炒股游戏也产生了厌倦，我做出了离开纽约的决定，想换个地方换个方向玩。我从14岁开始玩股票，15岁赚到第一个1000美元，21岁赚到第一个1万美元。我很多次赚了上万美元又亏掉了。我在纽约赚过几千、几万美元，又把这些钱亏掉了。我最多赚过5万美元，两天后，又赔得血本无归。我没有其他的生意，也不知道别的游戏。几年以后，我被打回原点。更不幸的是，我变得花钱如流水一般，虽然这没有赔钱那样令我不舒服。

第四章

好吧，我回家了。但是从回来那一刻开始，我忽然觉得，凑集些资本再转战华尔街，这才是我生活的目标。在整个美国，只有华尔街才是我唯一能玩大钱的地方。未来某一天，我找到那种感觉，并且凑够了钱，就会需要在华尔街那样的地方找存在感。当人状态比较好的时候，就会对那些有利条件充满渴望。

虽然希望不大，但是我对对赌行还是寄予厚望。这时候，城市里已经很少有对赌行了，有几家我还不熟悉。有些对赌行还记得我，不让我大显身手，虽然我跟他们解释说，我在纽约赔光了所有的钱，我并没有原来所想的那样清楚股市，让我玩一玩对他们没有什么损害，但他们就是不同意。而新开的那些地方又不可靠，新老板们都觉得，要是一个客户有理由认定自己会猜对，顶多只应该买卖20股。

我很缺钱，规模大些的对赌行能从客户手里收集足够多的资金，所以我找朋友跟我搭伙玩。我自己只偶尔进去瞧瞧，然后悄然撤退。有一次，我心痒难耐，劝说工作人员允许我玩一把，哪怕就50股。他当然拒绝了我。我和朋友提前编好了交流的暗号，以便于我指导他怎么玩。这种办法虽然一时管用，可于我来说太小打小闹。没多长时间，这个对赌行的人在接到我朋友的单子时开始抱怨。终于有那么一天，我朋友准备卖掉圣保罗的100股时，他们拒绝了他。

后来我们才明白是怎么回事。有人看到我们在外面说话，就去对赌行告了密。当我朋友拿单子要卖出圣保罗的100股时，对方就拉着脸说：“我们不接受任何圣保罗的卖单，尤其是你的单子。”

“为什么呀，乔？”朋友问。

“不接就是不接，就这么简单。”乔回答说。

“这些钱难道不是钱吗？你看清楚，全都在这里。”朋友拿出100美元递给他——我的100美元——一共10张10美元的。乔恼羞成怒地盯着他，我在旁边偷偷瞧着，像每一次看客户与对赌行吵架一样。其他股友们都围拢了过去，围在两个争吵的人身边。有人大声说话，或者对赌行和顾客之间，有任何争吵的迹象时，他们都会这样。他们喜欢凑热闹当看客，以便了解对赌行的实力。

乔是对赌行的经理助理，他从柜台后走出来，走到我朋友面前，看着他，然后又看看我。

“真好笑，”他慢条斯理地说，“太好笑了！你朋友利文斯顿没来时，你没事可干，光盯着公告牌看，一看就是几个小时，一句话都不说。可是他来了后，你就忙活得停不下了。你可能是在为你自己玩，但是这里以后就是不让你交易了。我们的交易规则还是跟原来一样，我们不上利文斯顿替你通风报信的当。”

唉，这简直就是要逼死我啊。幸好我挣来的那点钱比花掉的多几百美元。我就想着怎么花钱才能物超所值，要去纽约是件很紧迫的事情。我想，下一次自己一定会做得更好。花时间对曾经的愚蠢行为进行反省后，我慢慢明白，首要目标是进行下一次的冒险行动。你看，当一个人站得远一些，他就能更清楚地看清事实。

有一天，我和朋友们在一家旅馆大堂聊天。这些人都是稳稳当当的股民，我们一起聊着股市。我说：“以我的经验来看，经纪人执行方法拙劣，不可能有人赚钱，特别是像我这样，用市价交易的时候。”

有个人扯着大嗓门问，我话里说的经纪人是谁。

“全美国最好的经纪人。”我这样回答。他就继续问最好的经纪人又是谁。我知道他一点儿都不相信我曾经在最牛的公司里炒过股。

我说：“就是纽交所的那些经纪人。并非他们不实在或者不细心，是你在那里填单子的时候，没办法知悉股票的实际股价，直到经纪人把成交回报单给你以后才可以。股票波动个一两点的次数，总比波动十几点的次数多，可股民受限于成交的条件，抓不住那点小波动来赚钱。如果对赌行里不设限制可以大玩，我都想天天泡在那里。”

跟我对话的人叫罗伯茨，我以前从来没见过他。他好像很乐意帮我。他把我拉到旁边，问我是不是在其他地方玩过，我否认了。他说他知道一些棉花和其他农产品的交易所，还有些规模小点的交易所会员公司。这些地方非常小心在意，特别注重经纪人完成任务的质量，与纽交所那样的大机构的关系非常好。靠这些影响力和每个月几十万股的稳定生意，他们能为散户股民们提供更好的服务。

“他们真的能满足散户们的需求。”他说着，“而且，他们的特长就是做外地业务。不管10股还是10万股他们都一视同仁。那里的工作人员特别热情能干，值得信任。”

“好吧。可如果他们要向纽交所付1/8点佣金，那还赚什么钱呢？”

“嗯，他们付的应该是1/8点的佣金。不过……你懂的。”他朝我挤眉弄眼。

“是啊。”我说，“但是他们不退佣金，这不公平。证券交易所主管宁可让会员犯谋杀、纵火和重婚罪，也不愿意他们在和外地人做生意时，收取比1/8点佣金还低的费用。证券交易所能不能生存，靠的就是这个规则。”

他可能确定了我曾经在交易所与人交过手，就继续说：“你听我说，也有违反规则被罚停一年交易的证券交易所会员公司，是吧？退佣金的方法太多太多了，没人会告发的。”见我一脸疑惑，他又说，“另外，有特殊服务的时候，我们……我的意思是，那些有自己的通信办法的公司会在1/8点佣金之上加收1/32点。这很公平，除非出现特殊情况，比如有人的账户不怎么有动静，不然是不会额外收钱的。你懂的，不然他们就赔了。他们做生意可不是完全为了自己的健康着想。”

我终于明白，他是为一些冒牌经纪人拉活呢。

“你可以介绍个可靠点的公司吗？”我问。

“我知道全美国最大的经纪公司。”他答道，“我自己就在那里玩过，他们有78个分公司遍布美国和加拿大，生意特别好。如果不可靠，他们怎么可能年复一年做得那么好呢，是不是？”

“这倒是。”我附和说，“他们和纽交所做的一样吗？”

“一样，他们那里有交易市场和欧美交易所上市的所有股票，涉及小麦、棉花和其他农产品。任何你想做的，他们都做。世界各地都有他们的代理。他们是所有交易所的会员，不是用自己的名字参加的会员，就是秘密会员。”

我已经了如指掌了，但我仍然想多套出些内情。

“是啊。”我说，“可是即便这样，那些指令还是需要别人去执行，世界上没有谁能保证市况会怎么变化，报出的股价和报价机上显示的股价有多接近。股民们等在那儿得到消息，递上单子，再打电报到纽约，已经浪费了很多宝贵时间。我还是去纽约更好些，我宁可把钱输在一家可靠的公司里。”

“我不懂输钱，我们的股民没有这种习惯。他们负责赚钱，我们负责照顾生意。”

“你们的股民？”

“哦，我在这家公司有些股份，我如果能招揽生意进去的话，也是乐意去做的。他们对我还可以，帮助我赚了些钱。你要同意的话，我介绍你认识他们。”

“这家公司名叫什么？”我问。

他说了名字，我也听说过，这家公司在很多报纸上做过广告，宣传他们能通过内部消息帮别人炒股发财，这是他们的突出特点。这家公司不是通常所说的那种对赌行，而是个坑骗股民的地方。他们伪装得很好，总能让人相信他们是合法正规的普通公司。其实，这样的公司存在很久了。

在那个时代，他们是以卖空买空为职业的人，就是如今被吊销了执照的经纪人，他们的诈骗原则和形式都没有发生变化，只是路数上有了变化，那些谁都知晓的邪恶手段改了个形式。

这类人会经常放出些内幕消息，忽悠股民们买卖股票。他们发出大量电报建议人们买进某一只股票，同时又发出很多电报给另一部分人卖出这只股票，就像那些传统的赌马顾问一样。接着，买卖双方的交易单就会大量涌入，公司再利用一家名气好的交易所会员机构买进和卖出1000股这只股票，所谓的规范经营记录也就产生了，要是哪个家伙不礼貌，怀疑他们在客户的单子上做手脚的话，这就是他们用来反驳质疑者的凭证。

这类公司也发行自己经营的交易基金，以自认为最妥帖的形式，让参与者以书面形式把姓名和资金使用权授予他们。所以，当客户们的钱不翼而飞时，就算最暴躁的客户也没办法找到让他们合法赔偿的证据。他们会在账面上做多一只股票，然后忽悠股民们跟进，再耍个卖空的手段，骗掉几百个客户的保证金。他们谁都不放过，就连女人、教师和老人都是他们的忽悠对象。

“我讨厌所有的经纪人。”我对这个推销员说，“让我考虑一下。”随后我赶紧离开，以免他再跟我多说话。

我调查这家违规对赌行后发现，他们的客户有好几百人，虽然名声有些不好，可是我还没听说他们拒绝支付哪怕一个客户赚到的钱，本身要找到一个在那家公司赚了钱的客户就不容易，不过我还是赢钱了。当时总的来看，股市行情好像有利于他们，所以若一次交易有了损失，他们不会对客户耍赖。只是大多数这样的公司最后都倒闭了。美国出现过好多次这类公司的倒闭潮，就像传染病一样，一批批对赌行接二连三地倒闭了。没倒闭的对赌行，客户们也像惊弓之鸟，忙着把钱从里面抽出来。不过，在这个国家仍然有一些暂时停手的对赌行老板在卧薪尝胆，随时准备出击。

那个人介绍的这家公司一直在挣钱，不时会有些诈骗事件发生，此外也没什么令人惊讶的消息。他们最擅长的就是忽悠那些想一口气吃成胖子的笨蛋，让他们在感觉不对时没办法用法律来自我保护。

有个小伙子对我讲了他亲眼所见的一出戏。有一天，有家对赌行发出了600份电报，让客户们买进一只股票，同时又发出另外600份电报，忽悠另外一群客户出售这只股票。

“对，我清楚这种手段。”我对他说。

“不错。”他说，“第二天，他们又给那些客户发了电报，让他们平仓，去买卖另一只股票。我就问他们的一个高级合伙人，这样做的原因是什么。我明白他们前一部分的做法，是利用客户觉得会赚钱的心理，虽然最后他们都会亏损。可是你们发出这样的电报不就等于是把他们全部杀掉吗？这么做是为什么？”

“哦。”那个合伙人说，“不管他们怎么买卖，跟谁买卖，什么时候买卖，在哪里买卖，反正这些客户都铁定要赔钱。一旦客户亏了钱，我就会失掉这些客户，我不如趁机从他们身上大捞一笔，之后再去找其他客户。”

说实话，我对这些公司的商业道德丝毫不感兴趣。我提到过，泰勒公司欺负我，让我反感并决心去报复他们。可是这家公司，并没有让我产生那种感觉。他们是骗子没错，可也不见得有传说的那样可恶。我根本不想让他们替我做任何交易，不想遵照他们的内幕消息进行操作，也不会相信他们的鬼话。我只想赶紧赚钱去纽约，找一家名正言顺的公司做大生意，不用为警察忽然查访而提心吊胆，不用担心检察官们会冻结资金什么的。

不管怎样，我打定主意要去探访这家对赌行，看他们到底有哪些比正规公司更诱人的条件。因为没多少钱，这样的公司又比较随便些，我就可以用几百美元去试水，一探究竟。

我来到这家公司后，找到了经理。他知道我是个老手，曾经在纽约交易所会员公司开过户，而且把带去的钱全部亏光之后，就理所当然觉得我是个只会赔本的顽固分子，是经纪商稳定的衣食父母——不管他们是在你单子上作假的经纪商，还是乐于只赚手续费的经纪商。

我对这个经理说，我想找的是执行力最强的公司，我一直在市场中玩，不想看到那种比实际股价滞后1个点的情形。

他向我保证说，任何我认为正确的事情，他们都愿意做。他说他们想接我的生意，是因为他们想让我见识一下什么叫一流的公司。他们拥有很精明的工作人员，能以最快的速度完成操作，他们是靠这个出了名的。如果出现股价滞后的情况，他们不承诺一定精确到位，但会选择有利于客户的那个价格，我如果在这里开了户，马上就可以电报交易。很明显，他们对自家工作人员的执行水平很自信，如此一来，我完全可以当作是在正规对赌行玩一样。他们的意思是，希望我从下一轮就开始交易，我不想表现得太急切，所以拒绝了，说可能现在还不行。他就急切地忽悠我不要失去机会，要抓紧时间马上开始。

在他们眼里，确实该这样。股市只要有轻微波动的时候，就是鼓动股民们去交易的时机，再在股市不稳定的时候榨掉他们身上的钱，把他们套牢。

我只是留了姓名和地址。不过，从那天起，我就开始收到相关的电报和信件，劝我买某只股票，还说有一家大机构会把这只股票炒高50点。

我忙碌起来了，开始寻找类似的其他公司。要想不受这一家的桎梏，多赚些钱，就需要多方下手，在邻近的几家公司一起玩。

清楚行情后，我在三家公司开了户，还租了一个小办公室，安上了电报机，以便直接与他们联系。

我小心翼翼地行事，为了不吓着他们，我把钱平均了一下投了进去。刚起步，我就赚到了钱，不过他们还是劝我做大一些，胆小鬼是不怎么受待见的。他们以为我做得越大就会赔得越多，输个精光也是指日可待，这样他们也就赚得越多。这种理论是有道理的——要是你想到他们打交道的都是一般散户，而一般散户在财务方面，从来都无法长久生存下去。破产的客户没钱了就没办法交易，但半死不活的客户会抱怨、不满，制造一些伤害业务的事故。

我还联系了一家公司，他们可以直接用电报联系上纽约的代理人，这个代理人还是纽交所的会员。我买了一台自动收报机，谨慎地开始操作。我提到过，这很像是在对赌行里交易，只是稍微慢点。

在这样的游戏中，我可以赚钱，也的确赚了钱。我还没修炼到投进去多少就赚取多少的境界，但是我基本上都在赚钱，周复一周地赚钱。我又有了生活舒适的资本了，还为去华尔街大干一番存了些钱。我还选择了另外两家经纪商，加起来就有了五家——当然了，他们都是我来钱的源头。

我的计划也有失败的时候，选择的股票走势跟我的预期发展完全不一样。不过这对我没造成什么损伤，因为我的保证金不多。我与经纪人关系处理得也还不错，他们的账目和记录常常跟我的不同，自然是想坑我。这是多巧的事情——人为制造的巧合。每次遇到这类情况，我都会竭尽全力维护自己的利益，基本上都是以我获胜结束。他们也拼着命想从我手中捞走我捞来的钱，可能他们觉得我赚的钱只是暂时性的贷款。

他们真的不正派，因为他们靠耍花招或设骗局赚钱，对经纪商应该赚取的利润不满意。一味地想着发大财的人总会赔本——他们从来不慎重，你或许觉得他们在合法地做非法生意。其实不是这样。“把客户当上帝才能赚钱。”这是经得起推敲的古训，可是他们却视而不见，就想着靠欺骗换钱。

好几次他们都想耍老手段请我入瓮。我只要一不留神，就会掉入瓮中。他们总是在我的交易金额比正常少的时候，设法坑害我。我指责他们欺诈，他们当然不会承认，然后一切又照旧进行。与骗子交往，有个好处是，只要你能一直和他们保持交易，他们就会原谅你抓到他们的小辫子，这对于他们想赚钱的目的来说，都是小事一桩，他们乐于尽可能地包容你。真是好大方的一群东西啊！

对他们的鬼把戏忍受够了以后，我就准备采取反制。首先，我选择了一些炒得已经失去兴头的冷门股，如果我直接用垃圾股来玩，他们可能会对我产生怀疑。其次，我告诉五个经纪人要买入这只股票。他们收到我发的单子后，等着下一轮的股价行情，我就在熟悉的一家交易所里，让他们为我马上卖掉100股那只股票。你能想象得出，当卖单出现的时候，人们会怎么样想：一家和外地有关系的经纪商竟然这么急着想卖出冷门股票，肯定是有人手里有廉价股。我给出的股价会出现在报价单上，我耐心等着低价买进400股这只股票。那几家公司很疑虑，问我知道了什么消息，我只告诉他们我知道点内幕消息。闭市之前，我又让那家交易所赶紧为我买回来100股，反正我不想做这100股空头，也不管它价格多高，这立马抬高了股价。与此同时，我要赶紧抛售400股，他们就给纽约发电报立刻照办。这样的话，我就达到了要给那些跟着炒作500股的经纪人一点儿颜色的目的。这是个令人满意的买卖过程。

他们没有亡羊补牢，所以我惩罚了他们好几次，但其实这离他们应得的惩罚还远呢，100股对于推动股价显得太少，很少能超过1个点，不过我却能为以后去华尔街做投资积攒一点儿钱。有时候我会改变一下，卖空一些股票，但是从来没做得过于张扬。我很满意每次尝试都净赚600或800美元。

有一天，我怎么也没料到，我的绝妙技巧居然拉动了十几个点的波动。我不是有意做成这样的，只是我恰好在一家经纪商那里操作200股，而不是像平常一样操作100股。不过，我在其他几家还是做了100股，可对他们的教训已经不小了。他们像受训狗一样痛苦不堪，怨恨说股市被人操控了。所以我去找那个劝我开户的经理的时候，他气愤地说：“有人在操纵股市，我不会给你付钱的。”他之前每次耍花招被我发现的时候，都假装宽宏大量的样子。以他的职位来说，他当时说的话的确是大言不惭。

“我把单子给你的时候，并没有人操控，我能在你这里买进，就必须要卖出，这就是公平，你不能耍赖啊，清楚吗？”

他嚷道：“是，我就耍赖，我知道有人在捣乱。”

“谁？”

“有人。”

“那他们想捣谁的乱？”

他说：“你的朋友肯定知情。”

不过我告诉他：“你们都清楚，我是独来独往的，这个城市里每个人都知道这点，从一开始他们就知道。现在我客客气气地对你讲，快给我钱，我不想发脾气，快点。”

他吼道：“一毛钱都没有，这笔交易有人作弊。”

我烦躁得要命，正告他：“你立即把钱付我。”

嚯，他表现得更厉害了，骂我是个大骗子，但最终还是给我付了钱。其他公司的人都没这么暴躁。一家公司的经理在办公室研究了我操控冷门股票的那套玩法，他接到我的单子时，自己也跟着买了些，有清清楚楚的记录，他也赚了些钱。这些人不会害怕人们告他们欺诈，他们一直准备着各种说辞。可他们害怕我会把他们生财的物件给查封了，至于在银行的钱，他们不会害怕，因为他们不会让钱暴露在这种危险当中。说他们很精明是不会为他们带来损失的，但是说他们赖账就不一样了，这不是好名声。客户们在经纪人手里赔钱不是什么稀罕事，可如果拿不到赚的钱，那可是这一行最大的忌讳。

我拿到了钱，不过这次操纵10个上涨点的事情，结束了我骗那些骗子的美好时光。他们密切注意寻找他们用来欺骗几百个可怜客户的小花招。我又像以前一样玩，但市场并不是始终配合我的系统，我也不是一直很顺利——我的意思是我受到下单金额的限制，没办法赚大钱。

做了一年多，我使尽了这个行当里的各种解数，赚了钱，日子过得也还不错，还买了一辆车，只是钱还是不够用。我需要赚钱，也需要生活。即使炒股一切顺利，我也要节约些，不能大手大脚；如果不太顺利，自然没钱花了。我节省下来了一笔钱，觉得在这五家对赌行是没机会赚大钱的，所以就决定回纽约去。

我开着车，和一个做汽车生意的朋友，一起踏上了去纽约的路。在纽黑文停下吃饭时，我们碰到了一个做过生意的老交情，聊天时他说城里还有家生意很好的对赌行。

在驶离旅店去纽约的路上，我们看到了那家对赌行，光从外面瞅瞅是没办法消除心痒的，于是我们下车进去看。里面不是很阔绰，但是熟悉的看板，还有客户都在那里，而且股票游戏正在进行。

经理像是当过演员或者正在发表竞选演说，他的话动人心弦。他对大家说早安的样子，就好像他用显微镜花了十年的时间去找早晨，发现了早晨的好处，并且把这个发现跟蓝天、晨光和公司的资金，当成礼物献给你。他看我们开着很华丽的车，就觉得我们既年轻又显得无所事事——我估计我看起来才20岁——可能是耶鲁大学的学生。我们没告诉他我们真正的来历，他也没给我们说话的机会，就开始一番演说。他说很高兴见到我们，问我们能否找个位置坐下来，还说上午的这次交易是慈善活动，是为了给大学生们赚个零花钱的机会，而有史以来，聪明的大学生零花钱从来就没够用过。既然已经到了这里，就借机投入一点儿钱，会让你获得很高的收入。股市上能赚到任何人所能花费的零用钱。

呃，对赌行的经理这么急着让我们玩，不玩一把多可惜啊。所以，我就对他说要玩一下，因为我听说很多人都炒股赚了大钱。

一开始我只是小玩了一把，赢到钱后，就加大了些投入，我朋友也一起跟着玩。

我们在纽黑文住了一晚，第二天上午十点零五分，我又到了这家诱人的对赌行，经理很高兴再次看到我们，他觉得我们会好运连连。我赚了将近1500美元。又隔一天上午，我们进去看到那位伟大的演讲家后，我给了他一张卖出500股的单子，他犹豫不决，不过还是照办了。股价下跌超过1个点，我结束了交易，赚了500美元，加上500美元的保证金，他从钱柜里拿了1000美元，20张50美元的钞票，翻来覆去数了好几遍，又在我眼前一张张数一番，就像有汗粘住了钱一样，但是他终于还是把钱给了我。他站在我后面，双臂抱在一起，咬着嘴唇盯着我身后的一扇窗户上面看。

我说我要卖出200股钢铁公司的股票，他装作没听见，我又改口说300股，他才回过神来，只是望着我，然后吧唧着嘴咽了咽口水，一副要指摘腐败体制的模样。临了，他用手指着我手里的钞票说：“带着些玩意儿走吧。”

我问：“什么玩意儿？”我没搞懂他指的什么。

他生气了：“大学生，你们要去哪里？”

我说：“纽约。”

他絮絮叨叨地说：“很好，很好，你们必须走，今天我算认识了两个家伙——学生！我知道你们不是，你们是什么我清楚了。哼！哼！哼！”

我礼貌地说：“就这样吗？”

他稍顿一下后说：“就这样，你们——”说着他失去了在大厅里原有的理智，气愤地叫道，“你们两个是全美国最大的骗子！学生？一年级学生吧！哼！”

我们离开自言自语的他。他也许在乎的不是钱，所有把这种事当职业的人都不会在乎钱，有赚有赔在所难免，只是他受到了我们的耍弄，自尊心受到了伤害。

我就这样第三次来到了华尔街，其实我一直在研究我的炒股方法，试图找出真正的问题，找出让我在富勒顿公司功败垂成的原因。

20岁时，我第一次玩1万美元并且赔掉了，可我知道是为什么——因为我没抓好机会，没利用好经验和钻研出的方法，纯粹靠赌博。我想要赚钱，可是却不知道应该在适宜的时候来赚钱。22岁的时候，我已经凑够了5万美元，却在5月9日的时候赔了个精光，我也知道这是为什么——原因是股市行情记录滞后，还出现了幅度很大的波动。可是自打从圣路易斯回到纽约，经历了5月9日的恐慌事件后，我仍然没有搞懂输钱的真正原因。我有一些理论，能够起到些亡羊补牢的作用，但是我需要实际操作。

世界上没有什么比让你失去一切更能教会你什么是不该做的了，一旦你知道了不该做什么才能不亏钱时，你也就开始学习该做什么才能赚钱了，知道了吗？你开始学习了！

第五章

特别痴迷于股市的人会出错，我觉得这就像是太过专业化后就容易走入死胡同一样，少了灵活的东西就会得不偿失。不能只把投资看成是单靠数学或一些定律就能做好的事情。不管主要的法则多严格，就算我在看股市行情的时候，也不光是玩点计算题，其中有我称之为股票行为的东西，就是股票的动作，能够让我根据我所观察到的前例，判断股票是否会这样运动。如果一只股票不能尽如人意，就不能乱动。如果连其中的原因都搞不清，也就无法预估市场行情，没办法判断，就无法预测股票，也就赚不到钱。

观察股票走势，研究过去的变化走向，这是一门古老的学问。刚来纽约时，我就在一家股票公司听到一个法国人卖弄他的图表，当时我以为他是公司的一个弄臣。但是后来我发现他说的话都经得起验证，富有感染力。他说股市图表是唯一不骗人的东西，靠着图表就可以预估股票走势，以此分析股市。比如为什么凯恩可以操纵股票，在炒作凯奇逊股票的时候大赚特赚，而在投资南太平洋股票的时候却一败涂地。有的职业股民也尝试过这个法国人的方法，可不久就走回了老路，他们觉得靠运气投机的风险没那么大。那个法国人说过，凯恩也确信他的图表是完全没错的，可是在变幻多端的股市中，这个方法太慢了。

那时候，有一家股票公司保存了股价走势图，它能显示出几个月内每只股票的走势情形，通过比较个别股票和总的变化趋势，记住一些规律，股民们就能判断出他们靠不科学的消息买的股票是不是真的要上涨。他们把这张图当成了一种辅助性的资料来源。如今很多股票公司都有这样的图表，是统计专家们专门统计绘制的，除了股票走势外，还有商品期货的走势图。

或者我可以这样说，图表只对能看懂图表的人起作用，准确点说，只对能吸收图表信息的人有所帮助。一般的人看图容易变得执迷不悟，认定底部和头部，主要和次要波动，就是股票投机的一切。要是他把这种信心推展到理智的极限，他注定会破产。有个脑瓜子好使的人，他做过一家著名交易所的合伙人，还是位有实力的数学家。他从知名技校毕业，发明了各种图表，他专门研究过大量市场——股票、债券、谷物、棉花、货币等各种东西的价格形势，还追溯它们过去几年的关联和变化的所有方面。很多年里，他都在使用图表，他所做的事情其实是利用一些极为高明的平均法。听说他是常胜将军，一直到世界大战改变了市场性质才作罢。他说他和手下人在退出市场之前，赔掉了几百万。可一切都得看形势，牛市就是牛市，熊市也只能是熊市，谁都没办法阻止。想赚钱的人，都必须要正确地预估形势，确定是不是具备条件。

我无意这样谈论得离题太远，但是一想到自己在华尔街的最初几年，就忍不住这样。现在我弄懂了当时的很多事情，那时候犯的错都是一个普通投资人一直在犯的错。

第三次到达纽约后，我干得很积极，就为了能在交易所出一条道，我不指望能像在对赌行一样厉害，但我想过一阵子，我应该能够用很多很多的资金操作，我应该会有更好的表现。我明白我最大的问题是没弄懂股票赌博与股票投机的差别，不过我毕竟有天赋和七年研究股市行情变化的经验，我不只是赚钱了，而且赚了很多。我像以前有赢有输，但大致上都能赢钱。我赚得多，消费得也多，大家都这样，不见得是所有赚了容易钱的人才这样，而是不愿意攒钱的人才大手大脚。罗素·塞奇就是如此，他能赚也能攒，到入土的时候钱多得惊人。

每天，我都会从上午十点忙乎到下午三点，沉浸其中。三点以后，才是我享受生活的时刻。请别搞错，我不会让享受影响赚钱，我赔钱是因为判断出错，不是生活无度造成的。我从来不让精神恍惚或喝酒喝到手足酸麻妨碍我的游戏。任何事情都别想损害我的健康。就连现在我也常在十点前就入睡。即使年轻我也不熬夜，因为睡不好就干不好。我的表现比打平还好，这就是我认为不必剥夺生活中美好事物的原因。股市能满足你的所有需求，讲得职业一点儿，炒股是为了生活，所以要端正态度，自信心也就随之而来了。

我在炒股中的第一个改变是时间因素。我不像在对赌行里等尘埃落定了再出手，赚个一两点，我现在想在富勒顿公司顺势而为，就要早出手、迅速，也就是说，我必须要钻研市场，预测形势。这听起来没什么意思，但你应该明白，在炒股上转变态度对我是非常重要的。我慢慢懂得了在股价不稳时赌一把和提前预估股价的跌涨，以及赌博与投机，它们之间有着根本的差异。

我需要提前一小时以上的时间开始研究市场，就算在世界上最牛的对赌行，我也不可能明白这个。我对产业报告、铁路盈余、金融财务和商业统计都兴趣盎然。当然了，我喜欢玩大手笔，所以人们才送外号“投机分子”。我也爱研究股市行情，所有能帮助我去玩一把的事情，我都非常热心。在处理事情之前，我会仔细分析，只要觉得自己已经明白该从哪里入手了，就会去实际验证一番。自然，要证明只有一个办法，那就是用我的钱去证明。

现在看来我的进步似乎比较慢，可是于我而言已经很快了，因为整体来看我还是赚了钱，如果一直赔钱的话，可能会刺激着我花更多精力去研究股市。我必然也有很多问题没察觉。但是我不敢肯定亏钱的真正价值，如果亏得太多，我就没钱验证我的那些改变是否有效了。

研究我在富勒顿公司赚钱的操作方法之后我明白了，虽然我对股市行情和走势的预估一直是绝对正确的，但是我赚到的钱还是不多，原因何在？

没有彻底胜利，就跟失败了一样，也需要研究一番才行。

比如，在多头市场股价刚涨的时候，我就买进，它也按照我的预估在持续上涨，这就证明我的方法有效，到现在为止，一切都很顺利。那么我还需要做些什么呢？我听了老手们的话，不让年轻人莽撞乱窜，下决心小心谨慎地玩。谁都知道，要这样做，唯一的办法是获利落袋，然后在回调时买回你的股票。我就这么做了，确切点说，我尽量这么做着。我经常在获利落袋之后，等待从来没有出现的回调。我谨慎地怀揣着只有4个点的利润，可抛掉的股票还会继续上涨10个点，我只能眼睁睁地看着。大家都说钱能装到口袋就算有钱，是的，你是有点钱，可是在多头市场中只赚了4个点就收手，你也不会富有。

本来能赚2万，而我只赚了2000，这是力求稳妥造成的。当我发现自己其实只赚到了本来该赚的那些钱的一小部分时，我也明白了一些其他道理：根据经验的多少，傻瓜也分不同的等级。

新手一无所知，每一个人，包括他自己，都知道这一点。但是下一级或是下下一级的人认为他知道很多，而且让别人觉得他确实是这样。他是有经验的傻瓜，他做过研究，不是研究市场本身，而是研究更傻的人所说的一些市场评论。第二级傻瓜知道如何避免完全新手所犯的某些错误，避免亏损。就是这种半桶水，而不是百分之百的学徒，才是证券经纪商真正全年无忧的衣食父母。平均起来，这种人可以熬大约三年半，相比之下，通常第一次攻击华尔街的人只能熬3周到30周不等。那种半桶水的人，经常引述著名的交易格言以及各种游戏规则，他们对能言善辩的老手们所说的所有禁忌事项都一清二楚——只是不知道最重要的一条禁忌，就是不要当傻瓜。

半桶水的这种人认为自己已经懂事了，他喜欢在下跌时买进。他等待股价下跌，他根据股价从头部跌下多少钱来判定是否捡到便宜。在牛市，纯粹的傻瓜完全不知道规则和前例，会盲目地买进，因为他有盲目的希望。他赚到最多的钱，一直到一次正常的调整把他所有的利润都拿走为止。但是谨慎的二级傻瓜——就像我自以为是地玩这个游戏时一样——所做的事情是根据别人的智慧操作。我知道我必须改变自己在对赌行交易的方法，也认为我正在解决自己的问题，用的是备受交易老手们推崇、具有极高价值的方法。

大多数人都一样，你很难找到几个人能够诚实地说华尔街没有欠他们钱。富勒顿公司里也常有这样一群傻瓜，各种级别的都有。不过，有个老手显得很是鹤立鸡群。首先，他年龄比较大，其次，他没有好为人师的特点，也不卖弄赚了多少钱，他最擅长的是探听别人嘴里互传的各种内幕消息，而对市场本身的内幕不太热衷——也就是说，他从来不问说话的人听到什么或知道什么。要有人对他说了内幕消息，他会很感激，而且那些内幕消息如果确实起到了作用，他会更加感激，如果不准确，他也没什么怨言，所以别人不会知道他是不是真的受这些消息影响了。据说这人有很多钱，玩得也很大，只不过交易频率不是很高，至少别人所知的是这样。他叫帕特里奇，因为胸肌很发达，总把下巴托在胸前在各个屋子来回乱窜，所以人们偷偷给他起个“火鸡”的外号。

这些客户全都乐于在别人催促下，被迫做一些事情，好把失败归咎到别人身上，他们经常去向帕特里奇请教，对他说有内幕消息的人建议他们买哪只股票，在出手之前希望能请帕特里奇指教一二。不过他们所说的内幕，无论是让他们抛掉的还是买进的，在帕特里奇那里得到的建议都是一样的。

顾客们在说完困惑后总会问：“您觉得我该怎么做更好？”

老火鸡脑袋一歪，满脸慈父般的笑容，盯着提问的人，富含深情地说：“你知道，这是牛市。”

我就常听到他这么说：“嗯，你知道的，是牛市。”就好像他给你一个无价的护身符，用100万美元的保险单包起来一般，我确实听不明白他的意思到底是什么。

有一天，一个叫艾尔默·哈伍德的人匆忙跑进来，填了一张单子交给办事的人后就去找帕特里奇。帕特里奇这时候正在听一个叫约翰·范宁的人在倒苦水：有次他听到凯恩填了张交易单给经纪人，也就跟着做了100股，卖掉后只赚了3个点，但是当他卖出后三天，这只股票就上涨了24个点。这个故事约翰对帕特里奇至少说过四次，可老火鸡总是微笑着点点头，就像刚听到一样。

艾尔默直接打断了约翰，也没致歉，就走过去对老火鸡说：“帕特里奇先生，我刚卖了克莱曼汽车公司的股票，有知情人说市场应该会回调，到时候我再低价买回来，一定能赚的。你最好也一起玩吧，如果你还抱着这只股票的话，不会赔的。”

艾尔默疑惑地看着老火鸡，像其他提供内幕消息的那些人一样，消息未得到证实，就认为他们拥有接受他们内幕消息的人的身心。

老火鸡也是一副感激样儿：“是啊，哈伍德先生，我仍然抱着这只股票，当然抱着。”看来他非常感谢艾尔默心里还想着他这个老家伙。

艾尔默说：“喏，这是你赚钱的机会，下一轮的时候再买进。”他像刚刚替老火鸡填写了存款单一样。看不到老火鸡脸上有什么感激神色，艾尔默继续说：“我刚才把我手里的都卖了。”从他的声音和样子来判断，你就是保守估计，也会认为他卖了100股。

但是帕特里奇很遗憾地摇着头说：“不，不行，我不会卖的。”

艾尔默大喊：“什么？”

“我不能卖。”帕特里奇很苦恼地说。

“我这不给你提供内幕消息让你卖吗？”

“是啊，艾尔默先生，特别感激你，确实是，可是……”

“慢着，你听我说完！难道这个股票不是十天涨了7个点吗？”

“是这样，非常感谢，老弟，但我是不会卖的。”

艾尔默很不理解：“你真不卖？”他一脸疑惑。人们在提供内幕消息给别人时就是这个样子。

“不，我不卖。”

艾尔默踏前了一步问：“为什么不卖啊？”

“不为什么，现在是牛市。”一说这句话，就好像他的解释已经很到位了。

艾尔默很失望，生气地说：“好吧，我也知道是牛市，可是你还是卖了吧，在跌落的时候再买回来，不是就可以降低成本了吗？”

老火鸡很无奈地说：“小伙子啊，我现在要是卖掉，就会失去我的头寸，我以后怎么办？”

艾尔默挥了一下手，摇着头走向我，很关心地悄悄问：“你听清了没？”他用演戏般的语气低声问我，“我问你。”

我没说话，他又接着说：“我对他讲了克莱曼公司的内幕消息，他买了500股，赚了7个点，我现在让他卖掉，等股价跌的时候再买回来。他怎么回答我的？他说卖掉就没活可干了，你明白这话吗？”

老火鸡插话道：“请你原谅，哈伍德先生，我没说没活可干了，我说的是就会失去我的头寸。等你到我这把年纪的时候，千锤百炼过了，就会知道失去头寸是任何人都承受不起的，连洛克菲勒都承受不起。我期盼这只股票回调，好让你能用低价买回来你的那些股票。可我只能根据自己多年的经验进行交易，我为这些经验付过昂贵的学费，不想再重蹈覆辙。我仍然像已经赚钱了一样地感激你。你知道的，这是牛市。”老火鸡说完走了，留下艾尔默一脸纳闷。

那时候我对帕特里奇的话没多大感觉。想到以前股市好的时候，经常没赚到该赚的钱，我猛然意识到帕特里奇那些话中的道理，越想越觉得他很聪明。他年轻时也做过傻事，必定明白自己的人性弱点。过去的惨痛让他学会了不再受诱惑，因为要付出很大的代价，对于我也是一样。

帕特里奇最后总要对其他人说：“嗯，你懂的，这是牛市。”其实他的言外之意是，要赚钱就得看整个股市行情，而不是单个股价波动。也就是说，不能光看交易所的报价器上的数字，要研究整个股市行情和走向。明白了这个，我就觉得自己又长进了不少。

在华尔街闯荡这么多年，输输赢赢了几百万美元，我想告诉你一点：我能赚那么多钱，跟我的想法没什么关系，重要的是我能够坚持不动，懂了吗？是我坚持不动啊。能判断出股价走势不算什么本事。在牛市，有很多早早就做多的投资人，在熊市也有很多早早就做空的投资人。我认识很多看盘的厉害角色，他们也能瞅准最佳时间买卖股票，他们的经验跟我也差不离。可是呢，他们却没赚到多少钱。能够同时判断准确又坚持不动的人并不多，我觉得这才是最难学习的地方。股民们只有彻底理解了这点，才会赚大钱。搞懂了怎么样去交易而赚几百万，比不懂交易时赚几百美元还容易。

因为能把股市走向看得很明白的股民在看到股市行情跟他们预估的一样时，总会表现得焦虑不安，就是这样。华尔街的很多投资人都不是傻蛋，但是最终还是赔了，道理就在这里。不是股市让他们损兵折将，而恰恰是他们战胜不了自己。他们的聪明不能保证他们会坚持不动。老火鸡恰恰在这方面做得很好，他是那样说的，也是那样做的，他有坚持的勇气，也有坚忍的耐力。

不理会股市大的波动，光想着抢进抢出，是我的病灶所在。没人能够抓住所有的波动，在牛市，你要做的就是买进和攥在手里，坚持到你相信涨势快停的时候。想做到这一点，必须要搞清楚整体形势，并非只抓内幕消息和影响个股的特殊因素。你要忘掉你所有的股票，永远忘掉！一直到股市逆转，新一轮的走势就要到了为止。你必须要让你的头脑和观察判断能力发挥作用，不然我告诉你的这些就像低买高卖一样无意义。谁都该学会不要试图最后一刻卖出或第一时间买进，这两个时段太贵了，它们让很多股友的千百万美元葬送在了股海里，这些钱多到能建造一条横跨美洲的公路了。

我分析了一下在富勒顿公司的炒股情况，发现我一开始的那些交易大都赚了钱，这样自然使我决定一开始就玩大的。这让我对自己的判断很有信心，但是有很多次，我都被别人的建议甚至自己的不耐烦破坏掉了。一个人如果没有自信，就不会在这一行干出多少成绩来。我总结的经验是，全面研究行情，坚守住头寸。我耐心安分地坚持着，遇到了挫折也不慌乱，我明白这些都会过去。我一度放空过10万股，看出大反弹即将来临，这种反弹是不可避免的，甚至是健全的，在我的账面利润上会造成100万美元的差别，我预估到了这个结果，但是我还是纹丝不动，让一半的账面利润溜走，我根本没想着去把卖空的股票买回来，等到股价涨高了再抛掉。因为假如我那样做的话，可能会失掉头寸，从而失去确定赚大钱的机会。只有大的波动才能够赚大钱。

若说我学会这些花的时间太长，那是因为这些都来自我从失败中总结的经验。从失败到了解失败，这期间需要花很多时间；从了解失败到正确判定失败，这中间花费的时间更多。但同时，我干得还不错。我年龄还小，一切都还来得及。我赚钱的方式仍然有一部分还是靠研究那些股票记录单，因为这个方法适合当时的股市状况。我也不像更早一些时候那样经常赔钱，也不会赔得那么生气。回想一下，在一年多时间里，我破产了三次，所以没什么值得我骄傲的。我告诉你，破产是很好的教育机构。

我的资金并没有增加得很快，因为我一直尽量享受生活。其实我并没有有意识地阻止自己去享受我这个岁数和级别的人该有的生活，我有自己的轿车，能够从股市赚钱的时候，让自己的生活太拮据没什么意思。只有在周日和公休日，股市才不会开盘，情形本来就是如此。当我知道自己哪里出错的时候，我就会给自己新设置一条不该触碰的红线。享受我不断增长的财富的最好办法，就是不要削减生活开支。我当然有一些有趣的经验，其中一些并非这么有趣，但是如果我全部说出来一定说不完。事实上，那些在炒股中很重要的教训也很容易让我记忆犹新，正是这些教训督促着我对市场和自己更加了解。

第六章

1906年春，我远离股市，在亚特兰大度了个短假，想换换环境好好休整一下。顺便提一下，我回到了一开始的那个经纪商哈丁兄弟公司。我玩得很活跃，能够操作三四千股，这没比我20岁的时候在柯斯莫斯普利坦公司里玩得大多少，但是在纽约交易所，经纪商替我买卖股票，与在对赌行里赌1点的波动是完全不同的。

你或许记得我提到过一件事，就是在柯斯莫斯普利坦公司时，我放空3500股制糖公司的股票后，感觉不太对头后想马上结束交易的那一次。该怎么说呢，我经常会在冥冥之中有这种奇怪的感觉，我经常会遵照这种感觉行事。可有时我又告诉自己，光靠一时半会儿的冲动就改变自己的头寸是一件蠢事。我把自己的这种感觉归因于抽的雪茄太多，导致睡眠不足，肝脏不太好。每当我克制了自己的这种冲动，坚持我一开始的看法时，又总能找到些后悔的地方。好多回我都自我克制着没有卖出，隔天去看，市场会很强劲，甚至可能上涨，于是我跟自己说遵从感觉卖出多么愚蠢。但是再过一天，股价一定会有大跌。在起起落落的过程中，我明白了要赚钱不一定光靠理智和逻辑头脑，还要靠心理感应。

我说件事，这件事对我影响很大。它发生在1906年我在亚特兰大休假时期。有个同样是哈丁兄弟公司客户的朋友与我同行，那时候假期令人愉悦，我一点儿都不想靠近股市。当然，要是市场特别好，我的头寸又特别大的时候，我是没法停止炒股而去玩耍的。我记得当时是牛市，虽然股市跌了一点儿，不过各种迹象都表明它会上涨，所以人们都信心饱满。

有一天早晨吃过饭后，我读了纽约的所有早报，也看烦了这样的日常场景：海鸥叼着蚌飞到大约6米高的地方，然后把它们丢到硬邦邦的潮湿的沙滩上，美美地吃上一顿。于是我和朋友到木板大道上闲逛，这算是一天里最好玩的事了。

还没到中午，我缓步走在街上，呼吸着咸咸的空气，百无聊赖地消磨着时间。在这里，有个哈丁兄弟公司的分部，我们每天早上都要顺道去看看开盘情况，这成了无聊之人的习惯。

这次我们发现股市行情很好，交易也很活跃，朋友非常看好此时的市场，他手里有一些在股价很低时买进的股票。他对我说，持股等着价格上涨真是明智的做法。我对他的话并没有太在意，也不屑于与他讨论。我看了看报价板，发现大多数股票都已经上涨，然后看到太平洋铁路公司的股票，我觉得此时应该把它卖掉，也不知道为什么这么想，反正就有这样的感觉。我自问原因，可就是无法回答。

我紧盯着报价板，但是因为一直想着这件事，什么也看不进去，满脑子想的都是要放空太平洋铁路公司的股票，我无法解释为什么会有这样的想法。

我的神情在别人看来一定很奇怪，站在旁边的朋友碰了我一下，问我：“喂，怎么了？”

“我也不知道。”我只能这么说。

“你困了？”

“没有，”我说，“我没困。”

我想放空太平洋股票，我总能够靠着这样的感觉获利。

我直接走向有空白单子的桌位，朋友跟在我后面。我迅速填好要卖掉1000股太平洋铁路股票的单子后，递给经理。一脸笑容的经理看完单子后脸色马上变了。他瞪着我问道：“不会吧？”我没说话，只是望着他。之后，他马上把单子递给了操作员。

朋友问我：“你这是干什么？”

“我要卖掉这只股票。”我说。

“啊？”他大喊了一声。他是多头，而我却要做空，这里面一定有什么问题。

“太平洋铁路的1000股。”我说。

“为什么呀？”他显得很激动。

我摇了摇头，没法告诉他原因，可他肯定觉得我捏着内幕消息呢。他拉着我的胳膊把我拽到门外没人的地方，这里也不会有人听到我们说什么。

“你有什么内幕消息吗？”他问我。

他很激动，太平洋铁路是他最爱的股票之一，因为这家公司的发展前景很好，他坚信握着不撒手可以赚钱，不过他也愿意听到些负面消息。

“什么消息也没啊。”我说。

“怎么可能？”很明显，他怀疑我说谎。

“真的没什么消息。”

“那你为什么要卖掉？”

“我也不清楚。”我的确没说假话。

“呵呵，算了吧你。”他说。他了解我是个有的放矢的稳当人，可现在却要卖掉1000股太平洋铁路。在市场走势这么好的情况下，我卖出这么多股，一定有充足的理由。

“我不知道啊。”我说，“我就是觉得会发生些什么。”

“发生什么？”

“不知道！我说不明白，我只是想抛掉，我还想再追卖1000股。”

我再次走回桌子旁边，又卖掉了1000股。如果刚才卖那1000股是对的，我就该多卖掉些。

“到底会有什么事呀？”朋友不依不饶地问我，他也犹豫起来，在考虑是不是要学我这样。如果我直接对他说获得了这只股票要下跌的内幕消息，他肯定就不会纠缠着问了，连谁说的和为什么这样的白痴问题都不会问，而会直接学我卖掉。

“什么事都可能有，可我没法保证一定有什么事，我没办法对你说清原因，我又不能预知未来。”我说。

“你要疯了。”他说，“你这个疯子，没有原因就要卖掉股票，你真的不清楚原因吗？”

“我真不知道，我就是想卖掉。”我说。想抛股票的感觉来势汹汹，我就又卖了1000股。朋友这下快崩溃了，他抓着我的胳膊说：“听着，我们快离开这里，以免你放空整个股市。”

我已经卖掉了很多，心里舒服了，所以也就没等后面那2000股的成交单，就直接跟着他离开了。对我来说，即使有最好的理由，放空那么多股已经很多了。没什么理由，尤其股市行情整体不错，没有人会觉得熊市要来，放空那么多似乎更是过分。不过，每次我要是想卖的时候却没有出手，就总会非常后悔。

我把这样的事情讲给朋友们听，有的人就对我说，那不是莫名的感觉，而是一种潜意识的思维，就是所谓创造性的工作思维。源于这样的思维，艺术家们会做出一些连自己都无法搞清楚的事来。而我，可能是受到很多小因素的联合刺激，这些小因素单个来说毫无意义，集合起来却很有力量。或许朋友那种不靠谱的自信也激发了我否定的精神，所以要选择抛掉太平洋铁路的股票来释放，因为这是一只众所周知会上涨的股票。我没办法对你说清预感的源头，只知道当我从那里出来时就已经卖掉了3000股，而且是在股市上涨的时候，可我根本不担心。

我想知道后面2000股的成交价格，所以我们吃过午饭后又去了那里。我发现股市的综合行情很好，太平洋的股价也上涨了。

“你算是赔本了。”朋友说。你都能想象得到他没卖这只股票的得意样儿。

第二天，股票继续上涨，除了朋友的得意忘形外，我什么信息也没得到，可我一直觉得我没有卖错，我自认没做错的时候就耐心十足，这有什么道理吗？下午，太平洋的股票就停止了上涨，在那天快收盘时，开始下跌，没多久就跌破到我卖3000股时的价格平均线，我更加觉得自己没做错，我自然必须多放空一些。所以在那天收市之前，我又卖掉了2000股。

就等于说，靠着这种预感，我抛售了太平洋铁路公司的5000股，花完了我在哈丁兄弟公司分部的保证金。度假的时候，我没办法全力应对放空这么多股票的现状，只好放弃了假期，当天晚上就回了纽约。谁都不知道会出什么事，我想我还是回到现场，在更熟悉一点儿的纽约，我能更迅速地应对。

第二天，我们得到了旧金山发生大地震的消息，不过股市开盘只跌了几个点而已，多头很强势，人们不会独立对消息做出反应，这很常见。一旦处于很坚实的牛市，无论是否有报纸所说的多头炒作在进行，某些消息传出时，总是不会像华尔街偏空时那样发挥应有的效果。一切都看当时的人气而定。在这个例子里，华尔街股市没有对地震因素做出评估，因为大家不愿意这样做。在那天结束之前，股价还上涨了些。

我卖掉了5000股，灾难发生了，我的股票却没有下跌。我自信感觉没错，只是我还没挣到钱，连一点儿小利润都没有。与我同去亚特兰大度假的朋友在我卖掉股票时又庆幸又惋惜。他对我说：“预感是存在的，哥们儿，不过当钱和人都倾向于多头时，对抗不管用，他们肯定赢。”

“再等等看。”我说的是股价，我不想逃避，我知道事情比较严峻，太平洋公司的损失是最严重的，可是华尔街却表现得很盲目，真气人。

“等等看？等着你这张皮和其他熊皮都被暴晒在太阳底下，晒成个干皮。”他直截了当地说。

“你会怎么办？”我问，“凭着南太平洋公司和其他铁路公司蒸发了几百万就买太平洋的股票？他们付清损失后下一年的分红从哪里来？你最多觉得问题还不算严重，可就因为这个就买受到严重损失的铁路股票吗？你说啊。”

可朋友只是说：“对，好像有道理，可我告诉你，股市不会与你想的一样，行情记录不会骗人，是吧？”

我说：“行情记录总是滞后，不够及时啊。”

“听我说。在黑色星期五之前，有人和吉姆·菲斯克聊天，举出至少十个金价要下跌的理由。他受自己的话鼓舞，最后对菲斯克说要抛掉几百万的黄金，菲斯克看着他说：‘去吧，赶紧地，卖完了别忘记请我参加你的葬礼哦。’”

“对啊。”我说，“那人如果真的卖掉了黄金，看能捞多少。你也最好卖掉些太平洋的股票。”

“那不可能！我是个顺势而为的人，我这样的人能开心赚钱。”

第二天，出现了更加完善的报道，股市开始下滑了，但是即使到了那个时候，下跌也没预想的那么严重。在我眼里，世界上不存在能阻止股市猛跌的东西，所以我又卖出了5000股。是啊，这时候很多人都知道怎么回事了，我的经纪人也乐意效劳了。这不是谁的错，我预估的股市行情没错。过了一天，股市迅速下跌，我借机又卖出去1万股。这是唯一可以做的事。

我不想其他，只知道自己没错，绝对正确，这是个绝佳的好机会，只看我怎么来利用。我持续地抛售着。难道我没有想过，万一卖了这么多，要是股市反弹了，我的利润就会打了水漂，甚至连本钱都丧失掉吗？谁知道我想过没有，就算想过也不会有什么压力，我不是个鲁莽的赌徒，而是很小心谨慎的，谁都不能把地震造成的损失补回来，不是吗？谁也不能在一个晚上就免费把坍塌的高楼复原，不是吗？

我没有鲁莽，没有发疯，也没有被胜利冲昏头脑，更不会觉得一大部分旧金山在地图上消失了，一个城市成了废墟，是的，一点儿都没错。我没有把心思花在等着恐慌发生上，好吧，第二天我就平仓，赚了25万美金，这是我炒股以来获利最多的一次，而且就这么几天时间。刚开始时，华尔街一点儿都不理会地震的影响，他们还说一开始的那些报道没多严重。可我想说的是，要想转变公众对待股市的看法，得需要很长时间，就连职业股民在大部分时间里都是迟缓而短视的。

我没什么需要解释的，不管科学还是戏说。我只是对你讲讲我是怎么做的，为什么要这样做，最后获得了什么。我注重的不是那个神奇的预感，而是我获利25万的事情。这件事情说明，只要给我机会，我就可以做得更大。

那年夏天，我到了萨拉托加温泉度假，可总想着要看看股市。起初没多累，想想股市也不烦躁，而且我在这里认识的人都对炒股兴趣很大，我们顺理成章地就讨论上了。我觉得说和做之间有很大区别，有的人会让你想到那种像对待懦夫一样跟脾气暴躁的老板谈话的大胆的职员——确实让你有这种感觉，他们只懂得嘴上那一套。

哈丁兄弟公司在萨拉托加也有分部，而且客户还不少，真正的原因是做了广告。实际上在偏远的地方开设分部这件事本身就是打广告，我也总会顺道去转转，坐在人堆边上瞅瞅。那里的经理是从纽约总部过来的，很和善，对朋友和陌生人都会热心帮忙，也会借机拉一些业务。这里是内幕消息充斥的地方——赌马的、股票的、跑堂的——哪方面的消息都有，分部的人很清楚我对这些没兴趣，经理也不会向我悄悄透露他从纽约获得什么秘密。他只是把电报拿给我看，并说：“这是他们刚刚发的。”只有这样。

我自然要盯着股市，对我而言，看报价板和研究判断各种迹象是一种程序。我看到我的老伙计太平洋铁路的股票又上涨了，而且还比较高，有人在买进，我观察了两天还是没有买。我能肯定有个大客户在买进，他肯定是个有大量资金而且知道怎么操作的高手，我觉得他很聪明。

我确定了这点后，立刻以160美元左右的价格大力买进。这只股票继续表现良好，所以我继续买进，每次成交500股，我买得越多，股市越强劲，却没有急速冲刺，我很满意，我知道这只股票没有理由不猛涨。

经理忽然走到我跟前，他说纽约发电报了，问我在不在这里。得到答复后，有人过来说，让我等会儿，哈丁先生要跟我通话。

我说没问题，就又趁机买了太平洋的500多股，我不知道哈丁先生要对我说什么，估计不是关于炒股的事情，因为我有足够的保证金来玩。经理很快就来对我说，艾德·哈丁先生打长途电话找我。

我说：“你好，艾德。”

可是却听到他说：“你到底在干吗？你疯了呀？”

“是你疯了吧？”我说。

“你到底要干什么？”他又问。

“你这是什么意思？”

“你买那么多那只股票干什么？”

“怎么了？我的保证金不够吗？”

“与保证金无关，是让你别这么蠢。”

“我不知道你在说什么。”

“你买太平洋的股票干吗？”

“因为它在上涨啊。”我说。

“上涨个鬼啊！你难道不知道内部人士正在倒货给你吗？你大概是最好欺骗的人了，还不如去赌马呢，赔得还有劲儿。你别让他们给耍了。”

“没人耍我。”我对他说，“我没告诉过任何人。”

他继续说：“你不要以为每次掉进去都会发生奇迹，你有机会就快退出来。那些大户们都使劲儿往外卖呢，你还这样买，简直是胡闹。”

“从记录上看，是有人在买进啊。”我一根筋地说。

“你啊，你的单子过来的时候我都快犯心脏病了，别傻了，赶快退出来吧，说崩盘就崩盘了，我言尽于此，再见。”说完他挂了电话。

哈丁很聪明，消息也非常灵通，没有什么坏心眼儿，是个能做朋友的人，而且他所在的位置可以帮助他获取很多内幕。我买进太平洋的股票，靠的是这么多年对股票走势的研究，以及我所看到的一些蛛丝马迹，以经验来看，有迹象表明股价会大幅上涨。我不知道自己看出了什么变化，但是我猜想。我一定断定：我认定股票被人买进，完全是因为有内线在捣鬼。可能哈丁的话对我起了很大作用，他要制止我不能犯这么一个赔上老本的错，不管是他的能力还是动机，都是值得信任的。所以我听了他的话，我也不知道为什么要这么听他的话。

我抛空了太平洋的股票，不能做多头的时候当然要做空头，不然就是个蠢货。所以我卖掉了那些股票后又抛了4000股，差不多都是以162美元的价格。

隔天太平洋公司董事宣布要配股一成。一开始华尔街上没人相信这个消息。报纸开始抨击这家公司董事会，就在华尔街的高手们不知所措、犹豫不决时，市场沸腾了起来，一些在场的股民在一个小时内就赚了不少。我甚至听说有个笨蛋不小心买错股票，结果却赚了35万，第二周就卖掉了他在交易所的席位，去做农场主了。

我听到配股一成的消息后，就发觉我是活该倒霉，不听经验的指挥，却偏信内幕消息，结果受了这么大损失。我仅凭一个头脑清醒的朋友没有私心的劝告，就对他的警告深信不疑，从而失掉了自己的原则。

当看到太平洋股票创造了纪录后，我就对自己说：“真不该卖掉这只股票啊。”

我现在只剩下哈丁兄弟公司分部的保证金了，这让我没有高兴或者不高兴，显然我对股市行情的判断是对的，但却愚蠢地听从了哈丁先生的话。事后说别人是不对的，而且我也不能再浪费时间，既然木已成舟，我就只能下单补空头。我按照每股大概165美元的价格买了太平洋的4000股，也就损失了3个点。在收盘之前，经纪人以172美元和174美元的股价买了一部分。我拿到单子后算了一下，因为哈丁先生的好心干扰，我赔了4万美元，这次教训还不算贵，对一个连坚持自己做法的勇气都没有的人来说，这是个小代价。

我不太懊恼，按照行情记录来看，股价还会上涨，这是罕有的波动，董事会做出的决定也是亘古未有，不过这次我要遵照自己的想法来做，我平了4000股的空头，准备根据股市的行情记录玩一把，赚点钱。所以我毫无顾虑地买了4000股，第二天早上时，我卖掉了它们，这不光让我赚回了赔掉的4万美元，还净赚了1.5万。如果不是哈丁那么替我着想，我一下子就能赚很大一笔，但他也算帮了我一把，这是个教训，我相信这次事件把我锻造成了一个真正的股市商人。

我并不是说我所要学习的只是不去受内幕消息摆布，坚守自己的原则，而是我真正找到了自信，从根本上与以前炒股的老方法划清了界限。萨拉托加的这次经历是我最后一次依靠冒险和运气赚钱，自此以后，我就开始全盘考虑股市，而不只是单独地拘泥于个别股票。通过努力学习，我终于让自己在这个行业里达到了更高的层次，这一步走得的确漫长而艰辛。

第七章

我会告诉别人自己是看好市场，还是不太看好市场，但我不对别人说买进还是卖出。熊市来了，所有股票都会跌，牛市来了则正好相反。不过，不包括由战争引发的那种熊市，因为军火方面的股票会因为战争而上涨。我说的是一般情况。但是通常而言，人们不愿意考虑到底是牛市还是熊市，他们只想很清晰地知道买什么或者卖什么，不想用脑子去思考，要他们数数从地上捡起来的钱他们都嫌麻烦。

我没有那么懒惰，我只是觉得单独研究一只股票比通盘考虑股市要方便。同样，考虑一只股票的起伏比考虑全盘股市的起落要简单。我明白我必须要改变这种想法，而我确实也做到了。

人们想搞懂炒股的基本原则没那么简单，之前我总说最好在上涨的市场里买进股票，但如今重要的不是能不能买到便宜的股票，或者卖出高价股票，而是在正确的时机买进或卖出。当我在看空的时候卖掉股票，卖出价格肯定是一次比一次低。买入股票则相反，我一定是逐步向上承接。我肯定在股价上涨时买，不会在下跌时做多头。

假设，我正在买进某只股票。我会用110美元买入2000股，如果我买进后股票上涨到了111美元，那对我就是有益的，上涨1个点，说明盈利了。是啊，因为我是对的，所以会跟进2000股。如果股市还在上涨，我还会买2000股。比如价格到了114美元，我认为这时候我已经暂时买够了，我有了可以干一把的资本。我用平均111又3/4的价格做多6000股，现在涨到114美元，我就不会再买，而是等着看看。我估计涨到差不多了就会有回调，我想看看股市在回调之后有什么表现。很有可能会跌到第三次买2000股时候的价格，如果又上涨后跌回112又1/4，然后回升，到达113又3/4时，我会马上花市价买4000股。此时，我用113又3/4的价格买到了4000股后，就知道哪里有问题，再下个单子测试一下，也就是卖掉1000股来测试市场的反应。但是，如果我在111又3/4时买进4000股，在114时买进2000股，在114又1/2时买进500股，那么如果股市继续上涨，最后500股我就在115又1/2时成交，这时候我就知道我的操作是对的。就是这个买入4000股的经历，使得我知道了在那种特殊状态买特殊的股票是不是对——当然了，我已经把整个行情考虑明白了，在牛市的时候，我从来不买太便宜或者太容易买到的股票。

我记得我听过一个有关迪肯·怀特的故事。怀特那时候是华尔街的一位大股民，一位特别好的老人，精明又有魄力。据说他在原来属于他的那个时期干过很漂亮的事。

故事发生在早年，那时候制糖公司是市场上最容易迸出火花的股票，公司董事长哈维梅尔的权力也处于巅峰时期。我和前辈们聊过，知道哈维梅尔和他手下人有实力有资本，足以应付那些用他们的股票投机的人。前辈们说哈维梅尔在这只股票上修理过很多人，比其他人在其他股票上修理过的人都要多，所以经纪人在这些人炒股的时候，一般都会使绊子而不是帮忙。

有一天，一个认识怀特的人激动地跑进怀特办公室，说：“你让我有好消息了要告诉你，要是对你有用，你会替我挂进几百股，对不对？”他稍微停了一下后，喘着气等待回答。

迪肯像往常一样冷静地看着他说：“我忘了是不是说过，不过你要真有对我有用的好消息，我就会报答你。”

“那好，我确实有好消息。”

“是吗，那就太好了。”迪肯和善地说。

那人站起来说：“是的，先生。”然后凑近了些，生怕别人听到，“哈维梅尔买了制糖公司的股票。”

“真的？”迪肯很冷静地问。

这让来人很生气，他强调说：“是的，迪肯先生，他是有多少就买了多少。”

“你确定？”迪肯问。

“迪肯，我证据确凿，那些老东西正在不遗余力地买呢，估计跟关税有关吧，制糖公司的普通股能让人大赚，会超过特别股的价钱。我觉得会赚30个点。”

“你真这样觉得？”迪肯透过旧式银丝眼镜盯着他，这副眼镜本来是看股市行情记录用的。

“我真这么认为。据我了解就是这样，绝对的！怎么了，迪肯？哈维梅尔和他的朋友都在买制糖公司的股票，不能赚40点以上他们不会罢休，在他们吃货吃到饱之前，股市如果暴涨起来，我一点儿都不会感到意外的。经纪商手里的筹码已经没有一个月前那么多了。”

“他在买制糖公司股票，是吧？”迪肯若有所思地问。

“买？他那简直就是吞啊，能吞多少就吞多少，根本不限定价格。”

“是吗？”迪肯简单地说。

可这已经把送信的人惹急了，他说：“是的，先生。我觉得这是个特别好的信息，绝对没有水分啊。”

“是吧？”

“是的，这个消息很有用，你不需要吗？”

“哦，是的，我需要。”

“什么时候？”那人狐疑道。

“就是现在，立刻。”迪肯喊了一声，“弗兰克。”弗兰克是他最聪明的经纪人，就在旁边屋里。

“先生。”弗兰克说。

“我想让你去一趟交易所，卖掉1万股制糖公司的股票。”

“卖？”送信的人叫道，他的声音很惊讶，把已经往外走的弗兰克都喊停了。

“怎么了？是卖啊。”迪肯温和地说。

“可我说的是哈维梅尔在买啊。”

“伙计，我知道。”迪肯镇定地说完后转身对弗兰克说，“弗兰克，快去。”

弗兰克快步去办了，送信的人满脸通红。

“我来你这里，”他生气地说，“带来了大好消息，我把你当朋友才告诉你，我觉得你很正直，我想让你根据这个消息动起来……”

“我正在动啊。”迪肯平静地打断了他。

“可我告诉你的是哈维梅尔他们在买进。”

“是的，我听明白了。”

“买，买，我说的是他们在买。”送信人大吼起来。

“是买，我听清了。”迪肯说。他站在自动收报机前，盯着行情记录看。

“但是你却在卖。”

“对，卖1万股。”老头点点头。

然后，他开始沉默，专心盯着记录。送信人也凑过来，想知道他在看什么，这个老家伙很狡猾。正当他想通过迪肯的肩膀看时，有个职员拿着一张单子走进来了，正是弗兰克的汇报单。迪肯只看了一眼。他从行情记录上已经看出了情况。

于是他对那职员说：“让他再卖1万股。”

“迪肯，我发誓，他们真的在买啊。”

“是哈维梅尔对你说的？”迪肯一如既往地镇定。

“当然不是，他不会对任何人说任何事情的，他连帮最好的朋友赚一毛钱都不干。可我知道这是真的。”

“别激动，伙计。”迪肯抬了抬手，继续看行情记录。送信人无奈地说：“要是早知道你要做的事情跟我期望的相反，我就不该来浪费你的时间，也浪费了我的时间，可你若因此而赔惨了，我也不会高兴，我为你感到惋惜，迪肯。不好意思，我要去其他地方验证我的信息了。”

“我在做呀，我明白自己不太了解股市，至少没你和你的朋友哈维梅尔那么了解，可是我也略知一二，我现在就是根据经验和你带来的消息做出正确举动。像我这样一个人，在华尔街混了这么多年，任何人为我感到惋惜，我都会很感谢。镇定些，朋友。”

那人紧盯着迪肯，非常佩服他的判断和勇气。

刚才那个职员很快又进来了，把一份单子交给迪肯。迪肯看过后说：“现在让弗兰克买3万股。”

职员快步离开了，送信的人小声嘀咕了一句，瞧着那个头发花白的老狐狸。

“伙计，”迪肯和善地解释，“我并不是怀疑你带来的消息不属实，就算我听到哈维梅尔亲自对你说了，我也会像刚才那样做，因为只有这样才能验证是不是有人像哈维梅尔一样买入了股票。第一个1万股卖得很容易，这说明不了什么，可第二个也卖了，股价还在上涨，2万股都这样被吸走了，说明确实有人想统统收入囊中。就这而言，谁买的并不是很重要，所以我平了以后，又买了1万股，到现在为止你提供的消息都是好消息。”

“有多好？”送信人问。

“你会得到500股，价格是那1万股的均价。”迪肯说，“再见，伙计，下次镇定些。”

“好的，迪肯。”他说，“你卖出你的股票的时候也帮我卖掉吧，我比你知道的少多了。”

道理就是这样，所以我从来不会买便宜的股票。当然我总是设法很有效地买进，以便协助我所操作的方向。至于卖股票嘛，很明显，只有有人愿意买的时候，你才能卖掉。

假如你玩的是个大手笔，就得随时记住这一点，要先细察情势，再认真做好计划，最后才去实行。你如果握有很多头寸，并且有很大的浮动利润，就不能随便卖掉。你不能指望在股市中卖掉5万股跟卖掉100股一样简单，只有等到市场可以承接了，才是到了考虑必须卖出的时候。机会来了，就要抓住，而机会需要耐心等待，这是规则。必须等到可以卖的时候卖，而不是你想卖的时候卖。想知道什么时候才是最合适的时机，就要学会观察和尝试。想知道你想卖的股票在股市上什么时候能被吸收，这可没什么秘诀。但是，要开始采取行动时，你必须确定行情特别好，不然你贸然猛进是非常不明智的。请记住，股价不会有高到令你没法买进的时候，也不会低到令你没法卖出的时候。不过在第一笔做完后，除非第一笔有利润，否则别做第二笔。要耐心等，细心看。行情记录会为你提供是否可以开始去做的时机，在合适的时候行动对很多事情都非常重要。我花了很多年才明白这一点，与此同时还花了成千上万美元。

我不希望让人们觉得我是让大家持续加码。当然了，你加码可以赚到不加码赚不到的大钱，可我要说的是，如果有人想买500股，他不是在投机，就不应该一次性买进；如果只是赌一把，我只会建议他别赌。

如果他买了100股，而且立刻赔了，就不该继续买，而该立即认识到错误，认识到至少是暂时出现了错误。

第九章

我在佛罗里达州的外海航行，这里是钓鱼的好地方。我已经出脱股票，心情轻松自在，过得非常惬意。有一天，几个朋友驾驶摩托艇，来到棕榈滩海上玩。有人带了一张报纸。那些日子我没看过报纸，不管哪方面的内容，我都不想看。可是我瞄了一眼朋友带来的报纸后，发现股市上涨了十来个点。

我对朋友说：“我要跟你们一起上岸。”偶尔来个适度的反弹很正常，可此时还是熊市，华尔街上或愚蠢或绝望的股民们却不管资金情况，把价格抬高到合理范围之外，或是纵容某些人这样做。对我来说，这样太过分了。我必须得看看股市了，我不知道自己能干什么，或者不干什么，但我明白我最需要的是看看股市报价。

哈丁兄弟公司在棕榈滩也有个分部，我走进去时看到了很多认识的人。他们很多人都在议论说很看好市场。他们都是一些仅仅凭着行情报价玩股票的人，总想着快速交易。这样的股民没多少长远的眼光，他们的玩法也的确不需要这样的眼光。我说过，我是怎么在纽约获得“投机分子”这个称号的。当然了，通常情况下，人们喜欢把他人获利和炒股的事实夸大。这里的人听说我在纽约的时候通过做空赚了很多钱，此刻他们还是想让我再那样笃信一把空头。他们自己认为反弹还会持续一段时间，可同时又认为对抗反弹是我的责任。

我本来是来佛罗里达钓鱼的，前一阵子我承受了很大压力，我需要度个假。可当我知道价格反弹不少的那时候，一下子感觉不需要度假了。我上岸时没有想到要做什么，但是现在我知道我要赶紧放空股票。我是对的，必须要用我唯一的老方法，用钱来验证我的判断是否正确。把股票全部卖掉，这是一种慎重、有效而且可以说是爱国的行为。

我通过报价牌首先看到的是安纳康达公司的股票马上要突破300个点，简直是飞跃上涨，而且里面肯定有个很猛的团队在操控。有一条传统的交易规则：当股票首次突破100、200或300点的时候，价格不会停滞不前，而是会继续上涨很多，所以当它在突破重要关卡的时候，你马上买，必定会赚一笔。胆子小的人不爱在股价创新高纪录的时候买进，可是我却有这种股价波动的“史实”来指导我。

安纳康达是所谓的四分之一股票，也就是面值只有25美元的小额股，它的400股相当于100股的普通股票的面值，我估计到了300点后，它还会继续上涨，很快就会到340美元。

不要忘了，我还是很看淡后市的，可是我也是个能靠行情走势玩股票的人。我清楚安纳康达若能按照我的估计发展，就会很快地波动。不管多快，都吸引着我。我已经培养了耐心，知道了怎么样自我坚持，可我还是更喜欢快速行动。安纳康达绝对不是牛皮股，我在它突破300点的时候买入，是因为我想证实自己的观察，我这种意愿总是很强烈。

那时，买的人比卖的人多，所以股市上涨的情形会持续下去，因此观察一段时间后再卖空比较适宜。对我来说，等一等也会有所收获的，我可以从安纳康这只股票中迅速赚取30点，我看空整个股市，却看好这一只股票。所以我买了3.2万股安纳康达，相当于8000股整股。这只股票是一只很好的小型投机股，我相信自己的推断，而且我还觉得，这一次赚的钱或许能够增强我的保证金实力，为我以后放空打下基础。

第二天，因为受到北边暴风雨或者其他因素的影响，电报中断了。我在哈丁公司坐等消息。大家都在闲聊，猜测着股市行情。股票投资人不能交易时总是这样做。后来我们等到了那天唯一的一次报价，安纳康达是292。

当时有个我在纽约认识的人跟我在一起，他清楚我做多了8000股。当听到报价的时候，他也吃了一惊，所以我觉得他手里也有些安纳康达的股票。他没法判断，那时股票是否会再跌十几个点。按照安纳康达之前上涨的走势，现在跌个20点以上应该也有可能。可是我还是对他说：“约翰，不要担心，明天就没事了。”我确实是这么感觉的，可是他盯着我直摇头，他就是这样的人，自认为自己更懂一些。我哈哈大笑起来，然后继续等着股市报价，可是再也没有报价传回来。我们得到的唯一报价是，安纳康达是292美元。这表示我赔了10万美元。我想要迅速行动，我罪有应得。

隔天后，电报线路恢复了，我们跟以往一样看到了报价，安纳康达的开盘价是298美元，后来涨到了302又3/4，不过没多久又下跌了。而其他的股票也没有进一步上涨的迹象，我下定决心，如果安纳康达的股票如果回到301，我必须将整个事件看作是一种假象。按照正常情况，它应该能够涨到310才对啊。假如股价反而下跌就表示前例欺骗了我，我出错了。出错的人唯一可做的就是及时改正错误。我买了足足8000股，希望能上涨个三四十点，这不是我第一次也不会是最后一次出错。

安纳康达又跌到了301。一跌到这个价位，我就悄悄跑到电报员身边。他们可以直接跟纽约联系，所以我对他说：“把我那整整8000股的安纳康达股卖掉吧，全部卖掉。”我小声说话，生怕被别人知道我的行动。

他抬头看着我，一脸惊恐的样子，我点着头说：“全部卖！”

“利文斯顿先生，你肯定不是说用市价交易吧？”他的样子好像是因为营业员执行错误，自己亏好几百万美元一样。

不过我还是说：“卖！什么也别说了。”

此时，布莱克兄弟、吉姆、奥利弗都在交易大厅，他们没听到我和电报员说话。他们原来都是芝加哥有名的小麦期货商人，如今又是纽约很有地位的股票商人，他们特别有钱，是股票大作手。

当我回到报价牌前的座位上时，奥利弗·布莱克一边笑一边冲我点头。

“你会后悔。”他说。

“你什么意思？”我停下来问。

“明天你就得买回来。”

“买什么？”我问。除了那个电报员，我可没对任何人说过。

“安纳康达股票。”他说，“你要用320美元买，你这做法可不明智啊。”他笑着。

“什么做法不明智啊？”我似乎一脸茫然地问。

“你卖掉你的8000股安纳康达，而且那么坚定。”布莱克说。

我清楚谁都认为他特别精明，他经常根据内幕消息炒股，可我没想到，他居然知道我的交易，我深信公司没有出卖我。

“奥利弗，你怎么知道的？”我问。

他哈哈大笑着，对我说：“是查理·克里特斯说的。”他指的正是那个电报员。

“可他连动都没动啊。”我说。

“我不知道你们在说什么。”他微笑着说，“可是他发电报的时候，我可是听清楚了所有的内容。几年之前，别人给我发电报时搞错了一句话，我就开始学习电报密码了。我在像你刚才那样告诉电报员指令的时候，我要确定，他是不是搞对了，他发的内容可得是我的想法啊。你卖掉了安纳康达股票，一定会追悔莫及，它能涨到500美元。”

“这次可不会，奥利弗。”我说道。

他盯着我：“你这么自信啊？”

“不是我自信，股市行情就是这样。”我说。实际上那儿并没有接收股市行情的收报机，不过他知道我在说什么。

他说：“我听说有一些家伙，就算看了行情记录，也看不明白价格，反而像看列车时刻表一样，只能看到股票到站和离站的时间。不过幸好他们都已经住在精神病院的小房子里了，四壁都是软垫，他们不会伤着自己了。”

我不理会他，因为电报员这时给我送来了一个单子，他们已经按照299又3/4的价格卖掉了我的5000股。我清楚这里的报价很滞后，我告诉电报员的时候，棕榈滩报价牌上还是301块。我确信，纽交所正在卖的股票的实价比这还要低，所以要是那时有人花296买我的股票，我会高兴坏的。这些过程都说明，我从不限价交易是多么正确。如果我把卖出的价格限定到300以上，肯定卖不出去。好吧，先生们，如果你们有了平仓的想法就一定要出手迅速，时不我待啊。

如今，我买股票的价格差不多是300，他们用299又3/4卖了整整500股整股，用299又5/8的价格卖了1000股，然后以299又1/2卖掉100股，以299又3/8和299又1/4的价格分别卖掉200股，剩下的按照298又3/4卖了。在抛售最后100股时，哈丁兄弟公司里最厉害的经纪人花了十五分钟才卖掉，他们不想把股价砸下去。

我拿到最后这部分股票售出的单子后，就开始做真正促使我上岸的事情，也就是放空股票，我一定得这样做，市场经过离奇的反弹后，哀求大家放空。人们又在说很看好股市。我却觉得股市上涨已经到头了，做空是安全的，没什么可考虑的。

次日，安纳康达股票的开盘价比296还低，奥利弗·布莱克本想着它会继续上涨，很早就来瞧着。我不清楚他到底是不是做了多头，到底做了多少，可是当他看到开盘价时，就再也没法笑了。晚些时候，它还在下跌。我们后来听说交易所里已经没人买那只股票了。

当然，任何人都需要这样的证明。我的账面利润不停地提醒着我，我没做错。我自然又多放空了一些。放空一切股票！熊市的时候，各种股票都在下跌。第二天是周五，华盛顿诞辰纪念日。我不能再在佛罗里达州钓鱼了，我做了一大笔空头。有人需要我坚守纽约，这人是谁？自然就是我本人。棕榈滩又远又偏，光发电报就能浪费大量珍贵时间。

我从棕榈滩返回纽约，周一必须要在圣奥古斯丁等上三个小时的火车，那里有个经纪行，我自然要利用这点时间去看看股市走向。从上一个交易日到现在，安纳康达股票又下跌了好多点。事实上它一直都在跌，直到那年秋天的暴跌为止。

到达纽约后，我做了差不多四个月的空头。股市跟以往一样来回反弹，我只能跟着平仓和放空。严格来讲，我不是抓着头寸纹丝不动。不要忘了，我在旧金山地震那次赚到的30万全部折了进去，本以为不会出错，可还是差点完蛋。我现在的做法非常小心，人在逆境中走过，就会很喜欢顺境中的感觉，即使他还没有攀到最高山峰。赚钱的方法就是去赚钱，而想赚大钱，就要选择恰到好处的正确时机。身处这个行业，就要将理论和实际结合起来，不能只是光会投机，而要既做好学生也要做好投机人。

我当时做得还是很好的，虽然现在我感觉那时的做法有很多不完美的地方。夏天到了的时候，股市萧条了，看样子只有在秋天才能变好。我认识的很多人都去了欧洲，有的准备要去。我觉得这是个好计划，所以我也平了仓。我乘船前往欧洲时，一共赚了75万，这对我而言是笔非常大的财富。

我在法国埃克斯莱班愉快地游玩，反正已经赚了足够游玩的钱。能在一个好地方，有钱有朋友，一起铁了心快活一场，简直是一件特别爽的事，而埃克斯莱班就具备这些条件。远离华尔街，我差不多都要忘记它了，这一点我认为胜过美国任何一个度假胜地。我不需要再去与股市打交道，不需要交易，我赚的钱完全够我用上很久。而且，我也知道回去后该怎么赚钱，肯定会赚得比在欧洲花费的要多很多。

有一天，我在《巴黎先锋报》上看到了一条发自纽约的消息，炼铁公司宣布要发放一笔额外股利，他们的股票也已经上涨了，整体股市行情也很不错，而这也就影响了我在埃克斯莱班的计划。这个消息说明多头集团仍在绝望地和大势对抗，他们在跟常识和诚实顽抗，因为他们很清楚要发生什么事情，所以要借势在股市风暴侵袭他们之前把股票倒出来。可能他们不觉得股市会有我估计的那么急迫和严重，华尔街的要人们总像政客一般靠臆想做事。但是我却不能这么做，这对股民来说是很危险的事情。或许也有那种不怕身陷泥潭的人。

以我的了解，一切在熊市中想通过操纵提升股价的炒股行为都会失败。看到那条消息后，我觉得只有一件事能做得称心愉快，就是把炼铁公司的股票放空。在股市资金出现问题的时候，那些人还在提高配股比率，这就像他们在跪下求我放空一样。这种事情就像你小时候，有人找你挑战一样让你生气。他们挑战我放空这只股票。

我卖掉了一些炼铁公司的股票，还让我在纽约的朋友们也做空头。经纪人把单子给我的时候，我看到上面的股价比我在《巴黎先锋报》上看到的还低6个点，这足以说明实情了。

我原计划月底去巴黎，过三周后再回纽约，可当我拿到经纪人的单子后，当天就去了巴黎。到达巴黎的同一天，我向客船公司打电话咨询，第二天就有去纽约的快船，于是我订了船票。

就这样，我比原计划提前一个月回到了纽约，这里才是适合我放空股票的地方。我有大概50多万的保证金，我回来不是因为不看好后市，而是因为我是个讲理的人。

我又放空了很多股票。股市的资金越发紧俏了，短期贷款的利率也变高了，与之相应的是股价越来越低。我早就预感到是这样。一开始，我的判断害过我，可现在我成功了。不过，正儿八经的快乐是，我觉得身为一个炒股手，自己终于走对了路。我还有很多东西要学，但是我知道要怎么做。我不再犯错，再不会采用烂办法。在这个游戏中，分析行情是非常重要的。在适当的时候出手，坚持头寸也特别重要。但是我最重要的发现是，必须要全面研究所有因素，考量自己的所作所为，以便预估接下来可能发生的状况。总之，我学会了为钱工作。我不会再去鲁莽地下赌注，也不再关心如何掌握操作技巧，我通过钻研和深思熟虑获得了成功。我还发现，谁也不能免于犯下愚蠢的操作失误的危险。一个人操作愚蠢，就要为愚蠢付出代价。

我在股票公司赚了很多钱，我玩得很成功，成了人们平日的谈资，不过是经过夸大的。他们把很多只股票的崩跌都归功于我。不知道姓名的人也来向我表示祝贺。他们都认为最神奇的是我赚了那么多钱，却只字不提我第一次跟他们谈到熊市快来了时，他们都认为我是疯狂的空头，是在亏损之后恶意地发牢骚。在他们眼里，我预估到股市资金链断裂不值一提。他们认为，对他们来说，我的经纪商的会计用了三分之一滴的墨水，才在账簿的贷方写完我名下的获利，是惊人的成就。

过去，朋友们常常跟我讲，在很多股票公司里，人们都在议论着哈丁兄弟公司的投机分子狙击了想要抬高股价的多头集团——他们在情势很明显，股市一定会在比较低的水准寻求支撑的情形之后很久，还设法抬高很多种股票的价格。一直到今天，他们还在谈论我的几次掼压行动。

从9月下旬开始，资金市场就向全世界发出了警讯，可是大家都相信会有奇迹出现，不愿卖掉手中的股票。当有个经纪人对我说起发生在10月第一周的一件事时，我几乎对自己的不紧不慢感到羞愧了。

你还记得吧，以前资金贷款是在交易大厅的货币池完成的。经纪人收到银行的通知，说头寸需要多少钱，就知道还需要借款多少。当然，银行也知道这个。可以提供贷款的人会把钱拿到交易所，由几个经纪人处理。他们主要营生的方式就是放贷。一般快中午的时候，当天的新利率就会公布，差不多就是当时贷款利率的平均值。生意还能通过公开投标达成，谁都可以知道进展。一般情况下，从中午到下午两点的交易很少，不过过了交割时间两点一刻后，经纪人就能知晓当天准确的现金头寸，他们可以去货币池借贷需要的钱。这些通常都公开进行。

10月上旬的一天，我提到过的那位经纪人来找我，说他们都很生气，有钱都不想去货币池，因为几个大证券商总在那儿盯着，看到谁拿出钱就会围过去。当然没有一个公开做放款业务的人能够拒绝这些机构。他们要是有偿还能力和抵押品倒是好说了，问题是一旦他们打电话来借钱，这些钱就打了水漂。他们只要说一句没钱还，不管借钱的人是否情愿，都得继续借。所以，股票交易所想借钱给熟悉的人，一般会派人悄悄对他说：“需要100美元吗？”代表的含意是：“想借10万吗？”银行的资金经纪人也用这样的办法。你想想吧，货币池的情形真的是一片凄惨。

他告诉我说10月的那些日子股票交易所规定借钱的人可以自己确定利率，这已经成了证券交易所的习惯。你看，年利率一直在百分之百到百分之一百五十之间动荡。我觉得让借钱的人自己定利率，放贷人不会让人觉得自己就是个高利贷主，可他一分钱都不会少拿。债主也自然不想要高利息。他只要钱，钱能到手就很好。

情况变得越来越不像话了，最终到了一发不可收拾的地步，无论乐观与否，起初没胆量承受小损失，现在终于没办法控制了。虽然他们也怕赔本，可是大多数人都没有避开血本无归的痛苦。我会永远记住这个日子：1907年10月24日。

从一大帮要借钱的人那里传出来的消息，很早就显示借方愿意付出贷方认为应该要的利率。没有足够的钱来运转，那天的人比平时多出了好多。交割时间刚到，已有一百多人在交易池等着，他们都想借款救急。如果没钱，他们就得按照市场上的价格把股票卖掉，不计价格，因为买主像资金一样稀少——那个时候连一美元都难以寻到。

朋友的合作者们和我一样，不看好后市，公司也用不着去借钱。可我提到过的那位经纪人朋友，终于一脸憔悴地从交易池里摆脱了，他来到我这里。他清楚我有很多空头头寸。

他说：“老天爷啊，我不清楚到底怎么了，从来没见过这样的情况。不能这样下去了，这还了得，我感觉现在就有人已经破产了。你卖不出股票，现在市场上一分钱都很难找到。”

“你说的什么意思啊？”我问。

他回答道：“你听过这样一个实验吗？把一只老鼠放到一个玻璃器皿中，再把空气抽掉。你能看到老鼠的呼吸不断减弱，小身体两边就像风箱一样呼哧呼哧，真是可怜。它使劲儿地从玻璃器皿中获得稀少的空气。你能看到它喘不上气来，眼睛都要从眼眶里跳出来了，慢慢地喘息着死掉。唉，我看到资金交易池的那些人时，觉得他们就是老鼠。哪里都没有资金，也没人买股票，他就没法交易股票。如果你问我华尔街现在的状况，我会说这个时候它已经病入膏肓了。”

这种情形让我顿时沉思起来，我预测到会崩盘，可我承认没有预测到我们国家有史以来最严重的一次资本恐慌。这样继续下去的话，对谁都是莫大的损害。

事情已经明摆着了，再等下去也起不了什么作用，地狱正在召唤他们。

后来，我听说股票交易所总经理托马斯知道大家头顶都悬着一把剑，都在到处寻求帮助，于是他去拜访了全美国最有实力的银行——国家城市银行的行长詹姆斯·斯蒂尔曼，他曾经自豪地说过，他们的贷款利率从来没高出过百分之六。

斯蒂尔曼听托马斯讲明情况后说：“托马斯先生，我们必须要去跟摩根先生说说这个问题。”

他们都希望能够为有史以来最严重的这次金融事件努力做点事情，于是他们到了摩根的办公室。托马斯刚向摩根讲述问题的严重性，摩根先生就说：“回去吧，对他们说，钱会有的。”

“在哪里？”

“在银行里。”

这种危机四伏的时候，谁都对摩根先生充满信任，所以托马斯没再继续查问详情，就直接折回了交易大厅，向已经被判了死刑的老伙计们宣布缓刑。

接着在下午两点半之前，摩根派来了范恩·埃德波公司的埃德波来交易厅，谁都知道他和摩根关系密切。我朋友说，这个老经纪人快步来到交易池跟前，像复兴大会上规劝迷途者恢复信仰一般，高举着手。之前从托马斯那里得到消息的人们本来已经平静了，现在又开始担心计划泡汤，发生更糟糕的事情。他们盯着埃德波的脸，看到他举起了手，就都僵在了那里。

在无声的沉寂中，埃德波说：“我有给你们贷款1000万的权力，大家轻松点，谁都会有钱的。”

接着，他就开始了操作。他没有把放款人的名字告诉要贷款的人，而是简单记下了贷款人的姓名和所需资金，然后对他们说：“等着人通知你们去哪里拿钱。”意思是，稍后贷款人就可以去放款的银行拿钱。

据说过了一两天，摩根先生对那些担惊受怕的银行家们说，一定要向股票交易所提供需要的资金。

“可是我们没有钱啊，钱早就全部放出去了。”

摩根正色言道：“储备金呢？”

“这已经比法定限额都低了。”他们悲戚地说。

“用啊！储备金的用处就在这里。”

银行答应了，拿出了2000万左右的储备金，挽救了即将崩溃的市场。摩根先生是个很了不起的勇士，银行到现在也没有什么长进。

这一天，是我炒股以来印象最深刻的一天，也是这一天，我赚了100万美元。这说明，我第一次经过精心布局的交易最终成功了，我之前预料的结果也出现了。不过更重要的是，我实现了一个狂妄的梦想，做了一天国王。

需要说明的是，我在纽约待了几年，常会深入思考，为什么不可以像15岁在波士顿对赌行时一样，也在纽约股票市场上游刃有余地掌控一切呢。我清楚自己有搞明白的一天，然后就不会再犯错。那时候，我不光想做正确的事情，而且还有能做正确事情的资本，这就意味着权力。

请不要误会，这不是个毫无节制的大梦想，也不是因为虚荣心而妄想，只是我的感觉而已。我认为曾经在富勒顿公司和哈丁兄弟公司把我打垮过的股市，终有一天会匍匐在我的脚下，那一天一定会到来。这一天真的来了——1907年10月24日。

我之所以这么说，是因为那天早晨，一个与我有过长期合作，也清楚我一直做空头的经纪人和华尔街一家最著名的银行合伙人同车。他对这位银行家说，我这些年的交易量一直非常巨大，因为我确实在尽我最大的力量去赌博。

或许那个经纪人言过其实，好让他的故事听起来特别重要，也或许我有很多自己都不知道的粉丝，再或者这位银行家比我更清楚问题的严重性，总之我朋友对我说：“我对他说，你觉得再推动一两下，真正的股票销售期到来时，市场会怎么变化。他听得特别认真，我说完后，他还说稍晚一点儿的时候要找我办事。”

当证券商人们发现，用任何贷价都没法弄来一分钱时，我清楚时机到了。我把经纪人指派到了各处。老天，有段时间太平洋铁路公司的股票没有一张买单，不管什么价格！你想想吧，其他股票也都是这样。没有资金可以支撑股票，也没人愿意买进。

我的账面利润很惊人，而且我很清楚，要想撼动股价，要做的就是卖出股票。我卖出太平洋和其他六家股息较好的公司各1万的股票，随之而来的一定是哀鸿遍野。我认为，马上要出现的股市恐慌会很惨烈，甚至政府都会产生要关闭交易所的想法，就像1914年8月世界大战时一样。

这正好说明我的浮动利润要大幅度上涨了。

不过，要想把利润换成现金，也是没什么可能。不过还是要考虑其他事，其中之一是股票一直下跌，会对刚恢复的市场产生影响，从全局来看，这样的股市恐慌对整个国家都会产生损害。

我决定，既然再这么热心地做空是不聪明的做法，而且也不好玩，那么我如果继续做空就违反逻辑了，所以我转向开始买入。

经纪人替我以很低的价格买入股票没多久，银行就把我朋友叫去了。

“我让人喊你过来，”他说，“目的是想让你赶紧去找你朋友利文斯顿，对他说，我们希望他今天不要再卖出任何股票，市场的压力已经很大了。要扭转这次股市恐慌的确不是一件容易的事情。把你朋友的爱国热情激发出来吧，面对这样的局面，人一定要照顾大局，他有什么说法一定要第一时间告诉我。”

我朋友立刻就来找我了，他很讲究技巧。我想他可能觉得我既然计划击垮股市，应该会把他提出的要求看作是放弃赚1000万的机会。他同时也明白，那些人跟我一样都知道会出现什么情况，却还使劲儿把股票卖给大家，这是让人很不齿的事情。

其实，那些股票大户才是受害最严重的人，我用很低的价格买到的股票都是很有名的公司，当时我却不知道，可也没什么，我已经差不多平了所有空头。我觉得既有机会买了便宜股票，若没有人去打压股市的话，我还帮忙恢复了股价。

所以我对朋友说：“你去告诉银行的人，我答应了。我在他找你之前就明白，这件事的意义非同寻常。我不光今天不卖了，而且还要想办法买入些。”我信守了承诺，当天就买了10万股，还是多头。此后的九个月里，我都没再抛出股票。

这就是为什么我对朋友说，我的梦想实现了，做了一天国王的原因。那天的某段时间，股市确实是处于任人蹂躏的状态。我没有幻想自己很伟大，其实你知道的，我很明白人们指责我袭击股市时，以及华尔街传播我如何神乎其技时，是种什么感觉。

我没有受到一点儿损伤就脱身了，报纸上炒作说利文斯顿这个“投机分子”赚了几百万。呵呵，我在那天收市前赚了差不多100万，可我最大的获利不是这个，而是看不到的收获：我是对的，我预估了未来，并且策划周密。我学到要想赚大钱必须要做的事情，我彻底与赌博划清了界限，终于学会了怎么利用智商做大手笔的生意。这是我一生中最重要的日子。

第十章

我们认识到错误，应该不会比研究自己为什么成功更有好处。大家自然都不想受到错误的惩罚，当犯错带来恶果后，谁也不想重蹈覆辙，来自股市的错误会对你造成财产和自尊上的双重伤害。不过我要告诉你一些奇怪的现象：有时候交易商们做错事情的时候，是心知肚明的。他们出错后会自问原因，当后果带来的痛苦烟消云散后，思考良久，他们就有可能搞明白，自己什么时候、在哪里、怎么样出了错，可他不会知道出错的原因，只会骂自己一句，然后就放过了。

当然，如果一个人既聪明又运气比较好，就不会在同一条道上摔倒两次，可其他那么多类似的错误保不齐就会犯。世界上的错真是太多，当你每次想知道自己会不会出错时，可能有个错就悄悄守在你身边。

要告诉你我的第一个百万美元的错误，就得从1907年10月我第一次成为百万富翁后开始说。以我的交易而言，一百万只是说明我多了点保证金。金钱本身不会给股民带来更多的舒适，因为不管贫穷还是富有，都会出错，这是让人永远不爽的事情。当事情做对的时候，金钱只是个工具。赔钱对我也始终没产生过困扰，过上一天我就会忘掉。若做错了事情而不愿意接受所受的亏损，那就不光是金钱的损失了，心灵也会受到伤害。你还记得迪克森·华兹讲过的一件小事吧。有个人特别紧张，朋友问他到底怎么了。

他说：“我总失眠。”

朋友问原因，他说：“我的棉花期货的头寸特别大，想想就难以入睡，我被折腾得筋疲力尽。我该怎么办？”

朋友劝他：“卖掉吧，让你的头寸少到你能睡踏实的程度。”

一般而言，人是很能适应环境而丧失洞察能力的动物。他察觉不到有多大区别，就是说，他基本上不可能想起还没成为百万富翁的时候自己是什么感觉了，而只知道一些当时做不了，现在却可以做的事情。年轻、正常、理智的人由俭入奢易，由奢入俭难。我觉得原因是金钱会挑起人的欲望，人们总是多少抱着多多益善的观念。意思是说，当有人从股市赚了钱后，很快就纸醉金迷了，可一旦他又没钱了，要改掉大手大脚的习惯，就得花很长时间。

1907年10月，我不再做空而是开始做多。我计划先放松一下，于是就买了一艘游艇，想去南边的海域游玩一趟。我特别喜欢钓鱼，总想着要好好钓一场鱼，也盼望有实现的那一天，可股市却总不能让我如愿。

一直以来，我既进行股票交易，也玩商品期货。年轻的时候，我就开始在对赌行做期货交易了。这些年来，我一直在研究期货市场，只不过不像对股市那样上心。其实相比较的话，我更偏向做期货，不是因为它看起来更正统，虽然确实如此，可它也具备更高的风险。用一个假设的理由来反对或者支持期货市场的价格走向，即便成功也是短暂的，最后还是事实得到胜利。所以，就像做其他普通生意一样，交易商们总是靠研究和观察得到报酬。他可以观察和考虑各种情况，而且可以跟别人知道的一样多。他不用跟幕后集团做斗争。在棉花、小麦、玉米期货市场上，没有红利分配这一说法。长久以来，商品价格只受一种法则主导——供需的经济法则。玩期货的人只要知道供求状态、现况和趋势就行，不用像炒股一样对很多事情做预估，所以期货对我的吸引力更大。

所有的投机市场都有相同点，行情走势的分析技巧是一样的。对于所有热衷于思考的人而言，这一点非常清楚。如果人多问自己几个为什么，对各个因素考虑明白，答案就直接出来了。可是人们总是懒于发问，更不用说找答案了。一般美国人生性多疑，而且任何时候都是这样，只有到经纪商那里看盘的时候例外，不管看的是股票还是商品。在所有的游戏当中，玩之前真正需要研究的一种游戏，刚好就是美国人没有利用平常惯有的高度警觉和极为聪明的准备就投身其中的游戏。有的人拿出自己的一半身家去冒险时，花在思考上的时间还没买一辆车时考虑的时间长。

分析行情并没那么难。当然这需要经验，但是更需要的是在心里记住一些基本要素。分析情势并不是为了知道运气好不好，它可不会对你说下周四下午一点三十五你会有多少钱。分析行情是为了如何交易和什么时候交易——也就是说，应该买还是卖，这些对股票、棉花、小麦和玉米都一样有效。

你观察市场自然是依靠行情记录机显示的价格情况，目的只有一个，就是确定方向，即价格走向。我们知道，价格会根据实际情况上涨或者下跌。为了简单解释清楚，我们把价格看作跟其他东西一样，在沿着最小阻力线变化。它们通常是怎么变化容易就会怎么变，所以当上涨阻力小于下跌阻力时，价格就会上涨，反过来也一样。

如果股市开局很稳，后面不管牛市还是熊市，都不应该感到困惑。对一个思维敏捷并很有眼光的人而言，趋势很明显。对于投机客来说，总想着拿理论往事实身上死套，是很愚蠢的。清楚了是牛市还是熊市，就知道了该买还是该卖。人就应该在市场一开始就判断出走向。

比如，假设市场一如既往地起起伏伏，波动在10个点内，最高能涨到130，最低跌到120。可能当它快跌到支撑点120时，就会劲力不足而显得疲软。或者在上涨8个点或10个点的路上，看起来特别强劲。你不应该根据某些简单迹象就贸然行动，而是应该根据行情记录来判断时机是否已到。其实人们因为价格看起来便宜就买，或是因为价格看起来贵就卖，已经损失了几千万美元。投机的人跟投资的人不一样，他不是为了得到稳定回报，而是在价格的上下变动中谋取利益。所以他需要确定的是哪个投机路线阻力最小，他应该等待市场自行确定最高上涨点和最低下跌点，这是交易上该遵循的原则。

在看行情走势的时候，你觉得股价在130时，卖掉比买进要好。市场在持续变化，那些对行情分析半瓶子醋的人就会觉得股价能涨到150，所以买进，可是当价格回落时他们要么坚持，要么甘愿接受现实而做空。在120的时候，股价下跌遇到的阻力比较大，买比卖强，价格开涨，空头又去回补。很多人通常就是这样两面受打击，还总不吸取教训，真是让人深感奇怪。

反正最终肯定会出现让涨或跌变得比较强势的事，最大阻力点会上升或者下降。也就是说，在130的时候，买盘比卖盘强，而在120的时候则相反。价格会突破波动的区间而继续变动，很多人总会在120时做空，因为貌似市场很疲弱，而在130的时候正相反。当股市不利于他们时，他们就只能认栽。就是这些人协助确立了阻力位和支撑点。一些聪明又很有耐心的人却等着股市走向明确，他们会利用基本交易形式来帮忙，也会利用那些做错的人们对市场产生的交易力量而赚钱。那些人的错误会把价格推向最小阻力点。

我说的这个并不是很精确和公认的理论，但是每当我靠着自己对阻力最小的路线所做的判断，决定市场方向时，我的经验是，这些意外事件总是会顺从我的市场方向，也就是突发或无法预见的事件总是协助我做的市场方向。你还记得我提到过的那次在萨拉托加太平洋铁路公司的股票事件吗？我做了多头，是因为我觉得最小阻力线在上升。我就该坚持做多头，而不是听经纪人的话卖掉。公司董事们心里想什么没有任何差别，反正这也不是我能知道的事情。接着果然就发生了配股率突然提高，股价涨了30点的事情。股价若到了164，看起来就非常高了，可正如我之前所说，股价绝对不会高得不能买进，或是低得不能卖出。股价的高低，从本质上来说，与确立最小阻力线没什么关系。

如果你按照我说的方法交易，实际炒股时你会知道，收盘后出来的大信息通常都配合阻力最小的路线。在消息出来前，走向就已经定了。牛市时，人们会忽视利空消息，而夸大利好消息，反过来也一样。世界大战爆发前，股市很不好。德国宣布了无限制潜艇战政策。我当时放空了50万，并不是我得到了什么消息，而是我沿着最小阻力线来做。就我的操作而言，德国的宣布好比晴天霹雳。我利用这种情况，当天就回补了空头。

我说你只需要观察股市行情，确立好关口，只要你确定最小阻力线后，就准备沿着这条线路交易，这听起来很简单。可是，在实际的交易过程中，却必须要防备很多事情，最重要的是要小心你自己——也就是要对抗人心的弱点。这就是为什么我说正确的人总有股力量——基本情势和错误的人——在帮助他。在牛市期，人们会对利空消息不那么重视，这就是人性，可人们还对这一点表示震惊。因为一两个地区的天气很恶劣，大家会告诉你说，小麦作物完了，等到整个作物收成，所有的产区的小麦都被送到谷仓时，多头会惊讶地发现损害程度如此轻微。他们发现，自己只是帮了空头的忙。

做期货交易，不能保持固定不变的思维，而必须要思维活跃。不管你对谷物供需情况持什么态度，都不要忽略行情记录里面的信息。我记得有一次我由于鲁莽错失了良机。我对情势很确定，觉得没必要等待最小阻力线，我甚至有过要帮它确立的想法，因为好像只需要一点点协助就行了。

我觉得棉花会暴涨。棉花当时一直在每磅12美分上下浮动，范围很小。我知道自己应该稍等一下，可我同时觉得只要稍微推一下，就可以让它突破阻力位。

我买了5万包棉花，它果然涨了。我一停止买进，它也就不再继续上涨，接着跌落到了我开始买进时的价格。我退出来，它也就不跌了。我认为我现在更接近出发点了，于是我立刻认为我应该再度出发。我也这样做了。同样的事情又发生了一次，我抬高了价格，一停止买进我就看到价格下跌。我来来回回这样做了四五次，最终只好放弃，一共赔了20万。没过多久，棉花又开始涨了，居然涨到了让我恨死自己的程度，如果我不那么急着开始该多好啊。

很多玩家都经历过很多次这样的事情，所以我定了一条原则：市场窄幅波动时，价格波动范围很小，要预估下一个大波动是往上还是往下，这个实在没什么意义。应该做的事情是观察市场，分析走向，判定浮动上下线，在价格没有突破上下线时，千万不要有所行动。投机的人必须要一心一意靠市场获利，而非坚持等大盘形势与自己的预估一样。永远不要向综合行情叫板，不要询问理由或解释。事后替股市解剖验尸没有任何好处。

前不久，我和几个朋友在一起，他们在讨论小麦期货。有人觉得会涨，有人觉得会跌，他们最后问我的看法。我已经有了一段时间的市场经验，我知道他们想得到的不是统计数据，也不是对行情的判断，因此我说：“你们要是想在小麦市场赚钱，我可以教你们方法。”

他们当然说想赚钱，我就说：“你们要是真想赚钱的话，观察情势就可以，然后等着，耐心点。等到1.2美元的时候就买进，就能赚很大一笔。”

“为什么现在不买？才1.14美元。”有人说。

“因为现在还不能确定上涨的真实性。”

“那为什么要在1.2美元时买进？不是更贵了吗？”

“你想鲁莽地大赚一次，还是明智又保险地少赚点呢？”

他们都回答说，最好是稳稳当当赚点。于是我说：“那就听我的没错，1.2美元时再去买。”

我所料没错，我已经观察了很长时间。几个月来，小麦一直在1.1和1.2美元间浮动，没其他特殊的状况出现。终于有一天，收市时的价格是1.19美元。我早做了准备，如果没什么意外的话，第二天开盘价就是1.205美元。所以我买进了。小麦的价格从1.21涨到了1.25，我当然是一路加码了。

此时我跟你说不清到底是怎么回事，我对它的小小浮动也给不出解释，我不能告诉你，浮动只向上突破1.2还是向下跌破1.1。我觉得就是会上涨，因为当时小麦非常缺乏。

其实，欧洲似乎一直在悄悄地买进，很多人在1.19美元时放空。因为欧洲人的买入，加上其他一些原因，很多小麦都被转运从市场上消失了，因此最后出现了大波动，价格突破1.20美元。这是我的观点，也是我需要的唯一事实。我明白因为价格上涨积攒了力量，到了1.20美元时就会冲破上限。也就是说，过了1.20这个线，小麦价格的最小阻力线就确立了，随后的情形就不大相同了。

我记得那天是美国的节假日，美国所有市场都闭市。加拿大温尼伯在开盘时却每蒲式耳涨了6美分，第二天美国市场开盘时，也涨了6美分。价格只是按照阻力最小的路线在前行而已。

我说的这一切表明，我玩这些的主要方法就是研究市场行情。我只是了解了价格最可能的前行方向，我会多玩几次继续验证我的判断。我从一开始就注意观察，我的交易让市场价格发生了什么变化。

我买股票的时候，喜欢以高价买入，以低价卖出，很多经验丰富的股民听到这种话时都会露出吃惊的表情。如果交易者总是坚持自己的投机利器，赚钱不是什么难事。就是说，等到最小阻力线明确了以后，行情上涨的时候买进，下跌的时候卖出，并且应该一路加码，要赚钱并不困难。例如在上涨时积攒头寸，先买进总量的五分之一，若没有多少利润，就要停止买入，因为很明显一开始就搞错了，或者至少是暂时错了，不管什么时候出了错，都不会有钱可赚的。行情记录说会上涨，不见得是说谎，完全是因为行情记录现在是说：“还没到时候”。

我做棉花期货一直很成功。我有自己的理论，而且绝对遵照这个理论。如果我想做到四五万包，那么我就会像之前说的那样，研究好市场行情，搞明白到底是该买还是该卖。如果最小阻力线有上升迹象，我就会先买1万，然后市场如果还在上涨，我就会再来1万。如果我有20个点的利润，或者每包能赚1美元，我就会继续买2万包，然后达到满仓，我就是用这个方法赚钱的。可若我买了一两万包以后，有波动性的亏损，那就要平仓。这说明我看错了形势，或者只是暂时错了，可我不是提到过吗，不管哪种错，都不会有钱可赚。

我坚持自己的那一套，借着它我在每次的棉花市场波动时，都能够保持住自己的实力。在建仓的时候，可能会用暂时亏损五六万的操作去验证市场。貌似这个验证有点太贵了，可实际却不见得。当市场正儿八经开始时，我损失的那点钱很快就会赚回来。不要不放过机会，在正确的时刻采取正确的行动，就会赚到钱。

我已经说了我在市场交易时的整套方法。只在赚钱的时候下大注，而错的时候也就只亏损了那点用来测试的钱，这是个聪明的做法。如果按照我说的这种办法去玩，就会一直保持住有钱可赚的头寸，能在大赌注中获利不少。

专业玩家们总能依靠自己的经验，建立各种玩法，这些都取决于他们如何对待投机这件事。我记得在棕榈滩的时候，碰到过一位老人，猛然间还想不起他叫什么名字。我知道他从南北战争时期就在华尔街混江湖，有人告诉我说他非常聪明，身经百战，因此他喜欢说世界上没什么新鲜事物，至少股市中是没有的。

老人问了我很多问题，我告诉他我平时是怎么样做的，他点着头说：“没错，没错，你是对的，你的做事方式和思维方法，都对你非常有用。你很容易按照自己的想法行事，因为你投进去的钱是你最不重视的部分。我想起了帕特·赫恩这个人，你听过吧？他是个很有名的赌客，在我们那边开了户。他非常聪明，是个性情中人。他就靠炒股赚钱，所以会有人喜欢跟他交流要他提供建议。他从来都不肯说。如果有人直截了当地问他对他们持股的看法，他就会说出他在赛场上最喜欢的那句话：‘在你开赌之前一切都属未知。’他在我们公司炒股，会先选择很火的股票买100股，如果能上涨百分之一，他会继续买100股，接着涨的话还继续买。他经常说，自己玩这个游戏，不是为了把钱送给别人，所以他总会把止损单放在最后交易的那笔单子的价格以下1个点的地方。股价如果涨了他就继续，有个百分之一的回调，他就立刻平仓。他说如果赔到1个点以上，就是个大傻帽，不管赔的钱是原来保证金里面的还是浮动利润里面的，都一样。

“你懂的，专业赌徒对长线没多少兴趣，只想着赚点稳当的钱。当然了，如果长线能做好，那也是不错的。帕特炒股从来不听信内幕消息，也不想着在一星期赚20点。他只想着能赚点让他过得不错的小钱。我在华尔街碰到过很多人，有成千上万的外行，而只有帕特一个人把投机炒股当作机会游戏，像轮盘赌博一样，可他的下注方式很实用。

“帕特·赫恩去世以后，一个经常和帕特一起玩的人，用帕特的办法在拉卡万纳赚了十几万后就去做其他股票了。他觉得赚了很多了，不用再用帕特的方式玩了。当股价回调的时候，他没有止损，而是任由它发展，让亏损像利润一样持续扩大。最后当然是亏了个血本无归，还倒欠了几千块。

“他硬撑了两三年，赔钱后还一直很狂热。但是只要他自制，我们也不反对他待在股市里。我记得他坦白承认过，没一直按照帕特的方式交易是一个很笨的决定。忽然有一天，他来找我，显得很激动，求我借他一些股票，他要卖掉。过去他一直是个不错的客户，是个好小伙儿，所以我愿意替他的账户担保，让他放空100股。

“他放空了100股湖岸公司的股票，这是在1875年，是比尔·特瑞威尔斯正压制股市的那个阶段。我的这个叫罗伯斯的朋友，在点位正好时卖掉股票，股市下跌的过程中，他一直在卖，正如他之前遵守帕特的交易原则时常做的那样，很成功。

“嗯，罗伯斯一连四天加码抛售，账面上就有了1.5万美元的利润。我看到他没有设止损单，就提醒了他，他告诉我大跌还没开始，他不想被一点儿反弹干掉。这个时候是8月，到了9月中旬的时候，他居然到了跟我借10美元，为他的第四个孩子买辆儿童车的地步。他没有一直用被证实过很有效的办法去投机，这也是很多人的问题。”老先生摇着头发表了长篇大论。

他说得没错，我有时候感觉投机是个很不自然的工作，因为我觉得很多投机玩家都倾向于做违背本性的决定。谁都有弱点，这对投机来说是很严重的问题，而这些弱点在人们做其他事情时经常会被防范住，不像在炒股时这么危险。

投机商最大的敌人是自己的内心。人性与希望和恐惧密不可分。在炒股时，当市场不利于你时，你无时无刻不在祈求这是最后一天，可你赔了的总是多于你想象的；当市场对你有利时，你又恐惧了，你怕第二天就会失去利润，所以会赶紧抽身，可这太早了。害怕使你不敢赚本应该赚的那些钱。成功者必须要一直与这两种扎牢在内心的本能做斗争，必须打败本能的冲动。当充满希望的时候，他该有所敬畏；当害怕的时候，他该满怀希望。他必须害怕小亏损会变成大亏损，希望小利润变成大利润。像普通人那样在股票上赌博，绝对是错误的。

我从14岁开始投机，这是我做过的唯一一件事，我知道我在说什么。我有30年的交易经历，能赚几美元的小小交易我干过，几百万的巨大交易我也玩过，我得出了这样的结论：人在一段时间里可以战胜某只股票，可没有一个人能够战胜股市。人可能从棉花和谷物期货市场上赚钱，但没人能打败整个期货市场。就像赌马一样，人可能会赢一场比赛，但不可能战胜这种游戏。

如果我知道怎么让这个结论更具说服力和影响力，我必定会去做。若有人不同意，也没什么关系，我自己知道这些结论是完全正确的，不容置疑的。

第十一章

现在让我回过头来继续讲1907年10月的事情。我买了一艘游艇，做好所有准备，离开纽约去南边游玩。我太喜欢钓鱼了，现在有了游艇，我想去哪里都行，什么时候去都可以，只要我愿意的话。一切准备都做好了，我在股票上赚了很多钱。可是，临到最后时，玉米期货市场把我留了下来。

我必须解释一下，在那次我遇到的第一个100万的资金恐慌前，我就在芝加哥做过谷物期货。我各做了1000万蒲式耳的小麦和玉米的空头，我对这个市场研究了很久，就像看淡股市一样，我也看淡谷物市场。

谷物一直在下跌。当小麦下跌严重时，芝加哥的一个大玩家——我们把他称作斯特雷登吧——想垄断玉米市场。我把股票全部清盘后，准备乘游艇去游玩，却发现自己在小麦市场上有很大的浮动利润。因为斯特雷登把玉米价格抬得很高，我承受着很大的浮动亏损。

我知道玉米存货量不少，供需法则总是会发挥作用。可是需求主要来自斯特雷登，供应却比较匮乏，因为交通不好导致玉米没法运送。我曾祈愿要是有魔法相助多好，让农民们能把玉米送到市场中来，可惜这是不可能的。

事情就是这样，当我即将开始计划已久的钓鱼之旅时，玉米的亏损把我拉住了。市场这个样子，我没法走脱。当然了，斯特雷登很注意空头，我完全被他抓在股掌之间，而我也清楚这一点。可是，就像我说的那样，我把希望寄托在天气上。但当我觉得天气和其他好心人都没办法帮我时，我就将精力放在了研究如何靠自己来摆脱这种困境上。

我把小麦头寸平了，得到了比较高的利润。玉米的事情却非常艰难，我若用当时的价格回补我的1000万蒲式耳玉米的话，我会很高兴地立刻这样做，虽然这样损失会特别大。可当我一开始买进玉米，斯特雷登就会全心全力成为主要轧空我的人，我可不愿意因为我自己买进，而抬高我要付出的价格，就像我不喜欢拿刀子割自己的喉咙一样。

玉米虽然很强劲，可我想去钓鱼的愿望更加强烈。因此我要立即想方设法行动起来，进行一次战略性撤退。我需要把我做空头的那1000万蒲式耳买进来，而且要尽力把损失降到最低。

事有凑巧，当时斯特雷登也玩着一大把燕麦，牢牢地垄断了市场。我搜集了有关谷物市场的很多新闻与消息，研究它们的市场走向。据说很有实力的阿莫尔与斯特雷登关系不好，我也知道除非我按照他的价格买进，不然他不会让我买到我需要的玉米。所以我立刻想到要去阿莫尔那里找办法，寻求帮助。他们要帮助我，只有一个办法，就是把斯特雷登不肯卖给我的玉米卖给我，那接下来的事情就好办了。

我先是发了一些单子出去，每当降低1/8美分的时候，就买50万蒲式耳的玉米。等这些单子生效了，我就让四个经纪人以市价卖出50万蒲式耳的燕麦。我清楚那些交易商的想法，他们肯定会觉得是阿莫尔要跟斯特雷登开战了。他们看到有人损压燕麦之后，一定会很合理地断定下一个就会是玉米了，因此他们会卖掉玉米，从而打破垄断局面。那可赚的就多了。

我对芝加哥投机商这种心理的判断绝对正确。他们发现各地来的卖单敲开燕麦的价格垄断后，立刻开始打压玉米，迫不及待地开始往外卖。十分钟时间，我就买了600万蒲式耳的玉米。等我发现他们停止往外抛售玉米的时候，我干脆用市价买了另外400万蒲式耳，这就让价格又上涨了。我这样做的结果是，在抛售浪潮中，我用很好的价格回补了整整1000万蒲式耳的玉米头寸，价格跟我趁交易者卖出开始回补时的行情，差距在0.5美分之内。而且，我拿出来诱出投机商的那20万蒲式耳燕麦，只带来了3000美元的损失，这是特别廉价的投入。同时，我在小麦上赚到的钱，又把玉米的亏损补回来了。如此一来，我在谷物市场只损失了2.5万美元。这个事情之后，玉米每蒲式耳上涨了25美分。如果不管价格买进1000万蒲式耳玉米的话，损失可就无法估量了。

同一件事情，不能花了几年时间，还没有形成正确的做事态度，这是专业人士与业余人员的区别。如何对待事物，决定了人们在市场中是赚还是赔。一般人对自己的付出持有的观点很不专业，容易自高自大，思考也深入不下去。专业人士则重视做事的正确性，不只是赚钱，因为他们清楚，尽力把事情做好，钱自然就能赚到。交易者在玩这种游戏时要像撞球专家一样，看到前面很多步，而不要仅仅盯着眼前这一杆。为了争取优越而操作，必须变成一种直觉。

我记得好像听过一个有关艾迪生·科马克的故事，这是个特别恰当的实例。以我所闻，科马克是华尔街最有能力的股票作手之一，他不像很多人认为的那样总是在做空头。他觉得利用希望和恐惧两大人性因素，来帮助他做空是很有用的。他编造了这样一句警语：“在元气还在上升的时候，不要放空股票！”老前辈告诉我说，他赚得最多的钱都是做多赚来的，所以显然他炒股不片面，只根据实况来，确实是个很有水平的商人。有一次，离牛市结束还有一段时间，科马克就很不看好后市。不过当时市场还很强劲，股价一直在上涨——这都是多头集团和报纸报道造成的现况。一个叫乔瑟夫的喜欢传播消息的金融记者知道后找到科马克。他明白像科马克这样的人，非常需要利空的消息。

“科马克先生，我有个好朋友在圣保罗公司工作过，他刚才对我说了些事情，我认为你应该知道才对。”

“什么事？”科马克显得爱理不理。

“你改变方向了吗？你现在对后市不太看好吧？”乔瑟夫为了搞清状况，想知道科马克有没有兴趣，要是没有的话，他也用不着浪费宝贵的子弹。

“是啊。到底什么好消息？”

“今天，我去圣保罗公司了，每周我都会去采访两三次，我朋友对我说，老头子在卖股票，他说的是威廉·洛克菲勒。股价每每上涨3/8个点，洛克菲勒就卖出1500股。这两天他一直忙着卖。我可没耽误时间，立马就来对你说了。”

科马克可不是个沉不住气的人，而且他已经对各色人等冲进办公室这样的事习以为常了，这些人通常都会带来些乱七八糟的东西，他根本不信任他们了，所以他说道：“你肯定没听错吧，乔瑟夫？”

“我肯定，必须肯定。你觉得我是聋子吗？”乔瑟夫说。

“那你相信你的朋友吗？”

“绝对相信！”乔瑟夫说，“我们认识好多年了，他从来没对我说过谎，他绝对不会说谎。他非常可靠，我可以拿性命来为他的话担保，在这个世界上我最了解他——远比你我认识这么多年之后，你对我的了解还要深很多啊。”

“确定，没错吧？”科马克又看着乔瑟夫说，“好吧，你应该没错。”他喊来了一个营业员惠勒尔。乔瑟夫以为他会下单卖掉5万股圣保罗股票。威廉·洛克菲勒正在抛售圣保罗公司的股票，不管是投机股还是投资股，都没关系，最重要的事实是最高明的股票作手洛克菲勒想从圣保罗公司退出来。一个正常人听到这个可靠的消息会怎么办呢？根本不用问。

可是，科马克——这一时期最优秀的空头股票操控者，当时已经看淡了后市——却对营业员说：“比利，去交易所，每每上涨3/8美分就买进圣保罗的1500股。”那时候这只股票的价格是90美元左右。

“你说的是卖吧？”乔瑟夫插嘴说，他并不是华尔街的新人，可他对待市场的方式还是新闻人士，也就是普通大众的样子。因为内幕人士在抛售，价格自然会下跌，可哪个卖家还能比洛克菲勒更牛呢。标准石油公司正在抛售，科马克却在买进，怎么可能呢！

“不，”科马克说，“我说的是买入。”

“你不信任我？”

“不是，我信任。”

“你不相信我的情报？”

“我相信。”

“你现在不看好后市吧？”

“对。”

“那你这是要做什么呀？”

“这就是我为什么要买入。你听我说，你去跟你朋友继续联系，要是洛克菲勒停止了卖股票，就赶紧告诉我，快去吧，听明白没？”

“好的。”乔瑟夫说完就走了。他不知道是不是真明白了科马克的意思。科马克看淡市场，使他的操作更没法让人理解。不过，乔瑟夫还是去找他那个朋友了，告诉了他科马克的意思，而且每天打两次电话询问情况。

有一天，乔瑟夫的朋友对他说：“老头子不卖股票了。”乔瑟夫感谢了他，然后来找科马克。

科马克专心听他说完，转身问惠勒尔：“我们现在大概有多少圣保罗公司的股票？”惠勒尔查看后说，大概是6万股。

科马克一直做空，早在买入圣保罗股票之前，他就卖掉了很多其他公司的股票，是整个市场的大空头。他马上让惠勒尔卖掉那6万股圣保罗股票，当作是打压市场的武器，使他的空头操作大大获利。

圣保罗跌到了44美元，科马克大赚了一把。他用绝佳的技巧来操作，我认为最重要的是他对市场交易的习惯感知，他很敏感地看到了比单独靠这个股票来赚钱还要重要很多的东西，他发现了一个全面施展做空的绝佳机会。他靠着圣保罗股票的消息买入而不是卖出，原因是他明白这是一个积累筹码的最好时机。

要回过头来说说我自己了。我结束小麦和玉米的交易后，坐游艇去了南边海域。我在佛罗里达州玩得特别痛快，钓鱼也很顺利。一切都看上去很美。我不用去想这个世界上的任何事情，更不想去获得什么东西。

有一天，我到了棕榈滩，看到很多来自华尔街的朋友，他们在聊棉花期货市场的事情。从纽约传来消息说，珀西·托马斯赔掉了血本，这是这位厉害角色在棉花市场上第二次遭受巨大失败。

我很佩服托马斯这个人。初次听说他是通过报纸，当时证券交易所会员公司谢尔顿·托马斯公司倒闭，那个时候，托马斯想到垄断棉花市场，可是谢尔顿却没那么大的魄力和眼界，在快成功时害怕了。反正整个华尔街都是这么传的。他们不但没赚到钱，还遭遇了多年的大赔本。我记不清他们赔了多少钱，总之公司破产了，托马斯和谢尔顿也分道扬镳了。后来托马斯转过来把所有精力都用在了棉花交易上，没多久就东山再起，不但还清了所有的债，包括那些法律规定的并不需要还清的部分，还剩下了100万。他在棉花市场的东山再起的事迹，和“老手白”在股市的著名杰作一样让人惊叹，老手白在一年里靠股市操作，还清了100万美元的债务。托马斯的勇气和头脑使我非常景仰他。

棕榈滩的所有人都在说3月托马斯在棉花市场遭遇滑铁卢的事情，你明白他们会怎样以讹传讹的。我曾经遇到过一个关于我的谣言，也是这样被夸大其词、添油加醋地传播的，以至于在不到一天时间内，当这个谣言重新传回最初编造这个谣言的那个人耳朵里时，他都不知道是怎么回事了。谣言已经被增添得枝繁叶茂了。

托马斯事件也改变了我的想法，我不想再继续度假了，我要回到棉花市场中去。我找了很多交易文件认真研读，想了解清楚事实。回到纽约，我看到所有人都在做空头，大卖7月棉花期货。我觉得人们就像得了传染病，谁去做什么，是因为他周围的人都在这么做，或许这是群众心理的某种阶段或变化。不管怎样，很多人都觉得卖掉是最聪明最安全的做法。交易的人们只看到了市场的一面和有可能出现的暴利。他们的的确确觉得价格会崩溃。

我肯定也看到了这些情况，但是我想到放空的那些人是没多少时间回补的。我分析得越深入，就搞得越清楚，最后做出了买进7月棉花的决定。我开始着手实施，买了10万包，这很容易办到，大量的人都在卖出。在我看来，我甚至可以悬赏100万美元，不论死活，抓一个没有卖7月棉花的人，肯定没有人来领赏。

那时候是5月下旬，我不停地买进，他们不停地卖出。我把所有卖出的全部买了以后，一共是12万包棉花。我停手后没两天，棉花开始涨价，市场状态特别好，一天内就涨了四五十点。

我开始买入棉花十多天后，一个周六，价格上涨的速度放慢了。我不清楚是不是有人还想卖，所以一直等着，到了闭市前的最后十分钟。我知道这个时间经常是空头入市的时候，如果高位收盘，他们肯定会被我套住。所以，我发出了四张不同的单子，同时以市价各买进5000包，把价格拉高了30个点，那些做空的人慌不择路了。市场在最高价收盘了，请知悉，我只是买了2万包棉花。

第二天是周日，等到周一时，利物浦本来高开20点就能配合纽约的市场行情，没想到它高开了50个点，这就是说利物浦的涨势超过我们的涨势百分之百。利物浦市场走高与我是没关系的，这个情况说明了我的推断是正确的，我是按照最小阻力线完成的交易。当然我也不会忘记，我手上有大批的棉花要脱手。市场能够暴涨，也能够缓缓上涨，可它的容量也有限度。

利物浦的消息引发我们的市场狂涨，可是我却发现涨得越高，7月棉花的成交量却越少。我准备一点儿都不卖。总的来说，周一对空头来说，就是很崩溃的日子。不过，我也没发现任何空头惊恐，也没有空头争相回补的迹象，我必须要为我手里的14万包棉花找到去处。

周二一大早，我去办公室的时候在门口遇到了一个朋友，他笑呵呵地说：“《世界报》今早发了一则大消息啊。”

“什么消息？”我问。

“嗯？你难道还没看报纸吗？”

“呃，报道的是你呀，你把7月棉花垄断到手中了。”

“我没看报呢。”我回答道。我不知道他是否相信，说不定他觉得我没说真话，不是好哥们儿。

到办公室后，我拿了一份《世界报》，看到头版头条写着：“拉里·利文斯顿垄断7月棉花期货。”

我马上感觉市场要受这个报道影响了。我如果仔细研究该怎样刻意寻找什么方法卖掉我的14万包棉花的话，再也没有比这个更好的计划了。这时候，全国各地的人都从《世界报》或其他转载了这个消息的报纸上看到了这个消息，而且它也已被欧洲市场知晓了，利物浦的市场价格说得一清二楚，疯狂的市场因为这条消息而失控，也没什么惊奇的了。

我知道纽约市场会面临什么变化，也清楚该怎么去应对市场。上午十点开盘，十点十分的时候，我就已经卖完了棉花。我把那14万包棉花转给了别人，我的大部分头寸都是在当天价位最高的时候交易的。那些人替我塑造了很好的市场，其实我要做的就是抓住这个机会，卖掉我的棉花。我确实利用了这次机会，我可不能让机会随风而逝，我不这么做还能怎样？

本来要花费很大精力才能解决的问题，就因为这么一个机会而轻易解决了。要是没有《世界报》的这篇新闻，我一旦卖出就会赔掉大量的浮动利润。我可没能力卖掉14万包7月棉花期货，还不拉低市场价格。无论如何，《世界报》的这条新闻就是恰逢其时地帮了我，我不知道它为什么会报道这个新闻，我确实想知道。我觉得，那位记者可能从清楚棉花市场的朋友处听到了消息，就认为是个独家好新闻。我不认识这个记者，更没见过《世界报》的其他职员。那天上午九点我才知道了这个消息，而且要不是那个朋友跟我说，我还不清楚。

如果没这个新闻，也就没有大到可以让我卖掉棉花的市场。交易量大是很恼人的，平仓的时候就不能安全地退出来。你不能像在做小买卖一般自如，不能在想卖或者能卖的时候退出，而必须在市场有足够空间接纳你的卖出时再卖。只要错过时机，就要赔掉很多。要快刀斩乱麻，不可犹豫，否则就赔大了。你也不能把出货价拉高，这不是好办法，因为有可能会把买盘的力量减弱。另外，我还要说，想抓住机会并不容易，必须要行动迅速，在机会到你门口探头的时候，一定要抓住。

当然并不是每个人都知道我的运气来了。在包括华尔街在内的很多地方，任何让一个人赚大钱的意外事故都会令人起疑，可谁要是偶然赔光，人们就不会觉得是偶然，而会看作是欲望和自以为是的结果。一旦你突然赚了很多钱，人们就把你赚的钱看作是掠压来的财富，会说“厚颜无耻有好报，保守和正直没有好报”。

那些做空的人因为粗心而赔钱后陷入痛苦，骂我是在有计划地破坏市场，而其他的人也会这样想。

过了一两天，一个棉花交易市场上的世界级大佬遇到我，他说：“利文斯顿，这可是你玩得最聪明的一把。我那时候还想呢，你要是卖掉的话会赔多少。要知道当时市场没多少需求，市场是没有五六万包的容纳量的。你能够卖掉比这个数目多很多的棉花，而且没有赔掉一点点浮动利润，这其中的手法真让人拍案叫绝，真是没想到你有这么一手，厉害啊。”

“这与我无关。”我很诚恳。

可他却不断重复说：“兄弟，聪明啊，太厉害了，你不要谦虚。”

这件事情之后，很多报纸都把我称作“棉花之王”。但是就像我说过的，我根本配不上这个殊荣。不说你也能明白，美国人不可能富有到能买下《世界报》的栏目，也没有谁能牛到让报纸刊登那样的新闻。可是，《世界报》当时确实给我塑造了一个虚名。

但是，我告诉你这个故事，并不是想让偶尔强加在某些名不符实的交易者身上的头衔合理化，也不是为了说抓住机会有多么重要，不管这种机会在什么地方、以什么形式出现，而只是想说明，我做了7月棉花交易之后，数量大得惊人的报纸报道替我扬了名。如果没有那些报道，我是不可能有机会和著名的棉花奇才珀西·托马斯见面的。

第十二章

在那次出人意料地做完了7月棉花生意后，没过多久我就收到了一封信，珀西·托马斯想邀请我会面。我马上回复他说，非常愿意在办公室跟他约见，时间由他说了算。第二天，他就上门了。

我已经崇拜他很长时间了。只要在棉花种植和交易市场上，托马斯都是一块大招牌。在欧美地区，大家都对我引述过托马斯的观点。我记得在瑞士度假的时候，我和一个开罗的银行家聊过天，他与离世的内斯·特卡塞尔公爵一起在埃及种过棉花，当他知道我是从纽约来的人后，赶紧跟我打听珀西·托马斯的事情。托马斯的市场报告他期期必读。

我一向觉得托马斯做生意的方法很科学，是个货真价实的投机商，也是个很有眼界、非常勇敢的思想家，是个消息极为灵通的人，精通棉花交易市场的理论与实践。托马斯既爱听也爱表达观念、想法和抽象事物，对棉花交易商的心理也抓得很准，因为他已经做了多年的交易，是个大赚也大赔过的老手。

在他原来的谢尔顿·托马斯公司倒闭后，他把责任揽入自己怀中。不到两年时间，他就东山再起。我记得《太阳报》刊登过他的事迹。他先摆平了欠账，然后雇了一个专家，专门为他研究分析怎么去投资100万美元。那个专家经过分析和研究很多大公司的市场报告后，建议他买入德拉瓦·哈德森公司的股票。

赔过几百万，又赚了更多以后，托马斯还是在3月棉花交易中失去了一切。他跟我一见面就进入正题，提议我俩合伙来做。他得到的任何消息都会立刻转给我，然后才向大众发布。而我的主要工作就是实际去执行，他说我在这上面很有天赋，正好弥补了他的不足。

就算他说出一大堆条件来，我都不感兴趣。我很坦诚地对他说，我认为我没有办法跑双头马车，也不热衷学习这样做。可他就是认为我俩是最合适的合作伙伴，我最后只能直截了当地告诉他，我可不希望影响任何人的交易。

我对他说：“我如果赔了，自己来承担，也会坦然面对失败，没有什么其他烦闷的事情。我一个人做很自在，这是对我来说最明智最有效的方法。我在与其他交易者争斗时，从中获得乐趣。这些人我从来没有见过，没有说过话，也没有对他们提过该怎么去做生意的建议，我从来不期望会遇到他们或认识他们。我赚钱了，就会当作好的经验。我不违背我的经验，也不靠买卖与利用消息获利。我如果用违背意愿的办法赚钱，就会感觉像是没真正赚到钱一样。我对你的想法没什么兴趣，我只喜欢我自己的那一套游戏方式。”

他说，很遗憾听我这么说，并且会想办法让我知道，不跟他合作是个大错误。可我就是坚持我的观点。接下来我俩谈得倒是很轻松愉悦。我对他说，我就知道他一定能够东山再起，也表达了我愿意出钱帮他的意愿。但他却不想跟我借钱。最后他跟我打听有关7月棉花交易的情形，我全部告诉了他，怎么做的、做了多少、价格如何，还有其他的事情。我们又谈了一阵儿后，他离开了。

我原来说过，交易商有很多敌人，其中很多敌人能够成功地从内心攻击你。我也知道我出过很多问题。我知道，一个人可能有自己的观点，也会独立思考，却仍然可能败给能说会道的人。我相当能够避免一般投机的毛病，如贪婪、恐惧和希望。但身为大众的一员，我也有很多弱点在身。

此时我应该时刻警惕着才对，因为前不久我就遇到过一件事情，它说明人是很容易被轻易蛊惑去做有违自我判断和意愿的事情的。那是在哈丁兄弟公司的时候，我在那儿有个类似贵宾室的个人办公室，是他们为我提供的。在炒股的时候，没有我的同意，谁都不能打扰我。我不想让人打扰，是因为我做的是大生意，收益是很不错的，他们要对我严加保护。

有一天，在刚刚收市后，有人跟我打招呼：“下午好啊，利文斯顿先生。”

我转身看到了一个陌生人，大概35岁，我不知道他怎么进来的，可他确实出现在了我跟前。我想，他可能有跟我的业务有关的事情找我，所以才被允许进来的。我没说什么，只看着他。他马上就说：“我想跟你聊聊沃尔特·斯科特。”然后就不再开口了。

他是书市代理商人，他的态度不会让人感到特别愉快，而且也不是特别善于言辞，看来也不会特别有魅力。可是，他很有特点。他说话，我想我在听，但是我不知道他在说什么，我想我可能永远也不会知道。他滔滔不绝地说完后，就拿给了我一支钢笔和一张空白表格，我签了个名。那是一张协议书，用500美元买斯科特的一套书。

我签完名后才明白过来，他已经把协议书装在了衣服口袋。我不想买那套书，也没地方放书。那套书对我其实一点儿用处都没有，又没人可送。但我却同意花500美元买了它。

我对亏钱已经很习惯了，因此我在思考时，最先想的绝对不是错误的那一部分，我总是思考操作本身。我必须要先搞懂自己的思维习惯和局限性，其次我不该再犯同样的错误。生而为人，只有在一件错事上吸取教训，然后在出现同样的事情后，能够确证没有重蹈覆辙，这样才会完全谅解自己曾经的过错。

唉，我犯了一个500美元的错误，却找不到问题所在。我就盯着他看，首先要评量评量他。他也看着我，一脸笑容。他似乎知道我要做什么。我觉得根本没必要跟他解释什么了。我不说话他也知道我肯定要说话。所以我决定不去解释，也不能纠结刚才的事情，直接问他：“那500美元，你能有多少提成？”

他摇着头说：“对不起，我不能那样。”

“你能赚多少？”我继续问。

“三分之一，可我不能那样。”他回道。

“500美元，三分之一是166.66美元，如果你把刚才那份协议还给我，我给你200美元现金。”为了让他相信，我从口袋掏出了200美元。

“我说了不能这样做。”他说。

“你所有的客户都给你同样的条件吗？”我问。

“不是。”他说。

“那你怎么会知道我会提出这个条件？”

“这就是你们这类人的做事风格了。你是个优秀的输家，这一点使你成为一个顶尖的商人。我很感谢你，可我不能那样做。”

“那你为什么不想挣比你的提成更多的钱呢？”

“这不是挣不挣提成的事。”他说，“我不是为了那点提成工作的。”

“那是为什么？”

“为了提成和纪录。”他回答。

“什么纪录？”

“我的纪录。”

“你的意思是什么？”

“你光是为了赚钱才工作吗？”他问我。

“是啊。”我说。

“不是吧。”他摇着头，“不会的，你不光是为了钱，如果真是那样，你不会有那么大乐趣。你工作一定不光是为了让自己银行存折上的数字增加。你到华尔街，不是因为你喜欢赚轻松的钱。你能从其他方面获得乐趣，我也是这样。”

我不跟他争辩，只是问：“你怎样获得乐趣？”

“唉，我们都有缺点。”他很坦诚。

“你的缺点是什么？”

“虚荣心。”他说。

“对啊，你完成让我签字的工作了。”我对他说，“现在，我想把签字收回，而且为你的这十分钟支付200美元，这能对你的尊严给予补偿吗？”

“不能。”他说，“你清楚，很多人在华尔街忙上几个月，最后却一分钱没挣到。他们会觉得这是商品和这个地方的原因，所以公司找我来，只是证明他们的推销方法不对，而与卖的书和这个地方没关系。他们的提成是百分之二十五。我在克利夫兰，两周就卖掉了82套。我到这里来不光是为了把书卖给从不从代理商手里买书的人，也是要把书推销给他们根本见不着面的人。这就是我能拿到三分之一提成的原因。”

“我都不知道你是怎么把书卖给我的。”

“哦。”他安慰道，“我还卖给摩根先生一套呢。”

“哈，不可能。”

他没生气，只是说道：“真的，我给他推销了一套。”

“把一套沃尔特的书卖给摩根？他不但拥有一些最精美的版本，很可能连一些小说的手稿都收藏着。”

“看吧，这是他的签名。”他把一张摩根的签名协议在我眼前晃了一下。或许那不是摩根本人的签名，不过当时我并没有怀疑。他袋子里不还有我的签名协议书吗？我就是很好奇，所以我问：“门卫为什么没拦你？”

“我没看到门卫。我在办公室见到了他本人。”

“算了吧你。”我说。谁都知道要想空手进到摩根的私人办公室，比拿着一个像闹钟一样嘀嗒作响的包裹走进白宫都艰难。

可他却说：“我进去了。”

“你怎么进去的？”

“我怎么进到你办公室的？”他问我。

“不清楚，你告诉我吧。”我说。

“嗯，我进摩根办公室的方法跟到你这里来的方法是一样的。我只是跟门口负责阻挡我的朋友聊了聊，我让摩根签字的方法也跟让你签字的方法一样。你刚刚不是签个买书的协议，只是接了我给你的笔，做了我说的事情。摩根也一样签了字。”

“真的是摩根本人签的？”三分钟后，我怀疑地问。

“当然。他还是小孩子的时候就知道怎么签字了。”

“那就是真的了？”

“是啊。”他说，“我知道自己在做什么。这就是其中的秘密。很感谢你，再见吧，利文斯顿先生。”他准备朝外走。

“请留步。”我说，“我一定要让你公平地挣到我的200美元。”我给了他35美元。

他摇头说：“不，我不能那样。但是我可以这样……”接着他从口袋中拿出协议，撕碎了，然后递给我。

我掏了200美元给他，但他仍然摇了摇头。

“这不是你想要的吗？”我问。

“不是。”

“那你撕了协议书干吗？”

“因为你没对这件事发脾气，还感同身受地理解并接受这件事。”

“但这200美元是我想给你的。”我说。

“我明白，但是钱不是一切。”

他说的话感动了我，我说：“没错，钱不能解决大问题。那我能为你做点什么？”

“你心思很敏捷，是吧？”他说，“你真的想帮我忙吗？”

“是的。”我对他说，“我要帮你一下，不过这得看你想得到什么样的帮助。”

“带我去哈丁先生的办公室，告诉他我要跟他聊三分钟。让我跟他单聊。”

我无可奈何地摇头说：“他是我的好朋友呀。”

“他都50岁了，而且也是证券交易商吧。”他说。

这倒没错，所以我只好把他带去见哈丁。从此以后，我再没听到过那人的消息。过了几周后，一个晚上，我去城里，在第六大街L线火车上碰到了他。他摘掉帽子冲我致意，我也回了礼。他走过来问我：“利文斯顿先生你好，哈丁先生好吗？”

“他很好啊，你为什么这样问？”我觉得他隐瞒了什么。

“上次你带我去见他时，我向他卖了价值2000美元的书。”

“他没对我说过。”我说。

“是啊，他那样的人怎么会说这样的事。”

“哪样的人？”

“就是那些因为犯错不好而从来不犯错的人。他们非常明白自己想要的是什么，别人说什么都白说，就是这样的人能替我的孩子出教育费，让我的太太心情愉快。利文斯顿先生，你帮了我一个大忙。当你急着给我200美元的时候，我就预测到这样的事情出现了。”

“那哈丁要是不买你的书呢？”

“嗯，我有把握，我早了解他是什么样的人。没什么问题。”

“没错。但万一他不买呢？”我固执地问。

“我就会再到你跟前，向你卖。再见，利文斯顿先生，我要去跟市长见面。”火车在公园站停下了，他起身说道。

“希望你能向他卖十套。”我说，“市长大人是民主党人。”

“我也是共和党人。”说着，他悠闲地下车，一副自信车会等着他的样子，而实际上的确是这样。

这么详细告诉你这件事的原因，是它关联到了一个重要的人，这人致使我买了不该买的东西，他是第一个让我做了不愿意做的事情的人，应该不会出现第二个这样的人才对。但是，真的有第二个。不要觉得世界上最伟大的推销员就那么一个，也不要觉得自己一定能完全免于个性的干扰。

我礼貌又坚决地拒绝了托马斯的建议，当天他离开后，我敢发誓说：我一定不会跟他一起干，我不能肯定是否还会与他见面了。可就在第二天，他寄给我一封信，对我主动提出帮他表示了感谢，还邀请我去他那里。我回信说，我会去找他。他又回信了，于是我就去拜访他。

我逐渐跟他时常会面，听他说话其乐无穷。他见识广泛，说话有趣，我觉得他是我认识的所有人里最有魅力的一个。

他博览群书，对很多事情有惊人的理解力，而且拥有天分，能够很有趣地归纳出来，所以我们海阔天空地聊着天。他灵活机智，又不油嘴滑舌，给我留下了深刻的印象。以前有很多人说他各种不好，还说他很虚伪，但我有时候想，他这么会说话，是不是因为他先说服了自己，因此能够大大增加说服别人的力量。

我们详细聊了市场交易的事情，我并不看好棉花，他却与我相反。我完全看不出有什么利多的一面，他却看多，还举了很多例子和数据，似乎百分百正确，但我仍然没有听他的。我没有说那些例子和数据不可靠，可也不能不信任自己研判得到的信念。他一直鼓吹自己的观点，直到我不再相信商报和其他报纸上的信息了，这也就是说，我不能再用自己的双眼来看市场。你不能说服一个人违背自己的信念，但可以游说他进入一种犹疑不定、优柔寡断的状态，那就更不好了，这会让人在做交易时没了自信和乐趣。

我并不是说我完全糊涂了，可我不能很好地把控自己了。确切地说，我失去了独立思考的立场。我没法细致地讲出来，是怎么逐渐进入到这种后来证明代价极为昂贵的心理状态中去的。我觉得是他对那些精确数据的自信让我最终有了那样的结局，这些数字完全归他独有，加上我的数字不可靠，不是归我独有，而是公共财产。他不断地说着自己在南边有多少可靠的消息提供者，我最后用他的那些思路分析了一下情势，就像我和他读着同一本书同一页的内容，而这本书在他手中拿着。他的思路非常明晰，我只要接受了前面的事实，后面获得的结论也就跟他一样了。

一开始，他跟我聊棉花市场时，我是不看好的，而且也做了空头。后来我听了他说的那些证据，就觉得自己之前的做法所依据的信息是不正确的。一旦托马斯使我认识到自己是错的，我补上空头后就一定得做多。我是这样考虑的，你清楚，我一辈子除了股票和期货之外，没做过什么。我理所当然地觉得，如果做空是不对的，那就应该做多。如果做多是对的，就一定要买进，就像我棕榈滩的老友提到过，希恩也喜欢说的：“你行动以后才会明白。”我必须证明我对市场的判断是否正确，证据会在经纪人月底送给我的交易清单上看到。

我开始买进棉花，很快就到了平时操作的数量，大概6万包。这是我的买卖历史上最没脑子的决定，没有靠自己的观察与分析，光陪着别人玩游戏。我的愚蠢操作不应该就此结束，也就势所必然了。我不在形势好的时候买，也没根据经验积攒头寸，这个做法就是错的。你看吧，因为听别人的话，我赔了。

市场跟我的做法没有走到一起。当我明白了自己的处境时，没有害怕也没有着急。如果托马斯是对的，市场就不应该那样发展。第一步错了，后面我又跟着出错，事情搞得一塌糊涂。我被别人的话蛊惑着没有罢手。这是与我的风格不相符的做法，跟我的行事规则不合拍。就算我在对赌行的时候，也没现在糊涂。可是，我就这么糊里糊涂地像变了个人，被托马斯洗脑了。

我不光多头做了棉花，还买了很多小麦。小麦倒是很好，浮动利润挺不错。我愚蠢地想保住棉花市场，把头寸加到15万包。应该说，我当时预感并不怎么样，这么说不是为自己的愚蠢找借口，而只是想说清事实。我记得之后我就到海滩放松了一阵子。

在海滩度假期间，我回顾思索了很多事情。我觉得，我在交易上的数量太大了。通常而言，我不会害怕，但是我变得有些紧张，所以决定减减压。因此，我想要卖出些棉花或者小麦。

看起来很离奇的是，像我这么熟悉这种游戏的人，又有12到14年的经验，可却把事情整得乱七八糟。棉花让我亏损，我却留着棉花，小麦有了利润，我却卖掉了它，简直就是愚蠢之极。不过还能有点心理安慰的是，这并不是我自己的交易方法，而是托马斯的。在所有的错误当中，没有几个比设法摊平亏损的操作更愚蠢的了。后来的棉花交易正好验证了这点。卖掉已经有了损失的头寸，而留下能够赚钱的头寸，这才是明智之举，可到现在我还非常吃惊，对我来说非常熟悉的事情，我当时怎么会反过来做呢。

就这样，我卖掉了小麦，刻意缩减我在小麦中的利润，然后小麦价格每蒲式耳上涨了20美分，我要是没有卖掉的话，会赚800万的。紧接着，因为决定要坚守亏钱的头寸，我竟然又买了很多棉花。

直到现在，我还很清晰地记得，当时是怎样一天天地买棉花，越来越多。为什么这么做？是为了不让价格跌落。如果这样不是超级傻瓜的做法，还有哪一种才是！我源源不断地拿着钱往进买，结果却赔得越来越多。我的经纪人和朋友们都觉得莫名其妙，到现在他们仍然如坠雾里。如果这笔交易结果不同的话，我一定会变成奇才。

大家都好多次地提醒过我，不要那么信任托马斯的分析。可我就是听不进去，只管买棉花，不让价格下跌，而且我还跑到了利物浦去买。当我明白自己的所作所为时，已经积累了44万包的棉花，可是已经没办法了，只能全部再卖掉。

我基本上赔尽了在股票和期货市场上赚的所有钱，虽然还没到破产的地步，可是在遇到那个自以为很聪明的托马斯之前，我可是身缠几百万的富豪，可如今只剩区区几十万了。像我这样的人，居然违背经验教导我的所有成功法则，用愚蠢已经不足以形容了。

这件事让我明白自己可能没有任何理由就做出愚蠢的操作，我花了几百万，明白了这个道理。作为一个商人，有个很危险的敌人，当一个很有蛊惑力的人怂恿他时，他会被别人的魅力打动。可是，我始终觉得，如果用100万就可以买到教训，那又为什么花更多的钱呢？命运女神不会让你自己决定学费的。她严厉地教导你，然后把账单奉上，她清楚你一定会照单全付。知道我可能会做多么愚蠢的事情后，我结束了这件意外，托马斯消失在了我的交际圈内。

我的情形就是这样，九成的本钱赔了进去。当了还没一年的百万富翁，那些靠聪明和运气赚来的资本，因为操作程序搞反而打了水漂。我卖了自己的那两艘游艇，过着艰苦朴素的日子。

万万没想到，福无双至祸不单行，真是运气差极了。我突然病倒了，需要20万美元现金。要是几个月前，这点小钱算不了什么，可现在我已经赔光了那些钱。我非常需要这笔钱，可怎么办呢？去哪里找钱？我不想从保证金里取出钱来，因为那样的话就没本钱继续在市场上交易了，而且要想赚回老本，就得留些钱投资。我觉得毫无办法了，只好去股市得到这笔钱。

你想啊，那有多难。你要是了解股市交易厅的那些人，就会明白我说的话。指望股市为你付账单是华尔街大多数人赔本的原因之一。如果你顽固行事，就会失去所有。

确实如此，有一年的冬天，在哈丁先生的办公室，几个抱负不小的人花三四万买一件大衣，可谁也没机会穿上。

事情是这样的：有一个后来因为只象征性地领取一美元年薪而成名的场内交易人，穿了一件海獭皮外衣来交易所。那时候的皮货不太贵，那件皮衣顶多只值1万美元。哈丁办公室有个叫鲍勃·凯安的人，想买一件镶有俄国黑貂皮边的大衣。他去打听了价格，差不多也是1万美元。

“这太贵了，这么多钱。”有人反对他买。

“价格还可以，还行吧。”凯安愉悦地说，“大概一周的薪资足矣——除非你们有人答应凑这些钱，对办公室最好的一个人表达一下敬重之意。有人要发表赠礼演说吗？没有？好吧，那就让市场替我付账。”

“为什么买这个？”哈丁问他。

“皮大衣特别适合我这种身份的人啊。”凯安挺着腰杆一脸认真地说。

“你准备怎么付账？”最喜欢追逐内幕消息的吉姆·墨菲问。

“要靠一个短期的投资，这就是方法。”凯安说，他明白墨菲只想知道明牌。

吉姆又问：“你要买哪只股票呢？”

“不是，朋友。现在不是买进的时候，我打算放空5000股的钢铁股票。它最少会降低10个点的，我只要2.5个点就好了。是不是很谨慎？”

“你知道什么消息？”墨菲急着问。他又瘦又高，黑色头发，面黄肌瘦，总怕会漏掉市场信息，所以没出去吃过午饭。

“大衣是我想要的东西里最合适我的。”鲍勃·凯安对哈丁说，“哈丁，卖掉5000股钢铁公司的股票吧，就今天。”

凯安是个豪赌分子，喜欢开玩笑，这是他让别人知道他意志坚定的方式。他放空了5000钢铁股后，股价马上就涨了。他夸口时看起来傻乎乎的，其实挺聪明的，股票涨了1.5个点的时候，他赶紧回补止损，然后对公司人说，纽约天气不冷，不适合穿皮衣，皮衣也不利于健康，还有炫富的迹象。这些话引得人们讥笑，可是没多久，有同事买了太平洋铁路的股票，也想赚点买皮衣的钱，结果却亏了1.8万，他就说：皮大衣非常适合女士穿在外面，一个谦虚恭敬的男士当成内衣穿在里面就有点不太适宜了。

之后，他们一个挨一个想通过股市买件皮外套。有一天，我说：我去买了，省得公司破产。可大家都说这样做很不光彩，如果想买就利用股市。不过，哈丁先生很支持我，那天下午，我去皮货店去买这件衣服，得知有个芝加哥商人一周前就把它买走了。

这只是个例子。在华尔街有很多人想通过股市赚到买汽车、首饰、游艇、名画的钱，却最终赔了本。那些被市场拒绝支付的礼物钱，都能建起一座大医院了。事实上，华尔街所有的扫把星当中，我认为想说服市场担任乐善好施的小仙女这种想法是最忙碌又最常见的扫把星。

像所有千真万确的扫把星一样，这个扫把星有它存在的道理。一个人要想从市场上赚到他想要的东西，怎么办？他就会成为大赌客，承担比他冷静研究基本形势，得到合理的信念和意见，再据以聪明地投机时更大的风险。他从一开始就想一口气吃成个胖子，根本不想等。即使市场对他有利，也必须马上体现出来。他自以为是地觉得是下了一个机会均等的赌注。因为他做了速战速决的准备，比如当他只想赚2点时，用2点的跌幅止损，他抱持着错误的观点，认为自己只是赌一种成败各半的机会。我见过这样想法的人赔了成千上万的资本，特别是在多头市场的高峰，市场正要小幅回调的时候买进的人。这根本不是正确的赚钱方式。

唉，在我的从商生涯中，那个巨大的错误对我的打击太大，它击垮了我，我赔掉了在棉花市场赚的钱。它猛烈地打击我，我屡战却屡败。当时我一直想着，市场最后必定会让我赚到钱，可结果我却赔了夫人又折兵。我变成了一个负债累累的家伙，不光欠了主要的几个经纪人的钱，也欠了其他公司的钱。他们当时让我做交易，连保证金都不需要缴纳。如今我欠了一大屁股债，而且从此债务缠身。

第十三章

看，我再次破产了，真是糟糕，而更糟糕的是我的交易绝对错误，这让我忧心不已，紧张焦灼，烦躁得要命，没办法静下心来推理。这就意味着我的心智状态处在了一个交易商不该出现的状态之中。

我觉得什么都出问题了。我甚至觉得没办法再恢复已经丧失的判断能力了。因为我擅长大交易，例如操作10万股的股票，所以我怕看不准小买卖。如果你只交易100股，判断正确好像没太大价值。在习惯了搞大操作，并且赚大钱以后，我就不知道小额的交易什么时候才能获得利润了。真是没办法讲述我是多么力不从心了。

再一次赔了血本，这让我没有了重新发起攻击的精力。判断失误，又欠了这么多债务。

成功了这么些年，经历了那么多为了成功而付出的代价之后，如今我的状态简直比当年在对赌行的时候还要差劲。我虽然对炒股已经了然于胸，可我对人性的弱点还了解得不透彻。没有一个人的脑袋会像机器一般，什么情况下都能高效运转。我意识到了自己也会受到影响，来自别人和我个人的不幸的影响。

赔了钱不会让我这么烦恼，可其他方面的麻烦就不同了，它们必定让我焦灼不堪。我详细地研究分析了自己的境况，很容易就知道了自己哪里出了毛病。我知道了错在哪里，什么时候出错了。谁要是想在炒股过程中表现优异，就要对自己完全了解才行。知道我可能处在愚蠢的行列中，则是一个长久的教育过程。

我有时候会想，炒股的人们为了弄明白如何让自己不自大，付出再高的代价都是值得的。很多明智的人破产，都是因为自大，自大是一种在任何地方对任何人来说都是代价昂贵的疾病。而对于一个在华尔街玩股票的人，尤为严重。

因为我有那种感觉，我在纽约并不开心。我状态不好，一点儿都不想交易。我决定离开这里，去其他地方挣钱。我觉得换一下环境，也许能够帮助我找回正常状态。所以，在投机游戏中失败后，我再次离开纽约。我的境况比破产还要惨，我欠着好几家公司超过十万美元的债。

我到了芝加哥，在那里找了一笔钱，不是很多，这表示要给我比较多的时间，我才能够赚到赔掉的那些钱。我原来打过交道的一家公司相信我之前炒股的本事，他们同意我在他们那里小小地玩一玩。

我开始谨小慎微地行动了。我不清楚如果一直在那儿，会怎么样发展，因为我在经历一件非比寻常的事情没多久后就结束了在芝加哥的短暂停留。那真是件让人没办法相信的事情啊。

有一天，我收到了一封电报，是卢修斯·塔克发来的。我与他很早就认识，当时他在一家股票交易公司做经理，我有时候与他们有业务往来，不过早就没有联系了。他发的电报内容是，快来纽约。

我明白他从我朋友那里知道了我的境况，所以一定有事找我商量。但我根本就没钱去做一次没有必要的纽约之行，所以我没照他说的去做，而是打电话给他。

“你的电报我收到了。”我说，“有什么事情啊？”

“纽约有个大银行家想见你。”他说。

“谁？”我问。

“你来纽约详谈吧，一下子说不明白。”

“你的意思是他要见我？”

“是啊。”

“到底什么事？”

“你要是来了，他会亲自跟你讲。”卢修斯说。

“你写信给我不行吗？”

“不行。”

“那你透露点消息给我。”我提了一下请求。

“我不愿说。”

“那好吧，卢修斯。”我说，“那你直说，这一趟会不会让我白跑。”

“当然不会！来吧，好处多着呢。”

“透露一点儿风啊。”

“那可不能。”他说，“这对他不公平，况且我不知道他能帮你多少。不过你记住我说的话，必须要快些来纽约。”

“你确定他要见我？”

“就是你，不是其他人。我跟你讲，你赶紧来。把你要坐的火车告诉我，我去车站接你。”

“好吧。”我说完就挂了电话。

我不喜欢这么神神道道的，但我知道卢修斯人很好，他这样对我说必定有他的道理。我的芝加哥之行不算顺利，所以离开时并没有失落。如此下去，谁知道要到什么时候才能赚到足够的资金，像以前一样玩股票呢。

我再次回到纽约，不知道会发生什么事。真的，在去的路上，我不止一次担心什么事情都没有，我会浪费了车费，浪费了时间。谁知道我一生中最奇异的事情就这样拉开了帷幕。

在车站，卢修斯接到了我，然后他马上对我说，是非常著名的威廉森—布朗证券公司的丹尼尔·威廉森要见我。威廉森让卢修斯对我说，他为我做了一个交易方案，而且认为我一定会同意的，因为这能为我赚取大量的资金。卢修斯重申说，他对这个方案一点儿都不清楚。这个公司用信誉担保，没有什么特别的条件。

威廉森是这个公司的大股东。在19世纪70年代的时候，艾伯特·威廉森创立了这家公司。公司里没有一位叫布朗的合伙人，而且很多年来也没有一个这样的人。这家公司在丹尼尔老爹经营的时候名气很大，后来丹尼尔也继承了一大笔财产，就没再去做其他生意。公司有个以一抵百的客户，这个人就是威廉森的姐夫埃文·玛卡。这个人是十多家银行和信托公司的董事，而且也是奇萨比克大西洋铁路公司总裁。自詹姆斯·希尔之后，他是铁路领域里最牛的人物，也是实力雄厚的福特·道森帮派的发言人，是个重要角色。他个人有5000万到5亿美元资产，这估计是人们私下议论的。他死了以后，人们发现他的财产有2.5亿，都是从华尔街赚的。看，这是个大客户吧。

卢修斯对我说，他刚从威廉森的公司找了份工作，很适合他。他做的是在巡回中找业务的工作。公司在拓展代理业务，卢修斯建议威廉森开两个分公司，一个设在城中心的一家酒店里，一个设在芝加哥。我觉得他们可能想把后面这个分公司交给我经营——分公司经理，我可不干这个。我当时没有责怪卢修斯，心想等他们说了以后再推也行。

我跟着卢修斯到了威廉森的办公室，他介绍了我以后就出去了，好像不想见证他认识的两个人之间的交易。我想先听威廉森怎么说，然后再拒绝。

威廉森是个真正的绅士，让人如沐春风。他举止稳妥，一脸笑容，是个善于交际的人物，朋友肯定很多。他身体强壮，脾气又好，给人的印象特别好。而且他有那么多钱，别人也不会怀疑他图谋不轨。再加上他所受的教育和丰富的阅历，让他看起来礼貌而友好，还善于资助别人。

我沉默着，也没什么话要说，而且我一向就是先让别人说够，才开口说话的人。有人说过，当时的国家城市银行总裁詹姆斯·史迪曼——对了，他是威廉森的好友——有个习惯，就是会先毫无表情地听别人说话，等这个人说完后，史迪曼先生会继续看着他，依然不开口，就像这个人还没说完，因此这个人就觉得应该继续说。就这样，史迪曼光靠着凝视和倾听，经常使这个人提出比他开口时准备提出的还要优惠许多的条件来。

我不说话不是想引诱别人提出更好的条件，而是想把事情了解得更通透。听人说完了所有的话，你就可以立刻做决定，这是不浪费时间的做法，能够避免争吵，还省得讨论停不下来。就我参与的商业建议来说，基本上所有对我提出的与市场交易相关的建议，都在肯定或否定的结论中得以稳妥解决。我自己不了解全貌的话，是没法马上下结论的。

威廉森一直在说，我默默听着。他说他很早就知道我在股市上的一些传闻，也对我扬短避长地去做棉花期货的事情感到遗憾，同时也因为我赔本了，他才能够跟我见到面而感到幸运。他觉得我在炒股上的水平很高，是个天生的大玩家，不该离开股市。

“利文斯顿先生，这是我们想跟你合作的原因。”最后，他开心地说。

“怎么合作呢？”我问。

“你做经纪人。”他说，“我们公司希望接你的股票单子。”

“我倒愿意把单子交给你们。”我说，“可是不成啊。”

“为什么呢？”他问。

“我没钱。”我说道。

“这没有问题。”他笑着，“我给你钱。”他马上拿出一个支票本，开了一张2.5万美元的支票给我。

“这是？”我问道。

“存到你的账户里，你可以随时用。我希望你在我们公司做，我不在乎你是亏还是赚。如果这些钱损失殆尽了，我会再给你。所以，你不用太在意它。不知你听明白了没有？”

我知道他们公司很有实力，钱多得很，根本不需要任何人的业务，也用不着出钱给人当保证金。但威廉森却这么好心，给我的不是信用卡，而是现金，因此，只有他自己知道钱从哪里来。他唯一的条件是，如果我做交易的话，得通过他们公司成交，甚至还承诺在我赔钱后会继续出钱。这其中肯定是有原因的。

“到底什么意思？”我问。

“很简单，我们公司非常需要你这样的客户，大手笔的交易商。谁都知道你擅长大手笔地做空头，这是我喜欢你的地方。你是个大笔炒作的高手。”

“我还是不懂。”我说。

“利文斯顿先生，我明说了吧。我们有两三个非常富有的大客户，他们的股票玩得很大。我不想让华尔街人觉得，我们每次卖掉一两万股股票，都是他们在卖出做多的股票。要是你在这里，华尔街就不知道到底是你在做空，还是其他顾客把做多的股票卖到市场上。”

我终于明白了原委，他是要用我的名气来掩护他姐夫的操作。恰好一年半之前，我在空头上狠狠赚了一把。所以股价跌落的时候，华尔街那些爱嚼舌根子的人和愚不可及的造谣者们，就会理所当然地把责任归咎于我。一直到今天，股市行情不好的时候，我都被认为是罪魁祸首。

我用不着考虑，就能看出威廉森给我提供了一个快速上位的良机。我拿了支票，存到了银行，用他的公司开了账户，就开始行动了。市场行情非常好，很活跃，波动的范围很大，不用只盯着一两只特殊股。我说过，原本怕自己已经不会玩了，此时看来一点儿都没有。仅仅用了三周时间，我就用威廉森的2.5万美元赚了11.2万美元。

我找到威廉森说：“我把那2.5万还给你。”

“不用还。”他说着，挥手让我走，好像我给他递了一杯蓖麻油鸡尾酒一般，“不用，小兄弟，等你赚了大钱再说吧。别老记着这事儿了，你这才刚刚开始啊。”

我犯了个大错误，比在华尔街犯的其他错更让我后悔。多年来，这个错误让我很消沉很痛苦。我应该坚持把钱还给他。我正向着赚比亏损的钱还多的财富迈进，而且步伐很快。曾有三周，我的平均利润每周能有百分之一百五。自那以后，我开始稳当前行。可因为感激威廉森，我听他的，也没给他还那2.5万美元。当然，他没接受借给我的钱，我就觉得拿自己的利润不太好。我很感谢他，可是我天生不喜欢欠别人钱和人情。金钱的债务我可以用钱偿还，而人情和好心我也必须得用同样的东西去还。你很容易就看得出来，这些道德良心账常常是无法估价的，而且根本没有止境。

我又开始交易，而那些钱我放着没动。交易进行得很顺利。我觉得用不了多长时间，我就能恢复到1907年时候那样爽快的状态。要是恢复后，我需要做的就是先稳一下，不光是找回损失那么简单。赚或者赔，我都不太重视。令人开心的是我正在摆脱那种犯错的习惯，摆脱身不由己的习惯。几个月以来，这种习惯困扰着我，但是我已经吸取了教训。

就在此时，我放空了几只铁路公司的股票，包括奇萨比克大西洋铁路公司。我觉得就该做空，所以卖了8000股。

一天早上，我到市区去了，在市场开盘前，威廉森让我去他办公室。他对我说：“拉里，暂时不要动奇萨比克大西洋铁路公司的股票了。你放空8000股的操作真是太差劲了。今早我在伦敦给你平了仓，改成多头了。”

我确定奇萨比克大西洋铁路会下跌，行情记录说得很清楚。此外，我对整个市场都看空，但是看空的程度足以让我适量放空，并且觉得安全。我说：“你为什么要这样做？我看空整个市场，所有的股票都会下跌。”

可他只是摇头说：“我这么做，是因为我刚得知了一些你不知道的情况。我建议你，等我对你说可以放空了你再放空吧。”

我又能说什么？这不是的愚蠢的小道消息，是董事长姐夫的建议。威廉森不光是埃文·玛卡的老朋友，对我也是友好大方的。他信任我，也相信我说的话，我应该感激他才对，我不能造次。所以，我的情感又压倒了理智，我退步了。让我的判断臣服在他的意愿之下，正是我毁灭的开始。虽然感恩是一个有修养的人该具备的素质，可也不该用来绑架人。所以，我不光赔了利润，而且又欠了公司15万美元的债。我觉得很气恼，可是威廉森劝我不要担心。

“我会帮你过这个坎儿的。”他向我许诺，“我会这样做。不过，你得允许我这么做才行。你要停止自作主张地交易。我不能为你效劳，还允许你破坏了我之前对你的付出。你现在不要管市场的事情了，把为你赚钱的机会让给我吧。可不可以，拉里？”

我再问你，我能怎么办呢？我想着他的好，又不能做忘恩负义的事。我觉得这个人真不错，他很有风度，对人也很友善。我记得从他这里得到的，只有鼓励的言辞，他帮我建立了一切都会变好的信心。大约过了六个月，有一天他笑呵呵地来找我，给了我几张支票。

“我说过要帮你解决问题。”他说，“我现在实现了诺言。”然后我知道了，他不光消除了我的所有欠债，还送了我一笔小小的资金。

我觉得我会很轻而易举地赚到这些钱，因为市场行情很好，可他却说：“我替你买了南大西洋的1万股。”这是他姐夫埃文·玛卡控制的一条铁路，他也把控着这只股票的市场命运。

当有人像威廉森帮我一样帮你时，你能做的就是说句感谢的话，不管你怎么看待市场行情。你觉得自己是对的，可就像凯恩经常说的那句话：“你要下注后，才会知道结果。”威廉森就是用他自己的钱为我下了注。

好吧，南太平洋股票下跌了，一直处于低价位状态，我亏了钱，记不起亏了多少。威廉森为我卖掉了那1万股，我欠他的债更多了。但是，你这一生没见过一点儿都不令人烦恼和讨厌的债主吧，他一点儿都没有怨言，而且还努力说了些劝慰和鼓励我的话。最后，又是他慷慨地用神秘的方式为我结清了欠款。

他没告诉我其中的细节，全部都只是写在账本上的数字。威廉森对我说：“我用其他方面赚到的钱，给你补上了这笔亏损。”他还讲了怎样抛售了7500股其他的股票，并且赚了不少。老实说，在我得知所有债务都消除之前，我对自己之前的所有交易的细节都不太清楚。此事过后，我仔细想过几次，必须要从不同的角度来思考这件事，我也终究明白了里面的门道。显然，我是被威廉森长久利用的人，想到这一点，我就气不打一处来，更让我崩溃的是，我居然这么晚才明白。我仔细回忆了事情的经过，就去找威廉森了。我对他说，我和他公司之间已经没了情分，然后头也不回地离开了威廉森的公司。我没有说威廉森和他合伙人的任何坏话，就算说了又能起什么作用。可我也得承认，我对自己的气恼跟对威廉森—布朗公司的一样多。

我并不会因为赔本而生气，每次在股市赔本后，我都会从经历中学到一些东西。赔了些钱，从中吸取了教训，所以赔的钱就是应该付出的学费，要想获取经验，就需要付出一定的代价。可是在威廉森的公司，我获得的那些经验里有某种东西深深伤害了我，那就是失去了非常好的机会。赔钱了可以再赚，可像我遇到的那种机会，并不是随时都会有的。

你知道的，那时候的股市行情非常好。我对股市行情的分析也很正确，抓住机会就可以赚取几百万啊。可我让感恩之情压制了自己的步伐，束缚住了自己，只能做那些威廉森很和善地吩咐我做的事情。反正，这样的事情比跟亲戚一起做生意还让人心伤。

这还不算最糟糕的事情。最糟糕的是，从那以后，我其实已经完全失去了大赚的机会。市场崩溃了，行情一日不如一日。我不光丧失了手里的钱，还又让自己成了一个很大的债务人，比以前更严重。那几年是非常差劲的——从1911年到1914年。没有钱可以赚，也没有机会，导致我的生活比过去要糟糕很多。

如果把生意赔本与对以往不如意事情的悔恨掺和在一起，就会非常不痛快，这就是为什么我一直无法摆脱，这让我内心颇感焦灼。我明白，作为股票交易商，能暴露出来的缺点数量是没法计算的。于我而言，按照常人思维，在威廉森公司那样去交易是很正确的，可身为交易商，任由与自己的意愿不相符合的观点影响，既不正确又不明智。受恩不忘报的想法不该在炒股时出现，因为股市行情并没有骑士精神，也不奖励忠诚。我发现在当时没有自行决定的可能，我没有改变自己，仅仅因为我想继续在股市中交易。可是，事业就是事业，我就应该按照股票交易商的原则，坚持自己的判断。

这是一段奇特的过往。我会对你说这其中的门门道道。威廉森首次跟我见面时，说的话很诚恳。当他的公司买卖了几千股的任何一只股票时，华尔街上的人很快就会断定是埃文·玛卡在买进或卖出。他可是公司的大作手，只在这一家公司炒股，也是华尔街历史上很厉害又实力非凡的作手。唉，我被当作执行掩护任务的士兵一样使用，为埃文·玛卡的卖出做掩护。

我加入这家公司后没多久，埃文·玛卡就生病了，他很久之前就被下了死亡通知书。威廉森在埃文·玛卡自己知道这事之前就知道。这也是他为什么要买进我放空的那些股票的原因。他做的是把他姐夫手里的股票全部变成现金的勾当。

埃文·玛卡死后，财产管理人当然把他的投机和半投机股票全部卖掉。而到了那个时候，早已经是熊市了。威廉森设法照他那种样子控制着我，对玛卡的财产大有帮助。我说自己经验丰富，对股市的研究很正确，这并非吹牛。我在1907年成功做空的那件事情，我知道威廉森非常清楚。他不能冒着风险让我自由自在去做，原因何在？如果让我自由发挥，我会赚很多的钱，等他要把埃文·玛卡的个人资产变成现金的时候，我已经卖掉几十万股了。我是个活跃的空头行家，那将会给埃文·玛卡的继承人造成莫大的损失，因为他只留下2亿多资产。

他们让我欠账，再替我抹清债务，这比让我在其他地方猛烈地做空付出的代价要小很多。努力放空正是我应该要做的事情，如果不是因为威廉森的情面问题，我必定会努力放空。

我始终觉得，这是我身为股市作手的所有经验中最有趣却也最不幸的。我付出了莫大的代价，受到了很大的教训，延后我东山再起的时间很多年。我还年轻，有耐心去赚曾经赔掉的钱，但穷困五年时间可是很长的时间。不管年轻还是年老的人，都不喜欢穷困。生活中没有游艇，比没有市场交易要容易过。一辈子最好的机会就放在我的眼前，可是我却没有抓牢，而且我根本就不能伸手去抓。威廉森真是老奸巨猾，他狡猾老练，有眼光，聪明睿智，有胆量。他简直是个思想家，想象力丰富，能够抓住别人的弱点，毫不含糊地利用他。他自己预估情势，迅捷找到应对措施，让我在市场中变得丝毫没有抵抗力。他其实没有骗我半毛钱，相反的是，在钱上面，他表面上对我非常慷慨。他爱他的姐姐玛卡夫人，也尽到了身为兄弟的责任。

第十四章

离开威廉森的公司后，我一直心怀不满，它让我浪费了最好的交易时段。我经历了四年无钱可赚的漫长时段，没有一点儿收入，一分钱都没赚到。就像比尔·亨利奎兹说过的一句话：“市场冷淡得连臭鼬都没了味道。”

我感觉好像命中注定应该受困，可能这是上天的旨意吧，上天在历练我。说实话，我还没有自大到非得通过教训来惩罚自己的地步。在炒股经历中，我从没犯过一般傻瓜操作上的错误。我做的事情，或者说就是我没做的事情，是该在纽约金融区受表扬而非受谴责的事情。在华尔街，这件事很可笑，而且代价昂贵。但是这件事最糟糕的教训是不免让人认为，在股市上，你应该设法让自己略微减少一些人情味。

我离开威廉森的公司，到了其他地方去交易，在哪里都无钱可赚。我活该倒霉，因为我设法强迫市场给我不该给的东西，也就是给我赚钱的机会。想要得到通融很容易，认识我的那些人都对我充满了信任。我如果对你说，当我在股市中停止靠信用交易的时候，已经欠了别人100多万美元，你就知道他们对我的信任有多充分了。

并非我已经丧失了能力，而是在那困苦的四年中，根本就没有赚钱的机会。我想像以前一样埋头猛干，赚大钱，但结果却只会让欠款更多。因为我不想继续欠朋友们的钱，所以只好主动停止自行交易。此后，我靠着替别人管理账户来维持生活。他们都知道我非常懂行，就算市场不景气，也能游刃有余。如果获得利润，我就按照比例来获得提成——这时哪有半点利润？这就是我那时候的生活状况，应该说这就是我维持生活的办法。

话说回来，我也不是总在赔本，可就是还没有赚到更多的钱，来还我所欠的那些债。后来，情况变得更加不好，我平生首次有了一蹶不振的感觉。什么都不顺利，我从一个腰缠数百万、坐拥豪华游艇的富商，变成了一个债务缠身、生活拮据的人。我不喜欢这样的日子，但也顾不得自我可怜与抱怨。我不能就这么苦等时间来结束一切，要摆脱这种困境的方法只有一个，那就是赚钱。赚钱的办法就是去成功地交易。既然以前我这样交易过，那我就必须再接再厉。过去，我不止一次地靠着一点儿小钱，混成了资本大鳄，市场会把这个机会给我的。

我说服自己，认为不管有什么错误，都是我自己的错，一点儿都不能怪市场。那么我有什么问题呢？我秉持着一向研究不同阶段的交易问题时的精神，问自己这个问题，我冷静地分析了情势后，得出了结论：我的最大问题是担心我身上背负的那些债务，这个问题一直压迫着我。要讲清楚的是，这不光是欠账的心理在作祟。所有生意人在交易过程中都欠过别人的债务。我欠的债大多是商务债，是由不利于我的市场行情造成的。打个比方说，和商人遇到罕见而迁延很久的不正常气候相比，我的情形还没有那么严重。

日光如流水一般，因为还不上别人的钱，我对那些债务颇感烦躁。我需要说明：我欠着100多万，这都是在市场中损失的钱。很多人都对我很和善，没怎么为难我，只是有两个人总是纠缠我，一直跟在我屁股后面催债。我赚到点儿钱，他们就守在旁边，想搞明白有多少，逼我赶紧还账。有个人，我只欠他800美元，他还说要跟我上法庭，要扣押我的财产等，他竟然觉得我在藏匿财产，我对此很不理解，难道我看起来很不像即将穷困而死的无业游民？

我细心分析了炒股的问题，知道我需要做的是更加了解自己，而不是去研究股市行情。我沉着分析后明白：只要我一直担心，就不会有所作为，可显而易见的是，只要我欠着别人的账，就必定会心中忧虑。我说的意思是，只要那些曾借钱给我的人来找我的麻烦，或者逼我在取得足够的本钱之前就还他们钱，我就会这样。所以我就只能对自己说：“去办破产手续吧。”除此之外，我心里面的不快怎样才能消除呢？

这些听起来很容易，也很合理，是吧？但是，这么做就不光是令人不痛快了，我可以这样说，我痛恨那样做，痛恨让自己身处被人误解的处境。我个人没有看重过钱，从来没觉得要为了钱去说谎。可我明白，并非谁都会像我一样想问题。当然我同时也知道，如果状况变得好一点儿，我就会赶紧还钱，因为那种义务仍然存在。可我要是不用原来的方式交易，就丝毫没有还清100万的可能。

我鼓足勇气，去找债主。这是一件于我而言非常困难的事情，那些人大多是我的多年好友。我坦诚地把现状讲给他们听：“我并不是因为不想还你们钱才采用这个方法，而是为了对我们双方都公平，我要先解决赚钱的事情。过去两年，我断断续续地想着解决这个窘况的办法，一直不好意思出来对你们坦诚相告。如果我早这样做，就会对我们都有好处。我是说，如果这些账总逼迫我，让我心烦意乱，我就没法满血复活。如今我已经下定决心做一年前就该做的事。除此之外，我没有其他理由了。”

第一个出来说话的人代表他的公司，说出了所有债主想说的话。

“利文斯顿先生，”他说，“你说的意思我们都明白，我们也对你的现状非常理解。让我告诉你我们的想法：我们一定会让你解脱。请你让律师准备好你需要的东西，我们签字。”

这就是他们的想法，是华尔街好的那一面。那不光是对金钱满不在乎的天性，或者如体育赛事般公平竞争的风格，也是一种非常聪明的决定，因为这明显是正确的生意之道。我非常感谢这种美好的天性和精明的生意之道。

借款人对我共计100万的债务暂缓施压，可还是有两个小债主不想签字。其中一个就是我之前提到过的，欠他800美元的那个人。还有一个是我欠了6万美金的一家公司，他们已经破产了，接手的人不了解我，一天到晚地跟在我屁股后面。就算他们像其他大债主一样做，估计法院也不会让他们签字了结。总之，我走的破产程序，让我的破产账单上只有10万的债务，但是我实际欠了别人100万。

报纸报道了我的事情，真是让人不高兴。我从来都是欠钱就还的，从来不拖，这一次的事情深深伤害了我。我知道只要还在喘气，就要还清债务，但是，每一个看到那篇报道的人，不一定都明白我。看了那篇报道后，我都没脸出门见人了。但是，很快地，这种感觉消失了。很难形容，当清楚自己不会再受那些不明白你只有在毫无压力的情况下全身心投入市场，才能够成功交易的人的干扰后，心情是怎样的轻松愉悦，我感觉卸下了好大一个担子。

从债务围拢中解脱后，我想象着未来成功的美好光景，下一步要做的是积攒一些本钱。从1914年7月31日到12月中旬，股票交易所一直关闭，华尔街市场一片萧瑟。那么长时间没有一点儿交易，我欠着朋友的钱，他们对我很讲义气，我不好意思再向他们开口寻求资助，我也清楚那时没什么人能够助人到这种程度。

要寻得一笔合适的本钱非常困难，因为证券交易所关闭了，我不能要求任何一个经纪人帮我做点儿什么。我找了好几个地方，都没起到作用。

最后，在1915年2月，我只能去见威廉森。我对他说了我甩掉了债务的心理负担，要像原来一样交易。你可能记得，当初他用我的时候，我还没说话，他就急着让我用他的那2.5万美金。

而现在，当我需要他的时候，他却说：“当你觉得市场行情不错时，想买500股的话那你就去买吧，没有问题。”

我表达了谢意后离开了他。他原来总是阻止我，而他的公司却利用我赚了很多钱。一想到威廉森的公司不借给我足够的本钱，我就非常气愤。我觉得，刚开始进行交易，要稳当一些。如果有比500股多的钱来玩，我就能够更快更容易地恢复财力。可无论如何，情况就是这样的，这就是我东山再起的机会。

我离开威廉森的公司后，分析了市场行情，也反思了自己的弱点。当时是多头市场，这对我和其他成千上万的投资者都是一样清楚的，可我的那点儿资本只可以买到500股。我受到这样的限制，却没有任何其他办法。开始时，我就没法与哪怕一丁点儿的挫败相对抗。我一定要用这第一笔小资本筹得更多的钱。一开始买的500股必须要能赚钱，我必须赚到实实在在的资金。我知道除非有足够的本钱，才不会失去很好的判断；保证金不足，我就没办法在这个游戏中用冷酷而冷静的态度去交易。这个态度源于能承受一定损失的能力，就是我在大规模交易之前测试市场的那点儿损失。

此时，我深知自己处于一个股票投机客生涯中最重要的时刻。这次如果失败了，就算还有机会，也不知道从哪里、什么时候才能获取一笔钱，另外再尝试一次。显然，我需要一个最合适的时机。

我离威廉森的公司远远的，我是说在持续研判股市行情的六周之内，我从没到这家公司去。我害怕一旦到了公司看到交易大厅，知道能够交易500股，就会经不住诱惑而在不合时机的情况下出手交易不赚钱的股票。作为投机人，要研究市场基本行情，记住之前的经验，搞明白一般大众的心理和经纪人的受限因素，还需要认清自己的缺点。没有必要对自己身上的人性生气。我明白，了解自己和了解行情都非常重要。我细致分析思考自己在承受市场压力和活跃市场的诱惑力方面的反应，这样研究和估算时的心理和精神状态，很像我在思考谷物行情和收益报告时的状态。

所以，一天接着一天，我虽然一文不名，却急不可耐地等着进入股市。我坐在一家经纪公司的股市行情显示牌前面，不能进行交易，只能分析行情。我不让任何一条记录从我眼前溜走，我关注着股市上涨铃声响起的那一刻。

因为大家都熟识的因素，1915年前期的重要日子里，我很看好伯利恒钢铁公司的股票，我确定它会上涨。可为了确保首战告捷，我要等到它突破面值（100美元）之后再出手，我必须这么做才行。

我想我说过，我有这样的经验：不管何时，股票首次涨破100、200或300的时候，差不多就总会再继续涨30至50个点。超过300后，涨速还要快于突破100、200点后。我做得最成功的股票之一安纳康达就是这样，当它涨过200的时候我买了，一天后就到了260，然后我就卖掉了。我这样在股票刚刚突破票面价后买入的做法，在对赌行的时候就经常用，这是个很老的交易原则。

你能想象得出，我多么渴望恢复过去那种交易规模。我急于开始，什么都不想，可也能自我克制。就跟我想的一样，伯利恒的股票天天在涨，越涨越高。可我还是不允许自己贸然去威廉森的公司买进500股。我必须确保首次出手就赚钱。

那只股票每上涨1个点，就相当于我没有去赚500美元。上涨过了首次的10个点后，我就应该加码，如果那样，我现在手中就不是500股，而是有每上涨1个点就能赚1000美元的1000股了。可我仍然坐着不动，对自己的希望与信念在心中的呼唤充耳不闻，我只重视源于经验和常识的平稳安全的声音。我只要有足够的钱，就可以冒险，可我就是没有足够的钱，所以即使是冒小小的险，也是我完全无法承受的奢侈行为。不过，我最后还是遏制了自己的贪念和希望，忍耐了六周时间。

我开始犹豫了，就在那只股票突破90时。想到那些因我没买进而溜走的金钱啊，我的心在滴血。这只股票涨到98的时候，我心想它可能会突破100，只要等到了100，连房子都要被闹爆了，行情记录显示得很清楚。其实，记录上的内容谁都知道。这么对你说吧，当行情记录是98的时候，我就知道它肯定会到100。我清楚这不是我想要听到的、想要看到的，而是我对行情记录的本能反应。所以我想，不能等过了100再出手，此时此刻就要尽快买入，这只股票等于已经突破票面价了。

我匆匆赶到威廉森的公司，一次性买了500股伯利恒钢铁股票，当时的行情是98。我在98到99的时候，买了500股。之后到晚上收盘前，它疯狂涨到了114或者115，我就又买了500股。

次日，伯利恒钢铁的股票涨到了145，我有本钱了。等着股市上涨的六周，是我经历得最紧张焦灼的六周。不过，我的回报也来了，因为我此时已经有了足以让我大玩一把的本钱。如果一直玩500股的交易，我绝对不会有任何成就。

首次做对是很重要的，不管你从事哪一种行业都一样。在做了伯利恒的股票后，我接下来的操作都很顺利。真的，每笔都很帅，简直让我难以相信，这都是原来那个我在交易。但其实我已经脱胎换骨了，因为我原来备受骚扰、错误百出，现在却轻松愉快，正确无误。欠账的人不来找麻烦，我不会因为没钱而被打断交易，足够的资金对我耐心运用经验也不会造成影响，所以我在不断地获利。

就在我快要朝着目标财富挺进的时候，受“卢西塔尼亚号”被击沉的事件影响，股市猛然下跌了。每过一阵子，人总会在心窝被刺痛一下，这提醒人们，股市中没有永远的胜利，谁都会蒙受损失。据说，“卢西塔尼亚号”被击沉事件不该影响到那些专业的投资商，而且还不说他们在华尔街得知消息之前，就知道了这件事。我做了傻事，没有在提前听到消息后抽身出来。我要说的是，因为“卢西塔尼亚号”事件和我的缺乏预见造成了一两次损失，到1915年底的时候，我才发现我的保证金大概只有14万了，这就是我赚到的全部金钱，虽然这一整年我对市场的判断大部分都很正确。

接下来的一年，我做得也很好，运气也不错。在疯狂的多头市场中，我连战连捷，投资一直很顺畅。我不用考虑过多，只是一味地赚钱。这让我想起原来标准石油公司的已故人士罗杰斯的话，大概意思是，一个人赚钱的时机来临时，钞票挡也挡不住，就好比没有带雨伞，走到暴雨中，想要不被打湿很难。现在股市属于多头市场，大家都知道，协约国在美国购买物资，让美国成了世界上最发达昌盛的国家，拥有其他国家所没有的东西，世界各地的资金都源源不断地流入美国。我是说，这么大的世界，金子疯狂地流到这个国家来。通货膨胀也在情理之中，这说明所有东西的价格都在上涨。

一开始，什么都很明显，股价上涨是一点儿都没必要或者完全不需要炒作的。与多头市场相比，这就是准备工作少的原因。战争造成的繁荣局面，比其他因素引发的繁荣更顺理成章，而且为大家送来了很高的利润。就是说，1915年，人们从股市上赚取的钱比华尔街历史上任何一个繁荣时期赚得都多。人们没有把他们的全部账面利润完全套现，变成确实的现金，或是没有长期保有真正已经落袋的获利，只是历史自行重复而已。在华尔街，历史一次次地重演，比其他任何地方都频繁、有规律。当你读到有关那时候或兴或衰的文字记录时，你会发现，现在的股票投机和股票投机客跟以前相比，没有多大的区别。这个游戏本身没发生多少改变，人性也没发生多大的变化。

1916年，我跟着股市上涨的趋势炒股，与很多人一样乐观，同时也保持着警惕心。就像谁都清楚的那样，我也明白什么事情都有结束的时候，所以随时注意着各种迹象。我并不喜欢猜测那些迹象从哪里来，所以并不专注于一个地方。我不会，也没觉得自己会对市场的某个侧面情有独钟。多头市场让我的存款变多了，或是空头市场对我特别慷慨，我都认为不是充足的理由，不足以让我坚守多头或空头。人不该誓死对多头或空头效忠。你唯一关心的是要正确。

还有一件事要记住，就是股市没有鼎盛的终点，也不会突然以其相反的形式结束。股市或许常在整体下跌前很久就失去了多头市场。我明白了这点时，等了好久的警示迹象一个个出现了，在股市中一直跑在前面的股票，从高处跌落了几个点，属于好几个月以来的首次下跌，而且没有再涨回去。显然，我需要赶紧调整战术了。

要转变也很简单。在多头市场，股价大势一定是向上走的，所以要是有一只股票与之走向不符，你就可以假设它肯定是哪里有问题了。这足够让老到的投机者们深感不对劲。他根本不需要看行情记录，只用等着行情记录说：“撤！”而不是等待行情记录发出合法的批准文件。

就像刚刚说的，我看到那些冲在前面的股票没有了上涨的势头，已经下跌了六七个点，然后停住不动了。同时，其他股票还在一直上涨。这些上市公司内部都没问题，所以原因出在别处。那些股票上涨了几个月后突然停下来，虽然多头还是很猛烈，可却昭示着那些特定股票上涨的终结。股市上的另一些股票还在稳步上涨。

根本没必要慌乱，进而原地踟蹰。我在此时并没卖空，我看行情记录还不到那一步。多头市场结束的日子还没有来到，但是已经近在咫尺。在它来之前，还能做多头来赚钱。情况是这样，我只是看坏已经停止上涨的股票，因为市场上还有其他股票在上涨，我一边买进，一边卖出。

我卖空了已不再保持领先的那些股票，每只我都卖掉了5000股。然后我把新冲上去的股票做多。我手里做空的股票不怎么涨，而做多的在不停地上涨。等它们不再涨的时候，我就又卖掉，开始做空，每只股票各放空5000股。此时，我卖空的比买进的要多，因为很显然，下次要在股市下跌时大赚一笔。当我确定了牛市还没结束，熊市就已开始的时候，就知道赚钱的卖空的时机还不成熟。低调不动肯定不行，但可也不能太急躁。行情记录表明不景气的熊市快来了，此时应该做好准备。

我不断地买卖，一直持续了一个月，我按照每次5000股，共做空了6万股，是十几只不同股票。它们在这一年一开始是很受欢迎的，因为一直处于活跃上涨领先状态。这6万股不是很大的空头部位，但是不要忘记，股市并没有确定走空。

可是，终于有一天，股市疲软了下来，所有的股价开始下跌。在我卖出的十二只股票中，每只都赚了至少4个点，说明我的头寸没有出错。行情记录表明，这个时候做空就是安全的，所以我立刻加码一倍。

我建立了自己的空头头寸，此时这样的空头市场中，我放空手中掌握的股票。我根本没必要去打压，股市一定会和我的预估相符。清楚了这一点，我就可以安心等着。在我加码一倍以后，我有一大段时间没有交易。大概在我建立全部放空头寸六周后，发生了大家都知道的泄密事件，从而引发了股市的暴跌。

我听说，有人事先从华盛顿知道了一个消息，说威尔逊总统很快就要发布一个能为欧洲带来和平的政令。世界大战促成了战时的经济繁荣，也维持了很长时间，而伴随和平而来的自然就是熊市。当一个精明的投资人被指控说利用这个消息赚取利润的时候，他说自己卖掉股票不是靠消息，而是他觉得市场已经活跃过头了。而我，在此前七周就成倍增持了空头头寸。

听到了股市要暴跌的消息，我就做了应对，这是唯一合理的做法。在做计划的时候，如果发生了你没有估算到的事情，就该借助命运之神提供的机遇。原因之一是，股市如此暴跌，就会出现一个大市场，大到你可以利用这个市场，把你的账面利润转为现金。就算在空头市场，一个人回补了12万股，也不可能不让股价抬高。因此他必须要等市场给予的这个机会，买进这么多股票，而不致使账面利润受到影响。

我要说的是，我并非是借这么个特殊理由，在这样的时候指望股市能有异常大跌。恰恰相反，就像我说过的，身为专业作手，我有30年的炒股经验，它告诉我，这样的情况一般会朝着阻力最小的方向前行，我的理论就建立在这一点上。另外需要记住的是，千万不要想着在价格最高的时候放空，这是很不聪明的做法。如果没有迹象表明股价会止跌，而且要强势反弹，就要等市场回调后抛出。

1916年，我靠着在多头市场的持续做多，和在空头市场一开始就做空，赚取了300多万。我之前说过，没有必要坚持守住市场的一个面做交易。

那一年的冬天，我跟前几年一样，因为特别喜欢钓鱼而去了棕榈滩度假。我在炒股的同时，也在小麦期货中做空，两种交易都为我创造了很大的利润。没有烦恼事情影响，我的假期很愉快。只是，我没有去欧洲，也就不可能正儿八经与股票和期货市场斩断联系，比如我在纽约北部城市安迪若恩达克斯的家中，就安装了与纽约经纪公司相通的电话线。

在棕榈滩时，我养成了定期去经纪商分公司的习惯。我发现棉花市场很强劲，价格在上涨。大概在那时候，也就是1917年，有很多与威尔逊总统为和平而努力的事情传到了我的耳朵里。这些报道全是从华盛顿传来的，我是从新闻和棕榈滩朋友处获知的。这些致使我在某一天产生了这样的想法：各个市场的运行都与威尔逊是否成功有关。如果和平即将到来，股票和小麦期货应该下跌，棉花应该上涨。不管股票与小麦的市场如何发展，我已经准备好了一切，可棉花，我却已经很久没有碰它了。

有一天下午两点二十，我一包棉花都没买，可过了五分钟，我就觉得和平已经临近了，所以一下子买了1.5万包。我打算按照原来的老办法玩，这种玩法我之前说过。

那天下午股市收盘后，我们收到了德国的“无限制战争”声明，没有其他办法了，只有等隔日股市开盘后再看。我记得那晚在葛丽莱俱乐部，一位美国的工业大亨想以比那天收盘价低5个点的价格卖掉手中的美国钢铁公司股票。几个匹兹堡的百万富翁也在场，但没有人愿意买，他们觉得只要买了就会有很大的亏损。

事情果然是这样，你能够想象，第二天早上股市和期货市场一片混乱，有的股票开盘价比头天晚上收盘时低了8个点。而这正好是老天所赐的一个回补空头头寸的良机。我提到过，在熊市的时候，股市如果忽然混乱了，买进就是个好办法。你如果掌控得够好，就是个将一大笔浮动利润转化成现金的唯一时机。比如，我做了5万股钢铁公司的空头，同时也做了其他公司的空头，等我有了买进的机会时，我就会回补。我赚了大约150万美元。这是个不可小觑的机会。

在头一天收盘前半小时，我买进的那1.5万包棉花，一开盘就跌了500点，这太吓人了，我一夜之间赔了37.5万美元。此时，在股票和小麦期货上，正确的做法就是在下跌前平了空头，可我却在棉花期货上犹豫，不知道该怎么做才对。有很多需要考虑的事情，而且我在即将弥补损失时却认为自己错了，因为我不想在当天贸然挽回损失。接着我想到，我来南方是要过一段愉快的钓鱼日子，而不是被棉花市场的走势所困。我在股票和小麦期货市场上赚钱了，同时也在棉花市场遭受了损失。我这就能算出，我将获得的利润并非150多万，而是100万多一些。这纯属会计的事情，当你提出了很多问题后，他就是这样告诉你不怎么精确的数字的。

如果我在前一天收盘前没买棉花，我就不会赔损40万。这说明，当人在投资方面出现失误时，不管多么小的失误，就可能迅速亏掉大钱。我的主要寸头是完全正确的，而且我在一个与自己的考量相悖的偶发事情中，获得了利益。你看，最小阻力线的交易价值又一次出现在了交易商面前。虽然德国人的声明造成无法预料的市场因素，可股市走向还是在我的预料之中。要是事实证明我所料不错，那我的三笔投入就完全是对的。随着和平时期的到来，股票和小麦会下跌，而棉花会大涨，这三笔投入就是全赚。无论战争还是和平，我在股市和小麦期货的头寸都是正确无误的，这是突发事件助我赚钱的原因。在棉花期货市场上，我的投资是基于市场之外的事情，也就是说，我把考量因素集中到了威尔逊的和平谈判上，是德国军方的那些人使我在棉花市场遭受了损失。

我在1917年初回到纽约后，就还清了所有的欠债，一共100多万，这对我来说是一件大快心意的事情。本来，我可以在几个月前就能还清，只是有个小原因致使我没有还账。那时，我正处在交易期，做得很不错，正是我需要钱的时候。我得用我赚的钱和他们的钱，在1915年和1916年的繁荣市场中，利用好所有的时机。我清楚会大赚，不需要为此担心，所以我让他们再耐心等我几个月，而其中有的人甚至不指望能要回欠款了。我不想每次还一点儿，或者每次还一个人，我要还钱就一次性全部还清所有人的债务。所以，只要市场尽其所能地帮助我，我就会利用手中所有的资金去交易。

我提出了支付利息的想法，可所有与我签过拖欠协议的人都不要利息。我最后还清债务的那人，就是那个我欠了800美元的人。那时候，他给我增添了不少压力，让我非常不爽，不能轻松地去赚钱。我把他放到最后，一直到他知道我还清了其他所有人的欠账，他才拿到了那点儿钱。我想让他学会在别人欠他几百美元的时候，要换位思考。

这就是我东山再起的过程。

还清了全部欠款后，我支出了一大笔钱作为年度消费金，我发誓不再像以前那样，因为身上没钱而心情沮丧，从而让投资也非常不顺利。而且，我结婚后，也给了妻子一笔资金，孩子出生后，我又为孩子留了一笔钱。

我这么行事，不光是害怕多变的市场再次让我变成穷光蛋，而是我明白谁都可能把自己轻易获取的东西浪费光。安排好了以后，妻子和孩子就不会因为我炒股而生活受到影响。

我认识的很多人都像我一样，安排自己的生活。可是，当他们再次需要钱的时候，又穷尽手段哄妻子签字把钱交给他们用，他们拿去后就又亏损在了市场里。可是，我做得很妥当，不管我想做什么，或者妻子要拿钱为我做什么，那张托管协议都不会允许，一分钱都不能动。这是一笔安全的资金，我和妻子都不能随便挪用它，它不会受市场需求的影响，甚至不会受好妻子的爱心影响，我绝不冒险。

第十五章

在市场投机过程中，出现无法预估的事情的可能性很大，风险非常高。有些风险，很多非常谨慎的人都该承受，他如果想在市场上不那么畏畏缩缩，就要承担风险。正常的商业风险，没有出门逛街或者坐火车旅行那么危险。我对受到无法预测的事情而赔本的情势的怨恨不会比对来得不是时候的暴风雨更多。从摇篮到坟墓，这个生命的过程本身就是一场赌博。我没法预知未来，所以对遇到的所有事情都可以承受，不觉得受到困扰。不过，在我从事投机事业的生涯里，有几次我判断正确，操作也没错，却被一些宵小之徒卑鄙地骗走了获利。

一个反应迅捷和眼光深远的人会通过对骗子、懦夫和乌合之众进行反击而保护自己。除了在以前的一些对赌行里以外，我从来没有遇到十分卑鄙、恶劣的不诚实做法，就算在对赌行那样的地方，诚实也是最可取的准则。赚大钱需要公平公正地赚，而不是通过欺诈与蒙骗。我不觉得随时随地都必须放亮眼睛以免上当是好的市场交易行为。不过，一个正直的人遇到那种卑劣的人是丝毫没办法的。公平竞争就是公平竞争。我还可以说出十几个例子来，在这些活生生的实例中，我都是因为一言九鼎或者相信别人能够一言九鼎而受到损害。不过这些事情我不会讲出来的，已经没什么意义了。

有很多人，比如小说家、宗教人士或者妇女们，都觉得股票交易所是贿赂公行的战场，或是把华尔街人的日常业务说成是一场战争。这种说法相当耸动，却彻底误导了大家。我不觉得我的副业是引发冲突或者发动战争。我从来没有对哪个人或群体发过战书，只是各自有不同的看法，不同的观点，仅此而已。戏剧家们所谓的那种商战，不是人与人之间的战争，而是商业观念上的较量。我努力去相信事实，并且据此行动，这就是贝纳德·巴鲁奇能够成功的秘诀。有时候，我没有完全看清客观事实，或者没有及时了解全部的事实，或者没有做出合理的推论。一旦出现这种情况，我就会亏钱。只要一出错，代价就是付出金钱。

凡是理智的人，都不会反对为自己所犯的错付出代价。谁犯了错都要有代价，这是普遍规律。可我在对的时候，就很反对亏钱。我说的不是那种因为交易所规则突然改变让我付出了金钱的某些交易。我想到的是交易中的一些偶发事件，它们会经常提醒我：只有将钱存到自己的银行账户上后，才算是实打实的利润。

世界大战在欧洲爆发后，急需品价格上涨，人们对这样的情况非常容易估计到，正如人们觉得战争会导致通货膨胀一样。战争一直在持续，物价也在跟着上涨。你可能记得我之前说的，我在1915年的时候，忙的都是怎么样翻身的事情。股市热潮出现，抓住这个机会是我必须要做的。我做过的最稳当、最容易实现、最迅速的大事都是在股市中进行的，而且我很幸运，这件事你已经知道。

到了1917年7月，我不光能够还清债务，还有一定的结余，这说明我已经有了同时去做股票和期货交易的时间、资本和意愿。这么多年，研究交易市场，已经成了我的习惯。期货市场的商品，除了咖啡，价格都比战争之前上涨了1到4倍。这是有原因的，战争导致了欧洲商品市场被迫关闭，大量的咖啡被运到了市场广阔的美国，所以美国国内咖啡原料积压过多，导致咖啡价格下跌。我开始考虑咖啡投资的可能性时，它的价格已经低于战争之前的价格。造成这个反常现象的原因很明显，而更明显的是，德国和奥地利不断地对同盟国船只展开攻击，致使能用在商业方面的船数量减少，这也造成了咖啡进口生意不景气。随着时间的推移，咖啡进口减少，人们的消费速度却没有变化，积压的咖啡终会被消费掉，所以当这样的局面出现时，咖啡价格一定跟其他商品一样猛涨。

不需要有福尔摩斯的智慧就足以分析出这个情况。可为什么人们都不买咖啡，我却不知道原因。当我决定要买的时候，不觉得这是一种投机行为，而更像是商业投资。我知道想赚钱得需要时间，可我知道这个投资会产生很大的利润。这就使得买进咖啡成了保守的投资行为，是银行家而不是投机者的操作。

1917年冬天，我开始着手收购咖啡，买进了大量的咖啡。可是，市场却没有什么反响，还是那样的萧条，价格也并非我预想的那样会上涨，所以我手里握着没有前途的合约长达九个月之久。

九个月后，合同到期，我只好卖掉平仓，这让我又赔了一大笔钱。不过，我觉得我的分析并非没有道理，显然我是拿捏错了时机，我确定咖啡一定会跟其他东西一样涨价。所以，我刚一卖掉，就又立刻买入，而且是上一次买入的3倍。当然了，我买的是尽可能长久握在手里的期权合约。

这一次我可没有出错。我买进三倍的数量后不久，咖啡价格就开始上涨，每个人都好像一下子明白过来了，知道咖啡市场要出现什么情形。从市场行情来看，我的投资好像快要收到巨额回报了。

卖咖啡的人是咖啡烘烤业者，大多数是德国人或者是和德国有关系的商家，他们信心十足地从巴西买到咖啡后非常想运送到美国，可是没有货船。不久之后，他们发现自己处于非常紧迫的状态，一方面在遥远的南美洲那里，有无穷无尽的咖啡供应，另一方面又在美国大量放空给我。

请记住，咖啡价格处于世界大战之前的水平时，我开始看好它；也别忘了，我买了以后，被套牢了大半年，承受了庞大的亏损。亏本是对错误的惩罚，而赚钱就是对正确的奖励。因为这次做得非常正确，也属于长线投资，我绝对有理由可以赚一大笔。要赚到让自己满意的利润，并不需要市场价格涨多高，我手里可是有几十万袋咖啡。我不喜欢说能操作多少多少，这些数字听起来似乎有些不可能一样，人们会认为我是在说大话。其实我只是根据自己的财力操作，也为自己留足了投资安全的余地，在这个例子中我够谨慎了。我买了这么多咖啡期权，是因为感觉不会赔本，情况对我有利。我已经等待了一年时间，现在耐心等待和操作正确无误会让我得到报酬。我知道利润会源源不断地涌来，非常猛烈。这当中没有什么巧妙，而仅仅是因为我不盲目而已。

几百万的赚头确实很快就来了，可是钞票根本没到我手中。不是形势突然发生了变化，美国国内的市场没有转变，咖啡也没有涌进美国。到底出了什么事情呢？真是难以预料，是任何人都没遇到过的，我也没办法提前防范的事情。在投资过程中，那一连串的突发事件里，必须得加上这一件令我永远记住的事情了。这就是，那些卖给我咖啡的空头们，非常明白自己面临的现实情况，所以尽力摆脱现状，他们要把手里的咖啡抛售出去，想出了新的欺骗方式。他们匆忙来到华盛顿寻求帮助，而且确实得到了协助。

你可能记得，政府以前制定过很多条例，防止民生必需品遭到囤积居奇。你知道的，大多数都发挥了作用。呃，那些大慈大悲的咖啡商们跑到了战时的价格管制委员会，打着爱国的幌子，为美国人的早餐申请权利。这个委员会说，一个叫劳伦斯·利文斯顿的职业投机商可能垄断了咖啡，他想利用世界大战创造的条件，赚取巨额利润，而美国人不得不用很昂贵的价格来买每天的必需品——咖啡。那些卖给我几船咖啡却没有船只运送的爱国者，根本无法想象，1亿美国人或多或少要向没有良心的投机分子致意。他们代表的是咖啡这一行，而不是炒作咖啡的赌客，他们情愿帮政府打压市场上的或者可能出现在市场中的暴利投机行为。

现在有一大堆人抱怨我，我并不是暗示价格管制委员会没尽到职责去管控囤积居奇和浪费行为，我更想表达出我的看法，他们可能没有很深入地研究咖啡市场。他们制定了咖啡原料的限价，也定了个终止现有咖啡合同的期限。这就说明咖啡市场的交易马上要停了，我只有一件事可以做，就是卖掉所有的咖啡合约。正如之前曾赚几百万时一样，这次我认定能赚的几百万打了水漂。我从来都是强烈反对在生活必需品行业牟利，可当价格管制委员会制定咖啡条例前，所有的其他商品价格都已经比大战之前高了2.5到4倍，可咖啡价格实际上比战前那几年的均价还低呢。我觉得咖啡在谁手中都一个样，价格肯定要上涨，不是因为那些无情的投机分子操控了，而是咖啡数量越来越少。这是进口的数量越来越少导致的，而进口数量的减少又是由德国潜艇对船只的轰炸造成的。价格管制委员会还没等咖啡涨价，就采取了限价行动。

作为一种政策和没办法的办法，强迫市场停止咖啡交易简直是个错误。如果这个价格管制委员会允许咖啡交易正常进行，咖啡价格就会因为之前说过的其实与垄断没有丝毫关系的原因上涨。而且这样的上涨，不需要太高，就会起到刺激作用，让咖啡供给回到市场中来。我曾经听贝纳德·巴鲁奇提到过，战时工业委员会规定价格的时候，考虑过为市场做担保这个因素，所以一些针对某些商品的高价限制所发的怨言就很不公平了。后来，咖啡市场交易重新回归后，咖啡的价格达到了每磅23美分。供应量太少，美国人还是得掏腰包。同时因为那些慈悲为怀的空头的建议导致定价过低，使得连高价运费都没办法支付，进口量就变得很少，因此咖啡在美国的供应也就很少。

我一直觉得，在我所有的商品交易中，这笔咖啡的交易才是最合情合理合法的。我认为这是商业投资，而不是投机行为。我投资了咖啡一年多时间，要是真说其中有赌博因素的话，那也是那些有德国姓氏和血统的爱国者在赌博。他们在巴西买了咖啡，运回到纽约卖给我。价格管制委员会又管制了唯一没有上涨的商品价格，在暴利交易出现之前，对大众的利益起到了保护作用。可是，却没有抵挡得了随后无可避免的价格上涨。不光是这样，而且当生咖啡豆在每磅9美分盘旋时，烘干咖啡跟其他商品一样，价格在上涨，其实只有那些烘烤商人赚了钱。如果生咖啡豆每磅能涨价两三美分的话，我就会赚几百万美元，同时大众也不会在后来咖啡暴涨时付出那么高的代价了。

事后为投机验尸是浪费时间，不过像这样的特殊交易，却很有总结的价值。它跟我之前所做的所有交易一样顺利。价格上涨是显而易见的趋势，什么都符合规律，让我觉得不赚到那几百万都不可能，可是结果却真的没有赚到。

另外有两次，我是被那个委员会的规定所害，他们提前没有任何警示，就直接改变了交易规则。但是这两次，从方法的角度来看，我的所作所为是没问题的，只是没有我在咖啡投资交易时那么符合商业标准。在投机交易上，没有什么事情能够绝对确定。我刚说的那段经历，又为我那些意外事故增添了更多不可预估的因素。

这次咖啡投资事情过后，我在其他股票和期货买卖的交易上都做得很好，所以又听到了很多关于我的谈资。在华尔街，那些职业玩家和新闻记者看到市价出现无法避免的崩跌时，总习惯指责我，明里暗里地说是我在背后搞鬼。有时，说我所做的交易是不爱国的行为，却不管真正卖出的人是不是我。我觉得他们无端放大我在投资交易上的规模与影响，就是为了替人们找一个市价变动的理由，满足他们贪婪的需求。

我都说过一千次了，不论哪种操作手段，都不可能让股票价格下跌或者一直处在低价水平。这一点儿都不算神秘。任何一个人，只要不嫌麻烦的话，想上一会儿，就能清楚地得到答案。假设有个作手掼压一只股票，也就是让价格降到比实际价值更低的程度，一定会发生什么事情？嗯，聪明的内线人士就会迅速利用时机买进。能确定股票真正价值的人，总是会趁着股价低廉时买进股票。如果内线们不买进了，原因就是他们不看好股市行情，没办法自由支配足够的钱，这就不是多头的行情。人们在议论空头掼压时，总是认为掼压没有道理，甚至是犯罪。但是，把一只股票打压到远低于真正价值的水准，是非常危险的事情。要深深记住，那些被人操控着的，没有价格回升希望的股票，是不能够买的；只要有不正当卖空行为，使股价下跌猛烈，就容易引发买进行为，不管什么时候出现这样的事情，价格都不可能维持在低档。我应该说百分之九十九所谓的惯压，其实是合法合理的股价下跌，而且常常会加速下跌。不过，这种下跌并非主要是由哪个职业投机者造成的，无论他玩的是多大规模的投资。

那些认为股价突然下跌，或者出现比较异常的暴涨现象，都是由疯狂的幕后投机分子的投机行为造成的说法，都可能是编造的，只是为了提供给那些不用脑子思考，只知道盲目偏信的赌徒听，让他们得到个股价变动的解释。运气不好的投机者动不动就会在经纪人或者喜欢以讹传讹的人们口中听闻，说自己的亏损与股价变动都是幕后炒作的结果。这其实是一种反面的内幕消息。其中的区别是，空头的内幕消息是很清晰的，明确建议卖空，而反面的内幕消息就是一种没有给出说法的说法，它的作用其实是阻止了你卖空的明智决定。股票在下跌时，卖掉是自然而然的事，这一定是有理由的，是一个不知道原因但必定非常好的理由。所以，就应该脱手。可是，如果股价下跌是由幕后操控导致的，那脱手就不是聪明的做法。操纵者只要停止打压股市，价格就会马上反弹。这就是反面的内幕消息。

第十六章

内幕消息！人们是多么渴望知道内幕消息啊。不光渴望得到，还喜欢告诉别人。这是贪婪欲与虚荣心在作祟。每当见到那些很聪明的人到处获取内幕消息，就感觉很好笑。喜欢传播消息的人，不会管消息的好坏，因为需要消息的人并非只想得到好的消息，而是想得到所有的内幕消息。内幕消息如果有好处，那就好极了；如果没有，下一个会带来好运。我想到的是那些身在交易大厅里的散户。不过，有一些股票炒手和作手却从头到尾总是很相信内幕消息。于他们而言，一拨又一拨的内幕消息就是一种非常好的宣传方式，是世界上最好的促销剂。因为想得到消息的人和放出消息的人都会传播消息，所以内幕消息的散播就会发生连锁反应。传播内幕消息的人认为，没有谁能抵挡得了合理传播的内幕消息，顶着这样的假象，他们四处传播，也研究过怎么样才能非常巧妙地把消息扩散出去。

每天我都能从各色人口中听到好多内幕消息，我要讲个婆罗洲锡业公司的故事。你记得它上市时候是什么情形吗？那可是股市最繁荣的时候。他们公司按照一位智慧过人的银行家的建议，立马在公开市场上出售新上市公司的股票，而不是交给承销团去慢慢消化。这是个好建议，不过他们唯一的错就出在了经验不足上。他们不知道股市行情特别好的时候，股价是多么疯狂，而且他们又畏首畏尾，聪明不足。他们同意根据市场需求抬高价格销售股票，可是挂牌的价格却高得出奇，致使交易的人们和投机开拓者们买进股票的时候疑虑重重。

按照道理来说，公司必定会陷在进退两难的困境中，可是在疯狂的牛市，他们的贪心却变得特别保守。只要有一点儿内幕消息，人们什么股票都买进，根本不考虑什么投资不投资的，只想着轻松地赚点钱，靠着赌博性质的做法赚一次是一次。各个国家都在购买大量的军用物资，所以金钱如流水一般涌入美国。人们说，公司在制订婆罗洲锡业上市计划的时候，曾经三次提高开盘价格，最后才完成了第一笔交易。

也有人想让我加入，我调查了一下后没有接受邀请，因为如果要在市场操作的话，我喜欢单枪匹马做事，按照自己的方式来交易。婆罗洲锡业公司上市的时候，我调研了他们公司的财务情况、行动方案以及人们会形成何等疯狂的景象后，在首次交易那天的第一个小时内，就买进了1万股。从某个角度来说，这个股票的初次发行是成功的。事实上，当公司看到股民们这么疯狂地买了他们的股票后，就觉得这么快就放掉很多股票个错误。他们得知我买了1万股时，觉得就算把股价多抬高百分之二十五或者百分之三十，照样可以卖完。所以他们认为我买那1万股可能得到的利润，会占去他们的几百万美元利润当中的很大份额，因此就停止了炒作，还想把我挤出去，但我就是岿然不动。他们拿我没办法，觉得是运气不佳，就放弃了对我采取的行动，免得不小心失去对市场的控制。接着，他们开始拉抬股份，但是放掉的股数都在他们的可控范围内。

他们看到其他股票涨得非常离谱，就想着自己能赚到巨大的利润。婆罗洲锡业公司股票上涨到了120点的时候，我一次性把1万股全部卖给了他们，对股票的上涨起到了压制作用，于是公司负责人就放弃了拉高价格的做法。接下来股价反弹时，他们又想办法让这只股票引人追捧，调节了一大部分的持股情况。可后来的事实证明，拉抬股价的成本很高，最后他们把股票价格拉高到了150。股市此时逐渐冷淡，这个公司没办法，只好尽力往外卖出股票，抛给那些总喜欢在回落时买进的投机者。这些人离谱地臆想，原来150的股票，降到130就是非常便宜的了，而下跌到120美元，那简直就是捡了个大便宜。公司制造内幕消息，让交易场内的股民们都知道，然后制造出一个短暂的回光返照的繁荣局面。后来，公司也会放一些消息给交易所，反正哪种旁门左道都能起到一点儿作用，他们想方设法用尽了自己会的所有伎俩。只是，那种适合做多的好时节已经过去了，笨蛋们已经吞下了其他的诱饵。婆罗洲锡业公司的人没有看清现状，或者根本就是看明白了但不愿意接受罢了。

我和妻子去了南边的棕榈滩度假。有一天，我在葛丽莱小赚了一把，回到家拿出500美元给妻子。这是很奇异的巧合。在那天晚上吃饭的时候，妻子遇到了婆罗洲锡业公司的总裁维森斯坦先生，他就是这个公司那一伙股票发行人的老大。很久后，我才明白，他坐在我妻子旁边是花了一番心思的。

他想尽办法讨好我的妻子，最后还神秘地对她说：“利文斯顿夫人，我打算干一件从来没有干过的事情，我非常乐意去做，因为你明白这里面的意义。”他停住不说，着急地看着我妻子，想知道她有多聪明谨慎。我妻子看出了他明摆在神态中的意思。不过，我妻子只是随口应道：“我明白。”

“那好，利文斯顿夫人，我非常荣幸和你们夫妻二人见面。为了证明我的诚心，因为我希望能与你们长久交往。我确定不用我说，你也应该知道我要说的话是机密。”接着，他压低了声音，“如果你们买进婆罗洲锡业公司的股票，一定会赚一笔大钱。”

“是吗？”我妻子问。

“我刚从旅店离开的时候，”他说，“收到了几封电报，内容是需要对大众保密几天的。我准备尽力多买进一些这只股票。明天开盘的时候，如果你要买，就跟我一起按照一样的价格买吧。我保证婆罗洲锡业股票百分之百会大涨。我只把这个消息告诉了你一个人，绝对没有第二个人知道。”

妻子表达了谢意，然后对他说，自己一点儿都不懂股市。他就对我妻子说，只要知道这个消息就够了，其他也没必要懂。为了让她确定无疑地明白，他重复了一下自己的话。

“你只要尽量买进你想买的婆罗洲锡业公司的股票。我绝对保证，你这样做不会有损失。我这辈子，还从来没劝过哪个女人或男人去买哪家股票呢。我非常有把握，这只股票不会停在200点以下，我只想让你们多赚些钱。你应该明白，我一个人不可能买进所有股票的。除了我以外，如果还有人能从中获利，我希望是你们夫妻二人，而不是一些陌生人。我偷偷对你说，因为我知道你不会到处乱说的。利文斯顿夫人，请按照我说的话，买进婆罗洲锡业吧。”

他说得一本正经，所以我妻子相信了他的话。她就想把我给她的500美元物尽其用。这点儿钱于我而言不算什么，完全是由她自由花销的。也就是说，就算她运气差，也就亏损这么一点儿而已。而且，那人保证了她一定能赚。要是她能靠自己的力量赚钱——事后，她才告诉了我真相——一定棒极了。

嗯，是这样，就在次日早上开盘前，我妻子走进了哈丁兄弟公司，对经理说：“哈利先生，我想买些股票，可我不想用我常用的账户。在赚钱之前，我不想让我家先生知道。你可以帮忙安排吗？”

经理说：“哦，没问题。我们单独开一个户头就可以。哪只股票？你要买多少股？”

妻子把500美元给他，说：“你听好，我可不想赔光本钱，如果这些钱赔了，我不想欠账。你记住哦，不要让利文斯顿先生知道这件事。请你在开盘时，用这些钱买婆罗洲锡业公司的股票。”

哈利接过钱后，答应她不会对外透露半点儿消息，然后在开盘的时候替我妻子买了100股。我猜测她买的时候股价是108。那天，这只股票特别活跃，收盘的时候上涨了3个点。我妻子对自己的出手不凡感到非常高兴，因此她费了九牛二虎之力，才能够按捺住，不跟我说出这件事情。

无巧不成书，我一直觉得那个时候的市场整体不景气，婆罗洲锡业公司不正常的表现让我有所警惕。我觉得还不是任何股票上涨的时候，于是决定卖空，一次性就卖了1万股婆罗洲锡业公司股票。如果那天我没卖的话，它那天应该能上涨五六个点，而不是3个点。

第二天开盘时，我又卖了2000股，在临收盘的时候，又抛掉了2000股，股价下跌成了102。

又过了一天，哈丁公司棕榈滩经理哈利还在等着我妻子的到来。一般我如果在交易厅内炒股的话，她只能在11点左右才会偷偷去看。

哈利把她拉到一旁说：“利文斯顿夫人，你的那100股要是想保得住的话，就得赶紧再拿钱来。”

“可是我只有那些钱。”她说。

“我可以转到你的常用账户上。”他说。

“不。”她不愿意，“这样的话，我家先生就会知道。”

“可是，你新开的账户已经亏了。”他说。

“但我也确切地对你说过，我不想亏损更多的钱。我连那500美元都不想亏掉。”

“我明白，利文斯顿夫人，但是我不能在没得到你的许可时就卖掉，现在除非你授权我继续持有，不然我就要卖掉它了。”

“我那天买的时候行情不是很好嘛。”她说，“这么快就成这样，简直难以相信。你说呢？”

“对，我也不相信啊。”哈利说。在交易所做事的人必须八面玲珑。

“哈利先生，到底是什么原因啊？”

哈利非常清楚状况，可他说了以后就把我交代出来了，客户们的交易都是非常保密的。所以他只能说：“我也不知道到底是什么情况。哎呀，跌下去了！已经跌到这波低点了！”他指着股市行情牌说。

我的妻子看着下跌的股票行情，大声说：“天哪，哈利先生，我不想损失我那500美元，这可怎么办呢？”

“利文斯顿夫人，如果我是你的话，就去咨询利文斯顿先生。”

“啊，这可不成。他从来不让我炒股，他早就对我讲过，我要是问他，他就会知道情况。我之前可从没偷偷这么做过，我可不敢啊。”

“没关系，”哈利安慰道，“利文斯顿先生是个厉害的投资人，他知道该怎么解决。”她一边听着一边摇头，他又蛊惑道，“不行的话，你再拿出1000美元来挽回你的股票吧。”

遇到这样左右为难的情况，她只能在公司附近徘徊，情况越来越糟糕了，她只得来到我坐着看行情的地方，对我说，她想单独跟我说几句。我们来到私人会话厅，她告诉了我整个事情的来龙去脉。我只能对她说：“你可真笨，再别做这种事情了。”

她说她以后再也不这么干了，我就又给她500美元，她开心地离开了。此时的股价正好是票面价格100美元。

我知道为什么会这样。维森斯坦老奸巨猾，他认为我妻子会把他说的话对我讲，而我就会去研究这只股票。他了解我对这样的事情有多感兴趣，人们都知道我对能赚大钱的交易很在行。我估计他觉得我会买个一两万股的。

这是我经历过的设计最精心最有鼓动性的消息，只是它失灵了，也必然会失灵。首先，我妻子听到这个消息的时候，恰好手里有500美元，所以她具备比以往更大的冒险资本。她想要靠这点儿钱去获利，女人的特质使她不能控制这个小诱惑为她带来的向往情绪。她也清楚我不会同意她这个外行去炒股，所以没对我说。维森斯坦千算万算，只是没算准她的心理。

维森斯坦根本不了解我。我从来不关心内幕消息，我在整个股市都是卖空状态。他觉得那是个诱惑我去买婆罗洲锡业公司股票的好手段，他假传内幕消息，股价也上涨了3个点，他以为我会去买。却不知这正好是我决定放空整个市场时把婆罗洲锡业公司作为起步的原因。

听了妻子的话，我想卖掉那只股票的决心更坚定了。每天早上开盘和下午收盘时，我都会卖掉一些，直到我认定能获得不错的利润时，才会回补空头。

我觉得，靠内幕消息玩股票是非常愚蠢的做法。我认为我骨子里就不喜欢打听内幕消息。我有时觉得那些喜欢内幕消息的人就像喝多了酒一样。有的人架不住消息的传播带给自己的那种快感，总希望处在那种自以为与幸福关联的迷醉状态中。竖起耳朵听内幕消息，是非常容易的事情。在你很容易照办的情况下，让别人告诉你怎么做才能快乐，是世界上第二好的事情，只比快乐本身差一点儿，是实现你心愿很漫长的第一步。这不太像那种眼瞎心急的贪欲，更确切地说是因为懒于动脑而受到了自我限制。

不光是业余的股民们喜欢追寻内幕消息，那些纽交所里非常专业的投机人也在这方面非常投入。我很清楚，其中就有一部分人特别想听我对股市的看法，因为我从来不对人们说所谓的内幕消息。我如果对谁说：“卖掉你手里的5000股钢铁股票吧。”他必定会听从。但是，我如果对他讲，我做的是空头，就算理由非常充分，他也难以听进去，我说完后他还会怒气冲冲，嫌我只说些对行情的看法，而没有直接告诉他一个很明了的消息，耽误了他的时间，根本与华尔街上的大多数人不一样，不是个好心的人。在华尔街，那样的人处处可见，他们喜欢把几百万放到朋友、熟人甚至陌生人的口袋中。

人们都很希望奇迹出现，因为他们对希望抱着特别大的幻想，很大一部分人会不时地陷入希望的巨大泥淖中。我们很清楚，我们看见的那些酒鬼，都是些明显的乐观派，是对内幕消息抱着巨大向往的人。

我认识一个纽交所的经纪人，他觉得我是个很自私冷血的人，因为我从不向别人说一些内幕消息，或者拉朋友一起玩。好多年前的一天，他跟一个记者聊天，那个记者随意说起自己得到了一个值得相信的内幕消息：GOH股票会上涨。于是他马上买了1000股，没想到还没来得及止损就赔了3.5万美元。过了一两天，他又遇到了那个记者，就非常生气。

“太糟糕了，你告诉我的那个消息简直糟透了。”他怨愤地说。

“什么消息啊？”记者问，他居然不记得了。

“就是关于GOH股票的消息啊，你说非常可靠的。”

“我确实说了，是这家公司的一个董事兼财务委员会成员告诉我的。”

“是哪个人？”他问。

“你要是想知道的话，”记者说，“告诉你，是你的老丈人威斯莱克先生。”

“可恶，你为什么不早说呢？”这个经纪人大喊起来，“你害得我赔了3.5万美元。”他不相信他们家族提供的内幕消息，他觉得离这个内幕消息的源头越远，可靠性越高。

老威斯莱克是个成功的银行家，也是个富有的股票商人。有一天，他巧遇了约翰·盖茨，盖茨向他打听内幕消息，老威斯莱克野蛮地说：“你要是听了我的内幕消息后能照办，那我就说；如果不的话，那就别浪费时间了。”

“当然要照办啊。”盖茨笑嘻嘻地打包票。

“把里丁公司的股票卖了。会有25个点的赚头，或许还更多呢。反正至少保证25个点。”威斯莱克确信地说道。

“非常感谢。”这位动不动就要与人赌个100万的盖茨和威斯莱克握手道别，然后朝自己的公司走去。

威斯莱克专门研究过里丁公司的股票，对这个公司非常了解，而且也有内线，所以对他而言，这家股票没有什么秘密，谁都知道他有这么张底牌。此时，他建议这位号称“西部投机人”的盖茨卖掉里丁的股票。

可是，里丁公司的股票在不断上涨，没几周就几乎涨了100个点。一天，老威斯莱克又与盖茨在街上碰面了，他装作没有看到他，赶紧朝前走去。想不到盖茨追上他，春风得意地伸手过来，威斯莱克不知所措地和他握了握。

“很感谢你上次跟我说的关于里丁公司股票的内幕消息。”盖茨说。

“我可没对你说过什么内幕消息。”威斯莱克皱眉说道。

“你说过的。就是你的那条内幕消息让我赚钱了，6万美元啊。”

“赚6万？”

“是啊，你忘了？你让我卖掉里丁公司股票，所以我买进了。威斯莱克啊，我总是把赌注下在你提供的消息的反面上。”盖茨开心地说，“一直是这样。”

威斯莱克瞅着这个得意的西部投机人，嫉妒地说：“盖茨，我如果有你那么明智，就会有很多钱可赚。”

有一天，我遇到著名的漫画家罗杰斯先生。华尔街的经纪人都很喜欢他的那些与华尔街有关的漫画。多年以来，他那些刊登在《先锋报》上的漫画，为无数人带来了乐趣。他告诉我一则故事。在美国和西班牙打仗之前的一天傍晚，他和一个经纪人朋友聊完天分手时，那人从衣帽架上取下自己的礼帽，至少他觉得那是他自己的帽子，因为不光形状相同，而且戴着也合适。

当时，华尔街想的和谈的都是和西班牙作战的话题，能不能打起来呢？如果能打起来，股价必定下跌。不光我们美国人会卖出股票，那些手持美国证券的欧洲人也会抛出更多。如果不打仗，就需要买进股票，因为股市下跌严重，都是那些喜欢煽风点火的报纸引发的。罗杰斯接着说了这个故事的后半部分：

“前一天晚上，我在我那位经纪人朋友的家里度过。第二天，他还站在交易大厅，焦灼地判断到底该买还是该卖。他权衡了做多头还是做空头的种种理由，就是没办法确定哪些消息可靠，哪些消息是谣言。当时，已经没有更加信得过的消息了。他一阵儿觉得战争会打起来，一阵儿又觉得不可能打。可能是因为这样的焦虑心理让他身体发热，他拿下礼帽去擦头上的汗。他没法决定到底是买还是卖。

“恰好他看了一眼礼帽，里面有金色的‘战争’（注：WAR，罗杰斯全名的缩写，正好是战争的英文）字样，这就是他需要的提示。这不就是上帝通过帽子向他传达的指示吗？所以他卖出了大量股票。战争的消息真的传来了，他在下跌的股市中回补，赚了很多钱。”罗杰斯最后说了一句话，“我的那顶帽子一直没要回来。”

但是我知道的有关依靠内幕消息获得利润的故事里，有一个是关于纽交所资深成员胡德的。一天，一个叫波特·沃克的经纪人对胡德说，他因为给南大西洋铁路公司的一个董事帮了个忙，那位董事告诉了他一些内幕消息，让他大量买进南大西洋的股票。该公司的董事们正在想方设法让股票上涨至少25个点，所有董事都没有参与这件事情，但他们大多数都保证会赞成这么做。

波特·沃克确信公司的配股比率会提高。他将消息说给胡德听。他们两人就分别买进了几千股。这只股票在他们买进前和买进后一直不景气，可是胡德却觉得这样的情况显然是要让内线集团有机会吸进股票，而这个集团由感激波特·沃克的朋友负责。

到了下周四，南大西洋铁路公司的董事们在收盘后开会，确定了配股情况。周五早上开盘后这只股票在六分钟里就跌了6个点。

波特·沃克可被气坏了，他去找那个董事，这位董事也非常难过，后悔得不得了。他说他忘了对波特·沃克说过让买进的事情，所以就没告诉他，董事会主要成员们已经改变了计划。这位董事懊悔极了，想急于补偿自己造成的过失，所以又给波特·沃克透露了一个内幕消息。他好心地说，跟他当初的判断相反，他的同事们想廉价买进股票，他只能听他们的意见。现在，他们都买得过多，股价必定会上涨。现在买南大西洋铁路的股票，是恰逢其时。

波特·沃克不光不再怪罪他，还跟这个很有地位的商人热情地握手道别。然后他顺理成章地去找自己的朋友，就是跟着他亏损了的胡德。他们再次准备大捞一把。他们之前就得到消息，说这只股票一定上涨，他们也买进了股票，可是现在这只股票下跌了。情形很明显。因此他们合起来买了5000股。

当他们买进后，股票就暴跌了，明显是内线卖压。这两个内行证实了自己的判断，胡德卖掉了他们合买的5000股。波特·沃克对他说：“如果不是那个该死的浑蛋前天去了佛罗里达，我要打得他满地找牙。是的，我会这么做，你跟我来。”

“去哪儿？”胡德问他。

“去电报局。我要给那个畜生发电报，让他记住一辈子。咱们走吧。”

胡德跟着波特·沃克去了电报局。5000股让他们损失了一大笔。因为气愤难忍，波特·沃克精心写了一份骂人的电报，然后读给胡德听，读完后他说：“我要让他很快知道，我对他的看法到底是怎样的。”

当他正要把电报递给发报员时，胡德说：“算了吧，波特。”

“怎么了？”

“我不想发了。”胡德说得很诚恳。

“这是为什么？”波特·沃克大声问。

“这会把他惹得大发雷霆的。”

“我们不就是想要这样的结果吗？”波特一脸惊讶地看着胡德。

胡德还是摇着头认真地说：“如果你发了电报，我们就再不会得到他的内幕消息了。”

这个故事确实是一个专业的投机人对我讲的。唉，聊那些听从内幕消息的笨蛋有何意义！大家接受内幕消息不是因为他们很愚蠢，而是因为他们喜欢我刚才说的由希望做成的鸡尾酒。罗斯柴尔德男爵致富的方法，远远要比投机来得实惠，有人问他在股市里赚钱是不是特别难，他说正好相反，是很容易的事情。

“那是因为你很富有啊。”提问的人说。

“不是。我找到个简便的办法，然后坚持去实行。我简直是无法控制地在赚钱。如果你想知道，我就告诉你奥秘，就是从不在股市处于低谷时买进，而且卖的时候要快。”

投资人各式各样，很多人喜欢存货清单、盈利统计和各种数字，似乎这些代表了事实和确定不会变动的东西。人为的因素也都被量化。很少数的人喜欢一个人经营。但是我认识的最聪明的投资者，是一个德裔宾夕法尼亚人，他勇闯华尔街，和拉塞尔·塞奇性格很像。

他是一个伟大的调研员，一个不屈不挠的人。他相信自己提出的问题，相信眼见为实，他不愿意用其他人的眼睛看世界。这是很多年前的事情了。他似乎持有不少艾奇逊的股票。不久前，他听到了很多关于该公司和公司高层十分令人不安的消息。他得知，该公司总裁，被传说为商业天才的莱茵哈特先生并不名副其实，反而是个恣意妄为、鲁莽草率的人，搞得公司一团糟。等到无法避免的清算时刻到来时，定会有数不清的麻烦需要应付。

正是这样的新闻，令这个德裔宾夕法尼亚人立刻活跃了起来。他匆匆赶往波士顿，面见莱因哈特先生，当面问了他一些问题。会面过程中，他转述了听到的那些指控，然后问这位艾奇逊—托皮卡—圣塔菲铁路公司的总裁，这些是不是真的。

莱因哈特先生不仅坚决否认了所有指控，还说了很多别的事情：他用数字证明了所有这一切都是恶毒的谎言。德裔宾夕法尼亚人已经询问了有关精确信息的问题，而总裁也回答了他，向他展示了公司的运作状况和财务状况，详细到一美分是怎么流转的。

德裔宾夕法尼亚人谢过莱因哈特先生，回到纽约，迅速将他持有的艾奇逊的股票都卖掉了。一个星期后，他用闲置的资金购买了一大笔特拉华—拉卡瓦纳—西部联合公司的股票。

几年后，我们谈到幸运的换股操作的时候，他谈到自己的这次经历。他解释说到底是什么促成了他如此行事。

他说：“是这样子，我注意到莱因哈特总裁先生，在写下数字的时候，从他的红心桃木办公桌的活动桌板上的文件筐中拿了几页信纸出来。那是一种非常高级的重磅亚麻信纸，纸上印着双色的抬头，十分华丽。这种信纸并不仅仅是非常昂贵，而是昂贵得毫无必要。他在一张纸上写下了几个数字，向我展示公司某些部门到底盈利多少，或是他们如何削减开支，降低成本，然后他把那昂贵的信纸揉成一团，丢进了废纸篓里。不一会儿，他又想让我了解他们正在推行的经营策略，于是又扯了一页漂亮的有双色抬头的信纸，写了几个数字，大功告成后，又丢进了废纸篓里。太多钱就这么不过脑子地浪费掉了。如果总裁如此的话，那他几乎不可能去鼓励甚至奖励勤俭节约的员工。因此，我相信人们跟我讲这位总裁先生是个铺张浪费的人这件事是真的，而没有去听信总裁描绘的图景，于是我卖掉了艾奇逊的股票。

“而几天后，当我走入特拉华—拉卡瓦纳—西部联合公司的时候，事情也是类似的。他们的总裁是老萨姆·斯罗恩，他的办公室就在靠近大门的地方，办公室门大开着，而且一直开着。任何人只要走进公司大门，就可以看到他们的总裁坐在办公桌后；任何人只要走进去，就会立刻和他一起投入生意当中。财经记者对我说，他们和老萨姆·斯罗恩从来都不需要拐弯抹角，从来都是有话直说，斯罗恩也都是正面回答问题，不论其他董事会成员在股票市场有什么危机。

“我去的时候，老先生正在忙着，我起初以为他是在拆信，但是等我走入办公室，走到办公桌跟前，才看清楚他在做什么。后来，我得知这其实是他的日常习惯。在把信件归类拆阅后，他没有把空信封扔掉，而是拿到自己的办公室，闲暇的时候，他把信封拆开，然后用信封的内里空白的一面当作便笺。他把这些纸放在旁边，当需要时便派上用场，就如同莱因哈特先生用他的印刷亚麻信纸一样。空信封、总裁的闲暇时间都没有半点儿浪费。一切资源都被合理利用。

“我心中一动，这家公司能有这样的总裁，那整个公司所有部门都会厉行节约的。总裁会推行这样的作风。当然，我还了解到这家公司生产效益良好。于是我便用所有的流动资金购买了他们的股票。到现在，股票的市值已经翻倍又翻倍，我每年的收入都相当于最初的原始投资的总额。现在我依然还持有特拉华—拉卡瓦纳—西部联合公司的股票，而就在我看到莱因哈特总裁用双色印刷抬头的昂贵亚麻信纸向我举数字证明他一点儿都不浪费然后丢进废纸篓的事情几个月后，那些股票就转到了其他人手中。”

这个故事打动人的地方是它很真实，而且事实也证明，那位德裔宾夕法尼亚人所购买的其他所有股票带来的盈利都比不上特拉华—拉卡瓦纳—西部联合公司。

第十七章

我有一位好朋友，他最喜欢对别人说，他觉得我有种灵验的第六感。他说这个第六感可以在不用分析的情况，就知道该如何去做，我只要随意地听从那些神秘力量的驱使，就能够恰逢其时地从股市中抽身出来。他在早餐桌上最扬扬自得的言论与一只猫有关。他说那只猫告诉我，卖掉手里那些股票。我听了猫传达的消息后，心情沮丧，焦躁不安，直到我卖掉了牛市时期买来的所有股票，才安静了下来。如此，我才能在股价最高的时候卖掉，也就自然而然地证明了那位固执朋友的第六感理论。

我那时候在华盛顿，试图努力说服几个议员，让他们明白对我们大量收税是错误的，当时我并没有在股市上花费多少心力。我突然卖掉了手里的股票，才让朋友那奇怪的说法越发成真了似的。

我承认，确实在某些时候会出现一种难以控制的愿望，想在股市上有所动作。而这与我做多或放空股票没有什么关系。我一定要从市场中跳出来才会感到安心。我个人觉得，这次卖掉手中的股票，是因为我看到了很多警示性的小现象。或许，并没有一个很清晰的能给我一个明确答案的有力的指示信号，刺激我去做突然要做的事情。更可能的是，这就是人们嘴里经常所说的那种“炒股灵感”。老投机分子说，詹姆斯·凯恩和他之前的很多前辈曾经确实把自己身上的那种炒股灵感培养得很出色。我承认，这样的警示最后不但会被证明是非常健全的警告，而且时机能够掌握得一丝不差。不过在刚才这个特例中，没什么第六感存在，也与一只黑猫没什么关系。朋友对谁都说我起床后非常焦躁不安，我想如果我真的坐立不安的话，原因是我很失望。我知道我没有说服与我见面的国会议员，委员会对于课征股市税赋的问题，看法和我不同。我不是要阻止或者逃脱股市上的税收，只是按照一个经验丰富的老炒股手所想的，提出公平又明理的税收方式，我想让政府不要急着杀害在公平层面上能够生出金蛋的鹅。或许是我没有成功劝告他，从而让自己很烦躁，也让我对这个受到不公平税收的业务深感悲观。但是，我会告诉你到底发生了什么事情。

在这一次牛市开始时，我对钢铁和铜的股市行情非常看好，觉得应该做多头。所以我下手积攒股票，一开始买了5000股犹他州铜矿公司的股票，后来又停了下来，感觉股市行情波动不太对。意思是，这只股票变现出来的行情状况，与我对它的感觉不符，买进并不是聪明的做法。我想我是按照114美元的价格买进的。同时，我也按照基本差不多的价格，买了美国钢铁公司的股票，它的情况比较明朗，头天我就按照我以前的那种方式，买了2万股。

钢铁股市持续对路，所以我也一直在买进，直到手里积攒了7.2万股才罢手。但是我手里的犹他州铜矿公司的股票还是一开始买进的那些，一直没有多于5000股。它的行情不好，我没有多买一些的理由。

所有人都很清楚行情，我们处于牛市。我知道股价要上涨，整体来说前景很好。就在股价整体上涨活跃，同时我的账面利润非常可观的时候，行情记录还表现出“还不到时候啊，还不到时候”的状态。我在华盛顿时，行情还是这样的表现。不过，就在那天晚一些的时候，我还能去做多头，可我不想再买进增加头寸了。这期间，股市的前进方向显然跟我的想法一致，我都不必成日坐在行情记录牌跟前，期待着遇到个什么情况然后卖出股票。在退守的号角吹起之前，除非忽然出现所料不及的大事情，不然股市就会停滞不前，或者以其他的方式，让我做好准备，应付突然反转的投机情势。我能轻松愉快地跟议员们讨论事情，就是鉴于这个原因。

同时，股价持续在涨高，这说明多头市场正在走向结束。我不能确定到底什么时候结束，这是我没办法做到的事情。但我不需要对你讲，你就会明白，我一直对此非常留意。无论如何，现在我还是老样子，我做事的习惯已经养成了。

我不能保证，但我非常怀疑，在我抛出所有股票的前一天，还是有些警示的。我看到股市在高位上滞留，于是就考虑到了我手里的股票数量和利润，这确实不是个小数目。后来，我想到我白花了精力去试图影响立法者们，希望他们对华尔街上的股票交易纳税更明智公平一些，可能那时候就这样在我心中埋下了种子。我一晚上都处在这样下意识的状态中。早上，我想起股市，也不清楚它会怎样发展。到了交易大厅，我看到的不是上涨的价格，而是我能得到的不菲的利润和吸收力非常强悍的市场。面对这样的市场，我能够卖掉任意多的股票。当然，一个人手持数量庞大的股票就得随时注意买卖的机会，好把账面上的利润换成正儿八经的现金。在买卖过程中，要尽量不让利润减少。我的经验是，一个人总是不缺乏让利润变现的机会，而且机会总是出现在股市行情走向快要结束的时候。这可不是什么研究行情记录的能力，或者对股市走向的第六感。

那天早上，当市场出现一个让我不费吹灰之力就能卖出股票的时机时，我及时出手了。你在出清持投的时候，卖掉50股和5万股一样需要聪明勇敢，可是在市场不景气的时候，卖掉50股不会致使股价下滑，但卖出5万股就不一样了。我手里有美国钢铁公司的7.2万股，这不算什么大数量的持股，不过也不能卖掉这么多还不会使账面上看起来能获得的那些利润遭受损失，这种损失会与你银行里存着的钱一样，亏损了会让你一样心痛。

我的利润大概有150万美元，股市行情好的时候，我拥有这些利润，可这不能成为我觉得卖掉对了的理由。市场会为我证明对不对，这一点我也确实很满意。是这样的：我把手中美国钢铁公司的7.2万股全部卖掉了，卖出的平均价格恰好比这天股市行情的最高价低了不到1个点。这就说明我做得非常符合时机。但是就在当天的同一小时里，我卖掉5000股犹他州铜矿公司股票时价格跌了5个点。你想啊，我可是同时买进的这两只股票啊。我非常聪明地把美国钢铁公司的股票从2万股增持到了7.2万股，同样我也聪明地没有增持犹他州铜矿的股票。我之前之所以没有卖掉犹他州铜矿的股票，是因为我看好铜矿业，而市场也是多头市场，就算我用它赚不到钱，也不会因为它而赔掉多少。这里面确实没有灵感之说。

股民们在炒股中受到的训练就像医学教育一般。医生们必须要花费很长时间去学习解剖、生理、药物和另外很多的课程。他们学会这些理论后，开始终生行医。他们对各种疾病引发的病情察言观色后进行分类，学会诊断病情。一旦靠着精确的观察诊断对了，接下来就该更好地防治了。不过要牢牢记住，人是没办法不犯错的，同时还会遇到各种突发性事件的影响，使得诊断不可能百分百正确。其后，他们会逐渐积累更丰富的经验，不但知道怎样做正确的事情，而且会在片刻之间这样做，因此很多人认为医生靠直觉行事。而这真的不是反射动作，而是他通过很多年以来对病人情况的熟悉而逐步学会的。而且当病情得以诊断后，他是利用经验告诉他的正确治疗疾病的方法去进行后续工作的。人们能够学习到知识，比如你可以专门用卡片索引来传播你搜集到的知识点，可是经验这种东西就没办法传承。人们可能会明白该干什么，但是如果速度赶不上，还是要赔本的。

一个成功的股票交易者，靠的就是观察、经验、记忆、数学。他既需要准确地观察，也需要牢记自己观察到的结果。他不能在没有依据的事情或者意料之外的情况下去赌。无论他自己多么坚信没有依据的东西，也不管人们对预料之外的情况多么看好，他都要把宝押在可能性上，也就是说他要预测这些可能。在这样的投资游戏里，那些长年累月的行动、连续不断的研究、牢不可破的记忆，能够让人在可以或不能预料的情况发生的时候，都能够及时采取应对措施。

人能够具备很强的数学能力和对事物进行精确观察的能力，可如果他没有多少经验和记忆的储备，仍然会失败。而且，睿智的商人也要像随着科学进展而进步的医生那样，不停地研究整个大势，追踪各种可能对市场走向起到影响作用的发展情况。在这里面打拼几年后，他会养成保持信息灵通的好习惯，他差不多要能够自发地行动起来。他要修炼成珍贵的专业态度，这一点能够让他在行业内不断地成功。专业的炒股手和业余的炒股手，以及偶然玩一次的人之间有很大区别，强调这个差别也不是过分的事。比如我就发现数学和记忆对我帮助很大。数学是华尔街交易商赚钱的基本功，我是说，华尔街就是靠处理数字和事实来赚钱的。

身为交易商，就要时刻保持消息灵通，用纯粹的专业态度来看待整个市场和股市的走向。我只想再次强调：灵感和神秘的看盘能力与最终的成功没有半点儿关系。不过，这样的事情经常出现，经验丰富的交易商反应迅速，以至于没有多余的时间说明所有判断来由，可这些来由是很值得借鉴的，是建立在事实基础上的，而这些事实是他靠着多年的经验，在所有的工作当中，通过观察与思考收集来的，他把每件事情都盘算得清清楚楚。现在，我来说一下，我所指的专业态度是什么意思。

我一直关注着期货市场的动向，这是多年养成的习惯。就像你知道的那样，从政府的各类报道中可以分析出，今年冬小麦的种植量与去年持平，春小麦的种植量比1921年要大。种植情势好很多，我们可能会更早些得到收获。我了解了大致的情形，用数字预算了产量后，马上想到了煤铁工人的罢工。我一直在想着与市场相关的所有因素，所以也就不自觉地想到了这个。我觉得对各地的货物运输已经造成了影响的罢工事件，必定会波及小麦价格。我觉得，罢工引发了交通障碍，冬小麦的运输会被拖延，等到运输状态好点儿以后，春小麦就到了准备运输的时候。这就是说，铁路能够大量运输小麦时，一定会把延后运到市场的冬小麦和提早收成的春小麦一起运来。这意味着小麦会大量进入市场。这是非常明显的事实，那些跟我一样善于观察的交易商肯定不想在这段时间买进小麦。只有当小麦价格跌得差不多，购买能够产生很好的利润，他们才会买。市场没人买，麦价就会跌。这样考虑之后，我必须要搞清自己对不对。就像凯恩说的那句话：“在你赚到钱之前，什么都难说。”市场不景气了，就要及时地卖出，不能浪费时间。

我的经验是，交易商最好的指路牌就是市场的运动方式，正如医生为病人望闻问切一样。

正常的时候，一个人应该能在价格差距在1/4美分的范围内，买卖100万蒲式耳的小麦。那天，我卖了25万蒲式耳小麦去检验市场，了解操作时机，结果价格跌了1/4美分。那时候，这个情况对我来说不够明确，我就又卖了25万蒲式耳。我发现每次都是被人分批少量买走的。这就是说，买盘是由1万或5000蒲式耳的很多单子凑成，而不像以往那样两三笔就买完。除了这样零散的买卖外，由于我的卖出，价格下跌了1又1/4美分。此时我必须要说，市场吸纳小麦与小麦价格下跌是不对等的，这说明市场已没了购买力。这就是真实情况，那怎么办？那就再往外卖。按照经验行事，可能偶尔会让你出错，但不按照经验行事，就是个笨蛋。所以我卖掉了200万蒲式耳小麦，价格下跌更快了。几天后，市场迫使我又卖了200万，价格继续下降。又过了几天，小麦价格开始暴跌，每蒲式耳下跌6美分后还在跌。有时有点儿回稳，可只是一瞬，然后又会下跌。

我在此时没有遵照第六感行事，也没人对我讲什么内幕消息，而是我专业的市场观察力帮我实现了盈利。这也是我多年经商总结的经验。我做的是投资，就要深入研究。行情表明我的想法没错，我需要做的就是加大投入。我就是这么做的，事情也是这么发展的。

在这样的交易里，经验是可以带来稳定效益的，而要得到最好的市场信息就需要观察。你想弄清楚某只股票行情，就要一直观察。然后经验会告诉你，如何从跟平常不同的变化中获利，也就是说从可能性中获利。比如，我们知道股票的波动方式并不单一，可所有股票在多头时上涨，在空头时下跌，这却是很普遍的。这也是自发性的内幕消息里最常见的一个，股票交易所很清楚这点，它向所有不深思这个问题的股民传达这一信息。我的意思是，它总建议股民们买卖同一类股票里低迷的那个。所以，按照逻辑判断，若美国钢铁公司的股票上涨，其他几家钢铁公司也会跟着涨，只是时间先后的问题。交易状况和前景对同类股票中的所有股票都一样，市场带来的好处是惠及所有股票的。按照理论，哪只股票都有情况好的时候，这一点已经被市场验证过了。股民们会买这家没有上涨的钢铁股票，是因为另外两家钢铁股票都已经涨价了。

就算在多头市场，若哪只股票的发展与市场不相符，我就不会买。有时候，我在完全可以肯定的多头市场时买一只股票，可同时看到这类股票的其他股票没有涨高，我就会卖掉这只股票。原因何在？经验告诉我，与那种被我叫作明显类股倾向相违背是不明智的。我不能光靠能确定的东西，也要想到各种可能并且做出预估。有个老前辈曾对我说过：“如果我沿着一条铁轨走路，看见火车以100公里每小时的速度朝我驶来，我还要继续前行吗？朋友，我要躲到一边。我甚至不会因此而夸奖自己。”

去年，在多头市场里，我注意到在某一个类股中，有个股票与同类的其他股票走向不相符，可是这类股票中除了它以外，其他的都跟着整体股市在上涨。我买了很多布莱克·伍德汽车公司的股票。很多人都知道，这个公司发展繁荣，每天的涨幅都在1到3个点，股民们买得越来越多了。这只股票颇受关注，其他汽车公司的股票也跟着上涨。可是，切斯特汽车的股票却很落后，所以没多久人们就议论纷纷。他们拿切斯特的低股价与其他汽车股票的活跃上涨进行比较，也自然会向那些喜欢涉足内幕消息的人或者自以为明智的人打听，然后开始买进切斯特股票，他们觉得它会跟其他汽车股票一样上涨。

股民们买了切斯特的股票，但它并没上涨，而且还下跌了。其实在这样的多头市场中，要拉抬这只股票的价格毫无困难。想想看，在汽车股票中，布莱克·伍德是上涨最厉害的股票之一。而且，我们听到的全是人们对各式汽车需求量增加的消息，全是产量创纪录的新闻。

事情很清楚，切斯特公司内线集团在当时股市上涨时没有做应该做的事情——拉抬股价。这本是正常情况下该做的，没做的原因可能有两个，一个可能是他们想在上涨前多积攒些股票，所以没有力推，可假如你分析一下它的交易量和情势，就会知道这是个很白痴的理由。另一个可能是他们担心拉抬股价会吸进股票。

那些本来需要股票的人却不想要，那我为什么还要呢？我觉得，不管其他汽车公司的股票多么景气，卖掉切斯特总是很必然的事，因为我的经验就是要防范那些跟同类不相符的股票。

我非常容易地证实，切斯特公司没有内部买进，而且相反还有内部的人在卖出。另外也有警告我不要买切斯特股票的其他讯息，不过我只需要知道它与市场不相符的消息，这个是市场行情记录告诉我的，也是我卖掉它的原因。几天后，切斯特股票暴跌。后来我从官方渠道听说，因为公司内部人员知道情况不好，一直在卖股票。跟以往一样，股价下跌后，原因才会人尽皆知。可是，在股价下跌前就有迹象表明了的。我不注重下跌本身，只看各种前期征兆，我不清楚切斯特到底怎么回事，也没跟着感觉走，只是知道其中一定有不对劲的地方。

几天前，我看到报纸说，圭亚那金矿公司股票变动很厉害，在场外按照50美元左右交易，然后在证券交易所挂牌上市。刚刚挂牌时的交易价格大概是35美元，然后就开始下跌，一直下跌到了20美元以下。

我不会认为这样的下跌耸人听闻，因为本就是意料之中的事情，如果有质疑，可以去查看这家公司的发展史，不知道有多少人清楚这件事。人们这么对我说了其中的情形：这家公司组成了一个炒作集团，成员由六个著名的资本家和一家实力派银行共同组成，有个成员是贝尔岛勘探公司的老板，这家公司向圭亚那公司贷了1000多万美元的款，作为交易就得到了四分之一的股份和一些其他合约。这只股票配股后上市，也经过了大力宣传。贝尔岛勘探公司想兑现手中的股票，所以邀请银行家来探讨他们拥有的那四分之一的股份，也就是25万股。银行家采取措施卖出了这些股票，同时还卖了手中的其他股票。他们想委托一个专业人士去做这件事，回报就是把25万股按照比36美元高的价格卖掉后，得到其中三分之一的利润。我清楚，这个协议确定后在签字时，银行家却决定要自己来做，从而节省需要付出的酬劳。所以他们内部指派了个团队。他们要求那25万股按照36美元从贝尔岛勘探公司手中成交，再以41美元上市。也就是说，他们给自己的银行同伙们支付了5美元的利润，然后才开始放入市场去操作。我不知道他们是不是清楚这一点。

对这家银行来说，情形很明显，这次销售作业从各方面看来都是十拿九稳。市场成了多头，圭亚那公司旗下的这类股票在股市上处于前端地位，他们获得了很大的利润，支付了股息。这一情形再加上主办银行的名声很好，股民们觉得圭亚那金矿公司的股票完全适合去投资。我听说大概有40万股涨到了47美元后被出售给大众。

黄金股票的股价上涨形势很不错，可是没多久圭亚那就又下跌了10个点。假若当时公司内部还在继续行销这只股票这也没什么关系。可是，华尔街上不久就收到消息说，情形不是很好，公司的资产不足以支持承销商的高度期望。后来，股价下跌的原因也明了了，可在此之前，我就获得了警示，同时做了应对。这只股票与切斯特汽车股票的情况一样，所以我卖掉了圭亚那公司的股票。价格下跌的时候，我又继续卖，价格愈低。它与切斯特以及我所知的其他十几种有相似情况的股票出现了同样的结果。从行情记录上能明显知悉，公司内部不买股票，他们也明白自己不在多头市场买自家股票的原因。另外来说，不清楚内幕的股民们却在买进，他们觉得这只股票的价格曾上涨到45美元以上，现在按35美元及以下的价格购买就很值，一定会有钱可赚。公司继续配发股利。这只股票现在是便宜货。

接着消息就传出了。像以往重要的市场消息常见的情形类似，当人们知道详情之前，我就已经知道消息了。但是，证实这家公司并没有得到富有的金矿，得到的只是一堆不值钱的乱石的报道，只是让我明白了公司内部为什么很早就卖出股票的原因。我自己不是听到消息才卖出的，在这之前很早我就靠着行情把它卖掉了。我关心的事情与哲学没什么关系，我自己就是个股民，我只寻觅内部买盘的迹象，可这个迹象没出现。我不用知道公司内部在股价下跌时不买的原因，只需要清楚他们的计划中不包含拉高股价就行了。这就能使放空这只股票变得十拿九稳。股民们购买了大概500万股，股票所有权只是让股票从一群期盼止损而卖掉股票的笨蛋手中，转到了一群妄图大赚所以买了股票的笨蛋手中。

我说这些不是对大家买了圭亚那的股票因此赔本和我卖掉这只股票后获利而进行指手画脚，而是想说明对类股进行行情研究是很重要的事情，也想强调大大小小、能力不足的交易者如何忽视这种教训。行情记录的警示不光出现在股市中，在期货市场上也会出现。

在做棉花期货的时候，我经历了一个很有意思的事情。那时候我在股市上做的是空头，在慢慢往外卖，而且赚了钱。同时我也放空了5万包棉花，可是却没怎么重视。后来，我知道棉花期货的首个消息就是赔了25万。我说了，我的股票操作很有意思，而且我的表现也不错，所以我不想分心。关于棉花期货，我是这么想的：“我要等到回调时再平仓。”棉花价格会略微回调，但是在我决定认赔回补的时候，价格反弹了，随后又上涨得更加厉害。所以我就想再等等看吧，又回头操作股票，花心思去交易。最终我结束股票操作，赚了一大笔钱后，就去哈特温泉休假了。

这是我首次真正闲下来，把心思放在处理棉花期货亏损的问题上。这笔交易对我不利，有很多次甚至到了我马上就能赚到钱的程度。我注意到每次有人大量卖出，棉花价格就会适度回调。但是几乎立刻就反弹，并且创下新高价。

我在温泉度假的这几天，已经亏损了100万，棉花价格还在上涨。我细想我做的事情以及我没做的事情，然后对自己说：“我肯定哪里搞错了。”于是，我就立马决定从棉花期货中撤出来。所以我才平了仓，损失大约100万。

第二天，我心无旁骛地打高尔夫球。在棉花期货上我做错了，也付出了代价，这笔代价的收据就在我的衣袋中装着。我当时和此刻一样，对棉花市场毫不关心。吃午饭的时候，我去交易所看了看期货行情，棉花已经下跌了50点，而这并不能说明什么。关键是，我还看到它的价格跟之前几周有些异样，只要那种特意卖出而打压价格的形势稍微减轻些，价格就会反弹，过去这种情形说明最小阻力价格在上升，而我却视而不见，所以赔了100万。

致使我平仓蒙受了很大损失的原因已经不值得一提，因为那种通常意义上的激烈反弹已经不会有了。所以，我卖掉了1万包棉花，然后蛰伏待机。没多长时间，价格就下跌了50点。我又等了等，价格还是没有反弹，我饥饿难耐，只好去餐厅吃饭。点餐后在等服务员上菜的时候，我猛然一惊，赶紧跑回交易所，看到价格还是没有反弹，所以又卖了1万包。过了一会儿，棉花又下跌了40美分，这让我很开心，说明我的做法没错。我又到餐厅吃了午饭，然后回到经纪人办公室。那天，棉花价格一直没有反弹，晚上我就离开了哈特温泉。

打高尔夫球自然让人高兴，但我卖出棉花和回补棉花的举动都是错误的，所以我必须要回到更适合交易的地方开始忙活了。我第一次卖掉棉花，市场反响不错，这就又使我第二次往外抛了1万包，我从市场吸纳棉花的反应中知道，反转已经到来。这一点在不同的市场行为中都表现出来了。

我到华盛顿后，去了我一位老朋友负责的交易公司。到了那里，行情又下跌了。此时我更能确定，之前做得绝对正确。所以，我接着卖掉了4万包，市场价格跌了75点，这说明在这个价位上市场没法支撑得住。那晚到了收盘的时候，价格还是非常低，原本强劲的买盘力量已经消失了。也不知道棉花期货市场会在什么价位才能再次活跃起来，不过我对自己的明智做法信心十足。次日早上，我坐汽车从华盛顿回到了纽约，不用再那么匆匆忙忙了。

到费城时，我开车去了一家交易公司。我了解了棉花期货市场连一点儿支撑力都没有，价格跌得很严重，出现了一种小型恐慌。我也等不及到纽约了，就给经纪人打了个长途电话，让他替我回补空头头寸。当我接到回报单后，看到我其实已经将前一次赔掉的钱补回来了。我继续上路回纽约，再也没半道上停下车去查看行情。

与我一起在哈特温泉度假的朋友们，后来谈到了那天我在准备吃午餐的时候，忽然一惊跑回交易厅去再次卖掉1万包棉花的事情。显然，这不是什么第六感，而是源于对自己判断力的信任所做出的事。我坚信无论之前怎么出错，现在是到了卖出的时候了。我必须要抓住机会，这是我该利用的机会，下意识中的考量一直没停歇，最终有了良好的结果。在华盛顿的抛售，是我对市场考量的结果。这么多年的经验说明，这次最小阻力线的走向已经从上涨变成下跌。

对于在棉花期货中损失100万的事情，我毫无怨言。我没有因为出现了很大失误而自责，也没有因为在费城弥补回来了损失而得意。我的交易心理只关心交易问题，我觉得自己有理由宣称，我有丰富的经验和牢靠的记忆，因此能够补回一开始赔了的资金。

第十八章

华尔街上历史总在重演。你是否记得我曾讲起过的一个故事，说的是当年斯特雷登在抛空玉米的时候，我怎样去回补空头。有一次，我在股市上也用过类似的办法。这只股票是热带贸易公司的股票，不管我卖出还是买进都赚到过钱。热带贸易公司股票的市场交易一直比较活跃，那些喜欢赌一把的股民最喜欢这只股票。报纸一再指责内线集团，说他们比较关心股价的波动，比较不鼓励长期投资这只股票。一天，我认识的一个高水平营业员说，就算丹尼尔·德鲁在伊利公司股票或者哈弗梅尔在美国糖业公司的股票上，都没有热带贸易公司总裁穆里根和他的朋友们在该公司的股票上那样，使用那么完美的办法，赚取了那么多的钱。他们鼓动空头们放空热带贸易股票，再迅速而直接地把他们轧空。空头们在这样的轧空过程中感觉到的恐惧，不比被水压机压迫身体感觉到的恐惧少，他们一点儿都不装模作样。

当然了，也确实有人说过，在热带贸易公司股票的交易过程中，出现过很多名声不好的事情，可我也敢断定，这么说的那些人曾经都有过被轧空的经历。既然场内交易的人经常会被公司内部的人耍弄，那他们为什么还要玩这个游戏呢？嗯，至少有一个原因，那就是他们都喜欢比较活跃的市场。热带贸易公司的股票确实比较活跃，不存在价格持续不变动的情况。不需要打听或者说明原因，没必要浪费时间，也不必紧张，只要耐心等着行情记录中股价的波动。除非空头部位能够厉害到让股票变得很少、很贵，不然总会有大量股票在交易。这是一只随时都可能令人振奋的股票。

这件事发生在不久之前，我那时候与以往一样，在佛罗里达州度假。我在钓鱼，过得非常愉快。除了每过几天会收到一堆报纸外，完全不去考虑与交易市场有关的事。一天早上，是每周送两次邮件的时候，我看了股票价格，发现热带贸易公司股价为155美元。而上次我看到的时候它大概是140美元。我觉得很快就面临空头市场，我在伺机而动，准备卖空股票。可我不必那么忙着去卖，这也是我为什么只钓鱼而不管股市行情的原因。我一旦看到真正的机会，必定会去利用。同时，无论我做事与否，都不会着急地去赶时间。

从我那天上午收到的报纸看，热带贸易公司出现的情况在市场中并不多见，这事让我对股市综合行情的看淡想法变得更加具体了，因为我觉得在股市行情不太好的时候，公司内部的人去拉抬股价，是非常愚笨的做法。有时，公司内部必须要停止从市场中榨取利润。按照股民们的思维，那些不正常的事情，他们都很讨厌。而我觉得，拉抬这只股票的价格，是种错误做法。没有人能犯这么大的错而不用付出代价，在股市中不会的。

看完报纸后，我又去钓鱼，同时我也一直在想热带贸易公司内部有什么打算。我觉得他们必败无疑，这就如同一个人从20层楼上跳下，却没有带着降落伞一样，粉身碎骨是一定的。我没心思去想别的事情，最后只得放弃了钓鱼，向我的一位经纪人发了一封电报，授权他按照市价卖掉2000股的热带贸易。这么做完后，我才安心去钓鱼。我的成绩很不错。

下午的时候，我收到了回复电报。经纪人说，他们按照153美元的股价，替我卖了2000股热带贸易。此时，一切都很顺利。在股市下跌时放空，这是理所当然的。可我再不能继续钓鱼了，离股市价格显示牌太远了。之所以这么觉得，是因为我需要综合考虑所有的因素，来为热带贸易为什么会跟着综合股市一起下跌，却没有因为公司内部的炒作而逆行上涨找原因。所以我从钓鱼场返回棕榈滩，这样就可以直接与纽约通话了。

到了棕榈滩，我发现他们公司的内部人士还在继续做着抬高股价的错事，于是我就放空，又卖了2000股。等拿到单子后，我接着卖了2000股。市场情况也特别好，因为我的卖出，股价在下跌，所有的表现我都很满意，于是出门去欢快一下，可我也并不特别开心，我在想自己为什么没有卖出更多，因此我又返回交易厅，再次卖掉了2000股。

只有往外卖这只股票时，我才能感到舒坦。不久，我就又卖了1万股，然后做出了回纽约的决定。钓鱼暂且搁在一边，我还有其他事情需要处理。

到纽约后，我开始尽力去了解热带贸易公司的详情，包括现状和未来发展。了解得越多，越让我的信念牢固，我确定他们内部的做法不只是莽撞而已，比这样还糟糕，他们竟然在股市和公司盈余都不利于他们的时候操控抬高股价。

这样形成的一点儿涨势既不是时候也不合理，可那些普通的股民，却跟着买进，而这个小表现也鼓舞了公司内部人，他们继续做着愚蠢的举动。所以我放空更多，内线集团停止了拉抬，我按照自己的方式，多次试探，最终一共放空了热带贸易的3万股，此时的股价是133美元。

有人劝我说，热带贸易公司内部清楚每只股票的下落，而且还知道是谁在做着多大的放空部位，以及其他很重要的信息。他们很有能耐，又很精明，反正与他们对着干是非常危险的做法。可事实就是如此，你最可靠得力的战友是股市行情走向。

当然，从153跌至133时，空头部位增加，那些在回调的时候买进的普通股民与以往一样，说当热带贸易高于153时，人们都觉得很值得买进，现在跌了20个点，那就肯定是更值得买了。股票还是那个股票，利率也没变，经营者和业务都是一样的，这可真是来之不易的大便宜啊！

人们的买进，让在外流通的股票供应变少了，公司内部知道有很多的场内营业员卖掉了这只股，觉得轧空的时机到了，于是巧妙地把股价拉抬到150美元。我能肯定，很多人都在回补，可我就是纹丝不动，我为什么要不安呢？内部人或许清楚还有3万股没有回补，可这也没理由让我害怕。我在153美元开始放空，一直到133美元，促使我一路放空的原因还在，而且比之前更加充分。公司内部可能想逼我回补，可他们没有让我看到更加有说服力的因素。股市的基本状况在替我挡箭。要本着耐心和勇气应对并不是难事，投机必须要对自己和自己的判断充满信心。狄克森·华慈，这位已故的纽约棉花交易所前主席、《投机艺术》的知名作者曾经说过：“能够很自信地按照自己的决定展开行动，这就是投机人的勇气。”我不害怕自己会出错，因为除非事实证明我的确错了，不然我不会觉得自己有错。其实，我只有好好使用自己的经验，才能够心安理得。在有段时间，市场不一定会验证出我犯的错，而只有股票涨跌的情况能验证我的部位的对错。我只能够凭借着自己掌握的知识取胜，如果我失败了，也必定是我的错误造成的。

从133涨到150美元的过程中，什么情况都不会吓着我，让我回补。没过多久，这只股票就跟我预估的一样再次下跌了。跌破了140美元后，公司内部才开始应对，散播了很多跟这只股票相关的利多谣言，说这只股票还会上涨，同时他们也在买进。据说这家公司赚了巨额利润，那些利润足够让他们提高固定利率，而且空头部位好像也很大，这场世纪性的轧空马上开始打击普通空头了，放空特别严重的交易人更会受到特别严重的打击。当他们将股价抬高了10个点的时候，我都说不清听到了多少相关的谣言了。

对我个人来说，这场操控没太大的危险，可在股价到149美元的时候，我就确定，华尔街对所有有关那只股票利多的谣言都信以为真了，传播开来，对我来说并不合适。当然，我或者任何其他外人的话，都不值得那些失措的空头去相信，也不会让交易所那些靠听信内幕消息的无知轻信者相信。效果最好的反击手段，只有股市大盘才能讲得出来，而且只有它才能那样讲。谁都相信股市大盘，而不轻信任何喘气的人所说的话，更不会相信我这个卖了3万股的空头说的话。因此，我用上了在斯特雷登轧空玉米时采取的方式，卖掉燕麦，让交易者们看空玉米，这还是我的经验和记忆在发挥作用。

公司内部抬高股价吓唬那些空头时，我并没有用卖出这只股票的方式设法阻止股价上涨。我已经卖了3万股，在外面流通的股数里占比已经很大了，如果再卖就不是明智之举了。他们这么热心地设好圈套，就等着我把头伸进去。股价第二次反弹，的确就是他们多么想让我入套的表现，我不会自讨苦吃。当热带贸易到了149美元时，我要做的是卖出1万左右赤道商业公司的股票。热带贸易公司在这家的持股非常大。

赤道商业公司股票没热带贸易公司那么活跃，果然不出我所料，我抛售后价格大跌，我自然实现了目的。包括交易厅里那些指望热带贸易公司的多头消息能够畅通无阻的人们在内的所有交易分子看到这样的现状，自然就觉得赤道商业在热带贸易上涨的时候下跌，肯定是有问题，绝对的操控炒作，是为了让公司内部的人出售赤道商业公司的股票，而这样大量的操作肯定是赤道商业公司内部人手里的股票在交易，除此之外没有谁会在热带贸易股票涨势正迅猛的时候，卖掉这么多的股票。所以，人们跟着卖出热带贸易股票，这就遏止了它的上涨势头，公司内部根本不会去支撑那么多抢着卖出股票的人们造成的局面，他们没有了支撑，股价立马下跌。股民和一些大型的交易所也卖了一些赤道商业公司的股票，我回补了赤道商业的空头，赚了一点儿小钱。我卖出的时候想的不是赚钱，而是打击热带贸易股票的上涨势头。

热带贸易公司内部和公关人员持续在华尔街上散播各种该股票要上涨的消息，想把股价拉起来。他们一这么做，我就放空赤道商业股票，并且在赤道商业回调、热带贸易股价下跌时，回补赤道商业的空头部位。这样就有力地打击了他们内部集团的操作。热带贸易的股价最终跌到了125美元，放空部位非常大，公司内部能将股价上拉20至25个点，由于空头确实很大，这样的涨势很合理。只是，我预测到了这样的小反弹，但却没去回补，我不想失去自己的头寸。赤道商业配合热带贸易上涨的时候，我又卖出了一大把赤道商业股，取得的效果也与前面一样，让人们看清了热带贸易利多消息的真面目——这只股票经过猛烈上涨后，多头消息又充斥坊间了。

此时，股市大盘回归疲软，正如我之前所讲，我是相信即将要进入熊市了，才在佛罗里达钓鱼的时候就开始往外放空。至于其他股票，我也卖出了不少，不过热带贸易是我的最爱。整体股市在最后变得不堪重负，热带贸易内部也没办法再抵挡，于是股价大跌。这是它多年以来首次跌破120美元，然后又跌到了110美元以下，最后跌破面值，而我还是没有回补。有一天，市场非常疲弱，热带贸易跌破了90美元。我凭借与以往一样的理由，在市场的混乱中回补了。我抓住了机会——市场交易量巨大，行情不好，抛售市场比买进市场大很多。就算被你认为是没意思的自吹自擂，我也要告诉你，我基本上在跌到最低点的时候，回补了我的3万股。只是，我之前没想过要在跌势最低时回补，只是想把账面上的利润套现，在套现过程中不失去太多的利润。

整个过程我都把控得很平稳，我清楚自己的头寸正确。我没有与市场走向相抗衡，没有违背股市基本行情，而是顺应了市场，正因为这个原因，我才非常确定，内线集团一定会溃败。他们想做以前其他人试验过的事情，而这样注定会一败涂地。就算我像其他人那样，知道习惯性的反弹马上要到了，也没有被唬住。我清楚，只要能够忍耐得住，结果必然比想办法去回补，再在价格较高时放空要好很多。我坚守了自认为对的头寸，赚了100多万。之所以有这个结果，并非与第六感有关，也不是因为我有多么厉害的解盘技巧或者愚勇，而是源自我的自信心，我不是靠聪明或虚荣去赚钱的。知识给了我力量，有了力量就不会怕那些谎言，即使它们清晰地出现在报价牌上，也只会昙花一现。

过了一年，热带贸易股票又涨到了150美元，而且盘踞了好几周时间，整体市场也因为持续的涨势大幅回调，这时的市场已经不是多头了。我清楚这点，因为我已经投石问路了。热带贸易公司所属集团的发展情势很不好，我不知道它们怎么才能让股票上涨，就算大盘上涨，也没办法，更何况大盘没一点儿迹象表明要上涨。于是，我就开始抛售热带贸易公司股票，准备放空1万股。我的这个做法，让股价又下跌了。我没发现有任何支撑。然后，买盘的性质突然就发生了变化。

我说自己能够在支撑出现时看出来，不是说自己多么厉害。我忽然觉得，在大盘下跌的时候，公司内部大量买进，里面一定是有原因的。这些人不会感觉到道德上应该具备什么样的义务，来维持住股价。他们不是没用的蠢货，不是慈善家，也不是想拉高股价以便在柜台多卖些股票的承销银行家。我和很多人都放空了，但热带贸易的股价还是在持续上涨。股价在153美元时，我回补了2万股空头；涨到156美元时，我已经翻空为多了。因为，我看到的这个时候的股市行情最小阻力线是上涨的。我不看好整个股市，可这是一只股票的实际交易情势，而不是一般的投机理论。它涨势凶猛，达到了200美元之上，成了这一年最引人关注的股票。广播报纸都报道说，我在被轧空的过程中损失了八九百万美元。但其实，我不但没做空，还已经在做多了。我持股的时间稍微长了些，因此损失了一点儿账面利润。你想不想知道我这么做的缘由？因为我想，如果我是热带贸易公司内部人士的话，我当然会做该做的事情，可这样的事我不去想它，我做的是投机交易，就要照着眼前的事实来做，而不能理所当然地依靠我自以为别人应当做的事情去操作。

第十九章

我不知道是谁何时首次把“炒作”一词跟其实只是普通市场交易的商业过程联系到了一起，来描述在交易所交易大量股票的行为。通过操纵市场低价买进想要的股票也是炒作，但这个不一样，这个不需要你降低标准，用非法的手段去做，不过你也不容易避开去做那些别人认为不正当的事。在多头市场，你如何买到很大数量的同一只股票，而不会对股价造成抬升？这是个问题。而要解决这个问题的话，决定性因素比较多，没办法找到一个通用的办法，除非你笼统地说，要靠聪明的操作。有没有实例？这要根据具体情况来定。此外你再也给不出更加精确的回答。

对于我所从事的事业，每一个阶段我都兴致盎然，我从自己和他人的经验中学到了很多。但是今天下午收盘以后，从那些交易厅里传播的段子中，我很难学到炒股经验。原先大多数巧妙的方式方法都已经跟不上时代，或者成了非法手段。证券交易的法律法规和市场情况都发生了变化。50到70年前，丹尼尔·德鲁、小雅各和古德能做的很多事情，即便很详细、很真实，都已经失去了学习的价值。今天的股民们不用去想以前的股市大咖们做过的那些事情，不用考虑他们为什么那样做，这就等同于西点军校的学生们不用向古代人学习射箭技术，来增加弹道学方面的知识。

此外，对涉及人性的因素展开研究，总是比较好的，比如人为什么容易轻信自己希望的事情？人为什么会允许甚至鼓励自己受到欲望的影响，或者受到他人粗心大意、斤斤计较的影响？恐惧始终与希望对等，所以对投机的人们的心理进行研究，一直都有很大的用处。武器会发生变化，可是战略不会变。不管在纽交所，还是在战场，都是一样的。我觉得最能简单表述这种情形的话就是汤姆斯·伍德罗克说的那句：“假设人们未来继续犯以前出现过的错误是股市投机的基石。”

在市场特别景气时，炒股人员的数量会达到一个峰值。聪明与巧妙是徒劳的，所以在那种时候，花时间去研究如何炒作和投机，没多少道理，就像你想知道同时落在街对面屋檐上的两滴雨的不同点在哪里一样。笨蛋们总是想着不劳而获，所以在牛市的时候，总会吸引一大堆人参与到股市赌博当中，是市场的普遍繁荣刺激了人贪婪的天性。把赚钱的希望寄托在天上掉馅饼上面，迟早都要付出代价的。在我们生活的渺小的地球上，是不存在不劳而获这种东西的。早先，每当我听到人们谈论以前的市场交易和手段时，总认为19世纪60年代和70年代的人，比20世纪初的人更容易受欺骗。可是，我敢确定在当天或者第二天，就会在报纸上看到一种新式骗局，或者交易场所关张的报道，以及笨蛋们的几百万存款在不知不觉中悄然消失的事情。

我刚到纽约的时候，人们喜欢探讨洗盘和对冲单，不过证券交易所已经禁止了这样的做法。有时候洗盘太粗糙，骗不过任何人。谁要是想洗哪只股票，营业员就会立马说，洗得太厉害了。正如我之前所说，市场不止一次出现营业员毫不隐讳地指出交易公司洗盘，也就是一只股票在瞬间就下跌了两三点，目的是在报价牌上落实价格下跌，以便把交易公司里靠一点儿保证金做多的人洗掉。而对冲单的话，用起来总会出错，因为各个经纪商很难操作得非常协调齐整，这都是违反法令的做法。几年前，一个很知名的交易人取消订单后却没取消对冲单中的买单，结果导致一个不知情的营业员在短时间内就将股价炒高了大约25个点，他停下买盘后，就看到这只股票用同样快的速度下跌。这样做是为了制造活跃交易的市场假象，实在是个不好的做法，是种很不正规的手段。对了，就算是遇到最优秀的经纪商，也不要随便透露你的秘密，如果你想让他继续做纽交所的会员，就不能信任他。但是，那些与买空卖空相关联的一切做法，都因为税收而变得比以前昂贵多了。

在字典里，炒作还包含了轧空的意义。嗯，轧空或许本就是炒作出来的，也或许是人们争着买进造成的。比如1901年5月9日，北太平洋铁路公司股票的轧空很明显就不是炒作的结果。斯图兹轧空后，每个相关人都付出了很大的代价，他们的金钱和名誉都受损严重。这一次其实并非特意安排的轧空。

其实，在那些著名的轧空操作中，很少有能够让主导者获利的。范德比准将曾经两次轧空了哈林公司股票，赚了几百万，可是老家伙赚到的钱是来自那些想诈骗他的空头赌手和谎话连篇的议员，那些钱是他应该赚到的。另外，古德在做西北铁路公司的轧空交易时却亏了大钱，怀特在他的拉克万纳轧空时赚到了100万，可詹姆斯·凯恩在汉尼拔—圣乔股票上赔了100万。想要实现轧空赚钱，靠的是用高于成本的价格，卖掉一开始买来的股票，而且要很大规模地操作才能相对容易地实现。

我曾想，为什么在半个世纪之前的那些大作手中间，轧空这么流行。他们的能力都很强，经验也很丰富，而且智慧过人，不会像小孩一样轻信其他作手。但是，他们在轧空中受困的次数却非常多。一个精明的老营业员对我说过，六七十年代的所有大作手都梦想着主动制造一次轧空交易。虚荣心导致了很多次垄断出现，还有些是要报复别人而制造的轧空。总之，有人如果被别人指责说非常成功地实现了一次轧空，其实是说他是个聪明、勇敢并且取得了成就的人。轧空让那些操作者有了高于别人的优势，有同行对他佩服得五体投地也是理所当然的。促使这些人全力去轧空的不是能得到多少财务上的利益，而是虚荣心。

一条狗在咬其他狗的时候，是非常轻松愉悦的。我觉得以前可能说过，我不止一次地想办法从被轧空的危险中逃脱，并非我有多神秘的看盘灵感，而是我大致可以看出，什么时候买盘的性质不能轻率地放空。我靠普通的试探才做到了这点，当年的那些人也必定有这样做的。德鲁曾经好多次都轧空了同时期的其他作手，使得他们因为多次放空伊利股票而连连赔本。而他则在伊利股票上，又吃了范德比准将轧空的亏，他求范德比准将放过他一次，可是范德比准将却毫不心软，他引用德鲁自己曾说过的两句话：“谁把自己本没有的东西卖掉的话，就要重新买回来，或者去蹲监狱。”

华尔街人很少有记得有关一个作手的事情，这位作手在股市上叱咤风云了一代多人，能够让人们牢牢记住，主要是因为他创造了一个名词——灌水股票。

艾迪生·杰罗姆被公认为1863年春公共交易所霸主。有人对我说，他提供的市场内幕消息，简直与银行的现金一样有价值。总之，他确实是个很厉害的作手，赚到过好几百万。他放任不羁，非常奢华，在华尔街上粉丝很多。一直到后来在老南方股票交易时，被号称“沉默的威廉”的亨利·吉普轧空，杰罗姆损失了自己的几百万美元。顺便说一下，吉普是当时州长罗斯维尔·弗劳恩的小舅子。

在过去出现过的大部分轧空中，主要是靠着不让别人知晓你正在轧空这只股票来实现炒作目的，而其他人却不断地受到诱惑放空这只股票。所以，轧空的主要对象集中在那些同时期的专业作手群中，因为普通大众不喜欢做空的人。能够让那些明智的老作手放空的原因与现在让他们放空的原因差不多。我从自己的所见所闻里知道，范德比准将在轧空哈林股票的时候，除了不讲信用的议员们外，其他职业交易者放空，是因为股价太高了。他们觉得股价很高，是因为这只股票价格从来没这么高过。所以，股价高到了令人没办法买进的程度，那卖出就是自然而然的事情了。这是不是听起来很现代化呢？他们想的是价格，而范德比准将想的是价值。鉴于此，很多年后，老前辈们向我提到，当他们想形容贫穷状态的时候，总会说：“他放空了哈林股。”

多年前，我与古德先生的一个老营业员聊天时，他一本正经地向我保证说，古德不但是个异于常人的人，而且绝对比以前和现在的作手们都厉害。老德鲁曾心有余悸地说：“与他交手就意味着死亡。”他指的就是古德。古德必定是个正儿八经的金融牛人，所以才取得了那么大的成就，这是不用怀疑的。即使相隔年代很长，我仍然可以看出他身上有着适应新情况的惊人能力，这在市场交易中是非常难能可贵的。他可以游刃有余地改变攻防方式，他注重的是操纵股票性质，而不是投机本身。他炒作的目的，就是为了投资，而不是改变市场。他在很久之前就明白，要想大赚就要拥有铁路，而不是仅仅在股市中炒作铁路股票。他当然也玩铁路股票，可我猜之所以如此，是因为股市上赚钱最快最轻松，而且他需要大量的钱，正如克里斯·亨廷顿总是嫌钱不够一样。银行能够借给他的资金，总比他所需的钱要少那么两三千万美元。如果光有长远的眼光而缺钱，就只能忧心忡忡；如果有钱了，那么长远的眼光代表的可就是成就、权力和财富，等等等等。

当然，并不是只有当年的这些大咖在炒作，另外一些不太重要的作手也炒作。曾有一位老营业员对我讲过一件与19世纪60年代初的社会情形和道德现象有关的事情。他说：“首次踏进金融区时，我就对华尔街产生了最初的印象。我父亲去那里办事，不知为什么却带着我，我们沿百老汇大街向前走，在华尔街转了弯，然后继续向前，走到宽街还是拿骚街的时候，就到了如今信孚银行大楼这个街口上，我看见有一大堆人跟在两个男人身后。走在前面的男人假装很无所谓的样子朝东走了，后面一个男人满脸通红，一只手用力挥着帽子，另一只手也在空中乱挥，嘴里大嚷着：‘夏洛克，夏洛克（指的是放高利贷的狠心角色）’，金钱的价值到底是什么？夏洛克，夏洛克。我看见人们都从窗户里探头来看。那时候还没有高楼大厦，可我能确定二三楼的人都在张望。我父亲问发生什么事情了，有人说了一通话，我没有听见。我紧紧抓着父亲的手，免得被人群挤开。就像平时常见的那样，街上的人越来越多，我深感不舒服。人们惊愕地从街上走过来，最后我们终于挤出人群。父亲告诉我说，那个大声嚷着‘夏洛克’的人是谁谁谁。我忘了他叫什么，但我记得他是纽约主力股的最大作手。听说除了小雅各以外，他赚过和亏过的钱比谁都多。我之所以知道小雅各，是因为他一个大人叫这么个名字很有意思。被喊作‘夏洛克’的人因为控制着资金而名声很臭，他叫什么我也忘了，只记得他长得又高又瘦，肤色很白。当年，公司内部总是用借钱的方式把资金控制住，或者说让交易所里那些需要钱的人没多少钱可借。他们去借钱，只拿了保付支票，其实并没拿到真正的钱而去其他地方使用。这当然属于操控。我觉得这也是一种炒作方式。”

我非常同意这个老人的观点，这是如今我们并没有的炒作方式。

第二十章

我从来没跟现在还被华尔街津津乐道的那些股市高手说过话，我指的不是领袖，而是大作手。他们都是我炒股的这个时代之前的人。不过，我初次到达纽约时，所有作手中最伟大的人詹姆斯·凯恩正春风得意。可那时我只是个年轻人，只关心怎么样在一家靠谱的股票公司，做出当年在对赌行那样的成就来。而且，凯恩当时正忙于炒作美国钢铁公司的股票，这属于他的炒股杰作。我那时候还没有炒作经验，也没有真正了解炒作的价值与意义，而且对炒作的知识也没什么需求。如果我那时能想到炒作，那也是因为我把炒作看作一种高级的欺骗手段。对赌行用在我身上的那些手段都是低级的骗术。自那时起，我听到的有关炒作的话，都是推测或者质疑，猜的成分要高于理性分析的成分。

与凯恩很熟悉的人对我说过很多次，凯恩是华尔街上自古以来最精明、最有魄力的作手。这一点的意义很重大，因为厉害角色很多，如今都被人们所遗忘，他们叱咤江湖的时候，都是国王一般的显赫，在某一天都是国王。他们依靠报价牌，从毫不知名逐渐成长于金融界，最后创造了名气。可那小小的彩色报价纸牌没有多大的吸引力，不能让他们在那里驻扎多长时间，很难留名后世。反正，凯恩确实成了那代人中最出色的作手，有过很长一段色彩斑斓的岁月。

凯恩运用着他掌握的炒股知识、经验和才干，在哈维梅尔兄弟手下做事。哈维梅尔兄弟想让他为美国糖业公司的股票打造一片市场。当时他不名一文，不然肯定会继续自力更生地操作，他是个非常了不起的大赌徒。在美国糖业公司的股票上，他做得非常成功，他让这只股票成了最受欢迎、最活跃的一只。事情过后，他总被各个公司内部请去操盘。有人对我说，他在这些公司内部炒作时，不会索要或者接收费用，而是总要与公司其他成员那样，得到一份该有的分成。他全权负责股票在市场上的情势，双方总会产生各种叛离和偷跑的传言，他与惠特尼·莱恩集团的争斗，就因为受到了这样的传言攻击。作手想被同伴误解其实很容易，那些同伴不会像他一样，知道自己所需为何。我明白这点是源于自己的经验。

让人惋惜的是，凯恩1901年春完成的最伟大的杰作，即炒作美国钢铁公司的股票，没有确切的记录留给后世。以我的了解，凯恩与摩根先生一直没聊过这事。摩根公司通过塔波特泰勒公司交易，而这家公司则是凯恩的老巢。塔波特泰勒是凯恩的女婿。我敢肯定，凯恩对这家公司的付出，是包括了通过努力获得乐趣的。那年春天，他炒热了市场，也通过交易赚了几百万美元。谁都知道这件事。他对我的一个朋友说过，只短短几周的时间，他通过公开市场，为股票承销公司至少卖出了75万股。如果你了解了下面这两件事情，就会明白这是很厉害的成绩。首先，这是一只没有在市场中历练过的新股票，公司的总资本大过了美国当时的国债总额。其次，也是那个时候，凯恩帮忙打造的另一个市场中，雷德、利兹、穆尔兄弟、亨利·菲利普、弗里克及其他钢铁业的大腕们，也向大众卖掉了几十万股票。

当然，市场走向有利于他，不光当时经济状况是这样，人气和没有受限的资金支援也是他成功的因素。那时候的市场非常好，是一个很大的多头，那样的盛况再出现的概率很小。后来才发生了让人受不了的股市大恐慌。1901年，凯恩炒作抬高的美国钢铁公司普通股是每股55美元，到了1903年股市恐慌的时候，暴跌到了10美元，1904年更是到了8又7/8美元。

我无法具体分析凯恩的所作所为，因为他没写过书，一点儿详细记录都没留下。比如，知道他在联合铜矿公司是怎么样炒作的，肯定会非常精彩。罗杰斯和洛克菲勒曾试图把手中的股票抛出去，结果却遭遇了失败，只好求助凯恩帮忙。凯恩答应了他们的请求。请记住，在罗杰斯的那个时代，他自己本身就是华尔街上一位特别厉害的企业家，洛克菲勒更是标准石油公司里最勇敢的投机人。其实，他们手中拥有的资源非常强大，还有很好的个人名声和很多年驰骋股市的老到经验，但却需要凯恩帮忙。我说这个故事是要告诉你，有的事还非得请专家做才行。这是一只由美国最厉害的几个资本家支撑的备受青睐的股票，却没有很好的卖出市场，如果想要卖出去，就得牺牲很多资金和名声。罗杰斯与洛克菲勒聪明过人，所以觉得只有凯恩才能帮上他们的忙。

凯恩立马投入到了工作当中，他要应对多头市场，按照票面价格卖出22万股联合铜矿的股票。卖掉公司内部的股票后，大众还在继续买，价格也上升了10个点。公司看到股民们这么热衷于这只股票的时候，居然变成了看好卖出的股票。有传言说，罗杰斯还真的向凯恩提出建议，要做多。如果说是罗杰斯想把股票倒给凯恩，那可信度就不高。罗杰斯那么聪明，肯定不会把凯恩当冤大头对待。凯恩按照以往做法，在涨势好的时候，一直压低卖出。当然，他这么做是因为有这样的需求，有受到股市每天的小波动影响。在股市里，跟在战场上一样，要牢牢记住大的谋划和具体的做法之间是有区别的。

有个特别会空手套白狼的人，也是凯恩最信任的人，他前几天对我说，在联合铜矿的那次交易中，如果凯恩有一天发现，自己手中没有一点儿之前为了抬高股价而不得不买回来的股票，第二天他就会买进几千甚至几万股，再过一天，他可能又会卖掉。接着，他不再去理会市场，只让市场自生自灭，同时也给市场一个适应这种状况的机会。他真想彻底卖出手中的股票时，就会像我对你说的那样，一路压低抛售。普通股民们都希望股市会反弹，而且空头也会回补。关于这场炒作，一位和凯恩非常熟悉的人对我提到过，说凯恩帮助罗杰斯和洛克菲勒卖了股票，让他们得到了大概2000万或者2500万现金，罗杰斯送给凯恩一张20万美元的支票。这让人联想到一个百万富翁的妻子，拿出5美分答谢纽约大都会歌剧院的女清洁工，因为女清洁工帮她找到了一串价值10万美元的珍珠项链。凯恩退回了支票，并且顺带递去一张纸条，说自己又不是交易所的营业员，非常高兴能帮上这个小忙。罗杰斯接下了支票，写信说，非常期待能够再次合作。没多久，好心的罗杰斯向凯恩传递了内幕消息，让他在联合铜矿股价到130美元的时候买进。

真是个天才作手啊！好厉害的詹姆斯·凯恩！他的秘书对我说，市场的走向跟他的预期一样时，他会很容易发脾气。知道他的人说，他总是用冷嘲热讽的口气来说话，让人难忘，可以从中看出他的暴躁来。他脾气好的时候是赔了钱后，那时他总表现得像很有教养的上流社会的人，非常和蔼可亲，说话风趣幽默，妙语连珠。

他身上具备了一个成功的炒股专家所必需的那种优良品性，他不论在哪儿炒股都会很成功。很明显，他从不做违逆股市大盘的事情，也从不莽撞行事，他一旦知道自己做错了，会立马摆脱错误轨道。

从他那时候到现在，证券交易的法律法规变化太多，比旧法规也严格了很多，在交易和利润上增加了不少赋税，等等。所以，这个游戏貌似已经发生了变化，凯恩的那些赚钱妙招现在已经过时了。而且，有人对我们很肯定地说，华尔街现在的商业道德已经提高了很多。不过，我可以客观地说，在美国金融发展史上，不管哪个时代，凯恩都会成为一个伟大的作手，因为他是个伟大的炒股手，对投机游戏了解得非常全面透彻。他之所以取得了这样的成果，是因为当时的情况容许他这样做。如果他能在1922年的时候玩股票，一定会取得与1901年时同样的成就，也会跟1876年他初从加州到纽约那样获得成功，那时候他两年就赚了900万美元。有一类人的脚步就是比普通人要快得多，不管跟怎样的普通大众在一个时代，他们天生就是领袖级人物。

其实时代的变化并没有你所想的那么厉害。能够获得的利润确实大不如前，现在已经不是开疆扩土的时代了，也就没有了那些金融前锋获得过的那种利润。可在有些方面，却更适宜炒作了，此外的其他方面都比凯恩那时候难多了。

广告是一门艺术，这是毫无疑问的。把股市大盘当作媒介一样用来炒作，这也是广告艺术。股市行情所呈现的应该是作手们希望大家想看到的情况。故事的真实度越高，说服力也越强，同时广告效果也越好。如今的作手们不但需要让某只股票看起来很有力，而且也要真的让它变得有力。所以，炒作的前提必须是要有健全的交易规则。这是凯恩能成为股市圣手的原因，他自始至终都是最合格的交易者。

“炒作”一词已经成了贬义，它需要被一个其他名称代替。我觉得，假若炒作是为了卖出大把股票的话，那么炒作的过程并没多神妙，也没什么问题。当然，前提是炒作过程中不能混入误导别人的因素。作手们必须要在股民中间寻找买股票的人，这是铁定的。这些买主期望着能赚到大量利润，所以也情愿承担比正常商业风险更大的风险。我不同情那些明明知道这个道理却说自己不能赚到轻松钱是因为别人的原因的人。这样的人在赚钱时好像很聪明，但只要赔了钱就会把别人当坏人和作手。这个时候，炒作从他们的嘴里说出来，就添加了别人在偷偷作弊的暗示，而真实的情形其实不是这样。

一般来说，炒作是为了拓展出市场，也就是说能在任何时候都按照某个价位卖掉手中一大把的股票。有些公司内部如果发现手中的股票因为市场逆转而没办法卖掉，会因此受到很大的损失，他们就会做出雇专家帮忙的决定，他们认为专家的水平和经验有助于他们按照一定的秩序从股市缓缓抽身，而不至于受到很大的损失。

你会发现，我没有说到那些尽力按照最低价买大量股票为目的的炒作，比如以买股票为手段而实现控制股票的行为，因为这样的事情如今已经不常出现了。

古德想着要真正控制西联电报公司，就决定大量买入这只股票，而此时已经好久没有在交易大厅露过面的华盛顿·康纳却忽然出现在了交易所的西联电报股票交易点。他开始买进股票了，大厅里的人们都嘲笑他怎么如此愚蠢地觉得他们很单纯呢，所以都非常得意地把所有的西联电报股票卖给他。他们觉得这是低级的手段，认为康纳在假装古德想让他买进，然后可以拉高股价了。这是炒作？我觉得我可以这样回答：“是，但又不是。”

正如我所说，大多数情况下，炒作是为了按照最高的价格把手中所持股票卖给股民，这不光是个卖出的问题，而且也是分散抛售。不管怎么看，一只股票在1000个人手中，比在一个人手中要好很多，这样有利于市场。所以，作手们需要考虑的不仅是以高价卖出股票，也要考虑股票分散情况。

如果你后续不能诱使股民们从你手中买走股票，那拉抬股价到一个高价位，就没任何道理。当经验不足的作手们准备在头部卖出股票遭遇失败的时候，老手们就会好像很聪明地对你说：“你牵匹马到水边容易，但强迫它喝水就难了。”这人真是好有创意啊。其实，你必须记住炒作的一条规则，这是一条凯恩和其他厉害的老前辈们都很熟悉的规则，那就是要尽力把股票价格炒作到很高的价位，然后再一路压低，分抛给普通的股民。

我还是从头说起吧。假设一个人、一个股票承销商或者一家公司有一大把股票，想按照高价抛出，它在纽交所正常挂牌。股票买卖最理想的地方应该就是公开市场，而最好的购买者应该是普通股民。和卖股票有关的谈判应该由一个人负责，他是公司在位的或者已经退位的董事，他准备在交易所卖出这只股票，但是却没有成功。他已经非常熟悉或者很快就熟悉股市流程了，他清楚必须要有一个经验更丰富、更有水平的人来操作。他听到过或者本来就知道有很多符合标准的人，他打算运用专业手段来操作。他寻找其中一个人，就像生病了去看医生，或者需要工程技术时去找工程师一样。

假设他听说我非常擅长股票交易，那我觉得他就会想方设法地查找与我有关的资料看，接着见我，如果时间合适，他还会到我办公室登门拜访。

我可能对这只股票恰好很了解，知道它的价值所在。对这些很了解本来就是我的分内之事，也是我谋生的手段。来人会对我讲他与他的朋友的需求，进而提出与我合作的希望。

轮到我发言了，我让对方把我觉得必要的能让我知晓这次操作的资料交给我。我判断一下这只股票价格，对它在市场交易中的可能性进行评估，然后结合我对当时股市行情的判断，预估这次操作会不会成功。

我如果通过所有的信息资料得出了令人满意的结果，那我就会答应合作，当时就告诉他我的条件。假如他接受了我提出的条件，包括我需要的酬金，我就可以立即展开操作了。

一般情况下，我需要得到并且也能得到一大笔股票认购权。我绝对需要的是累进认购权，这样对谁都很公平。认购权股价一开始比市场价低一点儿，然后慢慢升高。比如，我获得了10万股的认购权，它的股价目前是40美元，我就一开始用35美元认购几千股，接着是37美元、40美元、45美元、50美元，逐步升高，直到75美元或者80美元。

如果经过我的努力和炒作后，股价上涨了，而且到了最高的价位，人们都很热心购买它，我就可以卖掉一大部分了，我肯定要执行我的认购权。我获得了利润，我的客户也一样赚了钱，这就是理当出现的结果。我拥有的技术如果真是他们用钱所寻找的对象，那他们自然就能获得价值。不过，有时候对方最终也有可能赔钱，不过这样的情况很少，因为我在接这份工作的时候就评估过自己能获得的利润了，不然也不会接手。今年，我接手的那么一两个任务运气不好，没有赚到钱。原因也很多，不过这是另外一回事了，以后有机会我可能会讲。

一只股票要想实现多头走势，首先要做宣传，让人相信正有一个多头走势在伺机而动。是不是听起来很有意思？你再看看，实际上也没那么搞笑，不是吗？其实最有效的宣传，就是你真心实意地去让这只股票活跃起来，变得力道很大。说完该说的，做完该做的以后，全世界最好的公关人员就是股价机器，股市大盘走向就是最好的宣传媒介。我没必要去为客户做任何宣传，不必通过报纸报道股价，不必让财经报道发表对公司未来有多看好，更不需要有粉丝跟在屁股后面。我只需要把这只股票玩得活跃起来，就可以实现我特别想要的结果。股票交易很活跃的时候，就自然会有人想知道原因，当然这一点也说明，那些必要的原因会自己冒出来，出现在媒体上，一点儿都不需要我去协助。

场内股民们需要的只是交易活泛的股票。只要存在自由市场，他们会在任何价位交易股票，看到活跃的交易就会买卖成千上万股，这些分散力量集合起来就很强大了。他们必定就是作手的首批买主。他们一直前行，跟着买卖。所以无论在整个操作的哪个时期，他们都是一股有用的力量。我知道凯恩常会利用最能做事的营业员，既能瞒住他的炒作，同时也因为凯恩知道营业员们是拓展市场和传播消息的好手。他经常按照比行情高的股价，通过口头承诺，把认购权交给营业员，以便他们在能够获利落袋之前帮点儿小忙。他能使他们获得该获得的利益。想让这些行业内的人为我做事，我自己一点儿额外的事情都不必做，只要把一只股票搞得活蹦乱跳就好。营业员没有多少要求。不过，你也要明白，在交易所大厅里买进，是为了卖出赚钱。他们不会坚持等到有很大的利润，但一定要是那种很快就能兑现的利润。

我把一只股票搞活，以吸引股民们的眼球，其中的原因已然讲明。我买卖一只股票，营业员也会跟着交易。既然有这么多股票用于投机，就像我坚持的那样，用认购权把它锁死，就不会有太大的卖出压力。所以，买盘总要比卖盘强，股民们主要不是跟着作手走，而是跟着营业员走，他们会转为买家。我对这样的需求非常满意，可能会抛出股票。如果市场需求是正常的，需要的股票数量就会远远高于我在炒作一开始时被迫买进的数量，如果这样的话，我就会放空。这是技术层面的放空，也就是说，我卖出去的比我的持股还要多。这对我来说是非常安全的，因为我是根据认购权卖出的。当然了，到了股民们没有那么多需求了，股价就不再上涨，我就会停下来等待。

然后，如果这只股票不再上涨，大盘在某一天会因为疲软而回调，或者那些眼光好的营业员能看明白我的这只股票没有人买，他们就会放空这只股票，跟着他们的那些人也会放空。无论什么原因，我的股票价格开始下跌。我就得买进，支撑这只股票，就像一只股票得到自己的公司派欢迎时，应该有的那种支撑一样。而且，我还不用买进股票，就能够支撑住它，也就是说我不用增加持股数量，省得以后还要往出卖。要记住，我如此支撑股价并不会因此损伤财力。自然，我的所作所为实际上是在回补我之前用高价放空的股票。那个时候，我能够在股民们和交易人员的需求前提下，高价放空这些股票。你总该清楚地向人们表明，当这只股票下跌了的时候，总会有人买。如此，一般会制止业内人士莽撞地放空，也会让那些担惊受怕的股东暂缓抛出股票。当股票的走势越来越不好，你一般都会看到这样的卖出压力。一旦没有支撑，股票马上就出现这样的情况。我这样回补，也是我所说的稳定程序中的一个步骤。

市场变好时，我自然会一路前行卖出，可总也不会到阻止股票涨势的程度。我这全是按照稳定计划进行。诚然，在合理有序的股市上涨情形中，卖出的越多，越能鼓励那些保守的投机分子，他们可比鲁莽的营业员数量多得多，股价也迟早会变得疲软，如此情况下，我卖出的越多，对这只股票的支撑就越大。因为我一直在维护放空的部位，所以对自己没有危险，还能支撑股票。一般而言，当我觉得价格到了能赚到利润的时候就卖出。不过，我也常在无利可图的时候卖，因为要为自己的买进创造或者增加买进力量。这就是我说的没有任何风险的买进，我所做的不只是要拉抬股价，或者为客户卖出多少股票，也要为自己牟利。这是我不让客户为我提供操作资金的原因，我的收费取决于我的操作能否成功。

当然，我说的这些并不是我一直在用的手法，我既没有一种一成不变的僵硬系统，也不会按照这种系统去操作。我会因势而动，与时俱进，随时调整。

如果想把一只股票卖出去，就该尽力炒作到最高价后再卖。我重复这一点，一是因为这是最基本的原则，二是因为我非常清楚，人们都相信所有的卖压出现在头部。有的时候，一只股票会停停走走，这样的话，股价是不会上涨的，也就到了卖出的大好时机。你的卖出会让股价下跌，甚至跌到你无法想象的地步，不过你一般也能拉起股价。只要我炒作股票的在我的买单下回升，那我就会很安全，如果有必要，我还可以有充足的信心去勇敢地花自己的钱去买进股票，如同我买进其他类似情形的股票。这是最小阻力线，你记得我曾说过与这个相关的交易见解吗？最小阻力线被确定后，我会按该路线前进，并不是因为我在那个特殊的时刻炒作那只特定的股票，而是因为我自始至终都是那只股票的操作人。

我的买进如果不能拉动股价，我就会停止买进，然后再卖出，即便我恰巧没在炒作它，我也会如此行事。你该清楚，卖掉一只股票的主要手段，是要一路向下卖。在股价下跌时能够卖出那么多，简直让人吃惊。

我再说一遍，在炒作的时候，我从来没有忘掉自己是股票交易人。毕竟我炒作股票的时候，所遇到的问题与操作股票时是一样的。作手如果不能让股票按照自己的意愿波动，就要停止炒作。你在炒作的股票如果没有按照应该出现的情势发展，就该马上出脱，不要跟股市大盘讲道理，也不要想着赚回你的利润，赶快在还能够脱身并且还算廉价脱身的时候就跳出来，为时不晚。

第二十一章

我知道，这些通用的规则是不会让人产生多深刻的印象的，它们就只能这样。如果我举个实实在在的例子，可能会说得更清楚些。我要对你讲，我是怎么通过只买进7000股就将一只股票的价格抬升了30个点的，我创造了一个了不起的市场，它差不多能够容纳任何一只数量庞大的股票。

这只股票名为帝国钢铁，是一群很有声望的人推上市的股票，也做了非常好的宣传，被认定为资产股。华尔街上的几家公司拥有这只股票的百分之三十，用以销售给广大股民。只是它挂牌后，一直交易萎缩，有时候也会有人问到这只股票，就会有一两个股票承销公司的内部人员说，这家公司的盈余比预期要好，前途非常让人兴奋。说得一点儿没错，确实如此，只是没那么让人兴奋，又没有什么亮点诱发投机。从投资角度看，价格是否稳定，能不能持续配股，都没有确定。它就一直没有过引人关注的走向变动，表现太中庸了，即便在公司内部发布了真实报告后，依然没有引起多少上涨，同时，股价也没有多少下跌。

帝国钢铁一直处于这样没名气、没人追捧，也没人传播内幕消息的状态之中，是一只没有人卖出，所以不会下跌的股票。没人卖出，是因为谁都不想放空股权相对集中的股票，因为如果放空就会对空头的地位不利，会受到公司内部操控。同时，也没什么值得买进的理由。所以对投资人而言，帝国钢铁股票是一只投机股。而对投机分子来说，它不冷也不热，你一旦买进做多，它就容易陷入昏睡套牢状态，你的投资思想不支持你这么做。一个人无奈地拖着一具尸体长达一两年，失去的要比尸体的原始成本还高，如果有真正的好东西出现了，他会发现自己被捆绑得不能动弹了。

有一天，帝国钢铁公司的一位重要人士代表他自己和他的同事来找我，表达了想让我为这只股票创造市场的意愿。他们手中有百分之七十的股票都没有卖出。他们希望我能够把那些股票处理给市场，卖出比他们绞尽脑汁在公开市场上售价还高的价位。他们想知道我要接受这个工作的话，需要多少酬金。

我对他说，过几天就让他们知道我的条件。随后我开始分析这只股票，请了一些专业人士去调查这家公司，生产、财务、业务等各个部门都搞清楚。他们给出的报告很中性，而我并非要知道好坏，只是想知道真实的现状罢了。

根据报告，这是一只很有价值的股票，如果投资人愿意等待的话，公司的未来发展会证明，按照现在的市场行情买进这只股是非常划算的。鉴于此，从市场波动上来说，最合理、最容易出现的就是股价上涨。意思是，分析了未来可能出现的情况后得出结论，股价应该会上涨。所以，我找不到不谨慎而有信心地为帝国钢铁公司做一次炒作的理由。

我告诉那个人，让他到我办公室商谈具体事宜。我告诉了他我的条件，我不要现金，只要帝国钢铁10万股的认购权，价格从70到100美元不等。在一些人眼中，这是狮子大开口，可他们应该想到的是，凭他们自己是没办法以70美元卖出10万股的，连5万股都卖不出去。这是一只没市场号召力的股票，一切利于未来的宣传都没吸引到多少人来买。而且，除非他们公司自己先赚到几百万，不然我也不可能拿到我的酬金。我能赚的不是很高的代销费，而是按比较公平的方式，以事情是否成功来决定的酬劳。

我清楚这是一只真正值钱的股票，股市大盘也在看涨，所以对好股票的价格上涨是有利的，我觉得自己可以做好。我提出的想法让客户深受鼓舞，他马上就同意了我的条件，这是个从一开始就令人愉悦的交易。

我尽力从根本上先维护好自己的安全。公司内部控制着百分之七十左右的流通股票，我让他们按照信托合约把这些股票锁定，我不想让大股东们成为股市垃圾场。锁定了这一大半股票后，我还要考虑其余百分之三十散落在市场中的股票，这也是我需要承担的风险。作为一个投机人员，我没想过做无风险的事情。其实所有股票一起进入市场的可能性很小，不会高于人寿保险公司的所有顾客在同一时间死亡的可能性。股市与人命相同，都有一本没有发行的账目。

我先进行了自我保护，免得受到本可避免的风险伤害，然后就行动起来了。我要做的是让我的认购权有价值，想实现目标就要拉抬股价，制造一个我能够卖出我那有认购权的10万股的市场。

我首先要做的是，明确在股价上涨的时候，市场上会进来多少股票。我的经纪商很轻松就搞清楚了这一点，他们一点儿困难都没遇到，就知道了在比现在行情高一点儿的价位上到底有多少股票在等待卖出。我不清楚是不是交易场里的中介专家们告诉他们说，交易场内的账户上有这么多卖单。此时的股价说是70美元，但按照这个价格，我连1000股都卖不出去。我连在这个价格甚至更低点的价格上有一点儿交易需求的证据都没有，我必须要按照经纪商提供的资料数据来开展工作，可这些数据也不能让我确定出想买卖的股票到底有多少。

我拿到这些资料后，就偷偷在70美元和稍微高一点儿的价位上买进了所有出售的股票。你知道的，我说的“我”实际上指的是我的经纪商。那些出售的单子都来自小股民，因为公司在封锁自己的持股前，就取消了所有卖单。

我并不需要买多少股票，而且我清楚适当的上涨会引发其他人购买股票，当然也会出现卖出的情况。

我没有向任何一个人透露帝国钢铁股票上涨的消息，我没必要这么做，我要凭借最好的宣传直接提升人气。我的意思不是说不需要多头宣传。纯新股票的价值，跟宣传羊毛产品、鞋或汽车的价值一样，是很合理也很有必要的。应该让股民们自己谈论精确可靠的消息。不过，我的意思是股市大盘为我做好了这方面的需求准备。我之前提过，信誉度高的报纸媒体总会想办法刊发能够为市场波动提供解释的文章，这就是新闻。读者不光想知道股市上出现了什么，也想知道为什么会出现。所以，作手根本不需要花力气，那些金融记者就会发表能扒拉出来的一切消息或谣言，还会对盈余、产业和发展方向等情况做分析报道，简单讲就是他们会报道出来为股市上涨做解释的新线索。当记者和认识的人向我问起关于这只股票的情况时，我会张口就说出心中的那只股票。我不需要自己提建议，也不透露内幕消息，不过我如果用背后偷着去做的方式来操作，一点儿益处都没有。我也知道，在所有透露内幕消息的人和业务代表里面，股票大盘的走向才最优秀、最具说服力。

我按照70美元和更高一点儿的价格买进了所有出售的股票，消除了市场压力。从交易目的的角度来看，这就表明帝国钢铁股票的最小阻力线显然是朝上走的。交易大厅里那些具备很强观察力的营业员看到其概况，就会很自然地把这只股票看作会上涨的股票，至于幅度他们不会知道，可这已经足够让他们考虑买进了。这只股票很明朗的上涨势头，致使他们对帝国钢铁有了需求，大盘走势提供的是最不会出错的信息。我马上就顺应这样的需求了。我卖掉了那些从疲惫不堪的股东手中买来的股票，他们被套了很久。我自然会万分谨慎、很高兴向市场提供这些需求。我不会向市场大力去销售股票，我不想让上涨势头过于迅速，在刚开始的时候，就把我的10万股卖掉一半一定不是好事。我要做的是搭建一个市场，从而能够销售掉手中的股票。

可是，就算我只卖出了那些营业员想要的股票数量，也还是丢掉了到现在为止还比较稳定的市场买盘。时机到了以后，营业员就不再买进，价格也就会停滞。如果这样，那些沮丧的多头就会抛售，因为没了涨势，就没有了买进的理由，营业员会跟着卖。可我已经准备好了面对这样的卖压。股价跌的时候，我买回之前以高出几美元的价格卖出的股票。我明白这样肯定会让股票不再下跌，也就会阻止股民们卖出。

接着，我从头再做一次。一路向上，把所有要卖的股票都买进，其实没有多少数量，股价也会再次涨高，从比70美元高些的起点开始涨。不要忘记，在股价下跌的时候，许多人都急于卖掉手中的股票，可不想在头部以下三四点的价位往外卖。这样的投机人总向天发誓要在下次反弹的时候再卖掉。在股价上涨的时候，他们开始出售股票，等看到了股价走势发生了变化，又跟着改变初衷。也有些想赚个安稳钱的人会迅速卖掉股票获得利润，在他们眼里，只有落了袋的利润才是真正的利润。

如此反复，我一次次地这样做，来回买卖交易，总是能把股价炒作得更高些。

有的时候，当你买了所有想卖出的股票时，对迅速拉升股价是有好处的，你要炒作的这只股票就会猛涨。这就形成了一个很好的广告契机，因为股票的剧烈涨势本身就成了人们的谈资，就会吸引到专业的玩家和喜欢热闹股票的股民们。我觉得这样的人特别多。我这样操作帝国钢铁股票时，猛烈上涨所带来的购买需求我会全部满足。我的卖单限制了股票上涨的速度和幅度，我持续买进，又持续卖出，不光能抬升股价，还能为帝国钢铁公司的股票拓展出很好的市场。

自从我开始炒作后，这只股票再也没有那种不能自由交易的情况。我的意思是，针对这只股票做很大的交易，都不会使得股价有太厉害的波动。股民们的那种买了以后就会被套牢或者卖出后被轧死的恐惧感不复存在了。因为谁都相信帝国钢铁股票市场会一直活跃，它也就慢慢分售到了专家和普通股民的手里，这与股价的波动让大家产生了炒股信心相关。同时，交易活跃也解决了其他方面的很多困难。最终，经过我买卖了成千上万股后，它的价格成功被拉升到了面值以上。所有人都想按照每股100美元的价格买进帝国钢铁，谁都知道这是一只很好的股票，为什么不买呢？现在跟以前一样便宜，涨势就能说明一切。许多人都觉得，一只股票如果能够从70美元上涨到100美元，那就也有从100美元涨到130美元的可能。

把价格拉升30点的过程中，我只买了7000股。这一批股票，平均持股价格在85美元左右，这就说明我每股赚了15美元。利润还只是在账面上，不过我的所有利润可要大大多于这个，而且非常稳当，因为我已经搭建了一个大市场，足够让我卖出所有的股票了。经过聪明的炒作，这只股票还会上涨，我手里有10万股的认购权，认购价位也在逐渐上涨，从70美元逐步到100美元。

因为后来行情的发展，使得我没有依计而行，把账面利润套现。请允许我自夸一下，我觉得这是一次非常成功的炒作，而且很符合法律法规。成功是行情发展的必然结果。帝国钢铁公司的资产价值很高，股票价位处于高点但也不算贵。原来的承销商里有些成员希望保住这只股的控制权，这是一家实力雄厚的银行。对于银行来说，控制帝国钢铁这样业务好又有发展空间的公司，或许比交给那些散户去控制更好。反正，银行让我把股票的所有认购权都转让出来。这就说明我可以得到一笔很大的利润，所以我马上就同意了。能够卖出这么一笔，从而赚取很多资金，这么做是我非常乐意的。我对自己在这只股票上的所获利润特别满意。

我在转让出那10万股票的认购权之前，获悉那些银行家找了经验丰富的专家评估了这家公司。他们提供的报告为这家银行请我让出认购权提供了理由。我手里仍然有帝国钢铁公司的几千股，我对它信心十足。

在炒作帝国钢铁的股票时，我没有做出任何不正确或者不合适的事。我的买盘如果能使得股价上涨，我就知道不会有什么问题。股票是会出现没法拉抬的情况，可这只股票却从没有萎靡过。当你在买进股票时，它没有什么反应，那就不必考虑获知更好的内幕消息，直接卖出。如果你清楚一只股票的价值很高，市场行情也非常好，你总能在股价下跌后把它再拉升起来，就算跌了20点都可以再拉升。不过，在帝国钢铁股票上，我一直都没必要这么去做。

在炒作股票的时候，我从没有忘掉基本的交易原则。可能你会奇怪，我为什么要反反复复说这一点，或者我为什么要强调不与股市大盘较劲，不因为市场的行为而责怪大盘。你肯定觉得，在事业上赚了好几百万，在华尔街证券交易中操作得很成功的人，必定懂得玩这个游戏的时候要非常冷静，是吧？如果你知道一些非常成功的大公司委派的那些炒作高手常常因为市场的发展走向与他们的预估不相符，从而焦灼得像个小女人的时候，你定会吃惊不小。这样的事情在他们眼里就是个莫大的侮辱，然后他们会因为自己的坏脾气损失掉金钱。

坊间流传着很多我与布兰迪之间关系不好的说法。人们都受到了误导，觉得我俩迟早会因为某个股票上的操作而闹翻，从而产生激烈的矛盾，而操作也会失败，或者会涉及一些诈骗行为，使得我们中的一位付出几百万或者类似的代价。呃，实际上并不是这样的。

布兰迪是我多年的老朋友，为我提供过好多次股市信息，我也因此获利不少。而我也对他提出过很多建议，他或者采纳了，也或者没采纳。如果他采纳了，就会节省一笔钱，因为他是一位推动石油产品公司上市和稀释股权的人。那只股票在成功上市后，综合行情不好，新股的表现没有布兰迪和他的合作伙伴们预料的那么好。情势转好后，布兰迪又召集了一个小组，来操作石油产品公司。

至于他使用的技巧，我不能告诉你。我没有问，他也没告诉我是怎么做的，不过在华尔街上，虽然他的经验很多，人也比较精明，可他做的一切努力都没有丝毫价值。没多久，这个公司就发现，他们在股票出售上丝毫没有办法。他肯定尝试过自己想到的所有办法，因为公司内部的操手们只有在确定自己不能够操作时，才会找外部专业人士帮忙，而这个事情是普通人士不愿意承认的。反正他就来找我了，很客气地说了些见面语后，他提出想让我来把油品公司的股票推出去，这个公司大概有10万多的持股。当时，它的价格在102到103美元。

我觉得这是个稀里糊涂的事情，所以委婉地拒绝了他，不过他还是坚持让我接受这次合作。他从他个人的角度来请我帮忙，我只好同意。我天生就不喜欢去掺和那些我没有把握做成的事情，可同时我觉得人应该对亲戚朋友们承担一些责任。所以我说我会尽力去做，不过同时我也说了，这件事我没有什么必胜的把握，也说了我必定会遇到的困难。可布兰迪却说，他不需要我保证能为公司赚几百万，他对我很有信心，觉得我做就会实现一个让所有理智的人都满意的目标。

是啊，事情就是这样，我答应了一件与我的判断不相符的事情。正如我的担心那样，我发现事情的发展举步维艰，主因还是源于布兰迪炒作这个公司的时候，出过一些错。对我来说，不利因素是时间。我坚信多头涨势很快就要结束，所以市场行情虽然有一点儿改观，布兰迪也受到了些鼓舞，可事实最终必定会证明，这就是个小小的回光返照而已。我怕在自己为油品公司股票做出成绩之前，市场就会变成空头。可我已经许诺过，所以还是要放手一搏。

我开始拉抬股价，但是并不顺畅。我觉得我把股价抬高到107美元左右的时候，就很不错了，我还能卖出一些股票。虽然不多，可让我高兴的是，没加大他们的持股总数。很多公司外的人在等着出现小幅度的上涨，以便卖出手中的股票。在他们看来，我会为他们创造绝佳的机会。如果综合行情好的话，我的表现可能会好一些。他们没早些让我来做，简直是个很糟糕的事情。我认为现在我只能尽力让他们以最小损失卖掉持股。

我把布兰迪叫来，对他讲了我的意思。他一开始不同意，然后我向他解释了我这么做的原因，我说：“布兰迪，我能够清晰地感受到市场脉搏，没人理会你的股票。想知道人们对我的炒作会产生什么反应并不要什么技巧。听着，当你尽力把油品公司的股票包装得吸引人，也准备随时提供所需的支持时，却发现人们不买账，你就能够确定其中存在问题了。不是股票的问题，而是市场的问题。违背股市行情行事不会起什么作用的。如果这么做，一定会赔本。有人跟进了，操盘的人就应该赶紧买回股票，可是如果市场上只有他一个买盘，那他还买的话就太蠢了。我买进5000股的时候，人们也愿意或者有能力跟买5000股，可我确实不想独自来买。我若这样做，就只是积攒了我并不想要的一些做多的股票。此刻能做的只有一件事情，那就是卖，往出卖才是唯一的办法。”

“你的意思是不管多少钱都卖？”布兰迪问。

“是的！”我说。察觉到他想马上反对，我赶紧说，“我如果卖出这只股票，你应该清楚，价格必定跌破面值，而且……”

“不，这可不行！”他大声说道。听他的声音，你一定以为我是在邀请他参加杀人俱乐部。

“布兰迪，”我说，“炒作股票的基本原则是要抬高股价以便卖出。可你在上涨的时候不能大量卖出，你做不到。大量往外卖，要从头部一直下跌的时候开始。我没办法让股价达到125美元或者130美元。我想要这个结果可无能为力。因此，你必须要按照目前的价格卖出。我觉得，所有股票都要跌，油品公司不会逃得过。反正都要下跌，与其等下个月那些股民抛售导致剧烈下跌，还不如现在你们公司自己卖。”

我不觉得我说的话会让人心痛，可是就算你身在万里之外的中国，也会听到他痛苦的喊叫。他一点儿都听不进去我的话。这肯定是不行的，这样会让这只股票留下非常糟糕的记录，更别提它在银行质押贷款可能造成的那些麻烦了。

我继续对他说：“我觉得世界上不存在什么力量能防止油品公司的股票下跌15或者20个点，因为整个股市都要这样下跌。”我接着对他讲，“如果我希望他的股票会是个让人惊讶的例外，那就太荒谬了。”可我说的话一点儿作用都没起到，他一直坚持让我必须要尽力支撑住这只股票。

我眼前的这个人，是个聪明的商人，以前最成功的股票作手之一，在华尔街股市上赚过几百万美元的人，他对炒股游戏的知晓要比普通人深入得多，可是却在空头市场的初期，坚持要支撑一只股票。当然了，股票是他的没错，可做法确实特别不靠谱。总的来说，这是一件不符合规则的事情。我与他据理力争，可是起不了任何作用，他顽固地让我买进以给予支撑。

在股市大盘疲软、股市真正开始了暴跌的时候，油品公司自然不能例外。只是，我不仅没有卖出，还因为布兰迪的坚持，为他们买进了很多股票。

布兰迪这么做的唯一原因是他不相信空头市场已经来临。我坚信多头市场已近尾声，我不光用油品公司测试了市场，也通过买卖其他股票进行了测试，为我起初的猜测给以验证。我不会在完全属于空头市场的时候才去放空股票。至于油品公司，我自然一股都没卖，只放空了其他的股票。

就像我想的那样，油品公司把他们一开始就有的股票和为了拉抬股价却丝毫作用没起而买进的股票全部抱在了怀里，最终的结果还是卖掉了股票，可与布兰迪不让我卖的那个时候相比，他们卖出的价格更低。这不可能有其他结果，可布兰迪还是觉得他们没错，或者他自己没做错。我清楚的是，他说我向他提意见，是因为我放空了其他的股票，可是股市依然是上升趋势。这明显是在说，如果没有进行限价就买完手中的股票，会让油品公司股票暴跌，这样会帮助我在其他股票的空头部位。

这纯粹是信口开河。我不看好股市行情，并非我放空了股票，而是因为我预估股市大盘的发展走向就是这样，我只有在自己从做多转为做空的时候，才会放空。朝着错的方向走，不会有钱可赚，尤其是炒股。我打算卖掉他们的股票，是因为二十年来的经验告诉我，这是最靠谱的操作。布兰迪本应是个很厉害的交易者，能够跟我一样搞明白情势才对。那时候，要做什么事情都为时已晚了。

我觉得布兰迪与大量不懂行的人类似，产生了错觉，认为一位作手什么都可以做到，没什么不可以。作手们可没有这样的本事，没办法做到。凯恩最大的成就是1901年春天炒作美国钢铁公司普通股与特别股。他做到了，不是因为他多么智慧过人或者资金多么庞大，也不是因为他背后有一大堆全美国的牛气富豪为他撑腰。这些都只是片面因素，主要还是因为当时股市大盘和股民们的心理状况都非常适合炒作。

与经验和常识不符的做法不是什么好做法，华尔街的笨蛋们不都是不懂行的人。布兰迪不满意我的做法，我刚刚已经说了。他非常痛心，原因是我违背了自己的意愿而居然按照他的要求炒作了。

只要炒作的过程中不添加肆意歪曲的成分，只是把手里的股票卖掉，就没什么神秘可言，也不会有不公平和欺诈的因子。炒作要健全，必须要有健全的交易原则作支撑。人们都很重视洗盘等这些老式的手段，可我保证，纯粹的技巧并没多大重要性。顾客性质不同，使得炒作股票和在柜台交易股票和证券有一定的差别，并不是因为人们的诉求不一样。摩根公司卖出证券，是卖给投资人，而炒作股票的作手卖出股票，是卖给投机分子。投资人想要的是稳中求胜，为投出的资本找到源源不断的回报，而投机分子要的是迅速获得利润。

股票作手的主要市场目标在投机人群中，投机者们只要机会合适，能够看到大笔好处，就想冒着高于正常状态的险去赚钱。这种盲目的赌法我并不相信，我可能会大笔操作，也可能只操作100股，可不管哪种情形，我都要找到要那么做的充分理由。

我记得很清楚，自己是如何投入到股票炒作——也就是帮别人行销股票——的游戏中的，提起这事我就非常愉悦，因为它能够很巧妙地展现出华尔街上的行家们是怎样看待股市操作的。这事发生在我那次东山再起以后，也就是1915年我交易完伯利恒钢铁股票并且收回资本的时候。

我的交易很稳定，运气也不差。我从来不想着通过报纸露面，不过我也不刻意回避。同时你也清楚，华尔街的专家们总会特意夸大活跃玩家的成败事迹。报纸会根据一点儿内幕消息刊登报道。按照谣言的说法，我都破产过多次了。按照一些很权威的人所传的那样，我也赚过几千万美元，所以对于那些传言，我只能做出一个反应，那就是很难理解它们是怎么来的，为什么会传播开来。我很吃惊的是，谣言怎么会这么猛烈。那些营业员朋友常常会来对我讲同一个故事，每一次都与上一次略有不同，故事在慢慢增加新的内容，然后逐步详尽起来。

我唆了这么多，只是要让你知道，我是怎样开始了帮别人炒作的业务。我偿还了那几百万美元的事情经过报纸报道后，发挥了很大的作用。我每次大量买进或卖出，都会被报纸无限放大，搞得我成了华尔街上的谈资。作手只要炒作20万股就可以完全操纵股市的时期已经不复存在了，可你知道，人们总想着要寻找一个能替代旧时代的新时代标杆。凯恩用高超的技巧博得了股票大作手的名气，依靠自己的本事赚了成千上百万美金，那些银行和承销商邀请他代操股市，帮他们抛售股票。简单地说，华尔街上流传着他过去的成功事迹，所以市场确实也需要他的炒作服务。

可凯恩已经离世了，此后还出现过两三个创造了几个月股市历史的人物，他们因为很久没有动静了，已经销声匿迹。我说的是那几位大手笔玩股票的西部人，他们于1901年来华尔街后，依靠自己拥有的美国钢铁公司股票赚了数千万美元。他们其实是大型股票承销商，不是凯恩那样的大作手。可他们的确很厉害，还很有钱，在推销他们与朋友控股的公司证券方面做出了很大的成绩。他们实际上与凯恩或者弗劳尔州长不一样，并非伟大的作手，可华尔街人还是觉得有一大堆关于他们的事情可谈论。在专业的炒股手和活跃的证券交易商当中，肯定有他们的一批忠实粉丝。他们不再积极交易以后，华尔街上再也找不到值得人们谈论的作手了，起码在报纸上很难出现相关报道了。

你该记得，1915年交易所恢复了业务后，在一段时期内，出现过很大的多头市场。市场规模不断扩大，协约国在美国买了价值数十亿美元的物资，美国从而变得异常繁荣。如论炒作，谁都不必花费多少心力，就能为战争带来的新形势创造出很大的市场。大量的人依靠合约，甚至依靠可以得到合约的口头承诺，就赚了几百万美元。他们靠着乐于帮忙的银行家，或者靠着让自己的公司在没有上市的市场中开展买卖，成了非常成功的股票承销商。任何一个被宣传过的东西，人们都会争相购买。

繁荣的高潮过后，这些承销商觉得自己需要一些股票专业人士来帮忙。当人们对各种证券感兴趣的时候，有的人以较高价格买进。想卖掉没在市场中经历风雨的股票是很难的事情。高潮过后，人们都确证，任何东西的价格都不再上涨了。这并非买的人变明智了，而是那种盲目的购买已经到了尾声，人们的心态变了。市价不用下跌，就让人们都变得很悲观。市场只要沉闷一定的时间后，就会出现这样的情况。

每一次市场繁荣的时候，都有一批公司冒出来，即便它们出现的原因不全是想借助人们强大的购买力赚钱，但至少主要原因是这样。有的人犹豫很久才把股票拿出来承销。承销公司出现这样的失误，原因是他们也只是人而已，不想让繁荣的现实离去。而且，只要潜在利润能大的话，就值得冒险一试。当希望遮挡了视线的时候，你就没办法看清头部。普通人见一只12美元或者14美元没人买的股票一下子涨到了30美元，以为这就是最高点了，可它却又上升到了50美元，这就必定是到了上涨的顶部了，可接着它又涨到60美元、70美元，然后到75美元。这样的局面能够确定了，几周前还是15美元，现在肯定不再涨了。可是，它又涨到了80美元，接着是85美元。此时，大多数普通股民都只想的是价格，而不去思考它应有的价值，同时他们的行动不是由情势主导，而是由恐惧主导，所以他们就采用了最容易的方式，不再觉得涨势会到头。就因为这个原因，不懂行的人可能虽然非常聪明，不在头部买进股票，但是也不获利落袋。市场繁荣景气的时候，人们总是先赚到很多账面上的利润，而最终只能把它们保持在账面上。

第二十二章

一天，我的好朋友，同时也是我的一位主要经纪商吉姆·巴恩斯来找我，他说需要我帮个忙。这样的话要是放在以前，他是从来不会说的。我问他需要帮什么忙，希望我能够帮得上，因为我确实想表达一下我对他的感激之情。他告诉我说，与某只股票有关，事实上他们是这家公司的主要承销商，而且握有很多股票，现在行情变了，他们想把这一大笔股票卖出去。吉姆想让我帮他推广这个联合炉具公司的股票。

因为很多原因，我不想受这件事牵连，可是我受过吉姆的恩惠，他又从个人角度来求我帮忙，仅凭这一点，就足以说服我。我的朋友吉姆是个好人，我想他的公司必定与这件事情关系很深，因此我最终决定要尽力帮他。

我总觉得，战争带来的市场繁荣与其他情况下的市场景气之间有个最明显的区别，那就是青年银行家们在股市中有了自己的新角色。

这一次的股市繁荣属于自发现象，谁都清楚其中的原因，可同时，美国的最大银行与信托机构也在使出吃奶的力气帮各种承销公司和军火商，使他们在很短时间内就摇身一变，成了百万富翁。其中的情形非常可笑，只要某人说他的朋友在联军委员会有朋友，就会得到别人送上的一大笔所需资金，开展还没到手的合约。我曾听人说过一些离谱的事情，小员工成了公司总裁，做了几百万的交易，就是靠着信托公司的信任借到了钱，然后在人们之间转来转去，让谁都受到了合约的恩惠。从欧洲向美国流入了数目巨大的黄金，银行就必须要找到办法来储存这些黄金。

这样做生意，让老前辈们看到肯定会非常不齿，可此时已经很少有老前辈们活跃了。在和平年代，老当益壮的银行总裁恰逢其时，可在这样的非常时期，他们压力很大，年轻才是主要的本钱。很明显，银行获得了非常令人艳羡的利润。

马歇尔国民银行的那位年轻总裁，与吉姆及其合伙人的关系很好，深获信任，他们打算将三家很有名气的炉具公司合并到一起，再把新公司的股票推销出去。过去的好几个月里，只要有股票，不管什么股，人们都想着要买进。

其中有个问题，就是炉具公司业务很好，所以，这三家公司自成立以来，普通股是首次赚到股利。大股东们不想丢掉控制权。在没有上市的市场中，股票行情很好，大股东们愿意放出去的股票都已经被抢购一空，这样的结果令他们非常满意。这三家公司有一些非常小的资本额，没办法让市场出现波动。此时，吉姆的公司进来了，他说只要三家公司合并，那就足以在交易所挂牌了。此后，新股的价值肯定高于旧股。在华尔街，这算是老套路了，让股票换身装扮，就能提高价值。比如当一只股票按照面值很难卖出的时候，只要把它一分为四，就能用30美元或35美元的价格卖掉。这就相当于原来的股票是按照120美元或者140美元的价格卖出。而这样的价位，原来的股票是不可能实现的。

看来吉姆及其合伙人鼓动了一群朋友支持合并计划，他们为了实现投机的目的，持有很多格瑞炉具公司的股票。这家炉具公司很大，因此合并方式是用一股格瑞的旧股票兑换四股联合炉具的新股票。然后，中部炉具与西部炉具也紧随其后，用一股换一股的条件加入了合并计划。他们两家公司在没上市市场上的股价是25到30美元，格瑞比较有名且有股利可分，因此股价大概是125美元。

他们从那些坚持要卖出股票从而套现的股东手里买断了股票，用来筹集资金。同时为了有足够改观业务的额外运营资金和承销费用，他们需要募集几百万美元。所以，吉姆以10万新公司的股票作为质押，去跟心肠不错的马歇尔国民银行总裁借了350万美元。就我知道的情况，公司内部向银行总裁保证过，股价不会低于50美元。这个交易的价值不小，所以里面的利润非常可观。

公司人士行事的第一个错是没有掌握好时机。新股在市场流通中已经饱和，他们应该知道这个，可即使这样，他们若不想像其他公司那样，得到在股市最景气的时候能得到的高额利润，也就能够赚到不小一笔资金了。

你不能轻易说吉姆和合伙人是一群笨蛋或经验欠缺的毛头小子。他们可都是精明的成年人，对华尔街上的一切手段都很清楚，有的人甚至是非常出色的股票交易者。可是他们的所作所为，却不光是高估了股民们的购买力。毕竟，他们在实打实地进行市场测试前，是没办法判断购买力有多少的。他们更严重的错是想着让多头市场持续时间更长一些。我觉得，可能是因为他们曾经都成功地做过交易，尤其是在快速操作而赚钱方面成就突出，从而致使他们对自己能够在多头市场疲软之前就赚到钱充满信心。他们都名气不小，在业内的专业交易者和证券经纪商当中都有粉丝。

这个事例的宣传很到位，报纸确实非常大方，报道了一大篇内容，提到那三家公司是美国炉具产业的范本，产品在世界上都很有名气，合并三家公司，是爱国主义行为。日报上发表了很多报道，说他们在世界范围内是如何开疆拓土的，已经在亚非拉地区的市场中站稳了脚跟。

阅读报纸财经版的读者们都知道，这家公司的董事都是非常著名的人物。公关工作搞得好，公司内部没有署名的人也做了承诺，说股价一定会呈现出什么样的结果，非常肯定且有说服力，所以为新发行的股票搭建了很大的市场需求。最终在申购完了以后，按照50美元公开销售的股票，认购量超出了四分之一。

你想啊，公司使了好几周的劲儿，把股价提升到了75美元以上，平均股价也达到了50美元以上，能够看到的最好结果是按照这样的价位，把所有新股都卖出去。以这个价位释股，说明合并了的几家公司的股票原来的价格大概翻了一番。这是一次危机，他们本该做出应对措施，却纹丝不动。这说明每个行业都有自身的特殊需求，常人的眼光没有专业人士的眼光那么有价值。公司的人因为股票被超额认购而非常高兴，他们很确定地以为，不论它的价格高到多少，发行多少股，人们都会拿着金钱没有节制地买进。他们真是愚蠢至极，竟然没有足额配售准备减持给大众的股票。公司内部决定要贪心时，也应该贪得稍微聪明点儿呀。

全额配售股票，这是他们最该做的事。如此一来，当他们把那些说要公开销售出去的所有股票都卖给股民后，还有四分之一的不足。在必要的时候，这个不足应该能够起到支撑股价的作用，不用公司内部自己出钱。公司内部没有丝毫付出，就能让自己位于非常优势的股市战略地位，这可是我炒作股票的时候，一直想办法找寻的优势。他们本来能够对股价下跌做出防范措施，鼓舞股民们对这只新股充满信心，从而对股票背后的公司坚定信心。公司应该知道在把配售的股票发售给股民们以后，自己的工作并没完，这些都仅仅只是他们必须要做的一部分。

公司自己觉得做得很不错，可没过多长时间，他们所犯的两个巨大错误就导致了严重的后果。人们看到股市出现了回调迹象，就不再去买进这只新发行的股票了。公司内部也跟着担心了，也就没有去支撑联合炉具股票。在股市回调期，如果连自己内部的人都不买进股票的话，那谁还会去买呢！内部人士都不支持，往往就会被看作已经是很清晰的利空信号了。

没必要再说那些详细的统计数字了，联合炉具股票的价格与股市中的其他股票一样，波动起伏着。不过再也没有高过一开始上市时稍高于50美元的价格。吉姆和他的合伙人最终只好买进，以便把股价稳定在40美元以上。在刚刚上市时不支持这只股票，这让人觉得非常遗憾和可惜。可是，没有把股民们认购的股票全部销售出去，这是更加失败的举动。

总而言之，这只新股票在纽交所顺利地挂牌，然后股价也很自然地在下滑，直至以37美元的价格停住才罢。股价能够在这个价格上停止，是因为吉姆及其合伙人必须把股价顶到这个价位上。他们合作的银行质押了10万股，按照每股35美元向他们借了钱，假如银行想要斩断股票收回贷款，那还真难说准股价会跌成什么样子。人们在50美元的时候急着往进买，如今跌成37美元了，反而对它没了任何兴趣，或许就算跌到27美元都还会是无人搭理的状态。

时间长了，人们就开始思索银行大量往外放款的事。青年银行家们的日子临近尾声了，银行业好像面临着重要转折，仿佛在猛然之间，就要回归原来那种谨慎保守的状态。那些本来和银行家非常亲近和友好的人，如今被银行家追着要债，让他无论如何都要还款，好像双方之间以前从来没有一起玩过高尔夫一般。

放款的这边不可能逼迫，贷了款的这一边又不会求着对方宽限些时日。这样的状态，让两边都很为难。就像我的朋友吉姆，与他打交道的银行还是那么友好的样子，可情况已经变成了：“请一定要还清贷款，不然我们都会面临无法想象的后果。”

面临这样的困难局面，以及有可能引发的严重后果，吉姆不得不来找我帮忙，让我代卖10万股，回收资金，还银行那350万美元的贷款。他已经不做通过这些股票赚钱的梦了，只要公司能少亏掉一点儿，他们就谢天谢地了。

这看起来是个没有任何希望的任务。股市大盘没有一点儿活力，后劲不足，偶尔出现个小小反弹，人们都精神一振，打算相信多头市场即将来临，仅此而已。

我对吉姆说需要分析一下后再告诉他，我如果想做这个事情，需要什么条件。我的确分析了一下这个事情，我研究的不是公司的最新年报，而只是想弄清这个问题发生在股市行情中的哪个阶段。我不用公司盈余和未来的理想走向去为这只股票打开市场，抬高价格，而要通过公开市场把这些股票清空。我需要思考的是，仅仅在这个任务当中，哪些因素应该能够或者可能帮到我，哪些因素又会或者可能会对我不利。

比如，我看到少数人手中握着大量的股票，意味着他们控制了过多数量的股票，因此会很不安全，数量多到了足以让人寝食难安的程度。克里夫顿·甘恩公司持股7万，他们公司的业务包括银行投资和经纪行当，也是纽交所会员，还是吉姆的朋友。多年以来，这家公司一直醉心于炉具股票，所以在三家公司的合并事宜上，他们的作用非同小可，他们也诱导了自家客户，使之对这只股票的前景抱了很大幻想。原参议员塞缪尔·戈登也手持7万股，他是他侄子开的一家名为戈登兄弟公司的高级合伙人。还有，名气很大的约书亚·伍尔夫也有6万股。华尔街的这几个老行家一共持有联合炉具公司的20万股，不用哪个好心人士对他们说什么时候应该卖出。如果我有炒作迹象，想吸引人们买进股票，也就是把这只股票弄得比较活跃有力，必然会看到甘恩、戈登和伍尔夫要往外抛出必定不是小数目的股票。一想到他们那20万股会像尼亚加拉大瀑布那样涌入股市，就不会愉快。不要忘记，多头市场的高峰期已经过去了，无论我有多高超的操作技巧，都不可能搭建出非常广阔的市场需求。吉姆有节制地退后，以便把事情交给我来做，而他并没有多少美好的幻想。在多头市场临终的时候，他把这只水分很高的股票交给我去卖。报纸上当然没有关于多头市场临近结束的报道，可我清楚这个局面，吉姆跟我一样清楚，甚至能够肯定，银行也非常清楚。

可我答应了，因此就托人去请甘恩和伍尔夫。那20万股，就像国王请达摩克利斯吃饭时，悬在他头顶的剑一样。我想，要把头发换成一条大铁链，这样才会安全。我觉得，最轻巧的办法就是与他们制定一个共赢合同。如果他们对我稍加配合，在我卖出银行那10万股的时候，他们能够忍住不卖，我就能够帮他们创造出一个大家可以一起出售股票的市场。事情本该如此，就算他们想卖出十分之一的股票，又不想让联合炉具股票下跌，是不可能的事情。他们非常明白，因此也没试图往外卖。我只是希望他们在合适的时候再卖，不要让自私压制了理智。无论是在华尔街还是其他地方，占了有利的位置却无所作为，不会有好果子吃。我准备让他们彻底明白，太早抛售或者不考虑别人就去抛售，是会妨碍出售股票的，时不我待啊。

我希望提出的建议能够说服他们这些经验老到的华尔街大腕，不要在联合炉具股票上抱太大的幻想。甘恩的公司生意非常好，分公司都开到了11个城市，有大量顾客，他还多次做过股票炒作集团的操盘人。

参议员戈登有7万股，是个大富豪。他曾经受到过一个年仅16岁的女美甲师对他背信弃义的控告，所以《都市新闻报》的读者们对他的大名非常熟悉。那个美甲师有一件5000美元的貂皮大衣和戈登写给她的132封信。戈登帮助侄子们创建了公司，他本人也是公司的高级合伙人。他曾经在几十个炒作集团里参与过业务。他以继承的方式掌握了中部炉具公司的一大把股票，其后用它们换了合并的联合炉具公司的10万股。他手中有这么多股票，完全不用管吉姆提供的不靠谱的利好消息，所以他可以在多头市场慢慢消散前就卖出3万股，换回现金。后来，他对朋友说，是其他股东和与他关系很亲近的老朋友们劝他不要再卖出，他才因为顾及情面，没有再出售，要不然他就会卖出更多的股票。此外我刚才也提到过，市场也没有为他的卖出提供机会。

第三个人就是伍尔夫，或许他是三人中间最著名的一个。在过去的20年，谁都清楚他是交易大厅里有名的赌棍。他在拉抬和掼压股价领域鲜有对手，对他而言，两三万股票和两三百股票是没什么不一样的。我在去纽约之前就对他的赌博名声耳熟能详。他那时候还在一个非常喜好赌博又没有限定赌资上限的小公司里做事，那是一家既赌股票又赌马的小集团。

人们都习惯于说他就是个赌徒，除此之外一无是处，可他的能力确实非常强，对待投机游戏也有很值得称赞的态度。而且，据说他对追求知识毫无兴趣，因此也有很多与他相关的奇闻逸事。一个流传最广的笑话说，有一次伍尔夫参加上流社会的宴会，女主人考虑不周全，使得很多宾客都互相谈论起了文学，气氛热烈得连女主人都没办法制止了。

坐在伍尔夫身边的一个女孩不知道他那张嘴巴只会用来吃饭，所以回头与他对话，急切地想知道这个大富豪有什么看法。她问他：“嗯，伍尔夫先生，你怎么看待巴尔扎克？”

伍尔夫非常礼貌，停止了吃东西，然后咽下口中的食物后说：“对于那些没有上市的股票，我是从来不交易的。”

他们就是联合炉具公司的三个最大股东。与他们见面后，我对他们说，假如他们能组成一个小团队，筹集到一笔钱，然后以比市价稍高一点儿的股价，把买进股票的选择权交给我，我就会设法搭建起赚钱的市场。他们马上就问，到底需要多少钱。

我回答说：“你们手里握着联合炉具的股票很长时间了，却没有任何办法。你们合起来有20万股，你们自己非常清楚，你们除了能够搭建一个市场去交易之外，根本没有丝毫的时机卖出。这个市场必须要足够大，才能完全吸纳你们的这笔股票，现金也要足够多，才可以在一开始买进必须要买的股票。如果钱不太够，开始了又停顿不前，是起不了作用的。我建议你们成立联合小团队，筹集600万，再按照40美元的股价，把20万股票的买进选择权授予你们的小团队，同时把你们手中所有股票托管在信托账户。不出问题的话，你们会卖掉手中那些僵死的鸟儿，你们小组也能赚到一笔钱。”

正如我之前所说，坊间流传着我在股市上赚钱的各种谣言。我想这些说我成功了但其实没有成功的流言是有助于我的。总而言之，我不需要向他们多做什么解释。他们非常明白，如果只靠单打独斗，事情不会有什么进展，他们觉得我的想法不错。临走时，他们答应要成立一个小团队。

这三人没怎么耗费精力就成功劝说了很多朋友加入。我想，他们谈论这个小团队的利益时，比我还要确定。我听到的所有消息都说，他们非常确信我的看法，所以他们的内幕消息有一定的依据。总之在几天后，他们就联合成立了一个小团队。甘恩、戈登和伍尔夫按照40美元授予了我20万股票的买进选择权，我为这些股票成立了信托管理。这样，就不会在我拉抬股价的时候，有股票溜进市场中了。这个团队中的人员之间没有多少信任度，很多非常有可能成功的交易，却没有像预料的那样成功，类似的例子很多，所以我要做好自我保护。在华尔街上，狗没有反对咬狗的愚蠢偏见。那时候，第二家美国钢铁线缆公司上市，公司内部互相指责说对方违约，在想办法出售股票。约翰·盖茨与他的朋友，赛里曼斯家族和银行合伙人之间，都曾经有过君子协定。好吧，我在经纪商那里却听到了别人读过下面这首据说是盖茨写的诗：

毒蜘蛛跳上蜈蚣的背，
残忍又幸灾乐祸地发笑，
我要毒死这个害人精，
否则的话它就会反过来毒死我。

请注意，我没有一丁点儿影射华尔街的朋友们曾经在股市上欺骗我的意思，不过出于原则，你还是要为所有突发事件做好准备，这是显而易见的。

甘恩、戈登和伍尔夫对我说了他们已经组团的消息，并说准备筹集600万现金。接下来，我无事可做，就等着这笔款到位。我让他们加快速度，这是非常重要的。不过这笔款项是分阶段到位的，大概通过四五次才完成筹备。我不知道其中的原因，可我有印象的是，我向他们三人发过特别紧急的求救信号。

某天下午，一笔大款项的支票到了我手中，我也就有了大概400万的现金，同时我也接到他们的承诺，说其余款项过上一两天就能到位。如今来看，在多头市场结束前，这个小团队可能会获得一些小成就。不过，就算各方面条件都达到最佳程度，那也不是百分百肯定的，我行动开始得越早越有利。一只本来不受待见的股票，忽然出现了一些新动向，股民们是不会有多大兴趣的。不过当你手中有了400万美金后，能够做的事情就会更多，完全可以使人们对这只股票产生兴趣。这笔款完全能够吸进一切有卖出可能性的股票。时机如果真的跟我说的一样迫在眉睫，我也就不需要等还没到位的那200万了，我越能够趁早把股价抬高到50美元，对这个小团队来说也越有利，这是显而易见的。

第二天一早，股市开盘后，我惊奇地发现，联合炉具公司股票出现了大量的交易，这是非常难得一见的现象。正如我刚刚所说，好几个月来，它一直处于萎靡不振、一步都迈不动的状态，股价也一直在37美元左右停滞。吉姆使出了吃奶的劲儿，试图让它不要再下跌不止。他按照每股35美元向银行质押，贷回来一笔巨款。提到上涨，他是想看到联合炉具股票价格上涨，可是这却比看到直布罗陀海峡的礁石在海面上漂移还要困难。

伙计啊，这只股票在那天早上表现出的需求量真是大，股价涨到了39美元。在第一个小时的交易段内，交易量就超过了以往半年的成交总量。当天，这只股票成了最热门的股票，同时整个股市都受到了它的影响，有了一点儿多头市场的气色。后来，我听说人们在交易大厅内都不谈论其他事情，只讨论与这只股票有关的话题。

我不清楚这是什么意思，可看到联合炉具股票活了过来，我就觉得在感情上没有受到打击。通常而言，我没必要去打听很难见到的股票波动的消息，我那些交易大厅里帮我做交易的朋友和其他好朋友都会向我传达消息。他们觉得我肯定想知道，所以会把他们听到的所有消息和谣言都通过电话告诉我。

我在这天听到了联合炉具公司确实有内部人在买进股票的消息，没有任何洗盘动作，所有的交易都是正儿八经的买进。买股票的人在股价到37至39美元的时候，把所有卖出的股票都尽收囊中，人们请他给个这么做的理由，哪怕提供一点儿内幕消息也行，可是却没有得到答复。这个现象，使得那些紧盯着市场的聪明的交易人员觉得，一定有什么内幕在酝酿，会有很大的行情变动。公司内部的人买进自家股票，使得股价上涨，而他们又不鼓励其他股民跟进，这就让那些执着的股民开始到处搜索消息，打听到底什么时候会有正式的变动通知。

我个人什么都没干，只是认真观察，甚觉奇怪。我也追踪着这只股票的交易走势。第二天，人们买进这只股票的数量越发多了，而且更加猛烈。按照业内账册的记录，之前几个月里37美元以上想卖却没卖出的股票，此时非常轻松地就被市场吸纳了，而且又没有更多的新卖单拉住上涨的势头。股价一如既往地上升，超过40美元，然后又涨到了42美元。

此时，我认为应该把银行质押的那些股票抛出了。我自然不会觉得，我卖出这么多股票会拉低股价，而只要我整体持股的平均成本在37美元，就没人指摘我。我清楚这只股票的价值，通过对它在几个月里被冷落的状态进行观察后，我或多或少了解了这只股票的市场情况。我谨慎地把股票卖向市场，最后卖出了3万股，真的没有拉低涨势。

那天下午，有人对我讲了出现这种及时又神奇的涨势的原因。好像在前一天收盘后到这一天开盘前的这段时间，有人向营业员透露消息，说我如烈火般凶猛地看好联合炉具公司，还打算按照以往惯例，把股价抬高15到20个点，中途不会停歇。所谓我的惯例，其实是那些从不会去研究我记录的人的片面看法。负责传播内幕消息的人是伍尔夫，真是来头好大呀。正是因为他自己的内线买进了股票，使得股价从前一天开始上涨。他那些营业员群体中的好朋友非常高兴跟着他的消息走，他了解的内幕真的很多，不会对跟随自己的粉丝们提供假消息。

其实，进入市场的股票比我原来担心的要少一些。你要是记得我已经控制住了30万股，就明白我起先的那些担心并非多余，现在要拉升股价变得轻松多了。弗劳尔州长说得对——每天都会有人骂他炒作自己公司负责的如芝加哥瓦斯和联邦钢铁等股票——他说：“我知道只有买进才是让股价上涨的唯一办法。”这也是营业员们抬升股价的唯一方法。价格会反映买盘，跟着上涨。

第二天早餐前，我在报纸上看到了一条消息，这是好多人都能看到的，没什么可怀疑的，这条消息会通过电报送达几百家股票分公司和外地的股票交易公司。报道说，拉里·利文斯顿马上会下大功夫做多联合炉具股票。各个报纸的报道中涉及的细节性内容大同小异，有一家说我组织了一个内部机构，准备向那些过度放空的空头进行大反击。还有一家报道说，公司在不久后就要发布配股消息。另有报道也在提醒人们，要注意我在操作那些吃香的股票时取得的成就，但同时也有报道说这个公司为了让内部人士吃饱股票，从而隐藏了资产。一切新闻报道都觉得这只股票的涨势才刚刚开始。

那天早上，在开盘之前，我还没到办公室看我的信件，就已经得知华尔街上充斥着刚出炉的内幕消息，让大家赶紧买联合炉具的股票。我的电话响了一上午，电话员接到了上百个电话，问的都是同一个问题：联合炉具的股价到底会不会上涨。我必须承认，伍尔夫、甘恩和戈登，或许还有吉姆，他们把透露内幕消息这样的事情做得天衣无缝。

我真不知道追随我的人这么多。哈，一早上收到了大量来自全国各地的买单，都买的是几千股，这只股票在三天前可是多低价位都没人搭理呀。你不要忘记，其实股民们完全是靠着报纸知道了我是个非常成功的大赌徒，这可得感谢那些极富想象力的记者。

伙计们，情况发展成这样，股价上涨第三天的时候，我卖出了联合炉具的股票，紧接着连卖了三天，然后才察觉我已经把吉姆质押给马歇尔国民银行的10万股抛售空了，这可是350万美元的质押股呀。如果说，一个作手花最低的成本实现了最终目标属于最成功的炒作，那么这次有关联合炉具的炒作肯定是我在华尔街的奋斗历程中最出色的成绩。啊，我连任何股票都没有买进，我都没有为了后来能够卖出得轻松些而先买进。我也没有把股票抬升到最高点再正儿八经地卖出。我甚至不必在价格一路走低时把卖出作为主要的行动，反而是在价格抬升时卖出的。这简直就如同在游乐场里做了个美梦，没有耗费多少精力，就挖掘出了别人为你搭建的庞大的买方市场。特别是在你急着想抛售的时候。以前，我听弗劳尔州长的朋友说过，有一次，这位伟大的多头领袖为一家公司炒作的时候，这家公司获利卖出了5万股，可是弗劳尔团队却赚了超过25万股的交易手续费。汉密尔顿提到过，詹姆斯·凯恩为了售出联合铜矿公司的22万股，通过必要的炒作过程，最少需要做70万股的交易。这样的手续费成本太高了。对照这些情况，再看看我付出的手续费，只有我为吉姆卖出10万股的那点儿费用，我觉得这是个非常了不起的事情。

虽然他们同意筹集的600万资金没有完全到位，可我向好友吉姆做出的承诺已经实现，我也不想把之前自己卖出的任何股票再买进来，反而只想好好找个地方去度个短假。我的记忆已经模糊了，可我清楚记得的是我让这只股票顺其自然地去发展，不久后它就价格下跌了。某一天，整个股市都很疲软，一个做多头的人很失望，他想迅速卖掉手里的联合炉具股票。由于他引发的卖压，使得股价跌破了40美元，到了我买进选择权的价位以下。好像没人再想要这只股票了。我原来说过，自己并不怎么太看好股市，所以我很感激出现了那一点儿奇迹，使我能够卖掉10万股，而且还没有出现与传达消息的大善人所预想的情形，即在一周内将股价拉升二三十美元。这只股票在没有支撑的情况下，价格一直下跌。有一天跌得非常严重，到了有史以来的最低价位32美元。估计你还记得，吉姆和他的伙伴们把持的股价是37美元，以防银行拿他们的10万股去市场釜底抽薪。

那天，我安静地坐在办公室里研究股市行情，有人说伍尔夫来了。我请他进来后，一眼就看到他直冲我过来，不太高大的身躯被怒气包裹着，好像发胖了一般。

他走到我跟前，大声说道：“哎，这算怎么回事？”

“伍尔夫先生，请坐吧。”我客气地说完后坐了下来，好让他能够平静下来。

“我不坐，我只想知道是怎么回事？”他把嗓门提到了最高。

“什么怎么回事？”

“你到底把它怎么了？”

“我把什么怎么了呀？”

“就是股票，那只股票！”

“哪只股票？”我问道。

我这样一无所知的样子更加使他生气了，他继续吼着：“联合炉具。你把它怎么了？”

“没怎么呀，我肯定什么都没做，出什么问题了？”我问。

他直勾勾地瞪了我足足五秒钟，然后大叫：“你瞧瞧股价！瞧瞧！”他真的特别气愤。

我站起来看了看股价，然后说：“现在股价是31又1/4美元。”

“没错！31又1/4美元，而我手里有一大把。”

“你有6万股，我清楚。这笔股票在你手中时间不短了，因为你当时买进格瑞炉具的时候……”

他不等我说下去就打断了我的话，他说：“但是我后来又买了很多，有的是按照40美元高价买的，现在还在我手里！”

他怒火中烧地看着我，我说：“我又没让你买。”

“什么？”

“我没让你买那么多。”

“我的意思不是说你让我买的，可是你准备要拉抬股价……”

“我为什么要这样做？”我打断了他的话。

他气得一言不发，直盯着我，半天才开口说：“原来你是要抬高股价的，你有钱买。”

“没错啊，可是我没有买。”我对他说。这像是我最后亮出的撒手锏。

“你没买？你拿着400多万美金可以用，但是你没有买？”

“连一股都没买。”我重复道。

此时，他已经气得说不出话来了，良久才说道：“你这玩的是什么把戏？”

还不知他心里面怎么恶毒地骂我呢。从他的眼神中，我看到了他给我定的一连串罪责。我对他说：“伍尔夫，你想问的是，我为什么没用50美元以上的价格买你手里那些40美元以下买进的股票吧？”

“不，不是。你有40美元吸进的选择权，而且又有400万现金可以用来抬高股价。”

“没错，可是我并没有用这些钱，而且我也没有让这个团队赔一美元。”

“你听我说，利文斯顿……”他说。

不过我堵住了他要说的话。

“你听我说，伍尔夫。我清楚你和戈登、甘恩一共有20万股套在里面了，而且知道我如果拉抬股价的话，肯定没多少股票冲进股市，但我必须要这么做，因为一方面得为这只股票搭建出市场来，其次要利用40美元的选择权赚钱。可你要么是因为对自己手里拿了好几个月的6万股只卖到40美元非常不满意，要么是因为对小团队分给你的利润不满意，因此你在40美元以下的时候买进了很多股票，想在我用团队的那笔钱拉抬的时候再倒给我，你认定了我会这样。你想在我买之前自己先买进，而且在我卖出之前自己先卖出，总之你把我当作你倒卖股票的对象。我想你肯定觉得我能把股价拉抬到60美元。事情很清晰，你可能买进了1万股，就是为了再倒出。我如果不背黑锅的话，你为了确保有人背黑锅，就向美国、加拿大和墨西哥的所有股民透露内幕消息，根本不考虑为我增加了多少困难。你所有的朋友都知道我该怎么做，在我和他们买进的时候，你幸灾乐祸。哼，你把内幕透露给朋友，他们买进股票的时候，再把消息一传十、十传百地传播给更多的笨蛋，这么一来，等我最终要卖的时候，会发现自己面对的是好几千个聪明的投机分子。伍尔夫，这可真是个好心的主意啊。在我还没想到要买的时候，联合炉具就开涨了，你知道我有多吃惊，我有多感激，竟然以40美元的价位替大家把10万股卖给了那些想着等涨到五六十美元再倒卖出去的人。我没用那400万为团队谋利润，特别傻吧？那是我可以用到股票买进上的钱，可我要在自认为该买的时候买。嗯，而我觉得没必要去买进。”

伍尔夫在华尔街上混了好多年，不会让愤怒的情绪妨碍正事。在我说话的时候，他逐渐心平气和了。等我说完，他就比较友好地说：“你听我说，拉里，我的朋友，那我们该怎么办呢？”

“你们爱怎么办就怎么办。”

“呵呵，拿出点儿风度啊。你如果是我，你会怎么办？”

“我如果是你，”我认真地说道，“你想知道吗？”

“怎么办？”

“我会全部卖掉！”我回答道。

他盯着我好一会儿，一句话也没说，转身离开了办公室，这之后没再来过。

事后不久，参议员戈登也来找过我，抱怨是我让他们身处困境。最后，甘恩也跟着起哄。他们忘了在组建团队时，他们手中的股票一点儿都没法大把卖出去。他们只记得我手里握着几百万现金，而在市场比较活泛，股价涨到44美元的时候，没有为他们卖出。此时股价下跌到了30美元，像一潭绝望的死水。在他们看来，我就该为他们卖出股票，该为他们赚很多的钱。

过了一段时间，他们都逐渐心平气和了。这个小团队没有赔钱，仍然面临着需要卖掉大量股票的问题。过了一两天，他们找我帮他们解决困难，戈登尤其坚持。最后，我让他们把共同的股票锁在25又1/2美元上。我为他们效劳，酬金是按照这个价格卖出股票后一半的利润。这只股票最终报价在30美元左右，我又要为他们卖出股票了。在考虑整体股市行情，特别是联合炉具股票情况的前提下，只有一个办法能够卖出它，那就是一路往下卖，而且不能提前去做拉抬股价的事。我敢肯定，如果想着为了卖个比较好的价格而一路抬高，那肯定能收到很多股票，可是如果压低了价格卖，我可以找到人买。他们总觉得，只要在高点上下跌了15或20个点，就变得很便宜了，特别是从近期出现的高点上下跌，他们就会认为股价马上就要反弹。之前联合炉具涨到了44美元，如今跌到30美元以下了，就觉得必定是非常便宜的好股票。

这样卖，就与原先一样，非常顺利地实现了目标。那些捡便宜的人买了很多，使得我能够卖完小团队的持股。只是，你觉得戈登、伍尔夫和甘恩会感谢我吗？不可能的。他们还是对我充满了抱怨，反正他们的朋友是这么对我说的。他们常常对别人说，我是怎样收拾他们的。他们对我没拉抬股价以达成他们的心愿一直心存芥蒂。

其实，伍尔夫和其他人如果在当时不传播那些热热乎乎的内幕消息的话，我肯定是没办法卖掉10万股的。如果按照我一向的那种做法，也就是合理而自然地去操作，我就要让自己接受能卖的一切价格。我对你讲过，市场已经处于空头状态，有这样的前提，要卖出股票，不一定非要孤注一掷地做，可一定不能在价格上计较。除此之外别无他法，不过我觉得他们可能不相信我的这个观点。他们三人还是对我气呼呼的，而我却很平和。发怒不是什么好事。我经历过的那些不止一次的教训使我明白，爱生气的投机分子是没什么前途的。在这件事情上，他们生气并没为我留下什么后续的麻烦。可我要对你说的是，发生了一件奇怪的事情。有一天，我妻子去了一个经人推荐的女裁缝师那里。她是一个水平很高的裁缝，性格非常好，服务态度也不差。这是我妻子第三或第四次去，裁缝跟我妻子已经比较熟悉了。裁缝对她说：“我希望利文斯顿先生能够把联合炉具的股价拉抬起来，我们手里握着一些它们的股票，因为有人对我们说他要拉抬这只股票，我们向来就听说他经手的所有股票交易都非常成功。”

我对你讲，一想到那些无辜的人们因为听了那些所谓的内幕消息而损失了钱财，我就很不愉快。或许，如今你会明白，我为什么从来不对人说什么内幕消息。女裁缝的话让我感觉到，要说怨气，该由我对伍尔夫来发才对。

第二十三章

股票投机生意是永远不会消失的，人们也不希望它消失，那些关于投机有多危险的劝诫也不可能阻止投机。无论人们能力多强，或者有多么丰富的经验，都不可能不出错。那些意料不到和没办法预估的事情总会发生，导致你小心翼翼做的计划最终失败。厄运可能来自天灾或气候，可能来自人的贪欲或虚荣，也可能来自恐惧或对希望的不可遏制。可是，除了那些被叫作天敌的东西外，股票投机商们必须要与一些做法对抗，或者要能解决在正常情况下和商业土壤中不可以立足的恶行。

回想25年前我刚到华尔街那些司空见惯的行为时，必须要承认，很多东西已经好多了。旧的那种交易场所已经被淘汰，可是存在欺诈行为的交易所却还是生意很红火，残害着那些致力于一夜暴富的男女们。证券交易所做得非常好，不光查处了那些骗子，也始终要求会员公司严格遵守规则，实施了很多健全的法律法规，不过还是存在值得改进的地方，也存在一些恶行，这是由华尔街长期培植的保守习惯导致的，而不是源于人们道德上的麻木。

股票投机商赚钱历来都是很难的事，如今更是难上加难。不久前，真正的交易商们在每只股票上差不多都有操作的知识。1901年，摩根公司在纽交所推出了由一些小型联合公司组成的美国钢铁公司股票，那时只有275只股票挂牌，没上市的大概100只，里面有很多股价没必要知晓，因为都是微小股、次要股或保证股，没有活跃的交易，所以也就没有多少人愿意投入。实际上在一年中，大多数股票连一次都没交易过。而今天，正常的挂牌股票就有900只，最近交易活跃的大概是600只。而且，原来的股票容易按类股分类跟踪，当时的类股很少，资本额又不大。股民们需要知道的消息，也没有多大的涵盖面。可今天你却能够对每一只股票进行交易，全球的哪个行业都有股票上市。只有花费更多时间和精力，才能使自己的消息灵通。光这一点对聪明的股民们来说就已经知道投机比原来艰难了很多。

做股票交易生意的人成千上万，可真正获得利润的却很少。从某种程度上来看，人们总徘徊在股市中，常常受到损失。缺乏知识、贪欲太盛、担心过大和希望太强，都是股票投机人的致命弱点。世界上所有的法令和证交所的规则都不能把它们从人的本性中赶跑。出乎意料的事会击碎认真做过的计划，头脑清晰的经济学家和乐善好施的慈善家都没办法制止那样的事。另一种导致亏损的来源，是那些故意提供误导的不同于直接内幕消息的信息造成的。这样的信息往往包裹在不同的伪装里，在股民们中间传播，这是更阴森、更危险的敌人。

普通的外部人士自然要凭借口头或文字性的、直接的或间接的内幕消息来交易。你无法抗拒正常的内幕消息，比如与你一直要好的朋友很真诚地想帮你赚钱，所以对你说了他做的事情，买卖了什么股票。他怀着好心，可要是消息有误，你怎么办？而且，在专业人士或者骗子们传播消息这方面，股民们受到的保护，与他在面临假钱和假酒侵害上受到的保护差不多。可是，在与纯种的华尔街谣言对抗方面，投机人没有得到任何保护和补偿。很多从事证券销售的商人、作手、内线或者个人，以不同形式与方法，帮股民按最理想的价格交易股票。报纸和股市行情传出来的有关多头市场的报道都是很致命的。

随便拿哪天的报纸财经版看，都会惊奇地看到它刊登着一些暗示是来自半官方的声明，都是“重要内线”“知名董事”“公司高管”“权威人士”等所提供的消息。人们都觉得他们说得很有道理。下面是今天的报道，我随便选了一个：“银行界领袖说，现在说空头市场会出现还为时尚早，不能断言。”

说话的真是一位银行领袖？他为什么这么说？又为什么不报出姓名？是不是怕报出姓名后大家不相信？

还有一条与这周股票交易比较活跃的一家公司有关的消息，是一位“知名董事”所说。好吧，要真有这么一个人，那么他是这家公司那么多董事中的哪一个？诚然，不署名的爆料即便出错为别人带来了损失，也没办法责怪。

股票交易人要很明智地研究各地的交易市场，还要考虑与炒股游戏相关的事情；要想办法搞清楚怎么赚钱和怎么才不会亏损，要明白什么该做、什么不该做也非常重要。所以，你最好记清楚，一种炒作差不多会出现在个股的任何涨势中，这是内线们发起的涨势，就是为了能卖出赚钱的股票。可普通的交易公司的顾客们觉得，如果顽固地去挖掘一只股票上涨的原因，就是个刨根究底的聪明人。作手们肯定会按照特意布置的有利于卖出股票的手段来解释涨势。我坚定地觉得，如果主管部门不让报纸刊发不报姓名的利多言论，那股民们赔的钱就会少很多。我说的是那种特别策划的引导人们交易股票的言论。

利用不报姓名的董事和内线人士言论的大多数报道，向人们传达的都是不值得信赖的信息。股民们觉得消息性质是半官方的，就有必要相信，因此每年都会赔掉成百上千万美元。

比如说，某家公司的某项业务在某段时间比较疲软，公司股票很不受人待见。它在普通股民们心中的价值表现就是股价，而且可能是真实的价值。假如这个价位的股价便宜，就会有人知道这一点，接着去买进，股价就涨高；假如这个价位的股价贵，有人知道后就会卖，股价也就下跌。不存在这两种情况的话，人们就不会议论它，不会对它采取行动。

是谁最早知道公司业务有了好转？公司内部人士还是普通股民？肯定不是普通股民。然后会出现什么事？假如一直处于好转状态，盈余就会增多，公司就有恢复配股息的机会，如果一直不断裂，股利率就会提高。也就是说，股票的价值会变高。

如果情况持续好转的话，经营者会不会对外讲这个让人开心的事情？总裁会对股东们说吗？哪位好心的董事会有名有姓地告诉看报纸的读者们吗？那些谦虚的内线们会跟往常一样不报姓名地说公司的前景非常好吗？不会！没人会说，报纸和股票报价机器上都不会有任何信息。

他们会小心谨慎地阻止这类股票增值的消息传播，那些不怎么说话的著名内线会在股市中尽力获取能买到的所有贱股。这样的状况在持续的时候，股价就会上涨。财经版的读者们清楚，内线们知道股价为什么上涨，所以会去问。都不愿意透露姓名的内线人士会统一口径地说，他们没什么可透露，不知道为什么上涨。他们有时还会说自己并不太重视股市的奇怪行情，不重视股票投机者们的所作所为。

股价上涨到了让人们兴奋的时候，了解内情的人也买够了他们想买进或有能力买进的股票，华尔街上就会再次出现各种利多的传言。“按照权威人士透露的消息”，电报机会把公司的确由逆境转到顺境状态的消息让股民们知道。一位谦虚谨慎的董事以前会说，他不知道股票上涨的原因，而此时他的话却在人们口中被引述出来：股东们有对公司未来非常看好的充足理由。当然了，他还是没有透露姓名。

股民们受到洪水般的利好消息的蛊惑，开始购买那只股票，这就会使股价更高。时机成熟后，全部不愿意透露姓名的董事们的预测就很准啊，公司恢复了股利分配，甚至可能增加股利。如此消息弥散后，利多的消息铺天盖地，数量大增，传播消息的人也变得热情。当人们请某个重要董事直接讲明情形时，他会告诉全世界，好转现象不只是能持续而已；某位重要内线架不住人们的请求，最终在报社怂恿下，说公司盈余非常之高；某个与公司关系紧密的著名银行家也在别人请求下说，股票销售量增多，简直创造了这个行业的交易历史，在没有其他订单的前提下，公司日夜不停歇地运转，还不知道需要多少个月才能完成目前手里的业务量；某个财政委员会成员的表述在报纸上通过特殊处理后会变成，他很惊讶人们怎么会对这只股票上涨颇感意外。让人震惊的唯一现象是，股价上涨的速度慢了下来。不管谁去对公司将发出的年报进行分析，都能随便看出来，这只股票净值要远高于市场价。不过，那些善于与人们沟通的好心人不管在哪种情况下，都是不愿意透露姓名的。

公司内线人士只要看到盈余还在增长，没出现公司运气要减弱的表现，他们就会牢牢地握住低价回购的股票。没有什么让股价降低，他们凭什么要卖？不过，公司业务变得很差劲的时候，你看会出现什么情况？他们会发出声明、警告或一点儿小暗示吗？不可能。正如当时公司业务好的时候，他们没有大张旗鼓地买进股票一样，此时公司业务走下坡路了，他们必定也在偷偷地卖出。公司内线的卖出导致股价下跌，股民们紧接着就听到了一些熟悉的说法。一个重要内线人士咬紧牙说什么都很通畅，出现的小下跌是一些空头在掼压这只股票，想对整个股市施加些影响而已。如果某个时候，经过一阵下跌后的股价出现暴跌的情况，那么就会有更多的声音要求说明原因，给出解释。只要有人解释清楚就好，不然人们就会非常担心出现那种最可怕的情况。所以，如今新闻媒体的印刷机上正在印着这些报道：“当我们要求公司的一位重要董事解释清楚，为什么股价会这么糟糕时，他说导致今天股价下跌的唯一原因，就是那些空头在掼压。不过大趋势还没有发生变化，公司现在业务非常繁忙。而且，下次开会时，非常有可能会讨论提高股利分配比率的问题，除非出现预料之外的突发情况。市场空头们太猖狂了，股价不景气是他们掼压的结果，他们就是为了卖掉手里不好的股票。”新闻媒体为了让新闻更权威，可能还会补充写道，他们获悉了可靠消息，完全是由公司内线人士在股价下跌的这一天吃进了大多数股票，而那些空头会明白自作孽不可活，自己陷入了自己挖的陷阱，迟早会付出代价。

股民们对那些利多说法信以为真，买了好多股票，结果赔了钱，除此之外也有人因为受别人蛊惑，放弃了卖出而赔钱。防止人们卖那些重要内线们不想支持或不想买进的同一只股，是除了让人们买进他们想卖出的那只股票外第二好的办法。股民们看到重要董事的说法后，会相信什么？自然是相信这只股肯定不会下跌，而是空头掼压的表现，一旦空头停止卖出，内线们就会大反攻，对空头们施以惩戒，到那时空头们必须要用更多的钱来回补。人们绝对对这个观点信心十足，如果股票下跌确实是空头们掼压的结果，那么后续发展也就会如他们所想。

这只股票的价格并没有反弹。虽然出现了很多威胁和承诺，说要轧死那些放肆的空头，可股价还在下跌。怎么可能不跌，公司内线人士把那么多股票卖了出去，市场根本消化不过来。而且，重要董事和内线人士卖向市场的那一批股票，被专业的交易商们来回踢皮球。股价持续下跌，好像没有到头的时候。公司内线们清楚，业务情况对公司以后的盈余有严重的影响，因此在公司业务情况再次出现好转之前，没胆量再支撑股票了。等到有所好转时，内线们又会一点儿都不对外张扬，悄悄买进。

我做交易很多年，对市场消息非常灵通。我可以这么说，没有哪次的股价大跌是空头掼压的结果。通常意义上的掼压，实际上只是精确掌握了实际情况后卖掉股票而已。可如果说是内线不支持或者卖出股票而导致了股价下跌，却也行不通，这样的话，谁都要赶紧卖出股票，没有人买进，情况就会变得惨不忍睹。

人们应该牢记，股价持续下跌，真实的原因并非空头掼压的结果。当一只股票一直下跌，你就能确定里面必定出什么事了，不是因为市场，就是因为公司内部。假如下跌是没什么原因的，那么等股价下跌到真正的价值以下，就会有人购买，跌势也会被拉止。其实，只有当股价特别高时，空头在卖出时才能赚很大利润。你可以用你的最后那份钱做赌，内线人士必定不会对外宣布这个真实情况。

纽海文铁路公司就是其中的代表性事例。今天所有人都知道，可在当时却只有极少的人了解。1902年，他们的股票价格达到了255美元，在新英格兰地区，是数一数二的铁路投资标靶。东北部的人就是根据是不是持有这只股票，来判断某人在社区里有多么受尊敬，或者有多大威信。如果有人说这家公司很快要倒闭，是不会被抓进监狱的，可他会被当成疯子一样，关进精神病院。可是，当摩根任命了一位闯劲十足的新总裁后，悲惨的情况开始了。起初，人们并没想到新的政策会把公司拉到最终那个地步。但是，当资金一次次地以浮夸价投入进去后，有些高瞻远瞩的观察家们就开始对此提出了质疑。按照200万买进的一套电车系统，一转手就可以按照1000万卖给纽海文铁路公司。此时，公司委员会里会有一两个不计后果的成员，对管理层的莽撞行事表示不齿，犯了不尊敬上级的罪过。他们的意思是，即便是纽海文这样有实力的公司，也不能胡乱挥霍。这些话脆弱渺小，起不了任何作用，就像你想要向直布罗陀海峡里的礁石发出挑战一般。

首先看出灾难迹象的肯定是公司内线人士，他们对公司的真实情况逐步进行掌握，然后卖出持股。经过他们的卖出，在新英格兰地区非常贵气而富有的纽海文铁路股票开始掉价。人们如像以往那般质疑，要求给予解释，而解释也如以往那般果真出现了。有重要内线放话说，他们不知道哪里有问题，股价下跌是因为愣头青的空头在掼压。因此，在新英格兰地区的所谓投资者们继续把他们的纽约、纽海文和哈特弗铁路公司的股票握在手里。是啊，他们有什么理由不继续握着呢？内线人士都说了是空头在放空，没什么问题嘛，公司不也还在说要发放红利吗？

原本公司董事承诺出现的轧空也没实现，出现的只是更低的股价记录。内线人士制造的卖压更加紧张了，也逐渐摆在了明面上。波士顿的那些具备公益素养的人，以及代表民意的出头人向发行方提出要求，让他们对这样的境况做出解释，到底是什么原因使得新英格兰地区那些本想稳当赚点儿钱的所有人，都蒙受了特大的损失，但他们却被指责为股票投机分子。

这只股票从255美元暴跌到了12美元，这绝不是、也不可能是空头掼压造成的。空头没有引发股票下跌，也不是他们造成了跌势无法停止。公司的内线人士一直在卖，抛售价要高于他们说明真实情况或者允许真实情况被人们知道时候的价格。无论股价是250美元、200美元、150美元，还是100美元，甚至50美元、25美元，对这只股票而言都属于高价，内线们很清楚，只是股民们不知道。如果股民们想通过交易某家公司的股票来赚钱，而事先就知道这家公司的业务状况只有一少部分人才能有办法完全了解，那可能会对他有利。

在过去的20年里，出现过的跌势最严重的股票，下跌原因都不是空头掼压造成的，而人们那么容易就接受这样的理由，正是他们亏损成百上千万的原因。那样的说法，让不喜欢这种股价变动态势的人没有出售股票，他们把希望寄托在空头停止掼压后的股价反弹上，不然也可能卖掉股票。我以前听到过别人抱怨凯恩，更早之前，人们习惯于骂查理·伍利雪弗和爱迪生·卡马克，而后来，我自己也成了股市的代罪羊。

我记得有关山谷石油公司的那件事情。这家公司的股票是被公司内线集团操控的，他们拉抬股价，也找到了在上涨的时候买进的股民。这些作手们把股价炒到了50美元，然后卖出手中的股票，股价就暴跌了。然后，人们一如既往地求解释，山谷石油股票为什么这么羸弱？有大量提问的人，对问题的回答也就成了新闻。一家财经媒体去采访最了解山谷石油公司股票上涨内幕消息的一个经纪商，作为炒作集团成员的他，对股票为什么下跌也一样清楚。报纸请他说一个可以向全国范围内刊登报道的原因。哦，那当然是拉里·利文斯顿打压股市引发的啦。除此之外，他还补上一句，说要准备收拾我。可山谷石油公司内线人士依然在出售，当时股价大概12美元，他们甚至可以卖到10美元以下，平均卖价还是要高于他们的成本。

公司内线把价格拉低后卖出股票是精明的做法，也做得恰到好处，而对那些花费了35美元或40美元的不知道内情的外人而言就不一样了。他们读到印刷机印出来的报纸报道后，就紧抱着股票不放手，还等着看利文斯顿被内线集团抓住后狠狠地修理一番呢。

在牛市里，特别是盛况空前的高潮期，人们最早都获得了利润，可后来都赔了本，完全是因为他们对牛市太不舍了。广大的股民要提防那种只解释不愿意透露姓名的内线人士希望股民相信的解释。

第二十四章

人们都喜欢从别人口中得到消息，这就是内幕消息能这么普遍地被传播与接受的原因。经纪商通过自己的市场通讯杂志和口耳相传，给顾客有关交易的建议很适当。可也不该对实际情况讨论得过于详尽，因为实际情况比股市走向要滞后六到九个月。今天，公司的盈余没有为经纪商提供足够充分的理由，让他去建议股民们购买这只股票，除非对六到九个月后的情况有把握，对业务的预估能保证维持住同样的获利率。假若你能清晰地看到这么长时间以后的事，能够看明白股市未来走向跟目前实际状况不同，那现在关于讨论股价便宜的说法就不会存在了。交易者要高瞻远瞩，可经纪商们关心的只是赚眼前的手续费，所以那些普通证券商发行的杂志里，有很多避不开的误断。证券商赚的钱是来自大众手里的手续费，他们也想尽办法用手中的杂志诱导股民，让他们买那些内线和作手卖出的股票。

我们会经常看到，公司内线人士会去拜访证券公司的老板，然后说：“我希望你能搭建一个市场，替我卖出5万股。”

证券商让他说得更加详细些。比如这只股票的报价是50美元，内线人士对证券商说：“我向你提供5000股买进选择权，每股45美元；每升高2个点，就给你5000股，总共给你5万股。此外，我也按照市价给你5万股的卖出选择权。”

只要证券商有很多跟随的粉丝，那这样的钱对他来说就非常容易赚，公司内线人士需要的就是粉丝。如果哪家证券商有联通分公司和全美国各地交易所的直拨电话，遇到这样的股市交易，就会找到特别多的追随粉丝。你要记住，不管怎么样，因为有卖出选择权，这家证券交易商做的是绝对有把握的事情。假若他能拉一批跟进的人，也就可以卖出他全部的持股，赚取一大笔利润，还有基本的手续费。

我想到了华尔街一位著名“内鬼”所干的一番成就。

他会拜访一家大型证券交易公司的资深营业员，甚至在有的时候，他会进一步去与公司某个小股东见面。他说的差不多都是这样的话：“你看哈，老伙计，你们帮了我好多次忙，我非常感谢。我要向你们提供一个能正儿八经赚到钱的机会。我们正在组建一家能够吸纳我们一家关系公司资产的新公司。我们会拉抬这只股票，股价会在现价的基础上有很大的涨幅。我准备以每股65美元转给你们500股班塔姆商店的股票。这只股票目前的价格是72美元。”

内线人士怀着莫大的感激之情，把这个好消息讲给好几家证券交易公司的几十位资深营业员们听。得到了内线人士所提供的礼物的那些人都在华尔街谋生，当他们获得了一部分有钱可赚的股票后，会做什么呢？他会对自己能找到的每个人提出建议，让他们买这只股。那些好心的送礼内线人很清楚这个。这些人就这样帮助内线人士，搭建了一个市场，让他们能用高价把手里的股票卖给可怜的股民们。

有一些对外出售股票的方式需要被禁止。证交所应该制止那些挂牌上市的股票按照分期付款的办法出售给普通股民。有正式的报价会对每一只股票都产生约束。此外，进入自由市场的正式证据和有时的价格差距，就是一只股票所需的全部诱饵。

还有一种出售股票的方法也比较常见，能给不善于思考的股民们带来成千上百万的损失，可却没有使任何一个操作者被抓。因为这种操作是合法的，以市场需求为基础，增加股本。这种程序并没有完全改变股票的颜色。

用老股票换新股票，不管是1股换2股、4股，还是10股，这样做的目的往往是想让旧股票变得容易出售而已。1磅包装的东西用1美元很难卖出去，换成1/4磅包装的用25美分就可能会卖出去，甚至还有可能卖到27美分或者30美分呢。

为什么人们不探究股票要变得容易出售的原因？这也是华尔街上慈善事业的做法，可明智的交易人员需要谨慎地对付这种特洛伊木马似的东西。人们需要的所有警告就是这个。可他们不管这些，所以每年都会赔掉数百万美元。

意图制造各种谣言并传播出去，对个人或公司的业务和名誉造成伤害，就会受到法律制裁。也就是说，故意怂恿大众抛出股票，打压它的价值，就会受到惩罚。这种做法本来的意图可能是在股市不太好的时候，处罚那些对银行的规范程度明确表示怀疑的人，以此削弱挤兑消除恐慌带来的危险。而这样也对股民们不按照比股票价值低的价格卖出股票给予了保护。意思是，美国法律会惩罚那些传播利空谣言的人。

怎么样才能保护好股民，让他们不要以比股票价值高的价格去买股票呢？谁来惩处那些传播利多谣言的人？无人负责啊。可股民们在股价过高的时候，依靠不愿意透露姓名的公司内线人士的消息来买股票，为此蒙受的损失，要比在所谓掼压情形下，因为利空消息而按照比股票价值低的价格卖出时受到的损失要大。

假如能够通过法律，像惩罚一些撒谎的空头一样，对欺骗股民的多头进行惩罚的话，我相信股民们会省下几百万。

当然了，那些作手、股票承销商，以及不报出姓名而只给出乐观看法并因此拿到好处的人会对你说，不管谁依靠谣言和不知名的建议去交易赔了钱，都怪你自己。这样的话，那你也可以说，不管谁笨得吸毒成瘾，都没有受保护的资格。

证交所应该帮忙保护股民们不受那些不公正的行为的损害。哪个知晓内情的人，如果想让股民们听从他的建议，或接受他的说法，那就请他签字画押来负好责任。在利多的消息上签字负责任，并不能让消息由假变真，可却能让所谓的内线人士和董事谨慎些。

股民们该永远记住交易股票的要点。当股票上涨的时候，没必要花心力去搞清楚其中的原因。一直买进，它就会一直上涨。只要它一直涨价，偶尔有个很正常的小幅度回调，你顺着股票的涨势操作，基本上都很安全。可股价若在长时间平稳上涨以后，慢慢转成了下跌形势，偶尔有点儿反弹，那就很明显了，是股票的最小阻力线开始变为向下走了。这就是实情，还为何要去找原因呢？或许股价下跌的原因非常充分，可却只有不多的几个人明白。而他们要么不会对你说，要么把话反过来说。这就是交易游戏的本质，大家都该清楚，知道内情的那几个人是不会告诉你真相的。

不管一些所谓内线人士或董事在给出很多说法的时候是否也报出了自己的姓名，他们都没有什么依据。甚至有时候没人让内线站出来说话，那些说法都只是在股市上拥有重大利益的一些人胡乱制造的谣言。在某只股票价格上涨的某个阶段，很多手里有股票的内线为了让股票变得容易交易，是不会拒绝专业人员的帮忙的。内线人士或许会向玩得大的人说明该什么时候买，但却不会告诉他什么时候卖。这样的话，那些大作手就和普通股民在同一地位的起跑线上，不过他需要的是一个特别大的市场空间，以便能够抛售。此时，对股民们最能造成误导的消息就会出现。其实，在这个游戏的任何时候，你都不能相信一些所谓的内线人士。一般情况下，大公司的某个老板或许会根据内幕消息去股市交易。他们实际上也没撒谎，就是没说话，他们知道有时需要闭口不谈。

我不止一次地说过，再多说一次也不算唆。根据我几十年的交易经验，我相信没有谁能够从头至尾地在股市中当赢家。不过，他可能会在某种条件下的某些股票上获利。无论一个炒股的人经验多么丰富，都存在着因为出错而赔钱的可能。股票投机并不是百分百安全的事情。华尔街上的专家们很清楚，依照内幕消息采取行动，比饥荒、瘟疫、灾荒、政治变动以及那些普通的意外事故，更能让人迅速破产。在华尔街，在其他的任何一个地方，都没有一条柏油马路通向成功。既然这样，那为什么还要去做堵塞交通的事情呢？

第一部分

1

镇上有两个哑巴，他俩总是形影不离。每天一大早，他俩便离开住处，手挽手地走过大街去上班。这两位好友区别很大。每次领路的那个是希腊人，大腹便便，总是神情恍惚。一到夏天，他总穿一件黄色或绿色的套头衫，前面草草塞进裤子里，而后面则随意耷拉着。天冷些的时候，他会在衬衫外面套一件松松垮垮的灰色毛衣。他的脸圆圆的，泛着油光，眼睛半闭着，唇边带着一丝温和而又傻气的笑容。另一个哑巴则个头高挑，眼神中透露出机敏和聪慧，干净整洁，衣着朴素。

每天清晨，两位好友默默地并肩走着，一直来到小镇的主街。然后他俩会走到一家水果兼糖果店，在门前的人行道上逗留一会儿。那个希腊人叫斯皮罗斯·安东纳普勒斯，给他的表兄打工，而表兄正是这家水果店的主人。安东纳普勒斯的工作是制作糖果和甜食，把水果从柳条箱里搬出来，还要负责这个地方的卫生。瘦瘦的哑巴叫约翰·辛格，几乎总要挽着好友的胳膊，盯着他的脸看一会儿，才会离开。道别之后，辛格穿过大街，独自一人继续向前走，到他工作的珠宝店去，他在那里做银器雕刻的活儿。傍晚时分，两位好友再次会合。辛格回到水果店门口，一直等着安东纳普勒斯收拾停当准备回家。那个希腊人要么在懒洋洋地拆一盒桃子或者甜瓜，要么在商店后面他负责烹饪的厨房里，看着一张连载滑稽漫画的报纸。离开商店之前，安东纳普勒斯总会打开一个纸袋子。白天，他把这只袋子藏在厨房的一个架子上，里面装着他收集起来的各种零零碎碎的食物——一片水果，甜点的样品，或者一小截肝泥香肠。通常在离开之前，安东纳普勒斯会摇摇摆摆、慢慢悠悠地走到商店前的玻璃柜边上，那里面装着肉和奶酪。他会滑开柜子后门，用胖胖的手充满爱意地摸索着他想吃的某种特别的可口美味。有时候他那位店老板表兄看不见他这么做，但如果看见了，便会瞪着这位表弟，紧绷着一张苍白的脸，带着一丝警告的意味。安东纳普勒斯便会不舍地把这一小块美味从柜子的一角挪到另一角。这时，辛格则把手插在口袋里，站得笔直，眼睛望着别处。他不想看见两个希腊人之间的这种小风波。除了喝酒和某种不为人知的私密乐趣之外，安东纳普勒斯在这个世界上最爱的，便是吃。

暮色中，两个哑巴慢悠悠地一起走回家。在家里，辛格一刻不停地跟安东纳普勒斯交谈。他的两只手用一系列快速手势表达着想说的词，脸上带着渴望的表情，一双灰绿色的眼睛闪着明亮的光。他用两只瘦削却健壮的手打手势，跟安东纳普勒斯诉说着白天所发生的一切。

安东纳普勒斯懒洋洋地瘫坐着，望着辛格。他几乎从不动手说话，即便动，也只是说他想吃饭、睡觉，或者喝酒。说这三个词的时候，他的手势总是含混不清、笨拙不堪。晚上，如果他醉得不太厉害，便会在床前跪下来祈祷一会儿，然后用两只胖手比画着“神圣的耶稣”“上帝”，或者“亲爱的玛利亚”。这些便是安东纳普勒斯唯一会说的话。辛格不知道好友能够听懂多少他说的那些事，但这些都没关系。

他俩所在的这幢房子很小，靠近小镇的商业区。他们租住在二楼，有两个房间。一日三餐，安东纳普勒斯就在厨房里那个油炉子上做。厨房里有把样式简单的直背椅，是辛格的，一张松软的沙发则是安东纳普勒斯的。卧室里主要的家具是两张床，铺着鸭绒被的那张大大的双人床，是给大块头希腊人睡的，辛格则睡在那张窄窄的铁床上。

晚饭总是吃得时间很长，因为安东纳普勒斯热爱食物，他吃得非常慢。吃完饭，大块头希腊人会躺倒在沙发上，用舌头慢慢挨个舔舐着每一颗牙齿，要么是因为刚吃完某种美食，要么是因为他不想就此告别这顿饭的味道，这时候辛格则在洗碗。

晚上，两个哑巴有时候会下象棋。辛格一直非常喜欢下棋，多年以前，他曾试着教安东纳普勒斯下棋。起初他的好友并不感兴趣，搞不懂为什么要在一块板子上把这些棋子挪来挪去。后来辛格开始在桌子下面藏上一瓶好酒，教完安东纳普勒斯便拿出来。马的走法稀奇古怪，皇后则可以无处不去，希腊人从来没搞明白这些，但他慢慢学着可以走上固定的几步。他更愿意执白子，如果给他黑子，他就干脆不玩了。在开头走了几步之后，辛格只好自己跟自己对弈，而他的好友就在边上看，一副昏昏欲睡的样子。如果辛格漂亮地攻击了自己的棋子，最后吃掉了黑子的国王，安东纳普勒斯便得意扬扬、兴高采烈。

两个哑巴没有别的朋友，他俩除了工作的时候总是单独相处。日复一日，生活都是一个模样，因为他们总是独处，不会受到任何打扰。他们每周去一次图书馆，辛格会借一本悬疑小说。他们每周五晚上去看一场电影。到了发工资的日子，他俩总会去军需品商店楼上的小照相馆，安东纳普勒斯会拍一张照片。他们常去的只有这些地方。这个镇上很多其他的地方，他俩从来都没有去过。

小镇地处南方腹地的中部。这里的夏天很长，冬天几乎没有多少寒冷的日子。天空总是呈现一种澄澈明亮的蔚蓝色，阳光肆意炙烤着大地。十一月会下寒冷的小雨，之后或许会有霜冻，未来几个月还会出现短暂的寒冷。冬天是多变的，但夏天总是酷热难当。小镇是个相当大的地方，主街上有好几家两三层楼高的商店和公司办公室。但镇上最大的建筑物是工厂，镇上很大一部分人都在工厂里干活儿。这些棉纺厂规模很大，生意兴隆，镇上的大多数工人却非常贫穷。走在大街上的那些人，脸上经常是一副饥饿和孤独的绝望表情。

然而，两个哑巴却一点也不孤独。在家里，他们能吃吃饭、喝喝酒就满足了，而且辛格会热切地用手比画着，跟朋友讲他的所思所想。岁月便这样静静地流逝。辛格三十二岁了，他已经跟安东纳普勒斯在镇上生活了整整十年。

有一天，希腊人病倒了。他坐在床上，两只手捂着肥胖的肚子，大颗大颗油腻腻的眼泪顺着脸颊滚落下来。辛格去找好友的那位当水果店老板的表兄，而他自己也请了假不去上班。

医生为安东纳普勒斯规定了饮食，并禁止他再喝酒。辛格严格地执行医生的命令。他一整天都坐在好友的床边，想尽办法帮好友打发时间，但安东纳普勒斯只是愤怒地从眼角瞥着他，就是不肯笑。

希腊人非常烦躁，对辛格准备的果汁和食物百般挑剔。他不断让好友帮他下床，好让他做祈祷。他跪下来，硕大的屁股压在肥胖的小脚上，用手笨拙地比画着“亲爱的玛利亚”，然后握住脖子上用脏兮兮的绳子系着的黄铜十字架。他的一双大眼睛沿着墙壁向上望到天花板，露出一丝恐惧的神色。之后他便闷闷不乐，不让好友跟他说话。

辛格非常耐心，尽心尽力地照顾希腊人。他画些小画，有一次还给朋友画了一幅肖像，想逗朋友开心。这幅画伤害了希腊人的感情，他拒绝和好。直到辛格把他的脸画得又年轻又帅气，把头发画成亮黄色，眼睛画成瓷蓝色，他才作罢，却又竭力掩饰着自己的喜悦之情。

辛格细心地照料着好友，一周后，安东纳普勒斯可以回去上班了。但从那时起，两位好友的生活就发生了变化，麻烦找上门来了。

安东纳普勒斯痊愈了，却变得跟之前不一样了。他急躁易怒，不再满足于安静地待在家里度过夜晚时光。他想出去的时候，辛格便会紧跟在他后面。安东纳普勒斯会到一家饭店去，坐下后便偷偷把糖块、胡椒瓶或者银制餐具塞进口袋。每次，辛格都得为他拿走的东西付钱，才不会引起纠纷。回家后，他会批评安东纳普勒斯，但大块头希腊人只是带着温和的笑容望着他。

几个月过去了，安东纳普勒斯的这些习惯变得越发厉害。一天中午，他平静地走出表兄的水果店，跑到街对面，公然在第一国家银行大厦的墙边撒尿。有时候，他走在街上，如果觉得哪个路人的长相让他不痛快，便会硬撞人家，还用胳膊肘和肚子推人家。有一天，他走进一家商店，没付钱便将一盏地灯拖了出来。还有一次，他在橱窗里看见一列电动火车，硬要拿走。

对辛格来说，这段时间让他痛苦不堪。他经常趁午餐时间，把安东纳普勒斯拉到法院去处理这些违法行为。辛格对于法院的程序越来越熟悉，自己也经常会觉得焦虑烦躁。他存在银行里的那些钱都用来交保释金和罚款了。他花费了所有的精力和财力把好友弄出监狱。好友所犯的罪通常包括偷窃，公然猥亵、袭击和殴打他人。

安东纳普勒斯的店老板，希腊表兄则根本没插手这些麻烦事。查尔斯·帕克（他表兄的名字）依旧让安东纳普勒斯继续留在店里干活儿，但会时时刻刻用那张苍白紧绷的脸对着他，却并不伸手帮他。对于查尔斯·帕克，辛格感觉很奇怪，并且开始讨厌他了。

辛格生活在持续的焦虑和担忧之中，安东纳普勒斯却总是不温不火，无论发生什么事，他脸上总挂着温和绵软的笑容。在之前的那些年里，辛格觉得，好友的这种笑容里似乎有一种特别微妙、智慧的东西。他从来不知道安东纳普勒斯到底明白多少事情，也不知道他到底在想什么。现在辛格觉得，他从大块头的表情里可以察觉到一种狡黠和戏谑。他会使劲摇晃好友的肩膀，摇到自己筋疲力尽。他也会一遍遍地用手语解释一些事情。然而，这一切都是徒劳的。

辛格的钱花光了，不得不从珠宝店老板那里借钱。有一次，他实在没钱给好友付保释金，安东纳普勒斯便在监狱里过了一夜。第二天，辛格去接他出来，他却非常不高兴，根本不想走。他很喜欢前一天的晚饭：腌猪肉和浇了糖浆的玉米面包。而且他很喜欢新的睡觉环境，还有令他开心的狱友。

他们一直独自生活，所以危难之时辛格也找不到帮手。安东纳普勒斯不让任何东西打扰他，也不肯改正他的毛病。在家里，他有时会做道在监狱里吃过的新菜，而在街上，谁也不知道他会干出什么。

终于，辛格遇上了麻烦。

一天下午，他到水果店跟安东纳普勒斯会合，这时查尔斯·帕克递给他一封信。信上解释说，查尔斯·帕克已经做好了安排，要把表弟送到两百英里之外的州立精神病院去。查尔斯·帕克动用自己在镇上的关系，已经安排好了所有细节。下周，安东纳普勒斯就要离开小镇，住进精神病院。

辛格把信读了好几遍，有一会儿他简直无法思考了。查尔斯·帕克隔着柜台跟他讲话，他却根本没去读他的唇语，也不想知道他说了些什么。最后，辛格将随身装在口袋里的小便笺本拿出来，写下一行字：

你不能这样做。安东纳普勒斯必须跟我在一起。

查尔斯·帕克情绪激动，摇了摇头。他不太懂美国人的语言。“不关你的事。”他一遍遍地说。

辛格知道，一切都完了。这个希腊人担心有一天必须得为自己的表弟负责。查尔斯·帕克不太懂美国的语言，但对美国的钱，他却懂得透彻，而且他正是利用自己的钱和关系，才让精神病医院立刻接收了自己的表弟。

辛格束手无策。

第二个星期过得非常紧张。他说啊说啊。尽管他的双手一刻未停，却还是无法说完想说的一切。他想告诉安东纳普勒斯自己心里所有的想法，却没有时间了。他灰色的眼睛闪着光，睿智的脸庞流露出极度的紧张。安东纳普勒斯昏昏欲睡地望着自己的好友，辛格不知道他到底听懂了什么。

安东纳普勒斯必须要走的那一天还是来了。辛格拿出自己的手提箱，小心翼翼地把他们最好的共同财产装进去。安东纳普勒斯为自己做了一份午餐，带在路上吃。下午晚些时候，他们最后一次手挽手并肩走在大街上。这是十一月末一个寒冷的下午，他们呼出的白气一小团一小团地出现在面前。

查尔斯·帕克要陪表弟一起去，但在车站，他离他俩很远。安东纳普勒斯挤进了公交车，费了一番功夫后，终于在前排的一个座位上坐定。辛格隔着窗子望着他，两只手拼命比画着，最后一次跟好友交谈。安东纳普勒斯忙于检查午餐盒里各式各样的食物，有一阵子并没有注意到辛格。车子就要驶离路边的时候，他才转身看看辛格，脸上的笑容如此温和和疏远，好像他们早已远隔了好几英里似的。

接下去的几个星期似乎一点都不真实。辛格整日趴在珠宝店后面的工作台上干活儿，到了晚上，他孤零零地一个人回家。他别无心思，只想睡觉。下班一回到家，他便躺到小床上，努力打一会儿瞌睡。他躺在那里，似睡非睡之间会做梦，每一个梦里都有安东纳普勒斯。他的手紧张地抖动着，因为他正在梦里跟好友说话，而安东纳普勒斯也在望着他。

辛格努力回想认识好友之前的那段时光，努力回想年轻时发生的一些事情。然而，他努力回想的这一切，似乎都不真实。

有一件特别的事情，他还记得，但对他来说又无关紧要。辛格想起来，尽管自己从婴儿时期起便失聪了，但他并非完全不会说话。很小的时候，他便成为孤儿，被送到一所聋儿学校。他学会了手语，学会了读书。九岁之前，他学会用一只手以美国人的方式说话，也可以学欧洲人的方式用两只手说话。他还学会了跟随人们嘴唇的动作，看懂他们说的话。最后，他也学着用嘴巴说话。

上学时，人们觉得他非常聪明，课堂知识他总是学得比别人快。但他一直没习惯用嘴巴说话。对他而言，用嘴巴说话很别扭，舌头在嘴里感觉像条鲸鱼似的。用嘴巴说话时，对方脸上怔怔的表情让他觉得，自己的声音一定听上去像某种动物，或者他说的话让人厌烦。用嘴巴说话对他来说是件痛苦的事情，而两只手总是随时待命，准备比画出他想说的那些词。二十二岁那年，他从芝加哥南下，来到这个小镇，很快遇见了安东纳普勒斯。从此，他再也没用嘴巴说过话，因为跟好友在一起，根本无须这样做。

除了跟安东纳普勒斯在一起生活的这十年，一切似乎都不真实。在半梦半醒之间，他看见了好友，那么真切。醒来时，一种巨大的孤独感涌上来，让他心痛。偶尔，他会收拾好一个盒子，寄给安东纳普勒斯，却从来没有收到过回音。在这种空虚恍惚中，好几个月过去了。

到了春天，辛格身上发生了一些变化。他开始失眠，坐立不安。晚上，他百无聊赖，绕着屋子转来转去，一种新的精力充沛的感觉怎么也消磨不掉。只有在破晓之前的几小时里，他才能真正安歇下来，沉沉睡去，直到清晨的阳光猛然照射进来，像弯刀一样刺入他的眼睛。

他开始绕着小镇散步，以此打发夜晚时光。安东纳普勒斯曾经住过的那个房间，他开始觉得无法忍受，于是他在镇中心附近找了一处死气沉沉的公寓，租住下来。

一日三餐，他都到一家餐馆去吃，那里离他住的地方只有两个街区。这家餐馆在长长的主街尽头，名字叫“纽约咖啡馆”。第一天去时，他快速扫了一眼菜单，写了个简短便条，递给老板。

每天的早餐，我要一个鸡蛋，一片烤面包，一杯咖啡——一角五分

午饭，要汤（什么汤都行），一个加肉三明治，一杯牛奶——二角五分

晚饭，来三份蔬菜（除了卷心菜都可以），鱼或肉，一杯啤酒——三角五分

谢谢。

老板读完便条，警觉而又克制地扫了他一眼。老板体格健壮，中等身材，胡子又黑又密，让他的下半截脸看上去像铁铸的一样。他通常站在收银机旁的角落里，双臂抱在胸前，静静地观察着周围发生的一切。辛格逐渐熟悉了这个男人的脸，因为一天三次，他都会在固定的一张桌子前吃饭。

每天晚上，哑巴独自一人，在街上一走便是好几个小时。有时候，夜晚非常冷，三月的风凛冽而湿冷，还会下大雨。但对他来说，这些都无关紧要。他总是把双手紧紧插在裤子口袋里，步伐中透露着焦虑不安。过了一周又一周，白天逐渐变得温暖，使人感到慵懒，他的焦虑不安慢慢变成疲惫不堪，身上总透出一种深沉的平静，脸上也逐渐现出一种沉思的宁静。通常，这种神情只有特别伤心或特别睿智的人身上才会有。然而，他依然在小镇的大街小巷徘徊，总是一个人，一言不发。

2

初夏，一个湿热难耐的漆黑夜晚，比夫·布兰农站在纽约咖啡馆的收银机后面。已经十二点了。外面，街灯早已熄灭，咖啡馆透出的灯光在人行道上投下一个鲜明的黄色长方形。街上空无一人，但咖啡馆里面，还有六七个顾客在喝啤酒、圣露西亚葡萄酒或者威士忌。比夫面无表情地等待着，胳膊肘支在柜台上，大拇指使劲按着长长的鼻尖。他的眼神很专注，正盯着一个穿工装的矮胖男人，这个男人喝得烂醉，吵嚷个不停。比夫的目光又不时挪到那个哑巴身上，哑巴独自坐在中间的一张桌子前。他的目光也会落到柜台前其他顾客身上，但最后总会把目光转回到穿工装的醉鬼身上。时间已经很晚了，比夫继续在柜台后面默默等待着。终于，他最后扫视了一遍餐馆，走向店后的那扇门。那里通往二楼。

他静静地走上楼梯，进了房间。里面漆黑一片，他走得小心翼翼。走了几步，他的脚趾碰上一件硬邦邦的东西。他弯下腰，在地上摸索着找到这只手提箱的把手。他在房间里只待了几秒钟，刚要离开，突然，灯亮了。

爱丽丝从凌乱的床上坐起来，望着他。“你弄那只箱子干什么？”她问道，“你难道不能赶紧把那个疯子打发掉吗？干吗还要把他已经喝光了的东西还给他？”

“起来，你自己下去吧。叫警察来，把他用铁链锁了去当苦力，到那儿就着玉米面包和豆子再去喝。去啊，布兰农太太。”

“如果他明天还来，我会这样做的。但你不许动那只箱子，它不再是那个寄生虫的了。”

“我了解寄生虫，但布朗特绝不是寄生虫。”比夫说，“我自己——我说不清，但我不是小偷。”

比夫平静地把箱子放到门外的楼梯上。房间里的空气不像楼下那么污浊湿热，他决定待一会儿，用凉水洗把脸再下楼。

“我早就告诉过你，如果你今晚不把那个家伙彻底解决掉，看我怎么治他。白天，他在后面打瞌睡；晚上，你又好吃好喝地伺候他。现在都一个星期了，他一分钱没交过。他的胡言乱语，还有随身带的这些东西，会搅了我们的好买卖。”

“你不了解人，也不懂什么叫真正的买卖。”比夫说，“十二天以前，这个可疑的家伙第一次到这里来，他是镇上的陌生人。第一个星期，他就给我们带来了二十块钱的买卖，至少二十块钱。”

“从那以后，他就一直赊账。”爱丽丝说，“赊了五天账，还喝得烂醉，这对我们的买卖不好。而且，他不过是个流浪汉加怪物。”

“我喜欢怪物。”比夫说。

“我觉得也是这样！我就是觉得，你肯定是这样，布兰农先生——因为你自己就是个怪物。”

他摩挲着青乎乎的下巴，不理她。在婚后的头十五年中，他们只是称呼彼此比夫和爱丽丝。然后，在一次吵架时，他们开始称呼对方为先生或太太，从那之后，便再也没能改回去。

“我警告你，我明天下楼的时候，最好不要让我看见他。”

比夫走进浴室，洗完脸，决定花点时间刮刮胡子。他的胡子又黑又密，好像已经三天没刮似的。他站在镜子前面，若有所思地摩挲着下巴。他很后悔跟爱丽丝说话。跟她在一起，最好保持沉默。跟这个女人在一起，总会让他变得自己都不认识自己了，会让他变得跟她一样强硬、渺小和普通。比夫眼神冰冷，直愣愣的，眼皮玩世不恭地耷拉着，把眼睛遮住了一半。他那只粗糙的小拇指上，戴了一枚女人的婚戒。身后的门开着，他从镜子里看见爱丽丝躺在了床上。

“听着。”他说，“你的问题是，你没有一点真正的善心。我认识的女人当中，只有一个人有我说的这种善心。”

“嗯，在我眼里，你干的那些事，换了这个世界上任何男人，都不会觉得光荣。在我眼里，你——”

“或者，我说的也许是好奇心。周围有什么重要的事情，你根本不看，也不关心。你从来不观察，不思考，也不想弄明白任何事情。也许，这就是我和你之间最大的差别。”

爱丽丝几乎又睡着了。他冷漠地从镜子里望着她。她身上没有什么特别的地方能够牢牢吸引住他的注意力。他的目光从她淡褐色的头发滑到被子下面那双脚的粗短轮廓，从她柔和的面部曲线滑到她浑圆的屁股和大腿。她不在面前时，他想不起她身上有什么特点，在他脑子里，她只是个完整的人而已。

“你从来就不知道欣赏一幕奇景是怎么回事。”他说。

她的声音很疲惫：“楼下的那个家伙就是一幕奇景，好吧，还是个马戏团。但是，我已经受够他了。”

“见鬼，那个男人对我来说什么也不是，他既不是我的亲戚，也不是我的老伙计。但是，一个人留意了许多细节，然后突然真相大白，你根本就不懂这是种什么感觉。”他打开热水，立刻开始刮胡子。

五月十五日的早晨，是的，就在那天早晨，杰克·布朗特走了进来。比夫立刻就注意到了他，密切地注视着他。这个男人个头不高，肩膀宽厚，像房梁一样，有撇小胡子，参差不齐，下嘴唇看上去像被黄蜂蜇了一样。这个家伙，身上有很多地方似乎都不太协调。他的脑袋很大，形状也好看，脖子却又软又细，像个小男孩。胡子看上去很假，好像是为了化装舞会临时粘上去的，如果说话太快，那胡子像是随时都要掉下来。这让他看上去像是已近中年。但他的面容却非常年轻，额头饱满平滑，眼睛瞪得很大。他的一双手硕大无比，沾满污渍，满是老茧，穿着一身廉价的白色亚麻布西装。这个男人身上有一种特别滑稽的味道，但同时，还有一种让你笑不出来的感觉。

他点了一品脱酒，半小时便喝了个精光，然后坐在一个雅座里，吃着大份的鸡肉晚餐。后来，他看书，喝啤酒。这只是开头。尽管比夫非常密切地关注着布朗特，但他怎么也没想到后面会发生疯狂的事情。他从来没见过哪个男人能够在十二天里变化那么大，从来没见过哪个男人能喝这么多酒，烂醉那么长时间。

比夫用大拇指把鼻尖往上推，用剃须刀刮着上唇的胡须。刮完后，他的脸看上去清爽了一些。爱丽丝睡着了，他穿过卧室，向楼下走去。

手提箱很沉。他把箱子提到餐馆前面，放到收银机后面，就是每天晚上他站着的地方。他有条不紊地扫视了一下四周。有几个顾客已经走了，房间里宽松了很多，但布局还是老样子。那个聋哑人依然在中间那张桌子前独自喝咖啡，那个酒鬼还在继续说话，说话的对象并不是周围哪个人，实际上也没人在听他说话。那天晚上，他来到餐馆时，穿着一套蓝色工装，并没有穿先前那十二天里一直穿着的那件脏兮兮的亚麻布西装。他的袜子不见踪影，脚踝布满抓痕，还粘着一块块已经干掉的泥巴。

比夫很警觉地听着他独白的只言片语。这个家伙似乎又在谈论某种奇怪的政治了。昨天晚上，他一直在谈论自己去过的地方，比如得克萨斯州、俄克拉荷马州，还有北卡罗来纳州和南卡罗来纳州。有一次，他还谈到妓院，后来，他的笑话实在太露骨，别人便用啤酒堵上了他的嘴。然而，大多数时候，没有人听得懂他到底在说什么。他只是一直说，一直说，一直说。那些词就像瀑布一样，从他的喉咙里倾泻而出。关键是，他说话的口音变来变去，用词种类也经常变。有时候，他说话像个棉纺工；有时候，又像个教授。他会用特别长的词，又会在语法上犯错误。很难判断他的家人是什么样子，或者他是哪个地方的人。他总是在变。比夫若有所思地抚弄着鼻尖，毫无头绪。但只要动动脑子，就一定会找到关联。的确，这个男人的脑子非常好用，但他会从一件事跳到另一件事，背后毫无逻辑可言。

他像一个被某种东西弄得偏离轨道的人。

比夫靠在柜台上，开始仔细地看晚报。大标题说，市议员委员会经过历时四个月的深思熟虑，终于做出决议：地方预算无法支付在镇上某个危险路口安装红绿灯的费用。左边一栏报道的是东方的战争。这两条新闻，比夫都看得非常仔细。他的眼睛读着报纸，其他的感官则随时警惕着周围各种各样的动静。看完这些文章，他仍然低头盯着报纸，半闭着眼睛。他感到紧张。这个家伙是个问题，天亮之前，必须得想办法把他打发掉。而且，他莫名感觉到今晚要发生一件大事。这个家伙不会永远这样继续下去。

比夫感觉有人正站在门口，他立刻抬起眼皮。一个十二岁上下、瘦高个、头发淡黄的女孩，正站在门口朝里张望。她穿着卡其布短裤、蓝衬衫、网球鞋，一眼看去像个男孩。比夫看见她，把报纸推到一边，微笑地望着她走上前来。

“你好，米克，去女童子军团了吗？”

“没有，”她说，“我不是她们一伙的。”

他用眼角的余光注意到，那个醉鬼正在用拳头砸桌子，并且转身背对着刚才的那些谈话对象。比夫开口跟眼前的孩子说话时，声音有点粗暴。

“你家里人知道你后半夜还出来吗？”

“不要紧，今晚我们那个地方的一帮孩子会在外面玩到很晚。”

他从来没见她跟同龄人来过这儿。几年前，她总是跟在她哥哥身后。凯利家人口很多。后来，她用小推车推着两个淌着鼻涕的娃娃到这儿来。但如果她不用照顾孩子，或不想跟在哥哥姐姐们后面，她就会自己来。现在，这个孩子站在那里，似乎拿不定主意到底想要什么。她不停地用手掌把湿乎乎且有点发白的头发向后拢。

“我想要一包香烟，请给我最便宜的那种。”

比夫想说话，犹豫了一下，把手伸进柜台。米克拿出一块手绢，开始解角上打的结，她的钱装在里面。她猛地拽了一下结扣，里面的零钱哗啦掉到了地上，滚到布朗特旁边。布朗特正站在那里自言自语，他迷迷糊糊地盯着那几枚硬币看了一会儿，还没等那个孩子追过来，他便专注地蹲下身子，把钱捡了起来。他步履沉重地走到柜台前，站住，在手心里晃动着那两枚一分、一枚五分和一枚一角的硬币。

“现在的香烟卖一毛七了吗？”

比夫等待着。米克看看这个，又看看那个。醉鬼把几枚硬币摞在柜台上，还用两只脏兮兮的大手挡着这一小堆钱。他又慢慢拿起一枚一分的硬币，一下把它弹到地上。

“五厘给那些种烟草的穷白人，五厘给那些卷烟的傻瓜们。”他说，“一分给你，比夫。”然后，他努力集中视线，好看清五分和一角硬币上的铭文。他用手指按住这两枚硬币，画着圆圈，最后又把硬币推开。“这算是向自由略表敬意，向民主和专政表示敬意，向自由和劫掠表示敬意。”

比夫不动声色地捡起钱，当啷扔进收银机。米克看着这一切，好像并不急着要走的样子。她久久地望着醉鬼，然后又将目光挪到屋子中间，看到哑巴一个人坐在桌前。过了一会儿，布朗特也不时朝同一个方向瞥一眼。哑巴默默地坐在那里，喝着一杯啤酒，用一根用过的火柴棒在桌子上无所事事地画着什么。

杰克·布朗特首先开了腔：“这很滑稽，但在过去的三四天夜里，我做梦时都看见了那个家伙，他就是不肯放过我。如果你注意一下的话，他好像从来没有说过话。”

比夫很少跟顾客谈论别的顾客。“是的，没有。”他含糊作答。

“很滑稽。”

米克把重心从一只脚挪到另一只脚，然后把那包香烟塞进短裤口袋。“如果你了解他，就不会觉得滑稽了。”她说，“辛格先生跟我们住在一起，他的房间就在我们家里。”

“是吗？”比夫问道，“我敢说，这个我不知道。”

米克朝门口走去，头也不回地答道：“当然。他跟我们已经住了三个月啦。”

比夫放下衬衫袖子，又仔细地把袖子挽起来。他的目光一直盯着米克，看着她走出餐馆。即便米克已经离开了好几分钟，他仍然摸索着衬衫袖子，盯着空荡荡的门口。然后，他把双臂抱在胸前，又转头看着醉鬼。

布朗特重重地靠在柜台上，棕色的眼睛看上去湿乎乎的，睁得很大，带着一种茫然的神色。他很久没洗过澡了，身上有股山羊的臭味，汗乎乎的脖子上有泥点，脸上有油渍。他的嘴唇又厚又红，棕色头发盖在额头上。他的工装裤太短了，他总是不停地把裤裆往下拽。

“老兄，你该明白，”比夫终于说道，“你不能这个样子到处晃。唉，你居然没有因为流浪被逮起来，真让人吃惊。你该醒醒了，你需要洗个澡，头发也得理理。老天！你根本不应该待在人类中间。”

布朗特满面怒容，咬着下嘴唇。

“好吧，别生气，别发火。按我说的做。到后面厨房，让那个黑人男孩给你烧一大锅热水，再让威利[1]给你条毛巾，多给你点肥皂，好好洗洗。然后，吃点牛奶吐司，打开你的手提箱，换上件干净衬衫，再找条合适的裤子。明天，你就可以开始做想做的事，干想干的活儿，重新回到正轨上。”

“你知道你能做点什么，”布朗特醉醺醺地说，“你可以只——”

“好吧，”比夫平静地说，“不，不行。现在，你要规矩一点。”

比夫走到柜台后边，接了两杯鲜啤酒回来。醉鬼笨拙地接过一杯，啤酒顺着他的两只手洒下来，弄脏了柜台。比夫啜着自己那杯啤酒，细细品味。他半闭着眼睛，目不转睛地盯着布朗特。尽管第一眼看到布朗特时，你会觉得他是个怪物，但他并非怪物。他身上似乎有什么地方是畸形的，但当你靠近了细看，他身上的每个部位都很正常，没有什么异样。因此，他之所以与众不同，如果不是身体上的原因，那也许就是脑子的原因。他这个人，像是曾经蹲过监狱，或者上过哈佛，或者在南美跟外国人混了很长时间。他好像去过别人不可能去的地方，或者做过别人不可能做的事情。

比夫歪了一下头，说：“你是哪儿的人？”

“哪儿的人也不是。”

“好吧，你总得有个出生的地方吧。北卡罗来纳、田纳西、阿拉巴马，总得有个地方。”

布朗特眼神恍惚，飘忽不定。“卡罗来纳州。”他说。

“看得出来，你去过不少地方。”比夫小心翼翼地暗示道。

但醉鬼并没有听见。他从柜台转过身，盯着外面漆黑空荡的大街。过了一会儿，他拖拖拉拉、摇摇晃晃地朝门口走去。

“再会。”[2]他回头喊道。

又剩下比夫一个人，他快速而仔细地查看了一遍餐馆。已经过了子夜一点，店里只剩下四五个顾客。哑巴依然独自坐在中间的桌子前。比夫悠闲地盯着他，晃着杯底残留的几滴啤酒。然后，他慢慢地咽下最后一口酒，走回柜台上摊开的报纸前。

这次，他无法集中注意力去看面前的那些文字。他想起米克。他不知道自己该不该把烟卖给她，也不知道吸烟是不是真的对孩子有害。他想起米克眯着眼睛用手掌把刘海儿往后拢的样子，想起她像男孩一样沙哑的声音，想起她总是把卡其布短裤向上提的习惯。还有，她大摇大摆的样子就像电影里的牛仔一样。他的心头涌上一股温柔的感觉，让他觉得很不安。

比夫心神不宁，转头去看辛格。哑巴坐在那里，双手插在口袋里，面前那杯喝了一半的啤酒早已温热浑浊了。他想在辛格离开之前请他喝点威士忌。他跟爱丽丝说的话没错——他的确很喜欢怪物。对于病人和残疾人，他有种特别友善的感觉。无论什么时候，如果有兔唇或患肺结核的人走进餐馆，他都会请他们喝杯啤酒。如果顾客是个驼背，或者是个重度残疾人，他便会请他们喝威士忌。曾经有个家伙在一次锅炉爆炸中炸飞了下体和左腿，无论他什么时候来镇上，都有一品脱免费威士忌在这里等着他。如果辛格喜欢喝酒，那么无论什么时候，都可以用半价买到酒。比夫暗中点点头。然后，他把报纸整齐地叠好，和其他几样杂物一起塞到柜台下面。等到周末，他就会把这些东西统统搬到厨房后面的储藏室去。过去二十一年的晚报都非常完整地收藏在那里，一张都不缺。

两点钟，布朗特又回到餐馆。这次，他带了一个高个子黑人进来，黑人手里拎着一个黑包。这个醉鬼想让黑人到柜台前喝一杯，但黑人一弄明白自己被领进餐馆的原因，就立马离开了。比夫认出来，这人是镇上的黑人医生，自他记事起，这个黑人便在镇上行医了。他跟后厨的年轻人威利还有点什么关系。比夫看见，黑人在离开之前，用一种颤抖着仇恨的目光狠狠瞪了布朗特一眼。

酒鬼只是站着不动。

“你难道不知道，白人喝酒的地方，不能带黑鬼进来吗？”有人问他。

比夫在远处望着这一切。布朗特勃然大怒，现在更能看出他醉得有多厉害了。

“我自己也有黑人血统。”他挑衅似的大叫起来。

比夫警觉地望着他，屋子里一片寂静。他的大鼻孔张开着，翻着白眼珠，看上去好像说的是实话。

“我有黑人、意大利人、东欧人还有中国人的血统，都有。”

有人大笑起来。

“我还有荷兰人、土耳其人、日本人、美国人的血统。”他绕着哑巴喝咖啡的桌子歪歪斜斜地转着，声音高昂但嘶哑，“我是知道的那个人，我是陌生土地上的陌生人。”[3]

“安静。”比夫对他说道。

布朗特对店里所有人都不在意，唯有哑巴除外。两人彼此对视着，哑巴的眼神冷淡、柔和，像猫的眼睛，似乎他的整个身体都在倾听。醉鬼正处于一种癫狂状态。

“这个镇上，你是唯一能听懂我说话的人。”布朗特说，“两天以来，我一直在心里跟你说话，因为我知道，你能明白我想说什么。”

有个雅座里的人大笑起来，因为这个不知情的醉鬼居然挑了个聋哑人，想跟人家聊天。比夫不时飞快地扫一眼两人，专心听着。

布朗特在桌前坐下，朝辛格倾过身去：“有知道的人，也有不知道的人。每一万个人当中，只有一个知道的人。所有的时代，都有这样的奇迹——数百万人知道得那么多，却唯独不知道这一点。正如十五世纪，人人都觉得地球是平的，只有哥伦布和其他几个人知道真理。但这又不一样，因为发现地球是圆的，这需要天赋。尽管这个真理显而易见，但纵观历史，人们偏偏不知道，这真是个奇迹。你懂的。”

比夫将胳膊肘支在柜台上，好奇地望着布朗特。“知道什么？”他问道。

“别听他的。”布朗特说，“别管那个扁平足、青下巴、爱打听事儿的杂种。你瞧，我们这些知道的人碰到一起，是件大事，这种概率非常小。有时候，我们碰见了，却都不会认为对方就是知道的那个人，这很糟糕。我多次经历过这样的事情。但是，你瞧，我们这样的人少之又少。”

“共济会的人？”比夫问道。

“你闭嘴！不然我会把你的胳膊拧下来，再用它把你狠揍一顿。”布朗特大声嚷嚷着。他弓起身子，靠得离哑巴更近些，压低声音，醉醺醺地窃窃私语：“为什么？为什么这种无知的奇迹一直持续着？原因只有一个：这是个阴谋，一个狡诈的、巨大的阴谋，愚民政策。”

这个酒鬼想要跟一个哑巴谈话，雅座里的那几个男人一直在嘲笑他，只有比夫一副认真的模样。他想搞清楚，这个哑巴是否真听懂了酒鬼的话。这个家伙不断地点头，脸上一副沉思的样子。他只是反应迟缓，仅此而已。布朗特一边说着知道不知道的话题，一边开了几个玩笑。等玩笑说完好几秒钟之后，哑巴这才绽开笑容。等谈话重归沉闷的时候，他的脸上却依然挂着笑容，迟迟没有消失。这个家伙实在神秘莫测。人们觉得，自己甚至还没等意识到他身上到底有什么地方与众不同时，就已经在盯着他看了。他的眼神让人觉得，他听到的东西是别人都未曾听说过的，他知道的事情也是别人都未曾想到过的。他似乎不像凡人。

杰克·布朗特几乎趴在了桌子上，话语滔滔不绝，犹如内心的堤坝决堤了一样。比夫什么也听不懂了。因为醉酒，布朗特的舌头发沉，语速极快，声音都搅在了一起。比夫忍不住想，如果爱丽丝把他赶出去，他能去哪儿。早晨，爱丽丝就会把他赶出去的，她是这样说的。

比夫疲惫地打了个哈欠，用手指拍着张开的嘴巴，一直拍到下巴松弛下来。马上就三点钟了，无论白天还是夜里，这都是最让人倦怠的时候。

哑巴非常耐心，他一直听着布朗特说话，听了将近一个小时。这会儿，他开始偶尔看看表。布朗特并没有注意到这一点，继续高谈阔论。最后他停了下来，卷了一支烟。哑巴则朝钟表的方向点点头，以特有的含蓄方式笑了笑，从桌前站了起来，两只手照旧插在口袋里，快步走了出去。

布朗特醉得厉害，根本不明白发生了什么事，他甚至没有注意到这个事实：哑巴没有做出任何回答。他张着大嘴，开始环顾屋子，眼睛骨碌碌地转着，整个人昏昏沉沉。一条红色血管在他的额头上突起来，他开始用拳头愤怒地猛砸桌子。现在，不能再任他撒酒疯了。

“过来。”比夫和善地说，“你朋友已经走了。”

这个家伙还在寻找着辛格。以前，他似乎从来没有这么烂醉如泥过。他的样子很难看。

“我这里有东西给你，还想跟你说几句话。”比夫连哄带骗。

布朗特从桌前站起身，摇摇晃晃地大步朝街上走去。

比夫靠在墙上。进来，出去——进来，出去。毕竟，这不关他的事。屋子里空了，非常安静。这几分钟，时间都停滞了。他疲惫地任由自己的脑袋向前垂下。屋子似乎慢慢凝固起来。柜台、人脸、雅座、桌子、角落里的收音机、天花板上旋转的吊扇，一切似乎都变得非常模糊，静止不动了。

他一定打瞌睡了。一只手晃动着他的胳膊肘，他慢慢恢复了神志，抬起头来，看看这人想干什么。站在他面前的，是厨房里干活儿的黑人男孩威利，他戴着帽子，穿着长长的白围裙。威利结结巴巴，因为要说的话让他太兴奋了。

“他用拳头砸——砸——砸这里的砖——砖——砖墙。”

“怎么回事？”

“就在那边小胡同里，离这里有两户——户——户人家。”

比夫挺起缩着的肩膀，整了整领带。“什么？”

“他们要把他带到这里来，现在随时都可能闯进来——”

“威利，”比夫耐心地说，“从头说，不然我搞不明白。”

“就是在这里的那个矮个子白人，长着胡——胡——胡子的。”

“布朗特先生，是的。”

“嗯，怎么开始的，我没见着。我当时正站在后门那里，突然听见一阵骚动，听上去好像有人在胡同里打架打得厉害。所以，我跑——跑——跑过去看。在这里的那个白人完全疯了，他用头撞这面砖墙，还用拳头打，一边骂一边打。我以前从来没见过这样打架的白人，打的就是这面墙。这样下去，他很快就会把头撞破的。两个白人男人听见吵闹声，就走过去，在一边看——”

“然后呢？”

“嗯，你知道这里的那个哑巴先生——手总是插在口袋里的——这里那个——”

“辛格先生。”

“他走过来，就那么站在那里，看着四周，想知道到底是怎么回事。布——布——布朗特先生一看见他，就开始又说又喊，然后突然倒在了地上。也许，他真的把头撞破了。一个警——警——警察过来了，有人报了警，说布朗特先生在这里。”

比夫低下头，琢磨着刚才听到的内容，总算理出一个清晰的思路。他搓了搓鼻子，想了一会儿。

“他们随时都会闯进来。”威利走到门口，朝街上张望着，“瞧，他们来了，他们拖着他。”

十几个围观者，还有一个警察，他们都想挤进餐馆里。外面，还有好几个妓女站在那里，从前窗向里张望。每当有意外发生时，也不知道从哪里冒出这么多人，都争着往里挤，这真是滑稽。

“别再制造不必要的麻烦了，没什么好处。”比夫说着，看了一眼正架着醉鬼的那个警察，“其他人还是出去吧。”

警察把酒鬼放到椅子上，把众人推搡回大街上，然后转过头，对比夫说：“有人说，他在这里跟你住。”

“不是，但他不妨就待在这里吧。”比夫说。

“需要我把他带走吗？”

比夫考虑了一下。“今晚他不会再惹麻烦了。当然，我也负不起这个责任，但是，我觉得待在这里可以让他安静下来。”

“下班前我会再来看看。”

店里只剩下比夫、辛格和杰克·布朗特三个人了。从醉鬼被带进来后，比夫这才得空好好看看他。布朗特的下巴似乎伤得非常严重，他瘫倒在桌子上，一只大手捂着嘴巴，前后摇晃着，头上有道深长的伤口，鲜血从太阳穴处流下来。他的指关节皮开肉绽，浑身肮脏不堪，像是刚从下水道里被人抓着后脖颈拖出来似的。他大口大口地呕吐着，已经彻底崩溃了。哑巴坐在桌子对面，用灰色眼睛望着这一切。

后来，比夫看到布朗特并没有伤到下巴，他用手捂住嘴巴，是因为他的嘴唇在哆嗦。泪珠从他满是污垢的脸上滚落下来，他不时瞥一眼比夫和辛格，居然被他们瞧见了自己在哭，这让他非常生气。这个场景令人难堪。比夫冲哑巴耸了耸肩膀，抬起眉毛，做了个“该怎么办”的表情。辛格歪了一下脑袋。

比夫不知所措。他若有所思，不知道该如何应对眼前的状况。他正努力想着对策，哑巴突然翻过菜单，开始在上面写字：

如果你没有地方让他去，他可以跟我回家。先给他喝点汤和咖啡，对他有好处。

比夫松了口气，使劲点点头。

他把前一晚的三盘特价饭菜、两碗汤，还有咖啡和甜点摆在桌上。然而，布朗特不肯吃，也不肯把手从嘴上拿开，好像嘴唇是他身上的什么秘密部位绝不能暴露一样。他的呼吸中带着断断续续的抽泣，宽大的肩膀紧张地抖动着。辛格挨个指了指桌上的饭菜，但布朗特只是坐在那里，手捂着嘴巴，摇摇头。

比夫说得清晰而又缓慢，好让哑巴看清口形。“太紧张了——”他以聊天的口吻说道。

汤里的热气不断飘到布朗特的脸上，过了一会儿，他颤抖着伸手去拿勺子。他喝了汤，吃了些甜点，厚嘴唇还在哆嗦着，头低低地垂到盘子上。

比夫注意到了这一点。他想，几乎每个人身上都有一个一直精心守护的特殊部位。在哑巴身上，是他的双手。那个叫米克的孩子用手拉扯上衣的前襟，是为了不让衣服摩擦到胸前刚刚开始发育的柔嫩乳头。在爱丽丝那里，是她的头发，如果他头上抹了油，她绝对不允许他和自己同床。那么，他自己呢？

比夫缓缓转动着小指上的戒指。无论如何，他知道什么东西是自己不再精心守护的了。不了，再也不了。他眉头紧蹙，插在口袋里的一只手神经质地去摸生殖器。他开始用口哨吹起一支歌，然后从桌前站了起来。然而，能在别人身上发现这一点，很有意思。

他们把布朗特扶起来。他很虚弱，东倒西歪。他不再哭了，但似乎还在思考着某些令他感到羞愧和不快的事情，他任由别人领着自己向前走。比夫从柜台后面拿出那只手提箱，跟哑巴解释了一下。对辛格而言，似乎对什么都已经见怪不怪了。

比夫跟他们一起走到门口。“振作起来，别干犯法的事。”他对布朗特说。

漆黑的夜空开始发亮，随着新的清晨的到来，天空变成了深蓝色。天上只剩下几颗闪着微光的银白色星星。大街上空空荡荡，一片寂静，凉意袭人。辛格左手提着箱子，空出右手，扶着布朗特。他点头向比夫道别，跟布朗特一起，沿着人行道离开了。比夫站在那里望着他俩。他俩走出了半个街区，只有背影还在蓝色夜幕中依稀可辨——哑巴身板笔直、结实，布朗特肩膀宽厚，靠在哑巴身上，走得跌跌撞撞。他俩终于消失在视野中。比夫又等了一会儿，仔细看了看天空。天空的浩瀚深邃令他着迷和压抑。他搓了搓额头，回到灯火通明的餐馆。

他站在收银机后面，努力回想着夜里发生的一切，脸上一紧，变得冷酷起来。他觉得要向自己解释一些事情。他回顾了整个事件的烦琐细节，却仍然迷惑不解。

门开开合合好几次，有客人陆续走进来了。夜晚结束了。威利把一些椅子堆在桌子上，在拖地板。他马上要下班回家了，一直哼着歌。威利很懒，在厨房里，他总是会停下手头的活儿，拿出随身携带的口琴，吹上一会儿。这会儿，他正昏昏欲睡地一下下地拖着地，一直哼着那首孤独的黑人歌曲。

店里并没有多少客人——这个时候，熬夜的男人们和刚睡醒准备投入新一天工作的男人们碰到了一起。睡眼蒙眬的女招待端上来的既有啤酒，又有咖啡。没有嘈杂的声音，也没人聊天，因为每个人似乎都很孤单。刚醒过来的人和正准备结束漫长一夜的人，他们之间互不信任，让大家都有一种疏离感。

黎明时分，大街对面的银行大楼显得非常苍白。慢慢地，白色砖墙逐渐清晰起来。旭日开始照亮大街。比夫最后检查了一遍屋子，上楼去了。

他转动门把手进门的时候，弄出了很大动静，这样就可以把爱丽丝吵醒了。“老天，”他说，“这一夜真够受的！”

爱丽丝慢慢醒过来，躺在凌乱的床上，像只闷闷不乐的猫咪，伸着懒腰。在清新、炎热的晨光照耀下的房间里死气沉沉，一双皱巴巴的丝袜松松垮垮地挂在百叶窗的绳子上。

“那个傻瓜酒鬼还在楼下待着吗？”她质问道。

比夫脱下衬衫，仔细瞧了瞧领子，看看是不是干净，明天能不能接着穿。“自己下去看看吧。早跟你说过，你要把他踢出去，没人能拦着。”

爱丽丝睡眼蒙眬，伸手下去，从床边的地板上拿起一本《圣经》、一份单面空白的菜单，还有一本主日学校的书。她哗哗地翻动《圣经》，找到一篇开始念起来，声音很大，十分专注。今天是周日，她正在准备每周一次的课程，学生是教堂初中部的那些男孩子。“耶稣行走在加利利海边，看见西门和兄弟安德鲁，他们正在海里撒网，因为他们是渔民。耶稣对他们说：‘来跟从我，我要叫你们得人如得鱼一样。’他们立刻舍了网，跟从他。”

比夫走进浴室洗澡。爱丽丝大声读着，在浴室中听来成了持续柔和的低语。他侧耳倾听。“……次日早晨，天未亮的时候，耶稣起来，到旷野地方去，在那里祷告。西门和其他信众出去找他。他们找到耶稣时，对他说：‘众人都在找你。’”

她读完了。比夫让这些话在他脑海里温柔地旋绕着。他极力把爱丽丝在读的这些真实字词的声音与对他说话时的声音区分开。他想记起当自己还是孩子时，母亲经常读的那篇经文。他生出怀旧之情，他低头望着小指上的婚戒，这戒指原本是母亲的。他又一次忍不住想，如果母亲知道他放弃了教堂和宗教，会怎么想？

“今天的课讲的是收徒的故事。”爱丽丝在备课过程中自言自语，“经文是‘众人都在找你’。”

比夫猛地一下从思绪中清醒了，将水龙头拧到最大。他脱下内衣，开始洗澡。一直以来，他的上半身总是洗得一丝不苟。每天早晨，他在胸脯、胳膊、脖子、脚上都抹上肥皂——在这个季节，他每天进到浴缸里洗两次澡，清洗全身。

比夫站在床边，不耐烦地等着爱丽丝起床。他从窗户里看到，今天将是个风平浪静、酷热难耐的日子。爱丽丝已经读完了那一课，尽管知道他在等着，她还是懒洋洋地横躺在床上。比夫心头悄然升起一股怒火。他嘲讽地轻笑了一声，然后挖苦道：“如果你喜欢，我可以坐下看会儿报纸，但我希望你能让我现在睡一觉。”

爱丽丝开始穿衣服，比夫整理床铺。他娴熟地来回颠倒着床单，把上面一层放到下面，把它们翻过来，又首尾调了顺序。床铺整理完毕，他一直等到爱丽丝离开了房间，这才脱掉裤子，钻进被窝。他的脚从被子底下凸出来，胸膛上的粗硬胸毛在枕头的衬托之下，显得更黑了。他很高兴没有跟爱丽丝说醉鬼身上发生的事。他很想找个人说说这件事，如果能大声地把这些事情说出来，他或许就可以发现让他感到困惑的原因。那个可怜的杂种说啊说啊，却没人明白他说的是什么，很可能他自己也不明白。他就那样一直围着那个聋哑人转，单单选中他，而且拼命向他倾诉一切。

为什么？

因为对有些人而言，他们会在某个时刻放弃一切个人的东西，趁这东西发酵、放毒之前——把它扔给某个人或某种想法。他们必须得这样做。对某些人而言，这就是他们内心的想法——经文是“所有人都在找你”。也许，这就是为什么——也许——他是个中国人，那个家伙曾经说过，他还是黑人、意大利人、犹太人。如果他对此坚信不疑，那也许的确如此。他所说的自己是什么人、什么事——

比夫伸出两条胳膊，把两只光脚交叉起来。在晨光中，他的脸更显苍老了，干瘪的眼皮紧闭着，两颊和下巴上的胡须浓密而坚硬。慢慢地，他的嘴巴放松下来。刺眼的黄色阳光从窗户里照进来，房间里闷热而明亮。比夫疲倦地翻过身，用手遮住眼睛。他不是什么大人物，不过是巴塞洛缪，是老比夫，有两只拳头、一张快嘴，是布兰农先生，孤零零一个人。

3

尽管前一晚米克在外面混到很晚才回家，但还是早早被太阳叫醒了。天气太热了，早餐时连咖啡都不想喝，她往冰水里加了糖浆，又吃了些凉饼干。她在厨房瞎转悠了一会儿，然后走到前面的门廊，去看报纸上的幽默漫画。她本以为辛格先生会像以往的周日早晨那样，也在门廊上看报纸，但他并不在那里。后来，她爸爸说，辛格先生昨晚回来得非常晚，他的房间里有客人。她等了辛格先生好一会儿。所有房客都下来了，唯独不见他。最后，她回到厨房，把拉尔夫从他的高脚椅中抱出来，给他换上干净衣服，擦净他的脸。等巴伯从主日学校回来时，她已经准备停当，要带孩子们出门了。她让巴伯跟拉尔夫一起坐进手推车，因为巴伯光着脚，外面炽热的人行道会烫伤他的脚。她拖着手推车走了大约八个街区，终于来到一幢正在建的高大新房子前面。梯子仍旧搭靠在屋檐的一边，她鼓足勇气，开始向上爬去。

“你看着拉尔夫。”她回头朝巴伯喊道，“别让虫子落在他的眼皮上。”

五分钟后，米克站起来，挺直身子。她展开双臂，像翅膀一样。这个地方，人人都想站上来。站在最顶端。然而，并没有多少孩子可以做得到。大多数孩子会害怕，万一失手，滚落下去，就摔惨了。周围有各种房顶，还有郁郁葱葱的树冠。小镇的另一边，有教堂的尖顶，还有工厂的大烟囱。天空蔚蓝，天气火烧火燎般热。阳光下，地上的一切要么白得晃眼，要么漆黑一片。

她想唱歌。她会唱的那些歌都一股脑儿涌到她的喉咙处，却没发出声。上个星期，有个大男孩爬到了屋顶最高的地方，大喊一声，便开始大声发表在高中学过的一篇演说——“各位朋友，各位罗马人，各位同胞，请你们听我说！”[4]爬到最高处，会让你有一种狂野的感觉，让你想要大喊、唱歌，或者抬起胳膊飞起来。

她觉得网球鞋的鞋底有点打滑，便小心翼翼地蹲下来，跨坐在屋顶上。这幢房子基本完工了，它将是附近最大的建筑物之一——两层楼，天花板很高，屋顶则是她见过最陡峭的。这幢房子很快就会建完，到时候木匠们就会离开，孩子们只能去别的地方玩耍了。

她独自一人。周围空无一人，很安静，她可以好好思考一会儿。她从短裤口袋里掏出昨晚买的那包烟。她缓缓吸着烟。香烟让她有种醉醺醺的感觉，以至于她的脑袋沉甸甸地耷拉在肩膀上，但她必须得把烟抽完。

M. K.[5]——等到十七岁出名时，她会把这两个字母写在所有东西上面。到时候，她会开一辆红白相间的帕卡德汽车回家，她家的门上都要刻上她名字的首字母。她的手绢和内衣上也要用红色字体写上M.K.。也许，她会成为一名伟大的发明家，她要发明一种很小的收音机，像一枚绿豆那么大，人们可以随身携带，塞到耳朵里听。她还要发明飞行器，人们可以像背背包那样把这种飞行器背在身后，然后嗖的一下就可以去往世界各地了。之后，她还将领先世界，挖一条巨大的隧道，穿过地球，一直通到中国去，人们可以乘坐巨大的气球顺着隧道下去。这些都是她首先要发明的东西，都已经计划好了。

米克香烟抽到一半时就捻灭了，并把烟蒂顺着屋顶斜坡弹了下去。然后，她向前俯下身子，头放在两只胳膊上，自顾自地哼起歌来。

这真是一件很有意思的事情——但自始至终，她的脑海深处都会回荡着某支钢琴曲或别的音乐。无论她做什么，想什么，音乐一直都在那里。寄宿在他们家的布朗小姐，房间里有台收音机。去年冬天，每个周日下午，她都会坐在台阶上听着收音机里的节目。那些曲子也许都是古典音乐，她却记得最清楚。特别是某个人的音乐，她每次听见，心都会揪成一团。有时候，这个人的音乐就像一块块彩色的小水晶糖；有时候，则是她能想象得到的最柔软、最悲伤的东西。

突然传来哭声。米克坐直身子，仔细听着。风拂过她前额的刘海儿，明晃晃的太阳让她脸色发白，脸上湿乎乎的。哭声还在继续，米克手脚并用，慢慢沿着屋脊向前挪动。当她挪到屋顶的尽头时，便俯身向前，趴在屋脊上，把头探出边缘，这样就可以看见地面了。

孩子们还在原地。巴伯正蹲在地上看什么东西，旁边投下一个矮小的黑影。拉尔夫依旧被系在手推车上，他还太小，只能勉强坐起身来。他抓着车子两边，帽子歪戴在头上，正在大哭。

“巴伯！”米克朝下面大喊，“看看拉尔夫想要什么，赶紧给他。”

巴伯站起来，认真看了看婴儿的脸。“他什么也不要。”

“好吧，那就好好摇摇他。”

米克又爬回刚才坐着的地方。她想认真思考一下两三个人的事，想一个人唱会儿歌，想制订计划。然而，拉尔夫一直在大声号哭，使她片刻不得安宁。

她大着胆子朝架在屋檐边缘的梯子爬过去。斜坡非常陡峭，只钉了几块木板，中间缝隙很大，是工人们当脚手架用的。她有点眩晕，心跳得厉害，身子有些哆嗦了。她命令式地大声自言自语：“用手紧紧抓住这里，慢慢向下滑动，等右脚踩住了，使劲踩稳，再往左摆过去。鼓起勇气，米克，你得勇敢点。”

无论任何攀爬，下来总是最难。她花了很长时间才踩到梯子，又感到安全了。等终于踩到地面，她感觉自己变得矮小了，有那么一会儿两条腿似乎就要瘫软下去。她提提短裤，把腰带紧了一个扣。拉尔夫还在哭，她却没在意这哭声，走进了这幢空荡荡的新房子。

上个月，他们在房子前面挂了个牌子，禁止孩子们到这个地方来。有天晚上，一群孩子在房子里扭打，有个女孩晚上看不清，跑进一个房间里。没想到，里面的地板还没有修好，女孩掉了下去，摔断了腿，现在还打着石膏躺在医院里。还有一次，几个粗野的男孩在一面墙上撒满了尿，还写了一些非常难听的下流话。然而，无论挂多少块“禁止入内”的牌子，他们都没办法把孩子们赶走，除非等到房子粉刷完毕，有人住进来为止。

屋子里散发着新鲜木头的味道，她走动的时候，网球鞋的鞋跟发出“扑通扑通”的声音，回荡在整个房子里。空气又热又安静。她在前厅中央静静地站了一会儿，然后，突然想到了什么。她把手伸进口袋去摸，掏出两支粉笔头——一支绿色，一支红色。

米克慢慢地画着大写字母。最上面，她写下“爱迪生”，下面又写下两个名字：“迪克·特雷西”[6]和“墨索里尼”。然后，在四个角落，她把字母写到最大，写下了自己姓名的首字母——M.K.，用绿色粉笔写的字，用红色粉笔勾边。写完后，她走到对面墙壁跟前，写下一个特别不雅的词——“阴部”，下面也写上了自己姓名的首字母。

她站在空荡荡的屋子中央，凝视着自己的大作。她的手里依然握着粉笔，觉得不太满意。她努力去想那个家伙叫什么名字，去年冬天，她从收音机里听到了他的音乐。关于这个人，她向学校里的一个女孩打听过，这个女孩家里有钢琴，而且上过关于他的音乐课。后来，这个女孩又去问自己的老师。这个人似乎只是个孩子而已，很久以前生活在欧洲的某个国家。但他即便只是个孩子，却为钢琴、小提琴、乐队或交响乐团写出了这些如此美妙的音乐作品。在她的印象里，她记得他写的六首不同的曲子。有几首快而清脆，另一首则像春天雨后的那种味道。但是，所有这些曲子都让她感到既悲伤又兴奋。

她哼起其中一支曲子，过了一会儿，独自站在这幢空荡荡、热乎乎的房子里，她感到眼泪流了下来。她的喉咙发紧，声音沙哑，再也唱不下去了。她飞快地把这个人的名字写在那些名字的最上方——“莫扎特”。

拉尔夫依然被系在手推车里，跟她离开时一模一样。他安静地坐起身子，一动不动，胖胖的小手紧紧抓着车子两边。拉尔夫留着方正的黑色刘海儿，眼睛也是黑色的，简直像个中国娃娃。阳光照在他的脸上，这就是他刚才一直大哭的原因。巴伯不见了踪影。拉尔夫见米克来了，又扯着嗓子大哭起来。她把车子推到新房旁边的阴凉处，又从衬衫口袋里掏出一颗蓝色的软心糖豆，塞进婴儿温暖、柔软的嘴巴里。

“消停一会儿吧。”她对拉尔夫说。其实这有点浪费，拉尔夫太小了，根本尝不出糖果的真正美味。给他一块干净的石头，效果是一样的，只不过这个小傻瓜会吞掉它。他不懂得品尝味道，也不懂得说话。如果你跟他说，你受够了，不想再拖着他到处走，很想把他扔到河里，对他来说，这话跟“你一直很爱他”没什么区别。没有什么东西会影响到他。正是因为这个原因，拖着他到处走真的很无聊。

米克把两只手捧在一起，紧紧合拢，使劲从大拇指的缝隙里吹气。她的两腮鼓起来，开始时只有气息穿过拳头的声音，接着响起了高亢尖厉的口哨声。过了一会儿，巴伯从房子的一角走了出来。

她拨拉掉巴伯头发上的锯末，又把拉尔夫的帽子戴正。这顶帽子是拉尔夫身上最好的东西了。帽子是蕾丝做的，绣满了花，拉尔夫下巴底下的缎带，一边是蓝色，一边是白色，耳朵两边有大大的玫瑰花结。这顶帽子戴在拉尔夫的脑袋上已经有点小了，刺绣的部分也扯破了，但她带拉尔夫出来时，总会给他戴这顶帽子。拉尔夫不像别人家的孩子那样，他没有真正的童车，也没有夏天穿的毛线鞋，她只能用在三年前的圣诞节得到的一辆做工粗糙的旧手推车，带着拉尔夫到处转。但这顶上好的帽子，给他长了脸。

由于是星期天，临近正午，天气又炎热，街上空无一人。手推车吱吱嘎嘎，发出刺耳的声音。巴伯光着脚，人行道很热，烫得他脚疼。郁郁葱葱的橡树在地上投下阴影，看着就凉爽，但树荫实在太少了。

“坐到车里来吧。”她跟巴伯说，“让拉尔夫坐在你腿上。”

“我可以走。”

漫长的夏季总是让巴伯犯腹绞痛。他打着赤膊，肋骨突出，身上很白。阳光照得他脸色苍白，不再是棕褐色，小奶头就像胸脯上的两粒葡萄干一样。

“我拖着你，没关系。”米克说，“快，上来吧。”

“好吧。”

米克拖着车子慢悠悠地走着，并不急着回家。她开始跟孩子们说话，但那些话不像是说给他们听的，更像是自言自语。

“这真是件很有趣的事——最近我老做那些梦。好像我在游泳，但不是在水里游，我伸出胳膊去，在一群人里游泳。那群人比星期六下午克雷斯家商店里的人还要多上一百倍，是世界上人数最多的人群。有时候，我一边大喊，一边在人群里游，不管游到哪儿，都会把他们撞倒在地——还有时候，我躺在地上，人们纷纷从我身上踩踏过去，我的内脏流出来，淌到人行道上。我觉得这不是一个普通的梦，更像是个噩梦。”

一到星期天，家里就到处都是人，因为房客们都有访客。有翻报纸的，有抽烟的，楼梯上总有人来来往往。

“有些事情你很自然地想要保密，倒不是因为这些事情不好，而是因为你就想保密。有两三件事，连你们我都不会告诉。”

到了街角，巴伯从手推车上下来，帮着米克把车子抬下马路，然后又抬上另一条人行道。

“有一样东西，为它我愿意放弃一切。那就是一架钢琴。如果我们有架钢琴，我会每天晚上都弹，然后学会世界上所有的曲子。这是我最想要的东西。”

他们走到自己家所在的街区，再过几户人家，就到家了。他们家的房子是整个小镇北部最大的房子之一，有三层，但家里住了十四口人。真正有血缘关系的凯利家族并没有那么多人——但这些人吃在这里，睡在这里，每人交五块钱，完全可以把他们计算在内。辛格先生不算在内，因为他只是租了一个房间，自己收拾得干干净净。

房子很狭窄，好多年没有粉刷，似乎不太结实，难以承受三层楼的高度，屋子的一侧已经有些下沉了。

米克解开拉尔夫，把他从手推车里抱了出来。她飞速穿过走廊，用余光看见起居室里挤满了房客。她爸爸也在那里。她妈妈应该在厨房。这些人在这里闲荡，等着开饭。

他们一家住了三个房间，她走进第一个房间，把拉尔夫放在爸爸妈妈睡觉的床上，给了他一串珠子玩耍。隔壁房间关着的门后传来说话声，她决定进去看看。

黑兹尔和埃特看见她，立刻住了嘴。埃特正坐在窗前的椅子上，用红色指甲油染脚指甲。她的头发用铁发卷卷了起来，下巴上有一小块地方涂着一点白色的面霜，那里冒出来一个粉刺。黑兹尔像往常一样，懒洋洋地瘫在床上。

“你们一直在聊什么？”

“关你什么事。”埃特说，“闭上嘴，赶紧走开。”

“这是你们的房间，也是我的房间。我跟你们一样，有权待在这里。”米克趾高气扬地从一个角落走到另一个角落，在房间里走了个遍，“但是我不想找碴打架，我只想要求自己的权利。”

米克用手掌把蓬乱的刘海儿拢到后面。她经常这样干，以至于额头上蓬乱的鬈发都一绺绺地翘了起来。她动动鼻子，冲着镜子做了个鬼脸，然后又开始绕着屋子转悠。

黑兹尔和埃特作为姐姐，倒还说得过去。但埃特是个很不安分的女孩。她满脑子想的都是电影明星，或者演电影。有一次，她给珍妮特·麦克唐纳写信，还收到了一封打字机打的回信，信上说，如果她去好莱坞，可以顺便到她家游泳池去游泳。从此以后，游泳池便一直折磨着埃特的心。她一心想着，等她攒够车票钱就去好莱坞，找份秘书的工作，跟珍妮特·麦克唐纳成为闺密，然后自己也去演电影。

她整天对着镜子精心打扮，而这是最糟糕的地方。埃特并不像黑兹尔那样天生丽质。关键是，她的下巴很短。她经常用手拽下巴，做很多锻炼下巴的练习，这些都是她在一本电影手册里学到的。她经常对着镜子看自己的侧脸，努力用嘴巴摆出一个特定姿势。然而，这一切都毫无用处。有时，埃特会为此在晚上双手捂着脸大哭。

黑兹尔则太懒。她长得很好看，但脑子不开窍。她十八岁了，除了比尔，她是家里最大的孩子。也许，这就是问题所在。无论什么东西，她总是最先得到，而且是最大份——新衣服是头份的，任何好东西她拿的也最多。黑兹尔从来无须争抢，她很温柔。

“你准备在这里走一整天吗？看你穿的这身男生衣服，傻乎乎的，就让我恶心。得有人管管你了，米克·凯利，教你点规矩。”埃特说。

“闭嘴。”米克说，“我穿短裤，是因为我不想穿你剩下的那些旧衣服。我不想跟你俩一样，也不想穿得跟你俩一样，我就是不愿意，所以我穿短裤。我随时都想当个男孩，真希望可以搬去跟比尔一起住。”

米克爬进床底下，拿出一个大帽盒。她抱着盒子向门口走去，那两人在她背后大喊：“终于摆脱了！”

比尔的房间是家里最好的。他的房间像个小窝一样——他一个人独享——巴伯除外。比尔在墙上钉满了从杂志上剪下来的照片，大都是美女的脸部特写。在另外一角，挂着米克去年上免费美术班时画的一些画。房间里只有一张床和一张书桌。

比尔正躬身趴在桌子上，看《大众机械》杂志。她走到他身后，搂住他的肩膀。“嗨，你这个王八蛋。”

他没有像往常那样跟她扭成一团。“嗨。”他说，微微晃了晃肩膀。

“我在这里待一会儿，会打扰你吗？”

“当然可以——你想待就待，没关系。”

米克跪在地上，解开大帽盒上的绳子。她的双手停在盒盖边上，不知道为什么，拿不准是否要打开盖子。

“我一直在想自己在这件事上所做的一切，”她说，“可能行，也可能不行。”

比尔继续看杂志。她仍旧跪在盒子旁边，却没有打开它。她的眼睛游移到比尔身上，他背对她坐着。他看书时，一只大脚总踩在另一只脚上，鞋子都磨坏了。有一次，他们的爸爸说，比尔吃的所有午饭都长到了脚上，早饭长到了一只耳朵上，晚饭长到了另一只耳朵上。这么说有点刻薄，整整一个月，比尔心里都不痛快，但这话说得又很有意思。比尔的耳朵向外支棱着，非常红。虽然他才刚刚高中毕业，却已经穿十三码的鞋子了。他站起来时，一只脚总是躲到后面蹭另一只脚，想以此藏起自己的脚，却往往欲盖弥彰。

米克把盒子打开几英寸的缝，立刻又盖上了。她实在太兴奋了，没法当下就查看里面的东西。她站起来绕着屋子走来走去，最后才稍微平静一些。过了一会儿，她站在她在免费美术班上画的那幅画前面，这个课程是去年冬天，政府为学校孩子们开设的。这幅画里画的是海上的风暴，还有一只在狂风中猛冲的海鸥，画的名字叫作“暴风雨中断背的海鸥”。在头两三次课上，老师讲的是大海，因此，一开始大家画的几乎都是大海。然而，大部分孩子和她一样，从未亲眼见过真正的大海。

这是她画的第一幅画，比尔把它钉在了墙上。她画的其他画，里面满满的都是人。起初，她还画过一些海上风暴的画——有一张画的是一架正在坠落的飞机，人们纷纷跳机逃命；另一张画的是一艘横渡大西洋的轮船正在沉没，所有人都争抢着往一条小救生船上挤。

米克走到比尔房间的壁橱跟前，拿出她在美术班上画的另外一些画——有些是铅笔画，有些是水彩画，还有一张油画，这些画里都画满了人。她想象着百老汇大街发生了严重火灾，然后就按照想象的样子画了出来。火焰是明亮的绿色和橙色，大火烧得大街上只剩下布兰农先生的餐馆，还有第一国家银行。街上躺满了死尸，还有些人在奔跑着逃命。有个男人穿着睡衣，有个女人拼命想扛走一串香蕉。另一幅画叫作“工厂锅炉爆炸”，里面的人纷纷跳出窗户逃命，而一群身穿工装的孩子则挤在一起站在那里，手里端着饭盒，他们是来给爸爸送饭的。有幅油画画的是全镇的人都在百老汇大街打架。她也不知道为什么要画这幅画，也想不出该给它取个什么名字才合适。这幅画里没有大火，没有暴风雨，也看不出这群人为什么要打架。但比起其他的画，这幅画里的人更多，人们的动作也更多。这是她画得最好的一幅画，很可惜她没能想出一个好名字。但在她的内心深处，她知道该叫什么名字。

米克把画放回壁橱架子上。这些画现在看来都不怎么样。画里的人没有手指头，有些人的胳膊画得比腿还长。但美术课很有意思。她只不过把脑海里的画下来而已，没有任何缘由——在她心里，画画带给她的感受根本无法与音乐带给她的相提并论。什么都比不上音乐那么美好。

米克跪在地上，快速掀开大帽盒的盖子。里面是一把裂了的尤克里里琴，安着两根小提琴琴弦、一根吉他琴弦、一根班卓琴弦。琴背面的裂缝已经用胶布小心粘好，琴中间的圆孔盖上了一片木头，一端的小提琴琴马撑起琴弦，两侧刻着几个音孔。米克正在为自己做一把小提琴。她把琴放在腿上，觉得之前从来没有好好看过它。前一阵子，她用烟盒和皮筋给巴伯做了一把玩具曼陀林，这让她有了做琴这个想法。从那之后，她就四处搜寻不同的部件，每天都做一点点。在她看来，她已经倾尽全力，就差把自己的脑袋也用上了。

“比尔，这跟我见过的真正的小提琴不一样。”

他还在看杂志。“是吗？”

“看上去就是不对头，就是不——”

那天，她原打算紧紧琴栓，调调音，但她突然意识到，自己这把琴做得不怎么样，连看都懒得看。她一根根地拨弄着琴弦，琴弦发出空洞微弱的砰砰声。

“我怎样才能搞到一把琴弓呢？你肯定琴弓只能用马尾巴毛来做吗？”

“是的。”比尔有些不耐烦地说。

“用细铁丝或者人的头发拴在软棍上不行吗？”

比尔搓着两只脚，没答话。

愤怒让她的额头冒出豆大的汗珠，她的声音都嘶哑了。“这连一把糟糕的小提琴都算不上，只是曼陀林和尤克里里琴的杂交品，我恨它们，我恨它们——”

比尔转过身来。

“一切都不对头，根本不行，根本没用——”

“冷静点，”比尔说，“你还要继续做手里的这把破尤克里里琴吗？我一开始就该告诉你，你觉得自己能够做出一把小提琴，简直是疯了。这种东西不是你坐着就能做出来的——你得买才行。我觉得所有人都明白这个道理，但我想，让你自己明白这个道理也无妨。”

有时候，比尔比这个世界上的任何人都可恶，他跟以前完全不一样了。她猛地把小提琴摔到地上，一通猛踩，但接着，又把琴草草收进帽盒里。她眼里的泪水滚烫。她踢了一脚帽盒，看都没看比尔，便跑出了房间。

她躲闪着穿过走廊到后院去，这时撞上了妈妈。

“你怎么了？碰上了什么事了？”

米克想要挣脱开，但妈妈抓住她的胳膊不放。她难过地用手背抹掉脸上的泪。妈妈一直在厨房里待着，这会儿戴着围裙，脚上是一双便鞋。她跟平时一样，似乎心事重重，没有时间再问米克问题。

“杰克逊先生今天和他的两个姐姐来吃饭，椅子不够了，你和巴伯到厨房吃吧。”

“这对我来说再好不过了。”米克说。

妈妈松开她，去脱围裙。餐厅里传来开饭的铃声，并猛然响起愉快的谈话声。她听见爸爸说，由于没有续交意外保险，他损失了很多钱，最后还把髋骨摔坏了。这件事总让她爸爸无法放下——他本来可以赚到钱的，却没有。碗碟碰撞发出叮当声，过了一会儿，谈话声停止了。

米克靠在楼梯的栏杆上。她先是打嗝，然后突然哭出声来。她回顾过去的一个月，觉得在心里似乎从未真正相信过那把小提琴能用。但在她心里，她一直让自己相信这一点，即便现在，也很难有一丝怀疑。她累坏了。比尔现在无论在什么事上，都不会帮她了。以前，她认为比尔是世界上最伟大的人。以前，无论他去哪里，她总是跟在后头——到树林里钓鱼，到他和别的男孩一块建起来的俱乐部，到布兰农先生餐馆后面的老虎机那里——无论哪里。也许，他不是故意这样让她失望的，但无论如何，他们再也做不成朋友了。

走廊里弥漫着香烟和周日午餐的味道。米克深吸一口气，走回厨房。午饭的味道很香，她饿了。她听到波西娅跟巴伯说话的声音，她好像在哼着歌或者在给他讲故事。

“这就是为什么我要比大多数黑人女孩幸运的原因。”当她打开门时，听见波西娅这样说道。

“为什么？”米克问。

波西娅和巴伯正坐在厨房餐桌旁吃饭。波西娅穿着一条绿色印花裙，在深棕肤色的映衬下显得非常清凉。她戴着绿色耳环，头发梳得紧致光滑。

“你总是在别人说到最后的时候才闯进来，又想知道来龙去脉。”波西娅说。她站起来，走到火热的炉子边，把饭菜盛到米克的盘子里。

“我和巴伯正在说我外公在老萨迪斯路上的房子。我告诉巴伯，我外公和舅舅们拥有整个那片地方，足足有十五英亩半。他们总是用四英亩种棉花，有些年份又种豌豆，这样才能使土壤保持肥沃。山上有一英亩地，专门种桃子。他们有头骡子，一头育种母猪，还一直养着二十到二十五只蛋鸡和小鸡崽。他们有块菜地、两棵山核桃树，很多无花果树、李子树和浆果树。这都是真的。没有多少白人建的农场能像我外公这样，把土地收拾得那么好。”

米克把胳膊肘支在桌上，向盘子倾过身去。除了谈论她的丈夫和弟弟，波西娅经常谈论的就是农场了。听她讲农场的事情，会让你觉得黑人的农场简直就是“白宫”。

“外公家一开始只有一间小房子。那么多年来，他们一直在建房子，最后，房子大得足够我外公、他的四个儿子和他们的老婆孩子住，还能装下我弟弟汉密尔顿。他们的客厅里有一架真正的管风琴，还有一台留声机。墙上挂着外公的大照片，是他穿着社团制服照的。他们把所有水果和蔬菜都做成罐头，到了冬天，不管多冷，也不管下多少雨，他们都有充足的东西吃。”

“那你为什么不跟他们一起住啊？”米克问道。

波西娅停下手里正在削土豆的活儿，边用修长的棕色手指敲着桌子边说：“是这样的，你瞧——每个人都为自己的家人建了房子。这些年，他们干得很辛苦。当然了，所有人都不容易。但你瞧——我小时候跟外公一起生活，但从那以后我在那儿就没干过活儿。不过无论什么时候，如果我和威利、海博埃碰到了麻烦，我们随时都可以回去。”

“你父亲难道没建房子吗？”

波西娅停止了咀嚼。“谁父亲？你是说我父亲？”

“当然了。”米克说。

“你很清楚，我父亲是个黑人医生，就在这个镇上。”

米克以前听波西娅说过，但她以为这只是个故事而已。一个黑人怎么能当医生呢？

“事情是这样的。在我妈妈嫁给我爸爸之前，她除了真正的善良之外，一无所知。我外公自己也是个‘善良先生’。但我爸爸跟他全然不一样，两者之间的差距就像白天和黑夜一样。”

“残酷？”米克问道。

“不，他不是个残酷的人，”波西娅缓缓说道，“只是出了些问题。我父亲不喜欢其他黑人，这个很难解释清楚。我父亲总是一个人学习。很久以前，他就建立了关于一个家庭应该是怎样的想法。家里的事情，事无巨细，都由他一个人说了算。晚上，他还要给孩子们上课。”

“我觉得，这不算糟糕。”米克说。

“听着。大多数时候他很安静，但有些晚上他会大发脾气，他生气的样子比我见过的任何人都凶。认识我父亲的人都说，他简直疯了。他做过很多粗鲁、疯狂的事情，我妈妈离开了他。那时我才十岁。我妈妈把我们这些孩子都带到了外公的农场，我们是在那里长大的。我爸爸一直想让我们回来，但即便我妈妈死了，我们都没回家住。现在，我父亲一个人过。”

米克走到火炉边，又盛了一盘饭菜。波西娅的声音起起伏伏，像唱歌似的，现在什么也挡不住她说话了。

“我很少去见父亲——也许每周见一次——但我一直想着他。他最让我难过。我觉得他比镇上任何一个白人读的书都多。他读了很多书，对很多事情都很操心。他满脑子都是书，都是忧虑。他失去了上帝，背弃了信仰，因此才有了这么多烦恼。”

波西娅很兴奋。无论什么时候，只要说到上帝——或者她弟弟威利、她丈夫海博埃——她都变得很兴奋。

“喏，我可不是什么呼喊派，我是基督教长老会教徒，我们不喜欢集会时在地上打滚，或者胡言乱语。我们不用每个星期都去接受净化或者一起四处游荡。在教堂里，我们一起唱歌，听牧师布道。跟你说实话，米克，我觉得唱唱歌、听听布道没有坏处。你该带你的小弟弟去主日学校，而且你也大了，可以去教堂。你最近趾高气扬的样子，让我觉得你好像有一只脚已经迈进火坑里了。”

“胡说。”米克说。

“我们结婚前，海博埃就是个虔诚的孩子。每个周日，他都喜欢去接近圣灵，喊一喊，净化自己。结婚后，我让他跟我一起，尽管有时候很难让他安静下来，但我觉得他已经做得很好了。”

“我既不信圣诞老人，也不信上帝。”米克说。

“等等！这就是为什么有时候我觉得，你比我认识的任何一个人更像我父亲。”

“我？你说我像你父亲？”

“我不是说脸或者长相，我是说你们心灵的样子和颜色。”

巴伯坐在那里，看看这个，又看看那个。他的脖子上系着餐巾，手里仍然拿着空勺子。“上帝都吃什么呀？”他问。

米克从桌前起身，站到门口，准备离开。有时候，折磨波西娅很有意思。她总是用同样的语调开始说，说的又总是同样的话——好像她只知道这些似的。

“像你和我父亲这样的人，不去教堂，就永远不会得到安宁。就拿我来说吧——我相信上帝，得到了安宁。还有巴伯，他也得到了安宁。我的海博埃，我的威利，他们也是一样。单从表面上看，我觉得辛格先生也得到了安宁。第一次见他，我就有这种感觉。”

“随你怎么说，”米克说，“你比你的父亲还要疯狂。”

“但你从来没有爱过上帝，或者爱过什么人。你像牛皮般强硬又粗糙。从我认识你，你就是这个样子。今天下午，你还要四处乱转，永远也得不到满足。你还要四处转悠，就像在找什么丢掉的东西一样。你会越来越激动，你的心跳会越来越快，让你承受不了，因为你没有去爱，也得不到安宁。总有一天你会一下子崩溃，就毁了。到那个时候，什么都帮不了你。”

“什么，波西娅？”巴伯问，“上帝吃什么东西啊？”

米克大笑起来，噔噔跑出了房间。

下午，她的确在房子周围乱转，因为她没法安静下来。有时候她就是这样。首先，一想到小提琴，就让她很焦虑，她永远没办法把它做成一把真正的小提琴了——她苦苦计划了那么多个星期，一想到这里，她就觉得很难受。但她当初为什么那么肯定这个想法会奏效呢？太愚蠢？也许，当人们极度渴望一样东西时，但凡有什么事情有可能让他们实现这个想法，他们都会深信不疑。

米克不想回到家人住的房间去，也不想跟任何一个房客说话。她无处可去，只能去街上——但街上骄阳似火。她在走廊里漫无目的地来回走着，不断用手掌把凌乱的头发拢到后面。“见鬼，”她大声地自言自语，“除了一架真正的钢琴，我最想要的就是一个可以独自待着的地方。”

那个波西娅身上有着某种黑人的疯狂劲儿，但她人还不错，她不会像有些黑人女孩那样，背地里对巴伯或拉尔夫做出卑鄙的事情来。但波西娅说，米克从未爱过任何人。米克停下脚步，一动不动地站在那里，用拳头搓着头顶。如果波西娅真的知道了，她会怎么想？她究竟会怎么想？

很多事情，她从来不对别人讲。这一点，毋庸置疑。

米克缓缓爬上楼梯，经过第一个平台，继续爬第二截楼梯。有些门为了通风而开着，房子里响着各种各样的声音。米克停在最后一截楼梯上，坐了下来。布朗小姐如果开了收音机，她就能听见音乐，也许还会有些好节目。

她把头伏在膝盖上，把网球鞋的鞋带打了一个结。如果波西娅知道，她爱过的人一个又一个，她会怎么说？每一次，她身体的一部分都好像要碎裂成千万片。

但她从来没告诉过别人，没有人知道。

米克在台阶上坐了很久。布朗小姐并没有打开收音机，除了人们的嘈杂声，再没有别的声音了。她思考了很久，不断用拳头捶打着大腿，她的脸感觉像裂成了碎片，没法保持完整了。这种感觉比饥肠辘辘还糟糕，却又很像是那样。我想要——我想要——我想要——是她全部的想法——但这种迫切的需求是什么，她却并不清楚。

大约过了一个小时，上面的平台传来转动门把手的声音。米克迅速抬起头，是辛格先生。他在走廊里站了一会儿，脸上是一副伤心、平静的表情。然后，他走过去，进了浴室。他的同伴没有跟他一起出来。从她坐的地方可以看见辛格先生的部分房间，他的同伴还在睡着，身上盖了一条床单。她等着辛格先生从浴室里出来。她的两颊非常热，用手摸着面颊。也许，她有时候到最上面的楼梯来，的确是为了一边听楼下布朗小姐的收音机，一边还可以看见辛格先生。她不知道，他的耳朵听不见但在心里能听到什么样的音乐。没有人知道。如果他会说话，会说些什么呢？也没有人知道。

米克等待着，过了一会儿，辛格先生又回到走廊里。她希望他能向下看一眼，冲她笑一笑。他走到门口时，的确朝下扫了一眼，点了点头。米克咧开嘴笑了，颤抖着。他走进屋子，关上了门。也许，他是想请她进屋看看他的。米克突然想走进他的房间。等他的同伴走了以后，她真的会很快找个时间到辛格先生的房间里去看看他。她真的会这样做。

炎热的下午过得非常缓慢，米克一直独自坐在台阶上。莫扎特的音乐又回响在她的脑子里。这很有意思，但正是辛格先生让她想起了这首曲子。她真的希望能有一个地方，让她可以大声地把这首曲子哼出来。有些音乐只能独自享受，没法在挤满人的房子里唱出来。一个人在一幢人满为患的房子里，居然可以如此孤独，这也很有意思。米克努力去想有什么私密的好地方，她可以独自待着，好好研究下这首曲子。尽管她想了好久，但从一开始她便知道，根本没有这样的好地方。

4

傍晚时分，杰克·布朗特醒了，感觉睡得很好。他躺着的这个房间小而整洁，有一张书桌、一张饭桌、一张床和几把椅子。书桌上，有一台电扇正摇着头，在两面墙之间慢慢地来回吹着，轻风扫过杰克的脸，让他想到清凉的水。窗前，一个男人坐在桌子前，盯着摆在面前的一盘象棋。日光下，杰克觉得房间很陌生，但他立刻认出了那个男人的脸，好像他们早就认识一样。

许多记忆同时涌上杰克的心头，搅在了一起。他躺着一动不动，睁着眼睛，手心朝上。他的两只手很大，在白色床单的映衬下显出一种很深的棕色。他把手举到面前，上面布满抓痕和瘀青——血管都突出着，好像他一直抓着什么东西抓了很久。他脸色疲惫，样子邋遢，棕色头发盖在额头上，胡子乱七八糟，眉毛又粗又乱。他躺在那里，嘴唇动了动，胡子也跟着紧张地抖动起来。

过了一会儿，他坐起来，用一只大拳头猛捶自己的太阳穴，好让自己清醒过来。他一动，下棋的那个男人就立刻抬起头来，冲他微笑。

“天哪，我渴死了。”杰克说，“感觉就像有支穿着袜子的俄国军队从我嘴里走过去一样。”

那个男人望着他，一直微笑着，然后突然伸手从桌子一侧下方拿出一个装着冰水的磨砂水壶，还有一只玻璃杯。杰克喘着粗气大口大口地喝水——他半裸着站在房间中央，头朝后仰着，一只手紧张地握成拳头。他一连喝了四杯水，这才深吸一口气，感觉放松了一些。

一瞬间，有些回忆浮上他的心头。他不记得跟这个男人回家了，但之后发生的事情现在越来越清晰。他醒来时，发现自己泡在一盆凉水里。后来，他们一起喝咖啡、聊天。他倾吐了心中很多事情，那个男人一直听着。他说得嗓子都哑了，说的什么他记不太清了，却牢牢记住了那个男人脸上的表情。他们早晨才上床睡觉，百叶窗拉了下来，遮住了光线。起初，他噩梦不断，总是惊醒，必须得开灯才能让自己清醒过来。灯光也惊醒了这个家伙，但他没有一句怨言。

“你昨晚为什么没把我踢出门啊？”

那个男人只是又笑了一下。杰克不知道他为什么会如此安静。他看着四周，找自己的衣服，发现自己的手提箱就放在床边的地上。他不记得自己是怎样把箱子从餐馆里要回来的，他还欠着餐馆的酒钱。他的那些书、一套白色西装、几件衬衫都在里面，原封不动。他开始飞快地穿衣服。

等他穿好衣服，桌子上一只电咖啡壶正在滤煮着咖啡。男人伸手去掏挂在椅背上的一件马甲的口袋，拿出一张卡片。杰克疑惑地接了过来。这个男人的名字——约翰·辛格——刻在卡片中央，下面用钢笔写着一条简短的信息，字迹跟刻的名字一样精致。

我是聋哑人，但我能读唇语，跟我说话，我听得懂。

请不要大喊大叫。

震惊之下，杰克觉得有些头重脚轻，大脑一片茫然。他和约翰·辛格就这么对望着。

“不知道我自己得花多长时间，才可能发现这一点。”他说。

他说话的时候，辛格非常认真地看着他的嘴唇——他以前就注意到了这一点。他真蠢！

他们坐在桌旁，用蓝色杯子喝着热咖啡。房间里很凉爽，半开的百叶窗让照进来的刺目光线变得柔和了许多。辛格从壁橱里取出一个铁盒子，里面有一条面包、几个橘子，还有奶酪。辛格吃得不多，一只手插在口袋里，靠在椅背上，杰克则狼吞虎咽。他必须得立马离开这里，好好考虑考虑这些事情。他现在处境不妙，应该赶紧四处转转，找份工作才行。房间里静悄悄的，宁静舒适，没法考虑这些令人焦虑的事情——他得离开这里，自己走一会儿。

“这里还有别的聋哑人吗？”他问道，“你朋友多吗？”

辛格依旧微笑着。他一开始没明白这些话，杰克不得不又重复一遍。辛格抬了抬尖尖的黑色眉毛，摇了摇头。

“孤独吗？”

男人摇了摇头，像说是，又像说不是。他们默默地坐了一会儿，然后杰克起身要走。他一连谢了辛格好几次，感谢辛格昨晚收留自己。他慢慢动着嘴唇，确保辛格能听明白。哑巴只是又笑了一下，耸了耸肩。杰克问是否可以把手提箱塞到床底下在这里放几天，哑巴点头应允。

然后，辛格把手从口袋里抽出来，拿出一支银色铅笔在便笺本上一笔一画地写起来。他把便笺本推过去，给杰克看。

我可以在地上放个垫子，你找到地方住之前，可以先住在这里。白天我基本不在家。你不会给我添麻烦的。

杰克觉得自己的嘴唇颤抖了，他突然生出一股感激之情，但他不能接受。“谢谢，”他说，“我已经有地方住了。”

他要走的时候，哑巴递给他一条紧紧卷成一团的蓝色工装裤，还给他七毛五分钱。工装裤很脏，等杰克看清楚这件衣服，他才突然回忆起前一周发生的事。辛格跟他比画着，说这些钱原来是装在他口袋里的。

“再见。”杰克说，“我会很快找个时间回来的。”

他走了，哑巴站在门口，双手依然插在口袋里，脸上留着还未褪去的笑容。他下了几级台阶，又转身挥挥手。哑巴也朝他挥手，然后关上了房门。

外面强烈的阳光猛地刺向他的双眼。他站在房子前面的人行道上，一下子被阳光晒得头晕眼花，什么也看不清楚。一个孩子坐在房子前面的栏杆上。他以前在哪里见过她。他想起她穿的那条男式短裤，还有她眯缝眼睛的样子。

他举起手里那卷脏兮兮的工装裤，“我想把这个扔掉，知道哪里有垃圾桶吗？”

孩子从栏杆上跳下来。“在后院，我带你去。”

他跟在她身后，穿过房子旁边那条狭窄潮湿的小巷。到了后院，杰克看到两个黑人正坐在后面的台阶上。他俩都穿着白色西装，白色鞋子，其中一个黑人个子很高，领带和袜子都是鲜艳的绿色。另一个黑人是个混血儿，中等个头，正摩挲着膝盖上的一个铁口琴。他的袜子和领结是火红色的，跟高个儿同伴形成强烈对比。

孩子指指后院栅栏旁的垃圾桶，然后转身冲着厨房的窗子大喊：“波西娅！海博埃和威利来了，正等着你呢。”

厨房里传出一个柔和的声音回应着孩子的话。“你不用喊那么大声，我知道他们来了。我戴上帽子就来。”扔掉工装裤之前，杰克先把工装裤展开，只见上面沾满了泥巴，都发硬了，一条裤腿也撕破了，前面还沾了几滴血。他把衣服扔进了垃圾桶。一个黑人女孩从屋里出来，走到台阶上两个穿白西装的男孩身边。杰克发现，那个穿短裤的孩子正密切注视着他，她把重心从一只脚挪到另一只脚，看上去很兴奋的样子。

“你是辛格先生的亲戚吗？”她问。

“不是。”

“好朋友？”

“嗯，还不错，可以跟他一起过夜。”

“我只是想知道——”

“主街怎么走？”

她指指右边。“这边，走两个街区就到了。”

杰克用手指梳理了一下胡子，走了。他在手里晃着那七毛五分钱，咬着下嘴唇，直到把嘴唇咬得红红白白的。那三个黑人在他前面，慢吞吞地一边聊天一边走着。在这个陌生的小镇上，他觉得很孤独，于是便紧跟在他们后面，听他们说话。女孩挽着两个男孩的胳膊。她穿了件绿裙子，戴了一顶红帽子，脚上是一双红鞋。两个男孩紧靠在她身边走着。

“我们今晚有什么计划？”她问。

“完全听你的，亲爱的。”高个男孩说，“我和威利没什么特别的事。”

她看看这个，再看看那个。“得由你俩来决定。”

“嗯——”穿红袜子的矮个男孩说，“我和海博埃觉得，咱仨也——也许可以去教堂。”

女孩用三种不同的腔调，唱着答道：“好——的——从教堂出来，我有个想法，我得去和爸爸待一会儿——就一小会儿。”他们在第一个拐角转了弯，杰克站在那里，望了他们一会儿，然后继续向前走去。

主街上静悄悄的，很热，连个人影都没有。直到现在，他才意识到今天是周日——想到这里，他觉得很沮丧。大门紧闭的商店都撑起了遮雨棚，楼房在明亮的阳光底下显得光秃秃的。他经过纽约咖啡馆，门开着，但店里空荡荡的，很昏暗。那天早晨他没找到袜子穿，炽热的人行道透过薄薄的鞋底烤着他的双脚。太阳像块烧红的烙铁，紧紧压在他的头顶。这个小镇比他见过的任何地方都显得孤独，寂静的大街让他感觉很怪异。他喝醉的时候，这个地方显得那么欢腾喧闹，而现在，一切好像都戛然而止，没了一丝动静。

他走进一家水果兼糖果店，买了份报纸。招聘广告栏内容非常少，有几家招聘二十五至四十岁的年轻人，要有车，通过销售各种产品抽取佣金。他快速跳过这些内容。一则招聘卡车司机的广告吸引了他的注意力，但最让他感兴趣的还是最下面的一则启事，上面写道：

招聘——有经验的技师。迪克西阳光游乐场。

请前往织工巷和第十五大街的路口处应聘。

不知不觉地，他又走到那家餐馆门口，过去的两周他正是在这里度过的。除了那家水果店，这片街区只有这里没关门。杰克临时决定进去看看比夫·布兰农。

从外面刺眼的阳光中走进来，咖啡馆里显得特别暗。一切都比他记忆中的样子显得更破败，更安静。布兰农像往常一样，站在收银机后面，两只胳膊抱在胸前，他丰满美丽的妻子则坐在柜台的另一头，正在锉着手指甲。杰克注意到，他走进来时夫妻俩对望了一眼。

“下午好。”布兰农说。

杰克感觉空气有些异样。也许，这个家伙是在笑，因为又想起了他烂醉时发生的那些事情。杰克呆呆地站着，有点愤懑。“请来盒塔吉特烟。”布兰农伸手到柜台下面拿烟时，杰克断定，布兰农不是在嘲笑他。白天，这个家伙的脸看上去不像晚上那么冷硬。他的脸色有点苍白，好像没睡好，眼神看上去像是一只疲惫的秃鹫。

“直说吧。”杰克说，“我欠你多少钱？”

布兰农打开抽屉，拿出一个学生用的便笺簿，放到柜台上。他慢吞吞地翻动纸页，杰克望着他。这本便笺看上去不像日常的记账本，倒更像一本私密的笔记。上面有长串的数字，加减乘除，还有简单勾勒的画。他在一页纸上停住，杰克看见页角写着自己的姓氏。这一页上面，没有数字——只有小的对号和叉号，上面还随意画了一整页圆滚滚的小猫，小猫是坐着的，尾巴又长又弯。杰克盯住不动。这些小猫的脸是人脸，而且是女人的脸。这些小猫的脸正是布兰农太太。

“这里画对号的，代表啤酒。”布兰农说，“画叉号的，是晚饭。直线，是威士忌。我看看——”布兰农用手搓搓鼻子，耷拉着眼皮。然后，他合上便笺簿。“大约二十块钱。”

“我得需要很长时间还钱，”杰克说，“到时候也许能还上这笔钱。”

“不着急。”

杰克靠在柜台上。“呃，这个小镇是个什么样的地方？”

“普通地方，”布兰农说，“跟其他和它一样大的地方一样。”

“有多少人口？”

“大概三万人。”

杰克打开那包烟，给自己卷了一支。他的手在哆嗦。“大部分地方都是工厂？”

“对。有四个大棉纺厂——这四个是主要的工厂，还有一个针织厂，几个轧棉厂和锯木厂。”

“工资怎么样？”

“一周差不多平均十到十一块钱——但当然，不时都有人下岗。你为什么问这些？你想到工厂里找份工作？”

杰克将拳头按到眼睛上，睡意蒙眬地揉着眼睛。“不知道，也许去，也许不去。”他把报纸铺到柜台上，指指刚才看的那则招聘广告，“我想四处看看，了解下这个。”

布兰农看了广告，想了想。“是的，”最后他说，“我见过这个游乐场，不太大——只有几个新奇玩意儿，比如旋转木马和秋千，进去玩的都是些黑人、工人和孩子。他们经常在镇上各个空地搬来搬去。”

“告诉我去那里怎么走。”

布兰农跟他一起走到门口，给他指了指方向。“今天早晨你跟辛格一起回的家吗？”

杰克点点头。

“你觉得他人怎么样？”

杰克咬着嘴唇。哑巴的面容清晰地浮现在他的脑海里，就像认识很久的朋友一样。自从离开他的房间后，他一直在想着这个男人。“我甚至不知道他是个聋哑人。”最后，他说道。

他又走回炎热寂寥的大街。他不像个在陌生小镇上的陌生人，似乎在找人。很快，他走进河边的一片厂区。道路变得很窄，没铺路面，但不再空荡荡的了。一群群脏兮兮的孩子都是一副饥肠辘辘的模样，呼朋唤友，玩着游戏。那些只有两间屋的窝棚，千篇一律，破败不堪，都没有粉刷。食物和下水道的恶臭跟空气中的尘土混合在一起。河里的小瀑布隐隐发出哗哗的水声。人们或站在门口一言不发，或闲坐在台阶上。他们望着杰克，面黄肌瘦，毫无表情。他睁大棕色的眼睛，也盯着他们。他深一脚浅一脚地走着，不时用毛茸茸的手背抹一下嘴巴。

织工巷的尽头是一块空旷的场地，以前是个废旧汽车回收站，地上仍然散落着生锈的机器部件，还有破损的内胎。场地一角，停着一辆拖车，附近有个旋转木马，用帆布盖住了一部分。

杰克慢慢走过去。两个穿工装裤的小孩站在旋转木马前面。旁边有个黑人坐在箱子上，在夕阳下昏昏欲睡，两个膝盖瘫软地靠在一起，一只手里还拿着一袋融化了的巧克力。杰克望着他把手指头伸进黏糊糊的巧克力，然后慢条斯理地吸吮着手指。

“这里的经理是谁？”

黑人把沾满巧克力的两根手指塞进嘴里，用舌头上上下下舔着。“是个红头发男人。”他舔完手指后说道，“别的我不清楚，先生。”

“他现在在哪儿？”

“那边，最大的那架马车后面。”

杰克一边穿过草地，一边抽下领带塞进口袋里。西边，太阳已经开始落山了。在那条黑色的房顶线之上，天空显出一种温暖的深红色。游乐场老板正一个人站在那里抽烟，红头发向上竖着，像头上顶了块海绵，他用无神的灰色眼睛盯着杰克。

“你就是经理？”

“嗯。我叫帕特森。”

“我来找工作，从今早的报纸上看到的。”

“好。我可不想要新手。我需要的是有经验的机修工。”

“我经验丰富。”杰克说。

“你干过什么？”

“我干过织工，修过织布机，在汽修厂和汽车装配车间也干过，什么活儿都干过。”

帕特森带他走到盖住了一部分的旋转木马跟前。在夕阳的照射下，这些一动不动的木马非常迷人。它们腾跃的姿势静止了，固定在褪色的镀金杆上。最靠近杰克的那匹马，脏乎乎的木头屁股上有细碎的裂纹，两只眼睛好像是瞎了一样，它神情狂躁，眼窝处的油漆也一片片剥落。在杰克看来，这些一动不动的旋转木马就像他醉酒后梦见的东西。

“我需要一个有经验的机修工来修理这个，让这些东西保持良好状态。”帕特森说。

“我完全可以做到。”

“这份工作需要两手兼顾。”帕特森解释道，“你负责整个地方。除了照看机器，你还得负责维持游客秩序。你得确保每个上来玩的人都买了票，还得确保他们的票是有效的，不是什么舞厅的旧票。大家都想坐木马，那些黑人没钱的时候总会想尽办法蒙骗你，你绝对想不到。你得一直瞪大三只眼睛看着。”

帕特森领他走到木马中间的机器那里，给他指了各种部件。他调整了一下手柄，随后便响起一阵尖细刺耳的机械音乐声。周围这群木马似乎把他们跟外界完全隔绝开来。等木马停下来，杰克问了几个问题，然后开始独自动手操作机器。

“上个家伙辞职了。”他们走出来又回到空地上时，帕特森说，“我一直讨厌换新人。”

“我什么时候上班？”

“明天下午。我们每周开放六个白天和晚上——早晨四点开门，晚上十二点关门。你三点左右就得过来，帮着做准备。晚上停业之后，还得花大概一个小时才能收拾停当。”

“工资呢？”

“十二块。”

杰克点点头，帕特森伸出一只苍白、瘦骨嶙峋的手，指甲很脏。

杰克离开空地的时候，天色已晚。刺目的蓝天变白了，东方出现了一轮白色的月亮。暮色之中，街道两旁那些房子的轮廓柔和了很多。杰克没有立刻沿着织工巷返回，而是走到附近的街区闲逛。一些味道，还有远处传来的一些声音，让他不时在尘土飞扬的大街旁驻足。他走走停停，会突然从一个方向转向另一个方向，漫无目的。他的头感觉轻飘飘的，好像是用薄薄的玻璃做的。他的身体内正在发生一种化学变化。他不断往身体里储存的那些啤酒和威士忌开始发生反应了，突然让他感觉到一阵醉意。之前看上去死气沉沉的大街，现在有了生机。大街边，有条参差不齐的狭长草坪。杰克走路的时候，感觉地面抬了起来，越来越靠近他的脸。他在草坪边坐下，靠在一根电话线杆上。他舒舒服服地坐在那里，像土耳其人那样盘起腿来，捋着胡须梢。有很多话涌上心头，于是，他神志恍惚地大声自言自语起来。

“愤慨是贫穷最宝贵的花朵。是的。”

说说话真好。自己的声音让他感到愉悦。声音似乎回荡着，萦绕在空中，每个词都响了两次。他咽口唾沫，润了润嘴唇，接着说。他突然很想回到哑巴安静的房间里，跟哑巴说说心里话。想跟一个聋哑人聊天，真是一件怪事。但是，他很孤独。

眼前的街道暗淡下来，夜晚就要来临了。偶尔有人从他身边经过，走在这条狭窄的街道上，彼此间沉闷地谈着话，每迈一步都会在脚边搅起一团尘土。也有女孩结伴经过，或者一个妈妈肩头扛着孩子走过去。杰克麻木地坐了一会儿，最后，他站起来，继续向前走。织工巷里黑乎乎的。几户人家的油灯在门口或窗外投下昏黄跳跃的灯光。有些房子里漆黑一片，家里人都坐在门前台阶上，借着邻居家反射出来的光才能看清东西。一个女人从窗户里探出身子，把一桶脏水泼到街上，有几滴溅到了杰克的脸上。有些房子后面传来尖厉愤怒的声音，还有些房子则传来摇椅缓慢摇动的令人感到宁静的声音。

杰克在一幢房子前停下，门前的台阶上坐着三个男人。房子里面透出的昏黄灯光照在他们身上，有两个人穿着工装裤，但打着赤膊，光着脚。其中一个个子很高，一副松松垮垮的样子；另一个很矮，嘴角生了脓疮。第三个人穿着衬衫和裤子，膝盖上放了顶草帽。

“嗨。”杰克说。

三个人盯着他，脸色蜡黄，面无表情。他们低声嘟囔着什么，却依旧坐着没动。杰克从口袋里拿出那包塔吉特烟，分了一圈。他在最底下一层台阶上坐下，脱掉鞋子。清凉潮湿的地面让脚感觉特别舒服。

“现在有工作吗？”

“有。”拿草帽的男人说，“大多数时候有工作。”

杰克抠着脚指头。“我这里有福音[7]。”他说，“想找个人说说。”

三个男人笑了。狭窄街道的对面，传来一个女人的歌声。他们吐出的烟雾缭绕在凝固的空气中，久久不散。一个小孩从街上跑过来停下，解开裤子前裆开始撒尿。

“拐角那边有个帐篷，星期天开放。”小个子男人终于说话了，“你可以到那里去，跟他们尽情讲你的福音。”

“不是那种福音，是更好的，是真理。”

“哪种真理？”

杰克吸吮了一下胡子，没有回答。过了一会儿，他说：“你们这里从来没有罢过工吗？”

“有过一次。”高个子男人说，“大概六年前，这里罢过一次工。”

“是怎么回事？”

嘴角生脓疮的男人挪动两只脚，把烟蒂扔到地上。“嗯——他们就是不干了，因为他们一小时想要两毛钱。罢工的大约有三百人，他们一整天都在街上瞎溜达。后来，工厂派了几辆卡车出去，一个星期以后，镇上到处都是到这儿来找工作的人。”

杰克转过身，面对着他们。三个男人坐的地方比他高两个台阶，所以他得抬起头来才能看着他们的眼睛。“这事难道不让你们愤怒吗？”他问。

“你说的什么意思——愤怒？”

杰克额头上的血管突出来，变成深红色。“老天，天哪，我的意思就是愤怒——愤——怒——愤怒。”他对着他们困惑不已的蜡黄面孔怒目而视。在他们身后，他可以从敞开的前门看见房子里面的情景。在前面的房间里，有三张床、一个洗漱台；后面的房间里，一个赤脚女人坐在一张椅子上，睡着了。从附近一个昏暗的门廊里，传来弹奏吉他的声音。

“我就是当时坐卡车来镇上的。”高个子男人说。

“这没有什么区别。我想要跟你们说的是简单直白的。那些拥有这些工厂的杂种们都是百万富翁，但那些落纱工、梳毛工，还有所有那些在机器后面纺纱织布的工人，他们几乎连肚子都填不饱。明白吗？所以，当你们走在街上思考，看见那些饥肠辘辘、疲惫不堪的人，看见那些佝偻着腿的孩子，你们难道不会愤怒吗？不会吗？”

杰克的脸又红又黑，嘴唇哆嗦着。三个男人小心翼翼地望着他，然后，拿草帽的那个男人哈哈大笑起来。

“继续，偷着笑吧。你们就坐在这里，笑破肚皮吧。”

三个笑一个，这三个男人笑得不急不慢、从容自在。杰克擦擦脚底的土，穿上鞋子。他的两只拳头攥得紧紧的，嘴角抽搐，带着一丝愤怒的嘲讽。“笑吧——你们只能干这个。希望你们就坐在这里，偷着笑吧，‘直到你们烂掉！’”他走在街上，浑身僵硬，身后的笑声和嘘声一直追随着他。

主街上灯火通明。杰克在一个拐角处徘徊着，在口袋里摆弄着那几枚硬币。他的头阵阵作痛，尽管夜晚炎热，但他觉得全身发冷。他想到了哑巴，急切地想回去跟他坐一会儿。他走到下午买报纸的那家水果兼糖果店，挑了一篮子水果，上面包着玻璃纸。柜台后面的希腊人说价格是六毛钱，付完钱他就只剩一枚五分硬币了。他走出商店，立刻觉得手中的礼物送给一个健康人未免有些好笑。几颗葡萄从玻璃纸下面垂下来，他贪婪地摘下来吃掉了。

杰克到的时候，辛格在家。辛格正坐在窗户前，面前的桌上摆着那盘棋。房间还是杰克离开时的样子，电扇开着，那罐冰水放在桌子旁边，床上有一顶巴拿马帽和一个纸包裹，看上去哑巴似乎刚刚回家。他朝对面的椅子抬抬下巴，然后把棋盘推到了一边。他的双手插进口袋，向后靠，脸上的表情似乎在问杰克走了以后情况怎么样。

杰克把水果放在桌上。“今天下午的情况，”他说，“可以用这句格言来概括：出去找条章鱼，给它穿上袜子。”

哑巴笑了，但杰克不清楚他是否明白了自己的意思。哑巴看看水果，很吃惊，然后解开玻璃纸包装。他收拾这些水果时，脸上有种特别怪异的表情。杰克努力想搞明白这个表情意味着什么，却还是被难住了。辛格露出灿烂的笑容。

“今天下午，我找了份游乐场的工作。我要去开旋转木马了。”

哑巴似乎并不吃惊。他走到壁橱前，拿出一瓶酒和两只玻璃杯。他们喝着酒，一言不发。杰克觉得，自己从来没有在如此安静的房间里待过。头顶上的灯光将自己的影子投在面前闪亮的玻璃杯上，很奇怪的影子——以前，他很多次都注意到自己在罐子或锡杯的弯曲表面上投下的影子，跟现在一模一样——脸是鸡蛋形状，矮墩墩的，胡子乱七八糟，都快长到耳朵上了。在他对面，哑巴两只手捧着杯子。酒开始在杰克的血管里活跃起来，他觉得自己又走进了醉酒的万花筒里。由于激动，他的胡子猛烈地抖动起来。他把胳膊肘支在膝盖上，向前倾着身子，睁大眼睛紧紧盯着辛格，似乎在寻找着什么。

“我敢打赌，这个镇上只有我一个人觉得愤怒——我说的是真正的愤怒——整整十年，都是这样。不久之前，我差一点跟人动手打起来。有时候，我觉得自己好像是疯了。我不清楚。”辛格把酒推到客人眼前。杰克直接就着瓶子喝起来，然后用手摩挲着头顶。

“你瞧，我就像两个人。一个我是受过教育的人，我去过国内最大的几家图书馆。我读书，一直读书，读那些讲纯粹真理的书。在那边我的手提箱里，有卡尔·马克思、索尔斯坦·维布伦，还有像他们一样的作家们写的书。我反复读这些书，读得越多便越生气。我明白每一页纸上的每一个字。一开始，我喜欢那些话。辩证唯物主义——狡黠的搪塞——”杰克嘴里滚动着这些音节，带着一种钟爱的庄严——“目的论倾向。”

哑巴用一块折叠整齐的手帕擦了擦额头。

“但我想说的是这个：一个人知道，却又无法让别人明白，这时候他该怎么办？”

辛格伸手拿过杯子，倒满酒，稳稳放进杰克瘀青的手里。“一醉方休，嗯？”杰克说，胳膊一抖，几滴酒洒在白色裤子上。“但你听着！我们的目光所及之处，都是刻薄和腐败。这个房间，这瓶葡萄酒，篮子里的这些水果，都是利润和亏损的产品。一个人活着，就必须被动接受这种卑鄙。我们吃的每一口饭，穿的每一件衣服，背后都有一个人累得要死——但似乎并没有人知道，大家都瞎了，哑了，呆了——愚蠢，卑鄙。”

杰克握紧拳头压在太阳穴上。他的思绪已经横冲直撞，无法控制了。他想发狂，想跑出去，到拥挤的大街上找人好好打一架。

哑巴一直耐心而专注地望着他，一边拿出自己的银色铅笔，在一张纸上认真地写下：“你是民主党还是共和党？”写完，他把纸从桌对面递给杰克。杰克一把抓在手里。屋子又开始在他周围旋转起来，他连字都看不清楚了。

他盯着哑巴的脸，好让自己镇定下来。屋子里，似乎只有辛格的眼睛静止不动。那双眼睛变换着颜色，夹杂着琥珀色、灰色，还有一丝柔和的褐色。他久久地盯着那双眼睛，几乎快把自己催眠了。他没了狂躁的欲望，觉得重新平静下来。这双眼睛似乎能明白他想说的一切，而且也给他传递了信息。过了一会儿，屋子又不转了。

“你懂了。”他的声音含混不清，“你明白我的意思。”

远处的教堂传来柔和清脆的钟声。月光洒在隔壁的屋顶上，雪白一片，天空是一种温柔的夏季蓝。无须言语，两人心有灵犀：杰克找到住处之前，会在辛格这里住几天。酒喝完了，哑巴在床边的地上放了个垫子。杰克和衣而卧，立刻进入了梦乡。

5

镇上的一个黑人区，远离主街，本尼迪克特·马迪·科普兰医生独自坐在黑乎乎的厨房里。已经过了九点，现在周日的钟声也停了。尽管夜晚非常炎热，但圆肚子柴火炉里仍然生着一堆小小的火。科普兰医生坐在火炉旁边，在一张直背餐椅上前倾着身体，两只瘦长的手捧着脑袋。炉子缝隙中透出的红光照在他的脸上——在这种光线下，他厚厚的嘴唇在黑皮肤的映衬下，几乎变成了紫色。他的头发灰白，紧贴着头皮，像一顶羊毛帽子，也显出一种蓝色。他保持着这个姿势，一动不动坐了很久，即便一双眼睛也透过银色眼镜框直直地瞪着，目光依然凝固而忧郁。然后，他重重地清了清喉咙，从椅子旁边的地上拿起一本书。在他周围，房间里非常暗，他必须把书凑近火炉才能辨认出上面的字。今晚他看的是斯宾诺莎的书。那些错综复杂的思想和话语，他并不能完全理解，但在读的过程中，他感觉到那些话语背后有一种强烈而真实的使命感，他觉得自己基本上懂了。

夜晚，尖厉的门铃声经常会将他从沉寂中唤醒。他走到前厅，总会发现有骨折的病人，或者被剃刀划伤的病人。但今天晚上没有人打扰他。他在昏暗的厨房里独自坐了好几个小时，开始慢慢地左右摇晃起来，从喉咙里发出一种像唱歌一样的呻吟。他正发着这种声音，波西娅突然来了。

科普兰医生预先知道她要来。外面的大街上，他听到有人在吹口琴，吹的是一支布鲁斯歌曲，他知道那是儿子威廉吹的。他没有开灯，穿过走廊，打开了前门。他没有走到门廊去，而是站在昏暗的纱门后面。月光很亮，波西娅、威廉、海博埃的影子投在布满尘土的街道上，黑乎乎的，分外清晰。附近的房子看上去都很惨淡，科普兰医生家的房子跟附近其他的房子都不一样，它是用砖和灰泥建的，非常结实。小前院的周围围着一圈尖桩栅栏。波西娅在大门口跟丈夫和兄弟道了别，敲了敲纱门。

“你为什么这么在黑暗里坐着啊？”

他们一起穿过昏暗的走廊，回到厨房。

“你有豪华电灯，一直这么在黑暗里坐着，好像不正常。”

科普兰医生扭了一下桌子上方吊着的灯泡，房间一下子变得明亮起来。“黑暗比较适合我。”他说。

这间屋子很干净，空荡荡的。餐桌的一头放着几本书和一个墨水台——另一头有一把叉子、一个勺子，还有一个盘子。科普兰医生坐得笔直，两条大长腿叠放着。一开始，波西娅也僵硬地坐在那里。父女二人长得很像——两人的鼻子都宽而扁平，嘴巴和额头像一个模子里刻出来的。但跟父亲相比，波西娅的肤色很浅。

“这里简直烤得慌。”她说，“我觉得除了做饭，你就不要生火了。”

“如果你愿意，我们可以去我的办公室。”科普兰医生说。

“我觉得还可以，不用去办公室了。”

科普兰医生调整了下银边眼镜，然后把两只手叠放在大腿上。“上次分开以后，你过得怎么样？你和你丈夫——还有你兄弟？”

波西娅放松下来，把脚从帆布鞋里抽出来。“我和海博埃、威利过得很好。”

“威廉还住在你们那里？”

“当然了。”波西娅说，“你瞧——我们有自己的生活方式，有自己的计划。海博埃——他付房租，我的钱用来买吃的，威利——他负责我们的教堂税、保险和房屋税，还有周六晚上的活动。我们仨有自己的计划，每个人都在尽一份力。”

科普兰医生坐在那里，低着头，拽着自己修长的手指，直到把所有关节都拽得咔咔作响。干净的袖口垂下来盖住了他的手腕——下面是瘦削的双手，颜色好像比身上其他部位浅一些，手掌是浅黄色的。他的双手看上去干净整洁，但很干瘪，好像是用刷子刷过而且在一盆水里泡了好久似的。

“瞧，我差点忘了带来的东西。”波西娅说，“你吃过晚饭了吗？”

科普兰医生说话时总是一丝不苟，每个音节似乎都是从他阴郁厚重的嘴唇里挤出来的一样。“没有，我没吃。”

波西娅打开刚才放到餐桌上的那个纸袋子。“我带了好吃的羽衣甘蓝菜，觉得我们可以一起吃晚饭。我还带了一片咸肉。这些蔬菜得用咸肉来调味。用肉来炒羽衣甘蓝，你不会介意吧？”

“没关系。”

“你还是不吃肉吗？”

“不吃。纯粹是个人原因，我是个素食主义者，但如果你用肉来炒甘蓝菜，也没关系。”

波西娅没穿鞋，站在桌前仔细地择着菜。“这个地板踩起来真舒服。我不穿那双又紧又磨脚的帆布鞋，就这么到处走动，你不会介意吧？”

“不会。”科普兰医生说，“没关系。”

“那么——我们就吃这些美味的甘蓝菜，加玉米饼和咖啡。还有，我要从这上面切下几片肉，煎了自己吃。”

科普兰医生的眼睛一直追随着波西娅。她穿着袜子慢慢地来回走动着，从墙上取下擦洗干净的锅，添了添火，又洗掉甘蓝菜上的沙土。他张了张嘴，想说话，却又把嘴闭上了。

“那么，你和你丈夫还有兄弟有自己的合作计划。”他终于说道。

“是的。”

科普兰医生使劲拉动手指，又想把关节掰响。“你们计划要孩子了吗？”

波西娅没有看父亲，她把甘蓝菜盆里的水倒掉，有些生气。“有些事情，”她说，“我觉得完全要看上帝的意思。”

他们没有再说话。波西娅把晚饭放在炉子上煮着，默默坐在那里，修长的双手无力地垂在膝盖上。科普兰医生的脑袋垂在胸前，好像睡着了一样。然而，他并没有睡着，他的脸上不时传过一阵紧张的震颤，然后他会深呼吸，调整自己的脸部。沉闷的房间里开始飘散晚饭的味道。在一片沉寂中，橱柜上面的钟表走动的声音很大，因为他们刚刚谈过的话题，所以，钟表单调的嘀嗒声像是一遍遍地在重复一个词：“孩子，孩子。”

他总会碰上他们当中的一个——光着屁股在地上爬，或者忙着玩弹珠游戏，或者在昏暗的大街上搂着一个女孩。这些男孩的名字都叫本尼迪克特·科普兰。但对于女孩们，则取了一些这样的名字：班尼·梅，或者马迪本，或者本尼迪恩·马迪恩。有一天，他数了数，有十多个孩子都是以他命名的。

然而，他这一辈子，一直在告知、解释、劝说。你不能这样做，他经常说。他会告诉他们，为什么不能要这第六个或第五个或第九个孩子，有充足的理由。我们需要的不是更多的孩子，而是要给已经出生的孩子们更多的机会。黑人的优生优育是他一直劝说他们的内容。他会用简单的语言告诉他们，总是用同样的方式。随着一年年过去，这些话已经变成了某种愤怒的诗歌，他早已烂熟于心。

对于任何一种新理论的发展，他都有研究，都了解。而且他经常自掏腰包，买了工具分发给病人。迄今为止，他是镇上第一个想到这些事情的医生。他会给予、解释、给予、告知。然而，即便如此，他也许每周还要接生四十次。马迪本或是班尼·梅。

这还只是其中一点。只是一点。

他这一辈子，一直知道，自己之所以做这个工作是有缘由的。他一直知道，他生来就是要教诲他的同胞。他整天背着包，挨家挨户地去跟他们讲各种各样的事情。

漫长的一天结束后，他会感到一种沉重的疲惫。但到了晚上，当他打开前门时，他的疲惫便会无影无踪。家里有汉密尔顿、卡尔·马克思、波西娅，有小威廉，还有黛西。

波西娅拿起炉子上平底锅的盖子，用叉子搅了搅甘蓝菜。“父亲——”过了一会儿，她说。

科普兰医生清清嗓子，朝手绢里吐了一口痰。他的声音痛苦而沙哑。“什么事？”

“我们不要再吵了好吗？”

“我们没有吵啊。”科普兰医生说。

“吵架并不需要语言。”波西娅说，“我觉得，就算我们这样坐在这里，一句话不说，似乎也总是在争吵。我就是有这种感觉。跟你说实话——每次来看你，几乎都让我筋疲力尽。所以，无论如何，我们都不要再吵了。”

“我当然也不希望吵架。如果你有这种感觉，我很抱歉，女儿。”

她倒了咖啡，把一杯没加糖的递给父亲，自己的那杯咖啡她加了好几勺糖。“我饿了，这个喝起来味道会很好。你喝着咖啡，我给你说说前一阵子我们发生过的一件事。现在一切都过去了，想想似乎有点可笑，但当时我们完全笑不出来。”

“说吧。”科普兰医生说。

“嗯——前一阵子，镇上来了一个长相英俊、穿着体面的黑人男子。他管自己叫B.F.梅森先生，他说是从华盛顿特区来的。他每天拄着拐杖，穿着漂亮的花衬衫，在街上走来走去。到了晚上，他会去“社会咖啡馆”，吃得比镇上所有人都讲究。每天晚上，他都给自己点一瓶杜松子酒、两块猪排当晚餐。他对每个人都笑容可掬，对身边所有女孩都鞠躬致敬，进来出去时会为你拉门。也就一个星期的时间，他无论去哪里，都成为受欢迎的人。人们开始对这位富足的B.F.梅森先生充满好奇和猜测。很快，他混熟了之后，开始着手干正事了。”

波西娅噘起嘴唇，吹吹她的咖啡。“我猜，你肯定在报纸上看到过政府给老年人发养老费的事？”

科普兰医生点点头。“养老金。”他说。

“嗯——他就是跟这件事有关系。他是政府派来的，他在华盛顿特区受总统之托，到这里来让大家都加入政府的养老费计划。他挨家挨户地跟人们解释，你交一块钱定金加入这个计划，然后每周交两毛五分钱——等你到四十五岁时，政府会每个月发给你五十块钱，一直付到你死的时候。我认识的所有人听到这个都非常兴奋。每个加入的人，他都免费给一张总统的照片，下面还有总统的签名。他跟人们说，六个月以后，每人都能得到一套免费制服。这个俱乐部名字叫‘黑人养老费领取者大联盟’——两个月后，每人都会得到一条橘色绶带，上面印着G.L.P.C.P.，代表俱乐部的名字。你瞧，跟其他政府部门一样，都用这种字母缩写。他拿着这个小本本走街串巷，人们开始纷纷加入。他记下他们的名字，收了钱。每个星期六，他都去收钱。不到三个星期，这个B.F.梅森先生让很多人都加入了这个俱乐部。星期六，他都转不过来了，他不得不花钱找人替他收费，每人负责三四个街区。每个星期六一大早，我也在家附近替他收那两毛五分钱的费用。当然，威利一开始就为他、海博埃和我交钱加入了俱乐部。”

“在你家附近的很多家庭里，我都见过总统的照片，记得有人提到过梅森的名字。”科普兰医生说，“他是个小偷？”

“是的。”波西娅说，“有人开始调查这个B.F.梅森先生，然后他被逮起来了。他们发现，他就是从亚特兰大来的，连华盛顿特区和总统的影子都没有见过。他敛到的钱全都藏了起来，或者花掉了。威利白白扔掉了七块五毛钱。”

科普兰医生激动起来。“我就是这个意思——”

“下辈子，”波西娅说，“那个人肯定也没有好下场。但现在，一切都过去了，似乎有点好笑，但当然了，我们完全笑不出来。”

“每个周五晚上，黑人这个种族都会自愿爬上十字架。”科普兰医生说。

波西娅的手一晃，手里的咖啡沿着杯碟流了出来，她舔着胳膊上的咖啡。“你这话是什么意思？”

“我的意思是，我总是在寻找。我的意思是，如果我能找到十个黑人——十个我的同胞——有脊梁、有脑子、有勇气的黑人，他们愿意倾尽所有——”

波西娅放下咖啡。“我们不要讨论这样的问题。”

“只要有四个黑人，”科普兰医生说，“只要汉密尔顿、卡尔·马克思、威廉，还有你，只要你们四个黑人，真正具有这些素质和骨气——”

“威利、海博埃和我都很有骨气。”波西娅生气地说，“这是个艰难的世道，我觉得我们三个人一直奋斗得很好。”

他们沉默了一会儿。科普兰医生把眼镜放到桌上，用干瘪的手指按住眼睛。“你总是用这词——黑人，”波西娅说，“这个词会伤害人们的感情。即便原来用的‘黑鬼’也比这个强，但有礼貌的人们——无论什么肤色——总是说‘有色人种’。”

科普兰医生没有回答。

“拿我和威利来说吧。我们并不完全是有色人种。我们的妈妈肤色很浅，我俩身上有很多白人血统。而海博埃——他是印第安人，身上有很大一部分印第安血统。我们都不是纯粹的有色人种，你一直用的这个词会伤害到人们的感情。”

“我对这些托词没兴趣。”科普兰医生说，“我只对真正的真相感兴趣。”

“嗯，这就是真相。大家都害怕你。汉密尔顿、巴迪、威利，还有我的海博埃，他们得喝很多杜松子酒才敢到这儿来，像我一样跟你坐坐。威利说，他还是个孩子的时候便记得你这副模样，而且那时候就开始害怕自己的父亲了。”

科普兰医生大声地咳嗽一声，清了清嗓子。

“每个人都有感情——不管是谁——如果在家里，一个人的感情必定会受到伤害，那便没人愿意到这个家里来。你也一样。我见过你的感情被白人伤害过很多次，他们都不懂这个道理。”

“没有，”科普兰医生说，“你没见过我的感情受到伤害。”

“当然，我知道，我和威利，还有海博埃——我们都不是文化人，但海博埃和威利都有一颗金子般的心。他们和你不一样。”

“对。”科普兰医生说。

“我和汉密尔顿、巴迪，还有威利——我们都不喜欢像你一样说话。我们说话像妈妈，或者她的家人，或者她的祖辈们。你用脑子思考一切，而我们更愿意用心说话，说那些在心中埋藏了很久的话，这就是一个差别。”

“是的。”科普兰医生说。

“人们不能抓起自己的孩子，把他们按照自己的想法变成自己想要的样子，不管这样做会不会伤害他们，也不管这样做是对还是错。你想尽办法，拼命要这样做。现在，只剩我一个人还愿意走进这个家里来，和你这样坐一坐。”

灯光照进科普兰医生的眼睛里，特别明亮，她的声音很大，很强硬。他咳嗽一下，整张脸都颤抖起来。他想端起那杯凉了的咖啡，手却怎么都端不稳。眼泪涌上他的眼眶，他伸手去拿眼镜，想要掩饰一下。

波西娅看见了，赶紧起身走到他跟前。她双手抱住他的头，用面颊去贴他的前额。“我伤害了父亲的感情。”她柔声说道。

他的声音很硬。“没有，老是说什么伤害感情，这很蠢，很幼稚。”

眼泪慢慢滚下他的两颊，在火光的映射下，呈现出蓝、绿、红的颜色。“真的非常抱歉。”波西娅说。

科普兰医生用棉布手绢擦着眼泪。“没关系。”

“我们不要再吵了。我真的受不了我们之间的这种争吵。我觉得，每次在一起，我们之间似乎都会发生真的很不好的事情。我们不要再这么吵了。”

“好，”科普兰医生说，“我们不要吵了。”

波西娅抽抽鼻子，用手背抹了一下鼻子。有几分钟的时间，她站在那里，抱着父亲的头。过了一会儿，她最后擦了一下脸，走到炉子上盛着甘蓝的锅跟前。

“这些菜应该煮得很嫩了。”她欢快地说，“现在，我要做点好吃的小玉米饼，好搭配着吃。”

波西娅穿着袜子，在厨房里慢慢来回忙碌着，她父亲的目光一直追随着她。有一阵子，他们又陷入了沉默。

他的眼里还有泪花，看东西轮廓都是模糊的。波西娅真的很像她妈妈。多年以前，黛西就是这样在厨房里走来走去，默默地忙碌着。黛西的肤色不像他这么黑——她的皮肤就像深色蜂蜜的颜色那么美。她总是很安静，很温柔，但在那种柔软的温和背后，她身上还有一种倔强。无论他多么认真地去研究，始终也无法理解妻子身上这种温柔的倔强。

他会劝告她，告诉她自己所有的想法，但她总是很温柔，却总是不肯听她的话，依旧我行我素。

后来，有了汉密尔顿、卡尔·马克思、威廉和波西娅。他对他们产生的这种真切的使命感如此强烈，他清楚地知道他们应该成为什么样的人。汉密尔顿要成为一名伟大的科学家；卡尔·马克思要成为一名黑人教师；威廉要成为一名律师，为正义而战；而波西娅要成为一名医生，专门为妇女儿童治病。

他们还是婴儿时，他就跟他们讲将来要从肩头卸下的枷锁——顺从和懒惰的枷锁。等他们长大一点，他再三跟他们强调，世上没有上帝，但他们的生命是神圣的，每个人都有真正的使命。他会一遍遍地跟他们说这些，他们挤在一起，坐得离他远远的，瞪着大大的黑人孩子的眼睛，望着他们的母亲。而黛西坐在那里，根本不听他说话，一如既往地温柔，却又倔强。

因为汉密尔顿、卡尔·马克思、威廉和波西娅都有各自真正的使命，所以，他知道每一个细节都应该如何去做。每年秋天，他总是把他们都带到镇上去，给他们买漂亮的黑鞋子、黑袜子。他给波西娅买黑羊毛衣料做裙子，白色亚麻布做领子和袖口；给男孩们买黑羊毛衣料做裤子，上好的白色亚麻布做衬衫。他不让他们穿颜色鲜亮的劣质衣服，但他们上学时，恰恰希望穿这样的衣服。黛西说，他们都觉得很难堪，说他是个强硬的父亲。他知道这个家应该是什么样子。家里不能有花哨的东西——不要俗气的日历、蕾丝枕头，不要小摆设——家里每一样东西都应该是朴素的、深色的，都应该象征工作和真正的使命感。

一天晚上，他发现黛西给小波西娅扎了耳朵眼儿要戴耳环。还有一次，他回家后发现壁炉台上有个穿着羽毛裙的丘比特娃娃，黛西温柔却强硬，不肯把娃娃扔掉。他还知道，黛西在教孩子们要温顺。她给孩子们讲地狱和天堂，还让他们相信有鬼魂，有闹鬼的地方。黛西每周六都去教堂，会很伤心地跟牧师讲她丈夫的事情。她每次都倔强地带着孩子们一起去教堂，孩子们对她言听计从。

整个黑人种族都病了，他整天忙碌，有时要忙到半夜。漫长的一天结束后，他身心疲惫，但他推开家里的前门时，这种疲惫会一扫而空。然而，等他真的走进屋门，往往会发现，威廉在梳子上包了卫生纸，正在用梳子弹奏音乐，汉密尔顿和卡尔·马克思正在掷骰子赌午饭钱，而波西娅正在跟妈妈一起笑。

他会带着他们重新来一次，却换了别的方式。他总是拿出他们的功课，跟他们谈话，而他们则会紧紧靠在一起，坐在那里，眼睛望着母亲。他会说啊说啊，但他们根本不想听。

他的心头涌上一种沮丧、可怕的黑人式的感觉。他会到办公室里，尽量坐在那里，看报，思考，直到平静下来，然后重新开始。他拉下房间的百叶窗，这样只剩下明亮的灯光、书，还有思考的感觉。但有些时候，他久久不能平静。他还年轻，单靠学习无法赶走那种可怕的感觉。

汉密尔顿、卡尔·马克思、威廉、波西娅都很怕他，他们会望着自己的母亲——有时候，当他意识到这一点时，那种沮丧的感觉会让他难以承受，不清楚自己到底做了什么。

他无法阻止那种可怕的感觉，过后自己又完全无法理解。

“我觉得这顿晚饭肯定味道鲜美。”波西娅说，“我想，我们现在就开始吃吧，海博埃和威利随时都可能进来。”

科普兰医生放好眼镜，把椅子朝前拖了拖。“今晚你丈夫和威廉去哪儿玩了？”

“他们扔马蹄铁去了。那个雷蒙德·琼斯在后院有个扔马蹄铁的地方，雷蒙德和他妹妹拉芙·琼斯每天晚上都玩。拉芙这姑娘很丑，海博埃和威廉想到她家玩，随时都可以去，我不介意。但他们说，九点四十五会来接我，现在他们随时都可能会来。”

“趁我还记得，”科普兰医生说，“我想，你经常能收到汉密尔顿和卡尔·马克思的信吧。”

“我的确经常收到汉密尔顿的信，实际上，他接管了外公家所有的活儿。但巴迪，他去了莫比尔——你知道，他不大喜欢写信。但巴迪容易跟人相处，我并不担心他，他这样的人总会混得很好。”

他们默默地坐在桌前，吃着晚饭。波西娅不断抬头看壁橱上的表，海博埃和威利该来了。科普兰医生只是低头吃饭，他手里拿着叉子，好像这叉子很沉，他的手指都哆嗦了。眼前的食物，他只是尝了尝，每一口都难以下咽。空气中有种紧张的感觉，他们俩好像都努力要想出些话来说。

科普兰医生不知道如何开口。有时候，他觉得以前跟孩子们说得太多了，他们几乎都听不懂，所以现在也就无话可说了。过了一会儿，他用手帕擦擦嘴，开口了，声音有些迟疑。

“你几乎没提你自己。跟我说说你的工作，还有最近你在做什么。”

“我当然还是在凯利家干活儿。”波西娅说，“但听我说，父亲，我不知道还能在他们家干多久。这份工作很难做，总是得花很长时间才能做完。但这个我倒不担心，我担心的是工资。我应该每周拿三块钱——但有时候，凯利夫人总会少发给我五毛钱，或者一块钱。当然，她总是会尽快补上，但这总让我手头比较紧。”

“这样不对。”科普兰医生说，“你为什么要忍着啊？”

“这也不是她的错，她实在没办法。”波西娅说，“家里有一半房客不付房租，要想维持日常生活，又需要大笔开支。跟你说实话——凯利家离摊上官司不远了，他们的日子过得很艰难。”

“你可以找点别的工作。”

“我知道。但凯利一家真的是特别好的白人雇主，我真的非常喜欢他们。那三个小孩就像我自己的家人，我感觉巴伯还有那个小婴儿都像是我养大的。尽管我和米克在一起总是有这样那样的争吵，但我对她也真有一种亲密感。”

“但你得为自己考虑考虑。”科普兰医生说。

“米克现在——”波西娅说，“她真是个问题，没人知道该怎么管教这个孩子，她又自负又任性，一天到晚脑子里也不知道在想什么。对这个孩子，我有一种很好笑的感觉。我觉得她好像总有一天要搞出个大意外，但到底是好意外还是坏意外，我不知道。有时候，米克让我很困惑，但我仍然很喜欢她。”

“你得先解决自己的生计问题才行。”

“我刚才说了，这不是凯利太太的错，维护那么大一幢老房子要花很多钱，房租又收不上来。房客里，只有一个人付得起一笔可观的房租，这个人总是按时付，从来没有拖欠过。他才刚刚来这里住了一阵子，是个聋哑人，是我近距离见过的第一个聋哑人——但他是个非常好的白人。”

“又高又瘦，眼睛是灰绿色的？”科普兰医生突然问道，“而且对所有人都非常礼貌，穿得非常得体？不像镇上的当地人——更像北方人，或者也许是个犹太人？”

“就是他。”波西娅说。

科普兰医生的脸上现出一丝急切的神情。他把玉米饼掰碎，放进盘子里的甘蓝菜汤里，开始吃起来，恢复了胃口。“我有一个聋哑人病人。”他说。

“你怎么认识辛格先生的？”波西娅问。

科普兰医生咳了一下，用手绢捂住嘴巴。“我只是见过他几次。”

“我最好收拾下这里。”波西娅说，“威利和我的海博埃肯定要来了。但这里有这么好的洗碗池和自来水，我一眨眼工夫就可以把这些小盘子洗好了。”

多年以来，他一直想从脑子里摆脱掉白人那种无言的傲慢无礼这件事。那种愤懑涌上来的时候，他会跑去思考或学习。走在大街上，在白人面前，他总会在脸上保持尊严，一直沉默着。年轻时，他是“孩子”——但现在，他是“大叔”。“大叔，跑到街角那个加油站，给我找个机修工来。”不久之前，一个开车的白人男子从车里大声对他喊道。“孩子，帮我干这个。”——“大叔，干那个。”他根本不听，只自顾继续走路，一言不发，心里涌上一种尊严感。

几天前的一个晚上，一个白人酒鬼走到他跟前，开始拽着他在街上走。他背着包，以为肯定有人受伤了。但这个酒鬼把他拖进了一家白人餐馆，柜台前的白人男子们开始傲慢地大喊大叫起来。他知道这个酒鬼在耍弄他，即便那个时候，他也没有丢掉自己的尊严。

但他和这个又高又瘦、长着灰绿色眼睛的白人男子发生过一次交集，这是以前跟任何白人都没有过的事情。

这件事发生在几周前一个漆黑的雨夜。他刚看完一个产妇的病例，冒雨站在街角。他想点根烟，但接连划了好几根火柴，却都熄灭了。他站在那里，嘴里叼着没点火的烟，就在这时一个白人走上前来，举着一根点着的火柴给他。在夜色中，两人借着火苗看清了彼此的面容。白人冲他笑笑，给他点上了烟。他不知道该说什么，因为以前从来没碰上过这种事情。

他俩一起在街角站了几分钟，然后白人递给他一张名片。他想跟白人说话，问他几个问题，但他不敢肯定对方是否能够真正听懂。因为白人种族一贯傲慢无礼，所以他很害怕因主动示好而丧失掉自己的尊严。

但是，这个白人给他点烟，冲他微笑，而且似乎想跟他一起相处。从那之后，他把这件事情仔细琢磨了很多遍。

“我有个聋哑病人，”科普兰医生对波西娅说，“是个五岁的小男孩。不知为什么，我总觉得自己要为他的残疾负责任。我给他接的生，后来又回访过两次，之后自然就把他忘了。他后来耳朵有了毛病，但他母亲没有留意他耳朵里流出来的分泌物，也没把他带来看病。等我最后注意到的时候，已经太晚了。当然，他什么都听不见了，后来自然也不会说话。但我曾经仔细观察过他，我觉得如果他身体没有残疾的话，很有可能是个非常聪明的孩子。”

“你总是对孩子特别感兴趣。”波西娅说，“你对孩子比对大人还关心，对吗？”

“孩子身上总是有更多希望。”科普兰医生说，“但这个失聪的男孩——我一直想打听，看是不是有什么机构可以接收他。”

“辛格先生可以告诉你。他真的是个善良的白人，一点都不傲慢。”

“我不知道——”科普兰医生说，“有一两次，我曾想过给他写个便条，看看他能否给我点信息。”

“如果我是你，肯定会写的。你特别会写信，我会帮你转交给辛格先生。”波西娅说，“两三个星期之前，他下楼到厨房来找我，拿了几件衬衫，想让我替他洗洗。那些衬衫非常干净，就像施洗者圣约翰自己穿的一样。我只需要把他们浸到温水里，稍微刷刷领子，然后烫平整就可以了。但那天晚上，我把五件干净衬衫送到楼上他房间的时候，你知道他给了我多少钱吗？”

“不知道。”

“他像往常一样满脸笑容，然后给了我一块钱。就那么几件衬衫，给了我整整一块钱。他真是个特别善良、特别好的白人，有任何问题，我都敢去问他。我甚至都想自己给这个善良的白人写封信。如果你想写的话，爸爸，赶紧去写吧。”

“也许我会写的。”科普兰医生说。

波西娅突然坐起身，开始收拾自己浓密油亮的头发。微弱的口琴声传过来，慢慢地声音越来越大。“威利和海博埃来了。”波西娅说，“现在，我得出去找他们了。你自己照顾好自己，如果需要我做什么，给我捎个信儿。我今天非常高兴跟你一起吃晚饭，一起聊天。”

这会儿，口琴声已经非常清晰了。他们能听出来，威利是一边在前门等着，一边吹口琴。

“等会儿。”科普兰医生说，“你丈夫跟你在一块儿的时候，我只见过两次，我觉得我们俩还没有正式认识过，威廉也已经三年没来看他父亲了。为什么不让他们进来坐一会儿呢？”

波西娅站在门口，摸着头发和耳环。

“威利上次来这里的时候，你伤害了他的感情。你知道，你就是不理解怎么——”

“好吧。”科普兰医生说，“我只提个建议。”

“等等。”波西娅说，“我去叫他们，我现在就去邀请他俩进来。”

科普兰医生点上一根烟，在房间里来回地踱步。他的眼镜怎么都扶不正，手指一直在哆嗦。前院传来低低的说话声，接着走廊里响起沉重的脚步声，波西娅、威廉和海博埃走进了厨房。

“我们来了。”波西娅说，“海博埃，我觉得你和我父亲还没有正式认识过，但你们彼此都知道对方是谁。”

科普兰医生跟两人握了握手。威利腼腆地向后靠在墙上，但海博埃上前一步，非常正式地鞠了一躬。“我经常听说很多关于您的事情。”他说，“很高兴认识您。”

波西娅和科普兰医生从走廊里搬来椅子，四个人围坐在火炉旁。他们一言不发，都不自在。威利紧张地盯着屋子四周——盯着厨房餐桌上的书、水槽、墙边的小床，还有他父亲。海博埃咧嘴笑着，拽着他的领带。科普兰医生似乎要说话，但舔舔嘴唇，又沉默了。

“威利，你口琴吹得很不错了。”终于，波西娅说话了，“我看，你和海博埃一定是掉到什么人的杜松子酒瓶里去了。”

“没有，夫人。”海博埃非常礼貌地说，“自从星期六以来，我俩什么酒都没喝过。我们俩玩马蹄铁游戏去了。”

科普兰医生仍然沉默着，他们都不断地瞥他一眼，等待着。屋子很小，这种沉默让所有人都很紧张。

“这俩小伙子的衣服洗起来真的让我很费劲。”波西娅说，“我每个星期六都要洗他们的白西装，每周还要熨烫两次。现在，看看他俩。当然，除了下班休息的时候，他们其他时间也不穿白西装。但只穿两天，白西装就会变成黑的。我昨晚刚给他俩熨烫了裤子，看现在，一点褶痕都没了。”

科普兰医生依然一言不发，他的目光停留在儿子脸上。威利注意到时，咬着自己粗糙迟钝的手指头，只顾盯着自己的脚面。科普兰医生感觉到手腕和太阳穴的脉搏怦怦直跳。他咳嗽起来，握紧一只拳头放到胸口。他想跟儿子说话，却想不出该说什么。那种熟悉的心酸痛苦又涌上心头，他没有时间认真思考和强压下去。他的脉搏怦怦直跳，他很困惑。但他们都望着他，这种沉默太压抑了，他必须开口说话。

他的声音很高，听上去好像不是他发出来的。“威廉，不知道小时候我跟你说过的那些话，你还记得多少。”

“我不明白你的意——意——意思。”威利说。

科普兰医生还没弄清楚自己说的什么，那些话便脱口而出。“我的意思是，我对你、汉密尔顿、卡尔·马克思付出了我的全部，我把所有的信任和希望都寄托在你们身上，而我得到的只有误解、懒散和冷漠。我为你们付出了那么多，却什么都没得到。我一无所有。我曾经努力要做的一切——”

“嘘，”波西娅说，“爸爸，你跟我保证过，我们不会再吵了。这简直是疯了，我们再也经不起吵架了。”

波西娅站起身，朝前门走去，威利和海博埃立刻跟了上去。最后，科普兰医生也走了过来。

他们摸黑站在前门口。科普兰医生想要说话，但声音似乎埋在了心底的什么地方，发不出来。威利、波西娅和海博埃紧紧站在一起。

波西娅朝丈夫和兄弟伸出一只手，又朝科普兰医生伸出另一只手。“离开前，我们和解吧。我们在这里争吵，真让我受不了。我们再也经不起争吵了。”

科普兰医生默默地又跟他俩分别握手。“很抱歉。”他说。

“我没关系。”海博埃礼貌地说道。

“我也没关系。”威利含糊地说。

波西娅把他们的手都拉到一起。“我们再也经不起争吵了。”

他们道了别，科普兰医生站在漆黑的门廊上，望着他们一起沿着大街走远了。

他们远去时，脚步发出孤独的声音，让他觉得虚弱而又疲惫。等他们走出一个街区，威廉又开始吹起了口琴。音乐声既悲伤又空虚。他待在门廊里，直到再也看不见他们，听不见他们的声音。

科普兰医生关掉家里的电灯，在黑暗中坐在火炉前，但他无法平静下来。他想要把汉密尔顿、卡尔·马克思和威廉都从脑子里赶出去。波西娅跟他说过的每一个字又重新回荡在他的脑海中，声音很大，很强硬。他突然站起身来，打开灯，走到桌前坐下，拿过斯宾诺莎、威廉·莎士比亚和卡尔·马克思的书。他大声读着斯宾诺莎的书，那些词发出一种丰富、黑暗的声音。

他想起刚才谈到的那个白人。如果那个白人能够帮帮那个失聪的病人奥古斯塔斯·本尼迪克特·马迪·路易斯，那该多好。即便没有这个理由，没有这些问题问他，给这个白人写封信也是好事。科普兰医生双手捧着头，喉咙里发出一种奇怪的声音，像一首呻吟的歌。他想起那个雨夜，想起那个白人在昏黄的火柴光焰后面微笑着的面容——他平静下来。

6

到了仲夏，辛格的客人比别的房客都多。晚上，他的房间里几乎总会传出说话声。在纽约咖啡馆吃过晚饭之后，他洗完澡，穿上一套清凉的浴衣，照常不再出门。房间里凉爽宜人。他壁橱里有个冰柜，里面放着冰啤酒和水果饮料。他从来不手忙脚乱，也不匆匆忙忙，总是站在门口，带着好客的笑容迎接他的客人。

米克喜欢上楼到辛格先生的房间去。尽管他是个聋哑人，却能听懂她说的每一个字。跟他聊天就像做游戏，但比做游戏有意思得多，就像发现了新的音乐知识一样。她不愿跟任何人说的一些计划，却愿意跟辛格先生说。他任她摆弄那些可爱的象棋小人儿。有一次，她很兴奋，衬衫下摆卷进了电风扇，他表现得那么和善，没让她感觉到一丁点尴尬。除了她爸爸，辛格是她认识的最可亲的男人。

科普兰医生给约翰·辛格写信，说了奥古斯塔斯·本尼迪克特·马迪·路易斯的事情，之后收到了一个礼貌的回复，并邀请他有机会前去做客。科普兰医生到了辛格所在的房子，先走到后面，跟波西娅在厨房里坐了一会儿，然后上楼到那个白人的房间去。的确，这个白人身上没有那种无言的傲慢。他们一起喝柠檬汽水，哑巴把他想知道的那些问题的答案一一写了下来。这个人跟科普兰医生见过的任何白人都不一样。过后，他琢磨了这个白人好长时间。后来，由于对方的热诚邀请，他又去拜访了一次。

杰克·布朗特每个星期都来。他上楼去辛格的房间时，整个楼梯都在颤动。通常，他会带来一纸袋子啤酒。房间里经常会传出他高亢而又愤怒的声音，但离开之前，他的声音往往会渐渐平息下来。下楼时，他手里便没有了那袋子啤酒，他若有所思地走出去，似乎并不在意方向。

有天晚上，就连比夫·布兰农都来到了哑巴的房间，但他不能长时间离开餐馆，因此，半个小时以后他便走了。

辛格总是对所有人都一视同仁。他坐在窗前的直背椅上，双手插进口袋，点着头或微笑着，让客人知道他听得懂。

如果晚上没有客人，辛格会去看场晚场电影，他喜欢坐在那里看着大屏幕上的那些演员说话，看着他们走来走去。看电影之前，他从来不去看电影名字，而且不管放什么电影，他都看得津津有味，极其认真。

后来，七月份的一天，辛格突然不辞而别。他把房间的门敞开着，桌上留了一封信，是写给凯利太太的，里面放了四块钱，用来付上周的房租。他把几件简单的物品都带走了，房间里干干净净，空无一物。他的客人们来到这里，看见空荡荡的房间，又吃惊又难过，都转身离去了。没有人知道他为什么要这样离开。

整个暑假，辛格都待在安东纳普勒斯所在的小镇上。好友住在这个镇上的精神病院里。为了这次行程，他准备了好几个月，想象着他们见面后的每一个细节。他提前两周预订了旅馆，把火车票放进信封里，然后一直把信封放在口袋里，放了很久。

安东纳普勒斯一点都没变。辛格走进他的房间时，他平静地慢步走过来，迎接他的朋友。他比以前胖了，但脸上那种恍惚的笑容还是老样子。辛格抱着几个包裹，大块头希腊人第一眼注意到的便是这些包裹。他的礼物是一件猩红色晨衣、柔软的卧室拖鞋，还有两件印有姓名字母的长睡衣。安东纳普勒斯仔细地查看着盒子里的包装纸的底下，看到底下并没有藏着什么好吃的，便不屑一顾地把这些礼物扔到床上，再也不看一眼。

房间很大，阳光充足，几张床摆成一排，中间留有空隙。三个老人在角落里玩排杰克的纸牌游戏，他们并没有注意辛格或安东纳普勒斯。这两位朋友单独坐在房间的另一头。

辛格觉得他们好像很多年都没见了似的，他有那么多话要说，两只手比画的速度都跟不上了，一双绿眼睛里燃烧着激情，额头上闪着汗珠。那种熟悉的快乐和幸福感再次迅速涌遍全身，他几乎无法自持。

安东纳普勒斯那双漆黑油亮的眼睛盯着好友，一刻都没有挪开，两只手无精打采地摩挲着裆部。辛格首先跟他讲了那些经常来看自己的客人。他告诉好友，这些客人分散了他的注意力，使他感觉不那么孤独。他告诉安东纳普勒斯，他们都很奇怪，经常在说话——但他喜欢让他们去做客。他画了杰克·布朗特、米克和科普兰医生的速写肖像，看到安东纳普勒斯并不感兴趣，便立刻把草图揉成一团，扔到一边。看护走进来对他们说时间到了，这时辛格的话连一半还没说完，但他还是离开了房间，虽然很累，却很幸福。

只有星期四和星期天病人们才可以会客。不能去见安东纳普勒斯的时候，辛格总是在旅馆房间里来回踱步。

他第二次去见好友时，情形跟第一次一样，只有一点区别：房间里的那几个老人没有玩纸牌，全都无精打采地望着他俩。

辛格费了很大力气，才终于得到允许，可以带安东纳普勒斯出去待几个小时。他预先为这次小小的短途旅行安排好了每个细节。他们乘出租车到了乡下。四点半，他们回到旅馆的餐厅。安东纳普勒斯非常喜欢这次加餐。他把菜谱上一半的菜都点了个遍，吃得狼吞虎咽。但吃完以后，他却不肯离开，紧紧抓住桌子不放。辛格连哄带骗，出租车司机则想动用武力。安东纳普勒斯呆呆地坐在那里，他们一靠近，他就做出一些下流的手势。最后，辛格从旅馆经理那里买了一瓶威士忌，总算把他又引回出租车上。辛格把没开封的那瓶酒扔出窗外的时候，安东纳普勒斯失望地大哭起来，而且非常生气。这次短途旅行的结局让辛格很伤心。

下一次探望便是最后一次了，因为他两个星期的假期马上就要结束了。安东纳普勒斯全然忘记了之前发生的事情。他们同样坐在房间的那个角落里，时间飞快地流逝着。辛格用两只手拼命说话，狭长的脸很苍白。终于，到了他该离开的时间。他抓住好友的胳膊，望着他的脸，就像以前他们每天上班前分别的时候一样。安东纳普勒斯昏昏欲睡地盯着他，一动不动。辛格双手紧紧插在口袋里，走出了房间。

辛格回到租住公寓的房间后不久，米克、杰克·布朗特和科普兰医生便又开始来拜访了。他们都想知道他去了哪里，为什么他不让他们知道他的计划。但辛格假装听不懂他们的问题，他的笑容高深莫测。

他们一个接一个地来到辛格的房间，陪他度过夜晚时光。哑巴总是一副若有所思、镇定自若的样子。他那双色彩丰富的眼睛很温柔，却又很严肃，像一双巫师的眼睛。米克·凯利、杰克·布朗特和科普兰医生经常来到这个寂静的屋子里说话——他们觉得，无论对哑巴说什么，他都会明白。也许，还不仅仅如此。

第二部分

1

这个夏天跟米克记忆中所有的夏天都不同。没有多少事情发生，她也无法用思想或语言向自己描绘，却感觉发生了一种改变。她一直很兴奋。早晨，她迫不及待地起床，开始一天的忙碌。晚上，她万分憎恨不得不又去睡觉了。

一吃完早饭，她就把孩子们带出去，除了吃饭时间，他们白天基本不在家。很多时候他们只是在街上瞎逛——她推着拉尔夫的手推车，巴伯跟在后面。她一刻不停地忙着思考、计划。有时候，她会突然抬起头来，发现他们已经走了很远，到了镇上一个她根本不认识的地方。还有一两次，他们在街上碰见比尔，她忙着思考，比尔不得不抓着她的胳膊，才让她看见他。

一大早，天气有点凉，他们的影子长长地投在面前的人行道上。但到了中午，天空总是像火焰一样，阳光强烈，让人不敢睁眼。很多时候，她对将来的计划会跟冰雪联系在一起。有时候，她好像到了瑞士，周围山上都白雪皑皑，她在绿莹莹的冷冰上溜冰。辛格先生也在陪她一起溜冰，也许还有收音机里传来的卡罗尔·隆巴德[8]和阿图罗·托斯卡尼尼[9]的音乐。他们一起溜冰，然后辛格先生掉进了冰窟窿，她则会不顾一切地跳进去，在冰下游着把他救上来。这个计划一直萦绕在她的脑海中。

通常，他们溜达一阵子之后，她便把巴伯和拉尔夫安顿在一个阴凉的地方。巴伯是个特别好的孩子，她把他训练得非常听话。如果她告诉巴伯不要离拉尔夫太远，要待在一喊就能听得见的地方，那么，他绝对不会跑到两三个街区外跟那里的孩子们玩弹珠游戏。他会一个人在手推车旁边玩，所以，她不在他们旁边的时候，一点都不用担心。她要么去图书馆，看《国家地理》杂志，要么只是到处瞎逛，思考更多的问题。如果她有钱，就会到布兰农的店里，买包烟或者一块银河牌巧克力。布兰农先生总会给小孩子打折，五分钱的东西，他三分钱就卖给孩子。

然而，自始至终——无论她做什么——都有音乐。有时候，她一边走一边哼唱，有时候，她静静听着心里的那些歌曲。她的心里有各种各样的音乐：有些是她从收音机里听来的，有些是她脑子里原来就有的，不是从任何地方听来的。

晚上，等孩子们一上床睡觉，她便自由了，那是她一天中最重要的时光。她一个人待着的时候，会发生很多事情，而周围一片漆黑。吃完晚饭，她会立刻又跑出家门。晚上她到底在干什么，她跟谁都不能说，妈妈问起来时，她便随口编些听上去很合理的小故事搪塞过去。但大多数时候，如果有人喊她，她会立马跑开，就像没听见一样，对每个人都如此，只有对她爸爸例外。爸爸的声音里有一种东西，让她无法跑开。他是镇上块头最大、个子最高的男人之一，但他的声音却非常安静、和善，他开口说话的时候，总会让人们大吃一惊。不管她多着急，只要爸爸一喊她，她总是不得不停住脚步。

今年夏天，她突然意识到，爸爸身上有种东西她以前从未注意到。在那之前，她从来没有真正把他看作独立的个体。有很多次，他喊她，她便走进他干活儿的前屋，在他旁边站一会儿——但她一边听他说话，一边走神。后来，有一天晚上，她突然理解了爸爸。那天晚上，一切如常，她也不知道为什么会一下子开了窍。之后她感觉自己长大了，仿佛她理解了他，也理解了其他人。

八月末的一个晚上，她急呼呼地向外跑。她必须九点以前赶到那所房子，不容商量。爸爸喊住她，她走进了前屋。他正疲惫地趴在工作台前。不知为什么，看到他在那里坐着，似乎不太寻常。去年发生事故之前，他一直是个油漆工兼木匠。每天天不亮，他便穿着工装出门，一去便是一天。到了晚上，他有时还会四处转着修表，算是副业。有很多次，他努力想在首饰店找份工作，可以整天穿着干净衬衫打着领带独自坐在桌前工作。现在，他没法干木工活儿了，便在房前挂了个牌子，写着“低价修表”。但他的长相跟大多数钟表匠不一样——市中心的那些钟表匠都是些行动敏捷、皮肤黝黑的犹太人。对工作台而言，她爸爸的个子太高，而且那副大骨架看上去松松垮垮的。

爸爸只是盯着她。她看得出，他叫她来并没有什么事，只是特别想跟她说说话。他努力想着如何开口，那张瘦长的脸上，棕色眼睛显得很大，头发都掉光了，苍白的秃顶让他看上去有一种赤裸的神色。他还是看着她，并不说话。她急坏了。她九点整以前必须到那所房子，没有时间可以浪费。爸爸看出她很着急，于是清了清嗓子。

“我有东西给你。”他说，“不是什么贵重东西，但你也许可以用它好好慰劳下自己。”

他根本不用因为孤独、想找人说话就给她五分或一毛钱。他赚的钱，只够他大约每星期喝两次啤酒。这会儿他椅子旁边的地上就放着两瓶，一瓶空了，另一瓶刚打开。他每次喝啤酒，都喜欢找人聊天。爸爸在腰带上摸了一通，她赶紧挪开目光。这个夏天，他变得像个孩子一样，总是藏些五分、一毛的硬币留着自己用，有时候藏在鞋里，有时候藏在腰带上自己挖的一个小口里。她并不很想拿走那枚一毛钱的硬币，但当他把钱递过来时，她的手很自然地张开，准备接着。

“我有很多活儿要干，不知道从哪儿开始。”他说。

这跟事实恰恰相反，他心里很清楚，她也很清楚。他根本没有多少表要修，干完那点活儿，他便总是在家里到处转悠，找些杂七杂八的事干。晚上，他坐在工作台前，清理那些旧发条和齿轮，努力磨蹭到上床睡觉的时间。自从摔断髋骨之后，他便失去了稳定的工作，但他从来没有闲下来过。

“今晚，我想了很多。”爸爸说。他倒出啤酒，在手背上撒了几粒盐，然后舔净盐粒，接着从杯子里喝了一大口啤酒。

她焦急难耐，几乎没法安静地站下去。爸爸注意到了这一点，想说点什么——但他叫她并不是有什么特别的事情要告诉她，而是只想跟她随便聊一会儿。他想开口，却又咽了口唾沫。他们就那么看着对方，沉默的时间更长了，两人都一句话没说。

就在那个时候，她开始理解了爸爸。她并不是获知了一个新的事实——之前，她从各个方面都明白这个事实，却偏偏没用脑子。现在，她突然知道自己理解了爸爸。他很孤独，他老了，从来没有哪个孩子会因为什么事情来找他，而且他赚的钱也不多。因此，他觉得自己被家人孤立了。在这种孤独中，他想靠近自己的一个孩子——但他们都很忙，根本不了解这一点。他觉得，自己对任何人都没有多大用处。

他们彼此望着对方，她就是在这个时候理解了这一点，这让她感觉有些怪异。爸爸拿起一根手表发条，用刷子蘸着汽油清洗起来。

“我知道你着急出去。我只是想和你打个招呼。”

“没有，我不着急出去。”她说，“真的。”

那天晚上，她坐在他工作台旁边的椅子上，他们谈了一阵子。他谈账目、花销，谈如果当初选择不一样的方式，如今会是什么样子。他喝着啤酒，眼泪一度涌上眼眶，他抽抽鼻子，用衬衫袖子擦了擦。那天晚上，尽管她很着急，但还是陪爸爸待了很长时间。然而，不知为什么，她没法跟他说她想的那些事——关于那些炎热而黑暗的夜晚的事。

那些夜晚是秘密的，是整个夏天最重要的时刻。她在黑暗中一个人走着，就像镇上只有她一个人。夜里，几乎所有街道都跟她家所在的街区一样平淡无奇。有些孩子害怕在陌生的地方走夜路，她却不怕。女孩们都害怕会有男人从什么地方钻出来，然后把他的那个东西放进她们体内，就像结了婚那样。大多数女孩都是傻瓜。如果乔·路易斯[10]或者“山人”迪恩[11]这种块头的男人在她面前跳出来，想要打架，她会撒腿就跑。但如果这人的体重比她多不了二十磅，她会给他一顿胖揍，然后继续走自己的路。

那些夜晚棒极了，她顾上不考虑诸如害怕之类的事情。每次走在黑夜里，她都会思考着音乐。她一边在街上走，一边独自唱歌。她觉得全镇的人都在聆听，却不知道这竟然是米克·凯利唱的。

在这些自由自在的夏日夜晚，她学到了很多音乐知识。她走在镇上的富人区，那里家家户户都有收音机，所有的窗子都敞开着，她能听到非常美妙的音乐。过了一阵子，她便知道哪户人家的收音机会播放她喜欢的节目。有户特别的人家会播放各种各样好听的交响乐。晚上，她总是到这户人家去，溜进人家漆黑的院子里侧耳聆听。房子周围有漂亮的灌木丛，她会坐在窗户附近的一丛灌木底下。等音乐播放完毕，她还会站在漆黑的院子里，双手插进口袋，思考很长时间。这是整个夏天最真实的时刻——她听着收音机里的音乐，仔细琢磨着。

“请关门，先生。”[12]米克说。

巴伯像野蔷薇一样机灵。“请您帮个忙，小姐。”[13]他机智地回答道。

在职业学校学西班牙语，这简直太棒了。说外语时，有种东西让她觉得自己似乎见多识广。自从开学后，她每天下午都在说新学的西班牙语单词和句子，觉得特别有趣。起初，巴伯被难住了。她说外语的时候，巴伯脸上的表情特别滑稽。后来，他迅速赶了上来。很快，无论她说什么，他都可以鹦鹉学舌，学过的单词也都记得住。当然，他并不能完全理解那些句子的意思，但她说西班牙语反正也不是因为这些话的意思。过了一阵子，这孩子学习的速度非常快，她会的西班牙语都说完了，只好急促而含混地发些胡乱编造出来的音。但很快，他就识破了她这套把戏——没有人能蒙得了“老”巴伯·凯利。

“我要假装第一次走进这座房子。”米克说，“那样，我就可以更好地判断出是不是所有装饰品都好看。”

她走出去，到了门廊，然后又回来，站在走廊里。她、巴伯、波西娅，还有她爸爸，他们一整天都在布置走廊和餐厅，为派对做准备。装饰用的是秋天的叶子、藤蔓，还有红色绉纱纸。厨房的壁炉台上和帽架后面，摆放了亮黄色叶子。他们在墙上挂了藤蔓，在要放潘趣酒大碗的桌子上也挂了藤蔓。铺在壁炉上的红色绉纱纸垂着长长的流苏，椅背也绕了一圈垂着流苏的红色绉纱纸。装饰品很多，很好看。

她用手搓着额头，眯眼看着。巴伯站在她旁边，模仿着她的每一个动作。“我确实希望这次派对办得很成功，肯定想。”

这将是她办的第一场派对，她参加过的派对也不过四五场。去年夏天，她参加了一个毕业舞会派对，却没有一个男孩邀请她散步或者跳舞，她只能站在潘趣酒大碗旁边。最后，所有茶点都吃光了，她便回家了。这次派对绝对不要像那次一样。再过几个小时，她邀请的那些人就该陆续来了，喧闹就要开始了。

她为什么想到要办这个派对，已经想不起来了。她到职业学校上学后不久，便有了这个想法。高中太好了，一切都跟文法学校不一样。要是她像黑兹尔和埃特那样必须得去学习速记课程，她就不可能这么高兴了——但她得到了特殊许可，可以像男孩一样学习机械课程。机械课程、代数、西班牙语简直棒极了。英语很难。她的英语老师是明纳小姐。大家都说，明纳小姐把自己的脑子卖给一个著名医生了，卖了一万块钱，所以，等她死了，他就可以把明纳小姐的脑子割开，看看她为什么那么聪明。写作课上，她会抛出这样的问题：“说出八位跟约翰逊博士同时代的名人”，或者“写出《威克菲尔德牧师传》中的十句话”。她总是按照字母顺序喊学生的名字，上课时，成绩册总是打开着。她尽管聪明过人，却整天绷着一张脸。西班牙语老师曾经去欧洲旅行过一次。她说，在法国，人们买回家的面包都是一整条，连包装都没有。他们会站在街上一边聊天，一边用面包敲打旁边的灯柱，而且法国没有水——只有酒。

无论从哪个方面看，职业学校都棒极了。课间，他们在走廊里走来走去，到了午饭时间，学生们到健身馆里闲逛。但很快，有件事情开始让她烦心。走廊里，人们结伴走来走去，似乎都属于某个特别的小群体。不到一两个星期，她便认识了走廊里、班里的人，会跟他们说话——但仅此而已。她不属于任何一个小群体。在文法学校时，她如果想加入哪个群体，可以直接走上前去，就这么简单。但在这里，一切都不一样。

第一星期，她一个人在走廊里溜达，思考着这件事。她很想归属到某个小群体，这个想法几乎跟她对音乐的渴望一样强烈。这两个想法一直在她脑子里挥之不去。最后，她想到了派对。

她对邀请的人精挑细选。不请文法学校的孩子，不请十二岁以下的孩子，只请十三到十五岁之间的孩子。她认识所请的每个人，他们都跟她在走廊里说过话——如果有不知道名字的，她便直接去问人家。那些有电话的孩子，她打电话过去邀请，其余的人她是上学时邀请的。

电话里，她说的话总是一模一样。她让巴伯附耳过来听。“我是米克·凯利。”她说。如果他们没听清名字，她会再重复一次，直到他们听清为止。“这个周六晚上八点钟，我要办一场舞会派对，现在邀请你参加。我住在第四大街一〇三号，A号楼。”“A号楼”在电话里听上去好极了。几乎所有人都会说很高兴受到邀请。有几个难缠的男孩想要故作聪明，一遍遍问她的名字。其中有个男孩想逗个趣，便说：“我不认识你。”她即刻顶了回去：“去你的吧！”除了这个故作聪明的家伙，有十个男孩和十个女孩，她知道他们肯定会来。这是一场真正的派对，将比她参加过或听说过的所有派对都好，都与众不同。

米克最后望了一眼走廊和餐厅。她在帽架旁边停住，站在“老脏脸”的那张照片前面。上面的人是妈妈的祖父，内战期间他是位少校，在一场战斗中牺牲了。有个孩子曾经在他照片上画上了眼镜和胡子，擦掉铅笔痕迹后，他的脸都脏了。因此，她管他叫“老脏脸”。这张照片镶在大相框中间，两边各有一张照片，上面是他的两个儿子，他们看上去大约跟巴伯一样大，穿着军装，脸上一副吃惊的表情。他们也在战场上牺牲了。那都是很久以前的事情了。

“为了派对，我把这张照片取下来吧，我觉得看上去太普通了，你说呢？”

“不知道。”巴伯说，“我们普通吗，米克？”

“我不普通。”

她把那张照片放到了帽架下面。房间装饰得很不错。等辛格先生回来后，他会高兴的。几个房间空荡荡的，很安静。桌子布置好了，就等摆上晚餐了。吃完晚餐，就可以开始派对了。她走进厨房，看看茶点的情况。

“你觉得一切都会顺利吧？”她问波西娅。

波西娅正在做饼干。茶点放在炉子上方，有花生酱、果冻三明治、巧克力饼干，还有潘趣酒。三明治用一块潮湿的碟布盖着。她偷偷瞧了一眼，但没拿。

“我跟你说过四十遍了，一切都会很顺利的。”波西娅说，“我回家做好晚饭，立刻就回来，然后系上雪白的围裙，很漂亮地上菜。到九点半，我要离开这里。今天是星期六，晚上海博埃、威利和我也有我们的计划。”

“当然了。”米克说，“我只想让你帮我，等事情开了头就好了——你懂的。”

她没忍住，拿了一块三明治。然后，她让巴伯跟着波西娅，自己走进中间的房间。她要穿的裙子正平放在床上。黑兹尔和埃特在这方面一直很慷慨，会把自己最好的衣服借给她——她们应该不会参加这次派对。埃特借给她的是一件蓝色双绉长晚礼服，一双白色浅口鞋，还有一顶水晶头冠。这些衣服美极了，简直想象不出她穿上会是什么样子。

到了傍晚，阳光透过窗子投下长长的黄色斜影。如果她要花两个小时才能打扮好参加派对，那现在就该动手了。想到要穿上这么漂亮的衣服，她简直坐立不安，迫不及待。她慢步走进浴室，脱掉身上破旧的短裤和衬衫，打开水龙头。她使劲刷着脚后跟、膝盖处的粗糙部位，特别是胳膊肘。她洗了很长时间。

她光着身子跑进中间的房间，开始穿衣服。她穿上丝绸内衣、丝绸袜子，为了好玩，她甚至穿上了埃特的胸罩。然后，她小心翼翼地穿上裙子，踩上浅口鞋。这是她第一次穿晚礼服。她久久地站在镜子前面。她个子很高，裙子离脚踝还有两三英寸的距离——鞋子太小，弄得脚疼。她在镜子前面站了很长时间，最后断定自己的样子要么像个傻瓜，要么美若天仙。

她尝试了六种不同的方式弄自己的头发。额头前翘起的一绺头发有点麻烦，所以她打湿刘海儿，做了三个波浪卷。最后，她把水晶头冠卡在头发上，涂了很多口红，还有腮红。打扮完毕，她像电影明星一样抬起下巴，微闭双眼。她慢慢地把脸转过来，又转过去，她看上去很美——就是很美。

她感觉自己像完全换了个人，完全不是米克·凯利了。还要再等两个小时派对才能开始，如果家人看见她早早就穿好了衣服，她会感到很难为情。她又走进浴室，锁上门。她不能坐下，怕弄乱裙子，于是便站在浴室中央。四面逼仄的墙壁压过来，似乎让她更为兴奋。她觉得自己跟以前的米克·凯利完全不同，她知道这将是她一生当中最美妙的东西——这次派对。

“耶！潘趣酒！”

“最漂亮的裙子——”

“嘿，你解开了那道题，关于三角形的，四十六——”

“让我过去，闪开！”

前门每一秒钟都会砰地响一下，人们蜂拥而入。尖厉的声音与柔和的声音混在一起，最后合成了一种轰鸣的噪音。女孩们扎堆站在一起，穿着漂亮的长晚礼服；男孩们则到处闲逛，他们穿着洁净的帆布裤子，或者后备军官训练队制服，或者崭新的深色秋季西装。到处都是一片嘈杂混乱，米克没法认清哪张脸或者哪个人。她站在帽架旁边，环顾整个派对的场面。

“大家都来拿一张舞会请柬，开始报名。”

起初，房间里很吵，没人听见，也没人留意。男孩们都密匝匝地围在潘趣酒大碗周围，根本看不到桌子和藤蔓，只有她爸爸的面孔在男孩们的脑袋上面露出来。他微笑着，把潘趣酒给男孩们分到小纸杯里。她旁边帽架的座位上放着一罐糖果、两块手帕。几个女孩以为今天是她的生日，她向她们道谢，把礼物打开，并没有告诉她们她还有八个月才过十四岁生日。每个人都像她一样，干净清爽、盛装打扮，身上散发出好闻的味道。男孩们的头发都抹得水润光滑，女孩们则穿着各种颜色的长裙站在一起，像一大片色彩艳丽的花朵。这个开头非常棒。这场派对的开端很不错。

“我有苏格兰—爱尔兰、法国血统，还有——”

“我有德国血统——”

她又喊了一遍领取舞会请柬，然后走进了餐厅。很快，他们开始从走廊里拥进来，每人拿了一张舞会请柬，然后一堆堆地靠墙排起了队。现在才是真正的开始。

然后，突然间变得非常怪异——这种安静。男孩们一起站在房间的一侧，女孩们则站在对面。不知为什么，大家都立刻同时住了嘴。男孩们拿着请柬，望着女孩们，房间里一片寂静。没有一个男孩按照惯例开始邀请舞伴。这种可怕的寂静越来越让人难以忍受，她参加派对的经验不足，不知道该如何是好。然后，男孩们开始互相打闹、说话。女孩们也咯咯笑起来——但即便她们没去看那些男孩子，你也看得出，她们满脑子想的只是她们是不是会受欢迎。这会儿，那种可怕的寂静消失了，但房间里有种紧张不安的气氛。

过了一会儿，一个男孩走到一个名叫德洛丽丝·布朗的女孩跟前，在她的舞会请柬上报了名。其他男孩见状，也都立刻冲到德洛丽丝跟前。当她的请柬签满名字的时候，他们又开始冲到另一个女孩玛丽跟前。在那之后，一切突然又停止了。还有另外一两个女孩得到了几个舞伴——因为是她主办的派对，所以有三个男孩来找她当舞伴。就是这些了。

人们只是在餐厅和走廊里闲逛。大部分男孩聚集在潘趣酒大碗周围，想要彼此炫耀。女孩们则凑到一起，时常哈哈大笑，假装玩得很开心。男孩们琢磨着女孩们，女孩们则琢磨着男孩们，但房间里却充满了一种很奇怪的感觉。

那个时候，她才开始注意到哈里·米诺维茨。他家就住在隔壁，她从小就认识他。尽管他比她大两岁，但她长得比他快。夏天的时候，他俩经常在外面大街边的草地上摔跤和打架。哈里是个犹太男孩，长得却不大像犹太人。他的头发是淡褐色的，很直。今晚，他穿得非常整洁，他进门的时候将一顶大人的巴拿马帽挂在了帽架上，帽子上还插了一根羽毛。

让她注意到他的，并不是他的衣服。他脸上有什么地方变了，因为他没像往常一样戴着角质架眼镜。他一只眼睛里长了一颗发红的麦粒肿，很大，看人的时候，他要把脑袋歪到一边才行，像鸟一样。他的两只瘦长的手不断地摸那个肿块，好像很疼的样子。他要潘趣酒的时候，直接把纸杯子戳到了她爸爸的脸上。她看得出来，他特别需要戴上眼镜。他很紧张，总是撞上别人。除了她，他没有邀请任何女孩做舞伴——而这是因为她是这场派对的主人。

潘趣酒喝光了。爸爸怕她难堪，便跟她妈妈一起去厨房做柠檬水。有些人在前面门廊里，人行道上也有人。她很高兴到外面来呼吸一下夜晚清凉的空气。从闷热明亮的家里出来，她在黑暗中闻到了初秋的味道。

然后，她看到了一件意料之外的事情。人行道边和漆黑的大街上有一群邻居家的孩子，皮特、萨克·韦尔斯、巴比、斯波尔瑞巴斯——一大群人，小的比巴伯还小，大的超过十二岁。还有些孩子她根本不认识，他们不知怎的都嗅到了派对的味道，到附近来转悠。还有跟她年纪相仿或者比她大些的孩子，她也没邀请他们过来，因为他们对她做过坏事，或者她曾经对他们做过坏事。他们都脏兮兮的，穿着简单的短裤或邋里邋遢的衬裤，或者破旧的日常衣服。他们就在附近闲逛，在黑暗中望着派对的场景。看到这些孩子，她心里生出两种感觉——一种是伤心，另一种是警惕。

“这支舞我约了你。”哈里·米诺维茨假装在念请柬上的内容，但她能看见那上面什么也没写。她爸爸走到门廊里，吹响了哨子，宣布第一支舞开始了。

“好的，”她说，“我们去吧。”

他们开始出门绕着街区走去。她穿着长裙子，依然觉得自己非常时髦而奢华。“你们看，米克·凯利！”黑暗中，一个孩子大喊起来。“看她！”她假装没听见，继续走路。大喊的就是那个斯波尔瑞巴斯，不久她就会抓住他的。她和哈里快速走在黑暗的人行道上，走到街道尽头时他们拐入另一个街区。

“你现在多大了，米克——十三岁？”

“马上就十四岁了。”

她知道他心里想什么，这件事曾经让她担心。她身高五英尺六英寸，体重一百零三磅，其实才只有十三岁。派对上，别的孩子站在她身边，简直都是些小矮子，但哈里除外，他比她只矮了几英寸。没有哪个男孩愿意约一个比自己高那么多的女孩当舞伴。但抽烟也许能抑制一下她以后的生长。

“我去年只长了三点二五英寸。”她说。

“我在集市上见过一位女士，足足有八英尺半高，但你可能长不了那么高。”

哈里在一丛黑乎乎的紫薇灌木旁边停住脚步，附近没有人。他从口袋里拿出一样东西，开始摆弄起来。她靠过去看个仔细——是他的眼镜，他正用手绢擦着镜片。

“抱歉。”他说道，然后戴上了眼镜，她听到他长出了一口气。

“你该一直戴着眼镜。”

“是的。”

“你为什么刚才一直不戴呢？”

夜色宁静而浓重。他们穿过大街时，哈里扶住了她的胳膊肘。

“派对上有位年轻女士，她觉得男人戴眼镜显得太女孩子气。这个人——哦，嗯，也许，我是个——”

他没说完。突然，他绷紧身体，跑了几步，跳起来去够离头顶还有四英尺高的一片树叶。夜色中，她勉强能看见那片高高挂着的树叶。他的弹跳力非常好，一下就够到了，然后他把树叶放进嘴里，在黑暗中打了几下空拳。她赶上他。

像往常一样，一首歌回旋在她的脑海中。她独自哼唱起来。

“你唱的是什么歌？”

“一个叫莫扎特的人写的曲子。”

哈里觉得非常美妙。他用脚向侧方跨着步，像个敏捷的拳击手一样。“听上去像个德国人的名字。”

“我猜是。”

“法西斯分子？”他问。

“什么？”

“我说，莫扎特是个法西斯分子，还是个纳粹？”

米克想了一会儿。“不是，法西斯和纳粹都是新名词，这个人已经死了很长时间了。”

“那很好。”他又开始在黑暗中打拳了。他希望她会问问为什么这么说。

“我说，这是件好事。”他重复了一遍。

“为什么？”

“因为，我憎恨法西斯分子。如果街上有法西斯分子走过来，我就杀了他。”

她望着哈里。在街灯的照射下，那些树叶在他脸上投下斑驳的阴影，颤巍巍的。他非常激动。

“为什么？”她问。

“天啊！你难道不看报纸吗？你看，是这样——”

他们绕着街区又转了回来。她家里一片喧闹。人行道上，人们都在大喊大叫，跑来跑去。她胃里涌起一阵强烈的恶心。

“除非我们绕着街区再来一圈，否则没有时间跟你解释。我不介意告诉你我为什么憎恨法西斯。我想跟你聊聊。”

也许，这是他第一次有机会跟别人滔滔不绝地说起自己的这些想法，但她根本顾不上听，她忙着看自家门前的场景。“好吧，回头见。”舞会现在结束了，她现在可以去看看眼前的这团乱象，好好琢磨下。

她离开后到底发生了什么事？她走的时候，人们穿着漂亮的衣服站在周围，还是场真正的派对。现在——仅仅过了五分钟——这个地方看上去就像个疯人院。趁她不在家，外面的那些孩子从黑暗中钻出来，直接去了派对。他们竟然胆敢这样做！老皮特·韦尔斯在前门口晃悠，手里端着一杯潘趣酒。他们又喊又叫，四处乱跑，跟邀请来的客人混成一团——穿着他们破旧的松松垮垮的衬裤和日常衣服。

巴比·威尔逊在门廊上乱钻——巴比还不到四岁。人人都看得出，这会儿，她该像巴伯一样在家睡觉才对。巴比一步一个台阶走下来，把潘趣酒杯高高举过头顶。她根本不应该出现在这里。布兰农先生是她的姨夫，只要她愿意，随时都可以到他店里拿免费水果和饮料。她一走到人行道上，米克就一把抓住她的胳膊。“赶紧回家，巴比·威尔逊，快，现在。”米克看着四周，想看看她还能做些什么才能让局势重新回归正常。她走到萨克·韦尔斯面前。他站在远一点黑乎乎的人行道上，手里握着纸杯，神情恍惚地望着所有人。萨克七岁，穿着短裤，光着上身，赤着脚。他倒没惹什么麻烦，但发生的一切让她气得发疯。

她一把抓住萨克的肩膀，使劲摇晃他。起初，他紧咬牙关，但过了一会儿，他的牙齿开始咔嗒作响。“赶紧回家，萨克·韦尔斯，没邀请你来，你不要在这里转悠了。”她放开手，萨克像夹着尾巴一样，慢慢沿着大街走了。但他并没有一路走回家。他走到街角，她看见他在路边坐了下来，望着派对上的人，他以为这样便会逃过她的目光了。

有那么一会儿，她打发掉萨克之后感觉很好。但紧接着，她心里又特别担心，开始喊他回来。搞砸这一切的是那些大孩子，他们才是真正的捣蛋鬼，在她看来，他们做坏事的胆子最大。他们吃光了茶点，毁了好好一场派对，把派对变成了一场闹剧。他们在前门来回穿梭，发出砰砰的声音，大喊大叫，又撞又挤。她走到皮特·韦尔斯跟前，因为他闹腾得最厉害。他戴着橄榄球头盔，专门冲撞别人。皮特已经十四岁了，却还留在七年级。她走到他跟前，但他块头实在太大，她没法像摇晃萨克那样去摇晃他。她让他赶紧回家，他抖动着身体像跳希米舞一样，朝她直冲过来。

“我去过六个州，佛罗里达、阿拉巴马——”

“是用银色的布做的，配了腰带——”

派对全乱了。大家都在大声说话，从职业学校邀请来的人跟临近街坊的那帮人混在了一起，但男孩和女孩还是各自分成一堆堆地站着——却没有人结成舞伴。家里，柠檬水所剩无几，只在碗底还剩一小洼水，上面漂着几片柠檬皮。她爸爸总是对孩子太好了，只要有人将纸杯子伸到他面前，他都会倒上潘趣酒。

她走进餐厅时，波西娅正端上三明治。不到五分钟，三明治便被一扫而空，她只拿到一个——一个果冻三明治，粉色的果冻从面包里渗了出来。波西娅待在餐厅，望着派对上的人。“我玩得很开心，不想走了。”她说，“我已经给海博埃和威利捎信儿了，让他们自己去欢度周六夜晚吧，不要等我了。大家在这里都这么兴奋，我要等等，看着派对结束。”

兴奋——就是这个词。她能感觉到，房间里、门廊上、外面的人行道上都充满了兴奋之情。她也觉得很兴奋，不仅仅是因为她的裙子，或者她看上去容光焕发的那种美——她经过帽架镜子时，看见自己两颊通红，还有头发上的水晶头冠。也许，她觉得兴奋，还因为所有的装饰品，所有来自职业学校的人，以及挤在一起的孩子们。

“看她跑了！”

“哎哟，住手——”

“也不看看你多大了！”

一群女孩沿着大街跑起来，提着裙子，头发在身后飞舞着。有些男孩砍下丝兰长长的尖锐叶片，拿着它们追赶着女孩子们。职业学校的新生们穿得像是参加真正的毕业舞会，行为举止却像些孩子。这像是开玩笑，又不像开玩笑。一个男孩拿着尖刺叶片朝她走过来，她抬腿就跑。

现在，派对的概念完全没有了，变成了标准的闹剧。这是她见过的最狂野的夜晚，那帮孩子是罪魁祸首。他们就像一场传染病，他们来到派对上，便让所有人都忘记了高中，忘记了长大。就像你下午要洗澡，但洗澡前你会跑到后院肆意打滚，弄得浑身脏透，只是为了进入澡盆那一刻的快感。每个人都变成了一个野孩子，在周六晚上疯玩——她觉得自己是里面最狂野的一个。

她大喊大叫，又推又搡，首先去尝试新的惊险动作。她弄出很大动静，跑得飞快，根本没注意到其他人都在干什么。她想随心所欲地去做所有疯狂的事情，但呼吸却急促得跟不上了。

“街上的水沟！水沟！水沟！”

她第一个朝水沟冲去。一个街区之外，人们在街道下面铺设了新管道，挖了一条很深的水沟。黑暗之中，沟边的火盆里都冒着明亮的红光。她简直等不及要爬下去。她一直跑到那些起伏的小火苗跟前，然后跳了下去。

如果穿着网球鞋，她本来可以像猫一样落地——但脚上的高跟浅口鞋让她跌了一跤，肚子撞在管子上，这让她一下子连气都喘不动了。她闭着眼睛，躺在那里一动不动。

那场派对——很长一段时间里，她都记得自己原来的构想，记得脑海中对职业学校那些新生的想象，还记得她每天都想加入的那个群体。现在，她站在走廊里会有不同的感觉，因为她知道他们并没什么特殊的，跟别的孩子一样。这场被毁掉的派对让她认识到了这一点。但一切都结束了，到此为止。

米克从水沟里爬上来。有些孩子正在那些小火盆旁边玩。火焰发出红色的光，照出长长的跳动的影子。有个男孩跑回家，戴上了一个面具，那是提前为万圣节买的。派对没有改变什么，除了她以外。

她慢慢往家走去。经过那些孩子时，她既不说话，也不看他们。走廊里的装饰物已经扯掉了，屋子里似乎空荡荡的，所有人都跑到了外面。她走进浴室，脱掉蓝色晚礼服。裙子的褶边撕破了，她把撕破的地方叠到里面，这样便看不出来了。水晶头冠不知道掉到哪里去了。她的旧短裤和衬衫还放在地板上，没有人动过。她穿上短裤和衬衫。过了今晚，她长大了，不能再穿短裤了。今晚之后，不能再穿了。再也不能了。

米克站在门廊上。卸妆之后，她的脸色很苍白。她把双手拢在嘴上，深吸了一口气。“大家都回家吧！关门了！派对结束了！”

在寂静、神秘的夜色中，又只剩了她一个人。时间不算晚——沿街的房子里，一块块方形的黄色灯光从窗子透出来。她走得很慢，双手插进口袋里，头歪向一边。她走了很久，并不在意自己在朝什么方向走。

后来，房子变得稀疏起来，有些院子里种着大树，还有黑乎乎的灌木丛。她看着四周，发现自己又来到了这幢房子，就是她这个夏天多次来过的那幢房子。她的双脚不知不觉便把她带到了这里。她走到房子跟前，等了一会儿，确定没有人看见她，然后她穿过了侧院。

跟往常一样，收音机开着。她在窗前站了一会儿，望着窗子里的人。那个秃顶的男人和头发花白的女人正在桌前玩牌。米克坐在地上。这是个非常好的私密之地，周围都是茂密的雪松，把她藏得严严实实。今晚收音机的节目不太好听——有人在唱流行歌曲，结尾都是一个样子。她的心里就像空了似的。她把手伸进口袋，用手指摸索了个遍。里面有葡萄干、一枚七叶树种，还有一串珠子——一根烟，还有火柴。她把烟点上，双臂抱着膝盖。她的心好像空了似的，没有感觉，也没有思想。

一个接一个的节目播放着，都很没意思，她不是特别喜欢。她抽着烟，抓起一小把草叶。过了一会儿，一个新播音员开始说话了，提到了贝多芬。她在图书馆看过关于这个音乐家的书——他的名字听起来有个“a”，但拼写时却是两个“e”。他跟莫扎特一样，是德国人，活着的时候说的是外语，也住在外国——她也想这样。播音员说，他们要播放他的第三交响曲。她漫不经心地听着，因为她还想再走走，并不太关心他们要播放什么音乐。然后，音乐开始了。米克抬起头，一只手握紧拳头放到了喉咙上。

这些音乐是怎么来的？有一会儿的时间，序曲像天平般从一边偏向另一边，像走路，又像行军，也像上帝在夜色中昂首阔步。她的身体突然僵住了，心里只有播放的第一部分音乐，令她的心炽热沸腾。她甚至听不见后面的乐声了，但她坐在那里，等待着，无法动弹，两只拳头紧紧攥着。过了一会儿，那段音乐又响了起来，这次更沉重，更响亮。这与上帝毫无关系。这就是她，米克·凯利，白天到处游走，夜晚形单影只。在炽热的阳光下和浓重的夜色里，想着所有的计划，带着所有的感情。这首曲子就是她——真实而又平常的她。

她再怎么努力听，都觉得无法听见全部的乐声。音乐在她体内沸腾着。该怎么听？牢牢抓住某些精彩的部分，反复思考，这样以后她就不会忘记了——或者她应该放手，先听完所有部分，并不仔细思考或试图记住？天哪！整个世界只剩下这首曲子，而她无论怎么听，都觉得不够认真。终于，序曲又来了，各种不同乐器的声音交织到一起，演奏着每一个音符，像一只结实、握紧的拳头，重重地击打着她的心脏。第一部分结束了。

这首曲子持续的时间不是很长，也不是很短。其实，跟时间的流逝毫无关系。她坐在那里，双臂紧抱着双腿，使劲咬着自己咸咸的膝盖。她或许听了五分钟，或许是半个晚上。第二部分很凝重——一支缓慢的进行曲。不是悲伤，但就像整个世界都死去了，都黑了，根本无法想象出世界以前的样子。一种类似号角的乐器演奏出一种悲怆、清脆的曲调。然后，音乐突然升高，宛如愤怒起来，背后还带着兴奋。最后，又是凝重的进行曲。

然而，交响乐的最后一部分也许才是她最爱的部分——快乐，就像世界上最伟大的那些人都在奔跑，在跳跃，艰难而自由。如此美妙的音乐是这个世界上最大的伤痛。整个世界都融入这首交响乐里，她怎么都听不过来。

音乐停止了。她坐着一动不动，双臂还抱着双膝。收音机里播起另一个节目，她用手指堵上耳朵。这首曲子留给她的只是这种巨大的伤害，还有一种空虚。听过的那首交响乐，她一点都想不起来了，连最后几个音符都已经记不起来了。她拼命地想，但脑子里想不起任何声音。音乐播完了，只剩下她心里如脱兔乱撞，疼痛不已。

房间里，收音机关了，灯也关了。夜晚漆黑一片。突然，米克开始用拳头捶打自己的大腿。她拼尽全力打着同一个地方的肌肉，最后，眼泪顺着脸颊流了下来。但她觉得还不够痛。灌木丛底下的石块非常锐利，她抓起一把石块，用它们在同一个地方来回刮擦着，直到她的手上鲜血直流。然后，她向后倒在地上，躺在那里望着夜空。腿上的伤口剧烈地疼痛着，让她感觉好多了。她无力地躺在湿漉漉的草地上，过了一会儿，呼吸重新变得缓慢而平静。

那些探险家为什么不能仰望下天空，然后以此判断出地球是圆的呢？天空是有弧度的，像个巨大玻璃球的内侧，呈现一种深蓝色，其中散落着明亮的星星。夜晚一片寂静，有雪松温暖的味道。她不再努力去想那首曲子，就在这时，音乐突然闪现在她的脑海中，回响着第一部分乐章，与播放的一模一样。她静静地、慢慢地听着，想着那些音符，就像解一道几何题，这样她便可以记住了。她能够清晰地看见那些声音的形状，不会再忘记它们。

现在，她感觉好多了。她低声说道：“上帝宽恕我吧，我也不知道自己做了什么。”她怎么想到这句话的？过去几年中，大家都知道并不存在真正的上帝。她想到以前自己想象上帝的模样时，只会想到辛格先生裹着长长的白床单的样子。上帝是沉默的——也许，这就是她为什么会想到辛格先生。她又重复了一遍那句话，就像跟辛格先生说话那样。“上帝宽恕我吧，我也不知道自己做了什么。”

这段音乐美妙而清晰。现在，她可以随心所欲地把它唱出来了。以后，也许她哪天早晨醒来时，脑子里会想起更多曲子。也许，如果她能再听一次这首交响乐，她能记住更多部分。也许，如果她能再听四次，只再听四次，这首曲子她便可以全部记下来。也许。

她又一次聆听着这首音乐的序曲部分。接着，音符变得越来越慢，越来越柔和，就像她正慢慢掉进黑暗的地下。

米克猛地一下醒了过来。空气中已经有了寒意，她刚才梦见老埃特·凯利抢走了所有的被子，逐渐从睡意中清醒过来。“给我点毯子——”她拼命想说出来。然后，她睁开了眼睛。天空一片漆黑，一颗星星都没有，草地很湿。她赶紧站起来，因为爸爸会着急的。然后，她想起了那首曲子。她不知道这会儿是午夜还是凌晨三点，急忙往家跑去。空气里有种秋天一样的味道，脑海里的音乐声很大，节奏很快，她在人行道上越跑越快，一路朝家的方向跑去。

2

十月份，天空蔚蓝，天气凉爽。比夫·布兰农换下薄泡泡纱裤子，穿上深蓝色哔叽呢裤。他在咖啡馆的柜台后面装了一个机器，可以做热巧克力。米克尤其偏爱热巧克力，每周都会过来三四次买热巧克力。他卖给她，只收五分钱，而原价是一毛钱。其实，他本想免费请她喝。望着她站在柜台后面，他感到焦虑而伤感。他想伸出手去，摸摸她被风吹日晒、蓬松凌乱的头发——但不是用触摸女人的那种方式。他心里有一种不安，跟她说话时，他的声音那么粗鲁，那么陌生。

他心头有很多担忧。第一，爱丽丝身体状况不太好。从早上七点到晚上十点，她还是照常在楼下工作，但走路非常缓慢，眼睛下面有黑眼圈。干活儿时，她的病态表现得非常明显。有个星期天，她在打字机上打当日菜单，“皇家奶油鸡”的特色菜应该是五毛钱，她却标成了两毛钱，一直等到好几位顾客点完菜要付账时，她才注意到这个错误。还有一次，别人付了十块钱，她找给人家两张五块和三张一块的零钱。比夫站在那里，久久地望着她，半闭着眼睛，摩挲着鼻子，若有所思。

他们没有一起讨论过这个话题。晚上，他在楼下干活儿，她去睡觉。早晨，她独自收拾着餐厅。等他们一起干活儿时，按照惯例，他待在收银机后面，照看着厨房和桌子。除了生意上的事情，他们也没什么话说，但比夫会站在那里望着她，脸上一副困惑的表情。

十月八日下午，从他们的卧室突然传来一声痛苦的喊叫。比夫急忙上楼。不到一个小时，他们便把爱丽丝送到了医院，医生从她体内取出一个肿瘤，足有一个新生婴儿那么大。又过了不到一个小时，爱丽丝死了。

比夫坐在她的病床旁边，震惊不已，思考着。她死的时候他在场。由于乙醚的麻醉作用，她的两只眼睛泪汪汪的，然后渐渐变硬，像玻璃一样。医生和护士都退了出去，他依然盯着她的脸。除了那层青白色，她的脸没有任何变化。他仔细研究着她身上的每一个细节，好像二十一年来他从来没有好好看过她一样。然后，他坐在那里，思绪逐渐转向一幅画面，那是一直在他心里藏了好久的画面。

冰冷的绿色海洋，一溜灼热的金色沙滩。小孩子们在那丝滑的泡沫边缘玩耍，那个健壮的棕色皮肤的女娃娃，那几个又瘦又小光着屁股的男孩，还有几个半大孩子，他们一边跑一边用可爱尖厉的声音彼此呼唤着。里面的一些孩子他认识，米克，他的外甥女巴比，还有一些陌生的年轻面孔，以前没人见过他们。比夫垂下了头。

过了很长时间，他从椅子上起来，站到病房中央。他能听到妻妹露西尔在外面的走廊上走来走去。一只圆滚滚的蜜蜂在柜子顶上爬着，比夫娴熟地用手捉起蜜蜂，把它从开着的窗户放了出去。再次望了一眼那张毫无生气的脸庞，他带着一种丧妻的镇静，推开通往医院走廊的大门。

第二天早晨，将近中午时分，他坐在楼上房间里缝东西。为什么？在很多关于真爱的故事里，为什么一个人失去爱人之后，并不会自杀，紧随爱人而去？只是因为活着的人还要埋葬逝者吗？因为有人死后，活着的人必须要履行严格的仪式？因为活下来的那个人有一段时间就像登上舞台一样，每分每秒都度日如年，要在众目睽睽之下生活？因为他还必须要履行自己的职责？或者，如果有爱，那么痛失爱人的那个人必须坚守着，等待着心上人的复活——那么，逝去的那个人并非真的死去，而是会在生者的灵魂中继续成长，甚至被再次创造出来？为什么？

比夫低头缝着，沉思着很多事情。他缝得非常熟练，指尖的老茧很硬，无须顶针便可以穿针引线。两套灰色西装袖子上的黑纱已经缝好了，现在他缝的是最后一个。

天气晴朗且炎热，初秋的第一批落叶扫过人行道。他早早就出门了。每一分钟都如此漫长，在他面前的是无尽的空虚。他已经锁上了餐馆大门，在门外挂了一个白色百合花的花环。他先去了殡仪馆，仔细挑选着棺木。他摸摸里侧的材料，试试框架的牢靠程度。

“这种绉纱叫什么名字——乔其纱？”

殡仪员用一种逢迎虚假的声音回答了他的问题。

“在你们这里，火葬占多大比例？”

比夫从殡仪馆出来，又走到外面的街上，走得缓慢而又庄重。暖风从西边吹过来，太阳非常刺目。他的表停了，因此他拐个弯朝威尔伯·凯利住的那条街走去。最近，凯利在那里挂了一个修表的牌子。凯利正坐在工作台前，穿着一条打了补丁的浴袍。他的工作间也是他的卧室。米克用手推车推着到处逛的那个婴儿，正安静地坐在地上的一个草垫上。每一分钟都那么漫长，他有充足的时间来思考，来询问。他让凯利解释了手表里轴承的具体用途。凯利的右眼戴着修表匠的放大镜，他注意到这只眼睛在镜子后面变了形。他们谈论了一会儿张伯伦和慕尼黑。然后，因为时间仍然尚早，他决定到哑巴家里看一看。

辛格正在穿衣服，准备上班。昨天晚上，辛格已经送去了一封吊唁信。葬礼上，他还要去扶棺。比夫坐在床边，跟哑巴一起抽了根烟。辛格不时地看他一眼，绿色的眼睛似乎洞察一切。他给比夫倒了一杯咖啡。比夫没说话，哑巴一度过来拍拍他的肩膀，盯着他的脸看了一会儿。等辛格穿好衣服，他们一起出了门。

比夫在商店买了黑丝带，又去见了爱丽丝所在教堂的牧师。一切安排停当之后，他便回家了。把一切做得井井有条——他心里就是这么想的。他把爱丽丝的衣服和个人物品捆好，交给了露西尔。他把斗柜的抽屉彻底清洁并整理了一遍，甚至把楼下厨房里的架子都重新收拾了一遍，把电扇上色彩艳丽的绉纱彩带都取了下来。做完这一切之后，他坐进浴缸，把自己全身上下都洗了一遍。上午就这样过去了。

比夫咬断线头，抚平大衣袖子上的黑纱。这会儿，露西尔应该在等着他了。露西尔、巴比和他要一起去坐殡葬车。他收好针线筐，把戴着黑纱的大衣小心翼翼地穿好，迅速环顾了一下房间，觉得没什么问题，然后便又出了门。

一个小时以后，他来到了露西尔家的小厨房。他坐下，两腿交叉，腿上铺一块餐巾纸，喝着茶。露西尔和爱丽丝在很多方面全然不同，很难看出她俩是亲姐妹。露西尔又瘦又黑，今天又穿了一身黑。她正在收拾巴比的头发。妈妈在忙活着她的时候，这个孩子坐在餐桌上，双手叠放在膝盖上，耐心地等待着。阳光照进来，房间里安静祥和。

“巴塞洛缪——”露西尔说。

“什么事？”

“你已经开始回忆以前的事了吗？”

“没有。”比夫说。

“你知道，我好像必须一直戴着眼罩，才不会胡思乱想，才不会回忆过去。我能让自己想的，只有每天上班，解决巴比的一日三餐，还有她的未来。”

“这才是正确的态度。”

“我一直在店里给巴比做手指卷发，但太容易开了，所以我考虑带她去做个电烫发。我不想自己给她做——我想，也许我去亚特兰大参加美容师大会时可以带她一起去，让她在那里做。”

“天哪！她才四岁，会吓着她的。而且，电烫会伤害头发。”

露西尔用梳子在一杯水里蘸了一下，把巴比耳朵上面的卷发打碎。“不，不会的，她也想烫。尽管巴比还小，但她已经跟我一样有志向了，这就说明了一切。”

比夫在手掌上磨了磨指甲，摇摇头。

“我和巴比每次去看电影，看见那些孩子演得那么好，她的感觉跟我一样。我保证她是这样的，巴塞洛缪，之后我想带她去吃晚饭都拉不动。”

“天啊。”比夫说。

“她的舞蹈课和表演课都学得非常好。明年我想让她开始学钢琴，如果能弹钢琴，会对她有帮助。她的舞蹈老师会让她在晚会上表演独舞。我觉得必须得全力督促巴比，她越早开始自己的事业对我们两个便越好。”

“天啊！”

“你不懂，对一个有天赋的孩子，不能像对待一个普通孩子那样。这就是我为什么要把巴比弄出这个普通社区的一个原因。我不能让她跟周围那些调皮孩子一样学着说粗话，或者像他们一样到处疯跑。”

“我认识这条街上的孩子。”比夫说，“他们很好，街对面凯利家的那些孩子——克兰家的那个男孩——”

“那你很清楚，他们哪个都达不到巴比的水平。”

露西尔做完巴比头发上的最后一个发卷。她捏捏孩子的小脸，好让脸上有点血色，然后把孩子从桌上抱了下来。为了这次葬礼，巴比穿了一件小白裙，白鞋子，白袜子，甚至戴了一副小小的白手套。有人望着巴比时，她总会把头那样昂着，现在就是这副姿势。

他们在闷热的小厨房里坐了一会儿，没有再说话。然后，露西尔哭了起来。“我们不像非常亲近的姐妹，我们截然不同，也不常见面，也许是因为我年龄小了很多。但人们的血缘关系里面有种东西，当发生这样的事情时——”

比夫发出啧啧声，像是宽慰。

“我知道你们俩是什么状况。”她说，“你和她之间并不都是浪漫，但也许正因为如此，才让你现在的状况更加糟糕。”

比夫把手伸到巴比的腋下，把她抡到了自己肩膀上。这个孩子越来越重了。他小心翼翼地抓着她，走进了起居室。巴比坐在他的肩膀上，觉得温暖亲近，她白色的丝绸小裙子在他黑色大衣的映衬下显得雪白，她用一只小手紧紧揪住他的耳朵。

“比夫姨夫！看我劈叉。”

他温柔地把巴比放到地上站好。她把两只胳膊弯过头顶，两只脚在打过蜡的黄色地板上慢慢地朝相反方向滑出去。很快，她便坐到了地上，一条腿直直地朝前伸着，另一条腿在身后，两只胳膊向上举着，角度很美。她的眼睛斜看着墙，带着一种忧伤的表情。

她又爬了起来。“看我做个前手翻，看我——”

“宝贝，安静一点吧。”露西尔说。

她挨着比夫坐到毛绒沙发上。“她是不是有点让你想到他的样子——特别是眼睛和脸？”

“见鬼，没有。巴比和勒罗伊·威尔逊之间一点相似之处都没有。”

就年龄而言，露西尔看上去太瘦，太疲惫。也许是因为身上穿着黑裙子，也许是因为她一直在哭。“毕竟，我得承认，他是巴比的父亲。”她说。

“你难道不能忘了那个男人吗？”

“不知道。我想，我在两件事上一直很傻，那就是勒罗伊和巴比。”

在苍白脸色的映衬下，比夫新长出来的胡子呈现出一种青色。他的声音听上去很疲惫。“难道你不能把一件事情想清楚，搞明白原委，然后从中吸取教训吗？你难道不能理性一点——如果这些都是既定事实，结果就该是这样？”

“我觉得，对他我做不到。”

比夫说话的样子很疲倦，眼睛都快闭上了。“你十七岁就嫁给了这个人，后来你们俩之间就争吵不断，你跟他离了婚。两年以后你再次嫁给他，现在他又跑了，你也不知道他去了哪儿。这些事实似乎都表明了一件事——你们俩彼此不合适，这还不包括更个人化的方面——那个男人碰巧就是这种人。”

“天晓得，我一直都知道他是个浑蛋，我只是希望他不会再来敲门了。”

“瞧，巴比。”比夫急促地说，他把手指交叉在一起，然后举起来，“这是教堂，这是那个尖顶，打开门，上帝的子民就在这里。”

露西尔摇摇头。“你不用为巴比费心。我把一切都跟她说了，她对这件事情的来龙去脉非常清楚。”

“那么，如果他回来，你会收留他，然后让他尽情在你家当寄生虫——跟以前一样？”

“是的，我想我会这样。每次门铃或电话响起来，每次有人走上门廊，我脑海里就会想起那个男人。”

比夫摊开两只手掌：“你就是这样。”

钟表敲了两下。屋里密闭而闷热。巴比又在打过蜡的地板上做了一个前手翻和劈叉。然后，比夫把她抱到腿上，她的两条小小的腿垂在他的小腿上。她解开他的坎肩，把脸埋了进去。

“听着，”露西尔说，“我问你一个问题，你能保证跟我说实话吗？”

“当然。”

“无论什么问题？”

比夫摸了摸巴比柔软的金发，把手温柔地放在她的小脑袋两侧。“当然。”

“大概是七年前的事了。那时候，我们刚刚第一次结婚。有天晚上，他从你那里回来，头上全是大包。他跟我说，是你抓住他的脖子把他的脑袋往墙上猛撞。至于你为什么这么干，他编了个故事，但我想知道真实的原因。”

比夫转动着手指上的婚戒。“我从来就没真正喜欢过勒罗伊，那次我俩打了一架，那时候我跟现在不一样。”

“不对，你之所以那么干，肯定有原因。我们认识都那么长时间了，现在我已经明白，你无论做什么事都有原因。你的大脑不是单凭冲动行事，而是靠理性。喏，你刚才答应会告诉我真相，我想知道。”

“现在都不重要了。”

“我跟你说了，我必须要知道。”

“好吧。”比夫说，“那天晚上，他走进来，开始喝酒，喝醉了便大放厥词。他说，他一个月回家一次，然后会把你痛打一顿，你总是默默忍受着。过后你会走到外面走廊里，大笑好几次，这样其他屋里的邻居们便会以为你俩只是在玩闹，开玩笑而已。就是这么回事，所以别再纠结这件事了。”

露西尔坐直身子，两颊上各出现了一团红晕。“你瞧，巴塞洛缪，这就是我为什么必须得像一直戴着眼罩一样，才不会想起过去，才不会胡思乱想。我把全部心思都放在每天上班、照顾好家里的一日三餐上，还要照顾好巴比的事业。”

“是的。”

“我希望你也会这样，别去回忆过去。”

比夫把头垂到胸前，闭上眼睛。整整一天了，他都没有想起爱丽丝。他努力要想起她的音容笑貌，脑海里却是一片奇怪的空白。关于她，他脑子里唯一清晰的印象就是她的一双脚——粗短，柔软，白皙，长着胖乎乎的脚指头，脚底是粉色的，靠近左脚跟的地方有个很小的褐色的痣。他们结婚的那天晚上，他脱掉她的鞋袜，吻了她的脚。现在想来，这倒值得好好想想，因为日本人认为一个女人身上最精美的部分——

比夫动了一下，瞥了一眼手表。再过一小会儿，他们就要出发去教堂了，葬礼在那里举行。他在脑海里过了一遍葬礼的所有环节。教堂——和露西尔、巴比一起坐着车，跟在灵车后面，缓慢而沉痛——一群人站着，在九月的阳光下低着头。太阳照在白色的墓碑上，照在枯萎的鲜花上，还照在新挖坟墓上面盖着的帆布上。然后，又回到家中——然后呢？

“不管怎么吵，亲姐妹之间还是有感情的。”露西尔说。

比夫抬起头。“你为什么不再婚呢？找个没结过婚的出色年轻人照顾你和巴比？如果你忘掉勒罗伊，你会找个好男人，做个好妻子。”

露西尔迟迟没有回答，最后说道：“你清楚我们两人之间的情况——一直以来，我们对彼此都非常了解，不必有任何令人心跳的杂念。嗯，我跟男人最多也只能到这种亲密程度了。”

“我有同感。”比夫说。

半小时后，有人敲门。为葬礼而备的车已经停在了家门前。比夫和露西尔慢慢站了起来，巴比穿着白色丝绸小裙子走在他们前面，三人在一种肃穆的沉默中走到外面。

第二天，比夫的餐馆还是没有开门。

傍晚时分，他把枯萎的百合花花环从前门取了下来，打开门，重新开始营业。老顾客们走进来，脸上带着悲伤的表情，会在收银机前跟他聊上几句，然后开始点餐。以前的那群人都来了——辛格、布朗特，还有在这条街其他店里干活儿或者在河边工厂上班的各色男人。晚饭过后，米克·凯利带着她的小弟弟来了，把一枚五分硬币投进老虎机。第一枚硬币被吞了之后，她用两只拳头砰砰猛砸机器，不断地打开出口，确认没有任何东西出来。然后，她又放进去一枚五分硬币，差一点中了头奖，硬币哗啦啦淌出来，滚到了地上。米克和小弟弟一边捡硬币，一边警惕地望着四周，以免有顾客趁他们还没来得及捡便拿脚踩住硬币。哑巴坐在屋子中央的一张桌子前，面前摆着晚饭。辛格对面坐着杰克·布朗特，布朗特穿着他最好的衣服，一边喝啤酒一边聊天。一切都跟以前一模一样。过了一会儿，空气中开始烟雾缭绕，嘈杂声四起。比夫很警觉，所有的声音和动作都逃不过他的眼睛。

“我四处走。”布朗特说着，热切地从桌子上俯过身子，眼睛一直盯着哑巴的脸，“我四处走，想要告诉他们，但他们哄堂大笑。我没法让他们明白任何事情，无论我说什么，就是不能让他们明白真相。”

辛格点点头，用餐巾擦擦嘴巴。他的晚饭已经凉了，因为他无法得空吃饭，但他非常礼貌，任布朗特继续说下去。

在男人们的粗大嗓门中，老虎机旁边两个孩子的说话声音很大，很清晰。米克正在把那些五分硬币塞回老虎机里。她不时朝中央的餐桌望一眼，但哑巴一直背对着她，并没有看见。

“辛格先生晚饭点了炸鸡，但他一块都没有吃完。”小男孩说。

米克慢慢拉下机器的手柄。“少管闲事。”

“你总是到他房间去，或者到你知道他会去的地方。”

“我让你闭嘴，巴伯·凯利。”

“你就是这样。”

米克使劲晃着他，晃得他牙齿咔嗒作响，然后让他转身对着门口。“你赶紧回家睡觉。我早就告诉过你，我白天就已经受够了你和拉尔夫，晚上我好不容易自由了，不想让你还在我身边转悠。”

巴伯伸出满是污垢的小手。“嗯，那给我五分钱吧。”他把钱装进衬衫口袋，回家去了。

比夫拽拽外套，向后拢了一下头发。他的领带是纯黑的，灰色外套的袖子上还有他亲手缝上的黑纱。他很想走到老虎机旁边，跟米克聊聊天，但有什么东西就是阻止他去。他猛地深吸一口气，喝了一杯水。收音机里传来舞会交响乐，他却并不想听。过去十年中，所有的音乐都差不多，他几乎分不清楚。自一九二八年以来，他就不欣赏音乐了，但他年轻的时候弹过曼陀林，熟悉当时每首流行歌曲的歌词和旋律。

他把一根手指放在鼻子一侧，头歪向一边。过去一年里，米克长大了很多，身高很快就要超过他了。她穿着红色毛衣和蓝色百褶裙，自从开学以来，她每天都穿这身衣服。现在，裙子上的褶皱都开了，褶边松松垮垮地拖在她尖瘦而突出的膝盖上。她这个年龄，看上去既像个女孩又像个长得过快的男孩。说到这里，为什么最聪明的人几乎都忽视了这一点呢？所有人生来都是双性的，因此，婚姻和床绝不是生活的全部。证据？看看真正的青年人和老年人。老年男性的声音会变得高而尖细，走起路来都迈着小碎步。而老年女性则有时候会变胖，声音会变得粗哑低沉，还会长出黑黑的小胡子。他自己甚至也是个证据——有时候，他心里有一部分希望自己是个母亲，希望米克和巴比是他的孩子。比夫猛然从收银机那里转过身来。

那些报纸乱七八糟。两个星期了，他没有整理过一张报纸。他从柜台底下拿起一摞报纸，熟练地从上面扫到最底部。明天他要仔细看看后屋里那一摞摞报纸，看能不能改变一下归档的方式，打几个架子，用那些装运罐头的结实箱子做几个抽屉。时间上，从一九一八年十月二十七日一直到今天，用文件夹整理出来，顶上标记出主要的历史事件。三种不同的标记方法——第一种是标注国际事件，从停战协议一直到慕尼黑事件；第二种是标注国内事件；第三种标注地方新闻，从莱斯特市长在乡村俱乐部射杀妻子到哈德逊工厂的大火。过去二十年所有的新闻，他都做了摘要，列了目录，非常完整。比夫用手搓着下巴，暗自眉开眼笑。爱丽丝之前一直想让他把那些报纸都清出去，她好把这间屋子改造成女厕所。她不断唠叨这件事。但那一次，他没有听她的。只有那一次。

比夫心平气和、全神贯注地开始详细阅读面前的报纸。他看得很慢，很专注，但出于习惯，他还有一只眼睛警惕着周围的一切。杰克·布朗特还在说话，不时用拳头砸着桌子。哑巴啜着啤酒。米克坐立不安地在收音机周围走来走去，盯着这些客人。比夫认真读着第一张报纸上的每一个字，在页边空白处做了一些笔记。

突然，他抬起头，一脸吃惊的表情，本来张着嘴打哈欠，猛地一下闭上了嘴。收音机里突然开始播放一首老歌，时间可以追溯到他跟爱丽丝订婚的时候。那是《只是一个孩子在暮光中的祈祷》。有个周日，他们坐着有轨电车去老萨迪斯湖，租了一条小船。日落时分，他弹着曼陀林，她唱歌。她戴了一顶水手帽，他用手揽住她的腰，她——爱丽丝——

他内心泛起一阵失落的感觉。比夫把报纸叠好，重新放到柜台底下。他站在那里，重心先是放在一条腿上，然后挪到另一条腿。最后，他冲着房间那端的米克大喊：“你没在听收音机吗？”

米克关掉收音机。“没有，今晚没什么好听的。”

所有这些他都不在意，他的注意力要放到另外一件事上。他伏在柜台上，望着一个又一个的顾客，最后注意力落在中间桌子前那个哑巴的身上。他看见米克慢慢挪过去，在哑巴的邀请下坐了下来。辛格指着菜单上的某个地方，然后女招待给她端来一杯可口可乐。只有像聋哑人一样的怪物，与其他人隔绝的人，才会邀请一个年轻女孩一起坐到他跟另一个男人喝酒的桌上来。布朗特和米克都盯着辛格。他们说着话，哑巴望着他们时脸上的表情也在变化。这是件很滑稽的事情。原因——是他们的原因还是他的原因？他坐得笔直，双手插在口袋里，因为他不说话，所以显出很优越的样子。那个家伙在想什么？明白了什么？他知道什么？

那天晚上，比夫有两次想要走到中间那张桌子跟前，但每次又都停住了。他们走了以后，他还在想这个哑巴身上到底有什么东西——凌晨时分，他躺在床上，把问题和答案在脑子里翻来覆去地考虑，他却都不满意。这个谜在他心里生了根，让他在脑海深处困扰不已，让他坐立不安。有什么地方不对头。

3

科普兰医生跟辛格先生聊了很多次。的确，他跟其他白人不一样。他是个睿智的人，他理解那种强烈、真实的使命感，这是其他白人所不能理解的。他懂得倾听，脸上有种温和的东西，像犹太人，他理解一个属于受压迫民族的人。有一次他带着辛格先生一起去巡诊，领他穿过冰冷狭窄的通道，那里散发着尘土、疾病和炸肥肉的味道。他给他看了为一个女病人做得非常成功的植皮手术，这位女病人此前脸部烧伤严重。他治疗过一个患梅毒的孩子，他指给辛格先生看孩子手心大量的鳞屑、暗淡无光的眼球，还有歪斜的上门牙。他们看了那些只有两间屋子的窝棚，里面却住了十二或十四个人。在一处房子里，炉膛里的火很微弱，发出昏黄的光，一位老人因为患了肺炎，几乎喘不过气来，他们却无能为力。辛格先生跟在他身后，观察着，理解着。他给了孩子们几枚五分硬币，他既安静又得体，所以不会像其他访客那样打扰到病人。

天气寒冷，变化无常。镇上爆发了流感，科普兰医生夜以继日地忙碌着。他开车穿梭在镇上的黑人区，那辆高大的道奇车他已经用了九年。他把鱼胶做的窗帘拉得严严实实，好挡住冷风，自己脖子上则紧紧围着那条灰色的羊毛围巾。这段时间他没见到波西娅、威廉和海博埃，却经常会想起他们。有一次，他不在家，波西娅来看他，留了张便条，借走了半袋子粗面粉。

有天晚上，他筋疲力尽，尽管还有一些病人要看，但他还是喝了杯热牛奶便上床睡觉了。他很冷，有点发烧，所以一开始没法入睡。后来，他似乎刚要入睡，突然有个声音喊他。他疲惫地起来，穿着法兰绒长睡衣，打开了前门。是波西娅。

“上帝帮帮我们，父亲。”她说。

科普兰医生站在那里打着哆嗦，睡衣紧紧裹住腰部。他用手摸着喉咙，看着她，等她继续说。

“是我们的威利，他是个坏小子，惹上了大麻烦，我们得做点什么。”

科普兰医生迈着僵硬的步子从走廊里走回来，在卧室停下，找到睡袍、围巾和拖鞋，又回到厨房。波西娅在那里等着他。厨房里冰冷一片，毫无生气。

“好吧，他干了什么？怎么回事？”

“等一下，让我缓缓神，这样才可以理出头绪，跟你说清楚。”

他压了压躺在炉膛里的几张报纸，捡起几块引火柴。

“我来生火吧。”波西娅说，“你到桌子跟前坐下，等炉子着起来，我们喝杯咖啡。也许，一切就不会这么糟糕了。”

“没有咖啡了，我昨天喝完了。”

他说完这话，波西娅哭了起来。她狠狠地把纸和木头塞进炉子里，手哆嗦着，点着火。“是这么回事，”她说，“威利和海博埃今晚在一个地方瞎逛，并没有什么正经事。你知道我为什么总是感觉得让威利和海博埃在我眼前了吗？嗯，如果当时我在场，就不会惹上这种麻烦。但我到教堂参加姐妹聚会去了，这两个男生就坐立不安了。他们去了丽巴夫人开的‘甜蜜快乐宫’。父亲，这肯定是个下流邪恶的地方。有个男人在那儿卖票——但是，他们也有那些趾高气扬、卑鄙下流、搔首弄姿的黑人姑娘，还有那些红绸缎窗帘，还有——”

“女儿，”科普兰医生两只手按住脑袋两侧，急躁地说，“我知道那个地方，说重点。”

“拉芙·琼斯也在那里——她是个下流的黑人女孩。威利喝了酒，绕着她扭来扭去地跳舞。紧接着，你知道，他跟别人打了起来，跟他打架的那个男孩叫朱伯格——为了拉芙打了起来。他们空手打了一阵子，然后这个朱伯格拿出了刀子。我们威利没有刀子，所以他开始一边喊一边绕着大厅跑。最后，海博埃给威利找了一片剃须刀片，他返回身差点把朱伯格的脑袋割下来。”

科普兰医生把围巾在身上裹得更紧了。“他死了吗？”

“那个男孩太坏了，不会死的。他在医院，但很快就会出来接着惹事。”

“威廉呢？”

“警察过来用囚车把他送进了监狱，还在里面关着。”

“他没受伤吧？”

“哦，他一只眼睛破了，屁股上被割掉了一小块肉，但对他来说没多大关系。我不明白，他为什么要跟那个拉芙搞在一起。她比我还要黑十倍，是我见过的最丑的黑人。她走起路来像是两条腿中间夹了个鸡蛋怕打破似的，而且她也不干净。这次威利居然因为她把自己屁股都割伤了。”

科普兰医生斜过身子，靠近火炉，痛苦地呻吟着。他咳嗽起来，脸部变得僵硬。他把纸巾捂到嘴上，上面喷了斑斑点点的血迹。他脸上的黑色皮肤呈现出有些发绿的苍白。

“当然，这件事一发生，海博埃便跑来告诉了我。要明白，我的海博埃跟这些下流女孩没有任何关系，他只是跟威利做伴。他很为威利伤心，后来一直坐在监狱前面的马路边上。”泪水映着火光，从波西娅的脸上滚落下来，“你知道我们三个人一直以来都是什么样子，我们有自己的打算，以前从来没出过差错，即便在钱的方面，我们也没有问题。海博埃付房租，我买吃的——威利负责星期六晚上的花销，我们一直像三胞胎一样。”

终于，天亮了。工厂的哨声响起来，第一班工人上班了。太阳出来了，照亮了炉子上方挂在墙上的那个干净的平底锅。他们坐了很长时间。波西娅一直拽着她的耳环，最后耳垂都拽疼了，变成了紫红色。科普兰医生仍然用双手捂着头。

“我觉得，”终于，波西娅说，“我们如果能让很多白人写信为威利求情，也许会有点用。我已经见过布兰农先生了，他已经照我说的写了信。事情发生以后，他像以前一样，晚上还在咖啡馆，所以我去了那里，跟他解释了这件事。我把那封信带回家了，放在《圣经》里，这样就不会弄丢，也不会弄脏了。”

“信上说了些什么？”

“布兰农先生完全按照我说的写了信。信上说，威利过去三年一直在为布兰农先生工作，还说威利是个正直的黑人男孩，以前从来没惹过麻烦。还说，他在咖啡馆有很多机会可以拿东西，但他跟其他一些黑人男孩不一样，还有——”

“哼！”科普兰医生说，“这些都没用。”

“但我们不能只坐在这里等啊，威利还关在监狱里。我的威利，即便他今晚真的干了坏事，他仍然是个贴心的男孩，我们不能只坐在这里等。”

“我们只能等，别的什么也做不了。”

“嗯，我觉得我不能只坐在这里等。”

波西娅从椅子上站起来，心烦意乱地扫视着屋子四周，好像在找什么东西。突然，她走向前门。

“等等，”科普兰医生说，“你现在要去哪儿？”

“我去上班。我一定得保住我的工作，一定还得给凯利夫人干活儿，这样每星期能拿到一笔工资。”

“我想去监狱看看。”科普兰医生说，“也许我可以见到威廉。”

“我上班路上要顺便去监狱一趟，我还得送海博埃去上班——否则，他会一早晨都坐在那里为威利难过。”

科普兰医生迅速穿好衣服，跟波西娅一起来到走廊里。他们走进清冷蔚蓝的秋日早晨。监狱里的人对他们很粗鲁，他们并没有得到什么有用的消息。科普兰医生去咨询以前打过交道的一位律师。接下去的几天，日子很漫长，他们充满了焦虑。到了第三周，威廉的案子开庭了。他被认定犯持致命武器伤人罪，被判九个月的劳教，并立即被送往本州北部的一座监狱。

即便现在，科普兰医生心里仍然有那种强烈的真正使命感，但他没有时间去思考这件事了。他走街串巷，无休无止地工作。一大早他便开车离开家，十一点，病人们陆续来到他的办公室里。从外面寒冷的秋天空气里走进来，屋子里那种闷热腐败的味道让他咳个不停。走廊里的长凳上总是坐满了生病的黑人，他们耐心地等着见他，有时候甚至前面门廊和他的卧室都挤满了病人。他会忙整整一天，经常还要忙到半夜。他觉得非常疲倦，有时候真想躺到地上，用拳头捶地恸哭一场。如果能好好休息，他也许会好起来。他患上了肺结核，每天给自己量四次体温，每月去做一次X光透视。然而他没法休息，因为还有一件事比他的疲倦重要多了——那种强烈的真正的使命感。

他总是一直想着这种使命感，但有时候，不分白天黑夜地工作了漫长的一天之后，他的脑子里会一片空白。这时候，他会暂时忘却这种使命到底是什么，过后它又会回到他的脑海中，让他坐卧不宁，迫不及待地要去接受新任务。但那些话经常会卡在喉咙里说不出口，他的声音也比以前粗哑低沉了。他把这些话倾诉给那些生病的黑人同胞听。

他经常跟辛格先生交谈。他跟他谈化学，谈宇宙的神秘，谈微小的精子，成熟的卵子的分裂，谈细胞复杂的百万倍分裂，谈生物的奥秘和死亡的简单。此外，他也会跟他谈种族。

“我的同胞们是从大平原、从郁郁葱葱的密林里被带到了这里。”有一次，他对辛格先生说，“他们戴着锁链，一路被拉到海边，路上死掉了数以千计的人，只有最强壮的才活了下来。这些幸存者又戴着锁链被拉到恶臭的船上，被带到这里来，路上又死掉了无数人，只有那些意志坚强的黑人才能够活下来。他们遭受毒打，拴着锁链，被拉到街上买卖，这些坚强的人里面的弱者又死掉了。终于，经过这么多年的磨难，我的同胞当中那些最强者依然生活在这里，还有他们的儿女、子孙、子子孙孙。”

“我来借东西，还要求您帮个忙。”波西娅说。

科普兰医生一个人待在厨房，这时波西娅穿过走廊，站在门口对他说道。威廉已经被带走了两个星期，波西娅变了模样。她的头发不再抹油，也不像往常梳得那么整洁，她两眼充血，好像喝了烈性酒一样。她的双颊凹陷，蜜色脸上带着悲伤，现在她真的很像她的母亲。

“您记得那些漂亮的白色盘子和杯子吗？”

“你可以拿走，留着吧。”

“不，我只想借用一下。还有，我过来是想请您帮个忙。”

“尽管说。”科普兰医生说。

波西娅坐到父亲的对面。“首先，我觉得最好解释一下。昨天，我收到了外公捎来的口信，说他们明天都要来，和我们待一个晚上还有星期天的部分时间。他们很担心威利，外公觉得我们都应该再聚聚。他说得对。我也特别想再见见我们的家人，自从威利走了以后，我非常想家。”

“去找找看，可以把那些盘子什么的都拿走。”科普兰医生说，“把你的肩膀挺起来，女儿，你的仪态很糟糕。”

“这次我们要来个真正的大团圆。你知道，这是二十年来外公第一次到镇上来过夜，他这辈子只在外面过了两次夜。不管怎么样，他一到晚上就有点紧张，夜里他得起来喝水，得看看孩子们是否盖得严实，是否一切都好。我有点担心，不知道外公在这里会不会舒服。”

“我这里的东西，只要你觉得需要——”

“当然，李·杰克逊会拉他们过来。”波西娅说，“李·杰克逊拉着他们，恐怕要走一整天才能到这里。我觉得他们到晚饭时才能到。当然，外公对李·杰克逊一直很有耐心，不会催他。”

“我的天！那头老骡子还没死吗？它应该足足十八岁了。”

“不止十八岁。外公使唤它已经二十年了。那头骡子跟了他那么长时间，他总是说李·杰克逊就像他的亲人一样。他对李·杰克逊的理解和关心就像对自己的亲生孙辈一样。我从来没见过有人像外公那样，那么懂得一头牲口的想法，他对所有能走路、会吃饭的东西都有一种亲近感。”

“使唤一头骡子二十年，这时间可不短。”

“的确是这样。现在，李·杰克逊已经很虚弱了，但外公真的把它照顾得很好。他们在外面炽热的太阳底下犁地时，李·杰克逊像外公一样头上也戴着顶宽大的草帽——有两个洞可以露出耳朵。那只骡子的草帽太好笑了，犁地的时候，李·杰克逊的头上如果没戴那顶草帽，它一步都不会迈。”

科普兰医生从架子上拿下那些白瓷盘，动手用报纸把它们包起来。“要做那么多饭，你的炒锅和平底锅够吗？”

“我有很多锅。”波西娅说，“我不用特别费心。外公是位体贴的先生——家人一起吃饭的时候，他总会带些东西来帮忙。我只需要准备足够的粗面粉、卷心菜，还有两磅新鲜的鲻鱼。”

“听上去不错。”

波西娅紧张地把蜜色的手指交叉在一起。“有件事，我还没有告诉您，一个惊喜。巴迪和汉密尔顿都要来。巴迪刚从莫比尔回来，现在在农场上帮忙。”

“我已经五年没见卡尔·马克思了。”

“我今天来，就是为这件事。”波西娅说，“您记得我刚进来的时候跟您说过，我来借东西，而且还要求您帮个忙。”

科普兰医生把手指关节掰得咔咔作响。“记得。”

“嗯，我来看看能不能请您也参加明天的团聚。除了威利，您的孩子们都去，我觉得您应该跟我们一起团聚。如果您能来，我真的特别高兴。”

汉密尔顿、卡尔·马克思、波西娅——还有威廉。科普兰医生摘下眼镜，用手指压着眼皮。一瞬间，他清晰地看见了他们四个人的样子，很久以前的样子。然后他抬起头，把眼镜在鼻子上架好。“谢谢。”他说，“我去。”

那天晚上，他独自坐在火炉旁，在黑乎乎的屋子里回想着往事。他想起自己的童年时代。他的妈妈生来就是奴隶，获得自由后靠给别人洗衣服为生。他的父亲是名牧师，曾经见过约翰·布朗[14]。他们教他学知识，他们每周赚两三块钱，省吃俭用。他十七岁那年，他们把八十块钱藏在他的鞋子里，将他送到了北方。他在铁匠铺里干过活儿，做过服务生，在旅馆当过行李员。但自始至终，他一直坚持学习、读书、上学。他父亲死了，之后母亲也没活多久。经过十年的奋斗之后，他成为一名医生，深知自己的使命，于是他又回到了南方。

他结婚成家，无休止地走街串巷，给人们传递着使命和真理。他的同胞所遭受的那种无望的磨难让他发狂，带给他一种疯狂邪恶的摧毁感。有时候，他喝烈性酒，把头向地板上撞，他的心里有一种野蛮的暴力。有一次，他一把抓起炉膛里的拨火棍，把妻子打倒在地。她带着汉密尔顿、卡尔·马克思、威廉和波西娅回了她父亲家。他在心里挣扎着，拼命压下这种阴郁邪恶。然而，黛西再也没有回到他身边。八年后，她死了，他的儿子们都长大成人，也没有一个回来看他。他成了一位老人，独自住在一幢空荡荡的房子里。

第二天下午五点，他准时来到波西娅和海博埃住的地方。他们住的那片地方叫糖山，房子十分狭窄，有门廊，还有两个房间。屋里传来嘈杂的说话声。科普兰医生很拘谨地走近房子，手里抓着那顶破毡帽站在门口。

屋里很挤，起初没人注意到他。他搜寻着卡尔·马克思和汉密尔顿的面孔。外公就在他们身边，地上还坐着两个孩子。他一直盯着儿子们的脸看，这时波西娅发现了他站在门口。

“父亲来了。”她说。

所有的声音戛然而止。外公在椅子上转过身来。他很瘦，驼背，满脸皱纹，身上依然穿着那件墨绿色西装，背心上斜搭着一条褪了色的铜表链。三十年前，在女儿婚礼上他穿的就是这件衣服。卡尔·马克思和汉密尔顿先是看看对方，然后盯着地板，最后才望向他们的父亲。

“本尼迪克特·马迪——”老人说，“很久不见，真的很久不见了。”

“可不是嘛！”波西娅说，“我们今天是这么多年来第一次团聚。海博埃，去厨房搬把椅子来。父亲，巴迪和汉密尔顿在这里。”

科普兰医生跟两个儿子握了握手。他俩都又高又壮，有点局促不安。他们穿着蓝衬衫和工装裤，皮肤跟波西娅一样，透出一种饱满的棕色。他俩没有直视他的眼睛，脸上的表情既不是爱也不是恨。

“还有人来不了，太可惜了——萨拉姨妈、吉姆，还有其他人。”海博埃说，“但我们已经很开心了。”

“骡车太挤了。”一个孩子说，“我们不得不走了很长一段路，骡车实在太挤了。”

外公用一根火柴掏着耳朵。“总得有人留下看家。”

波西娅紧张地舔着薄薄的深色嘴唇。“我一直想我们的威利，无论什么聚会或热闹，他都积极参加，我脑子里总是想着我们的威利。”

房间里，大家低声附和。老人向后靠在椅子上，点着头。“波西娅，宝贝，你给我们念点《圣经》吧。遇上麻烦的时候，上帝的话肯定很管用。”

波西娅从房间中央的桌子上拿起《圣经》。“你现在想听哪段，外公？”

“只要是上帝的书就可以，翻到哪里就念哪里吧，都可以。”

波西娅开始念《路加福音》。她念得很慢，用修长纤弱的手指挨个指着所读的字。房间里很安静。科普兰医生坐在一群人的边上，咔咔地掰着自己的指关节，眼神从一个地方飘到另一个地方。房间很小，空气密闭，流通不畅，四面墙上凌乱地挂满日历和杂志上撕下来的广告，都印刷得粗糙不堪。壁炉台上有个花瓶，插着纸做的红玫瑰。炉膛里的火着得很慢，油灯灯光摇曳，在墙上投下各种影子。波西娅读得很慢，抑扬顿挫，那些话好像是在科普兰医生的耳朵里睡着了，让他也昏昏欲睡。卡尔·马克思四仰八叉地躺在两个孩子旁边，汉密尔顿和海博埃也打着瞌睡，似乎只有老人在细细品味这些话的意思。

波西娅念完一章，把书合上。

“这件事，我仔细考虑过很多次。”外公说。

屋里的人全都从混沌中清醒过来。“什么事？”波西娅问道。

“是这样。你们记得那些内容吗？耶稣救死扶伤？”

“当然记得，先生。”海博埃恭敬地答道。

“很多时候，我犁着地或干着活儿的时候，”外公慢悠悠地说，“我一直在想，耶稣什么时候能再次降生到地球上，因为我一直都盼望着耶稣再次降临，所以我觉得死之前应该还能看到。这件事我仔细研究了很多次，我是这么打算的。我想着，我会带着所有的孩子、孙辈、曾孙辈、亲戚和朋友都站到耶稣面前。我会对他说：‘基督耶稣，我们都是可怜的黑人。’然后他会把圣手放在我们头上，我们立刻就会变得雪白。这个打算，这种念头，我已经想了很多很多次了。”

房间里一片沉默。科普兰医生抖了抖袖口，清了清嗓子。他的脉搏跳得非常快，喉咙发紧。他坐在房间角落里，感到一种孤立、愤怒和孤单。

“你们当中，有没有人接到过上天的启示？”外公问。

“我有过。”海博埃说，“有一次，我得了肺炎，我看见上帝的面孔从壁炉里看着我。那是一张硕大的白人面孔，长着白胡子和蓝眼睛。”

“我见过鬼。”一个孩子说，是个女孩。

“有一次我看见——”小男孩也开口说。

外公举起一只手。“你们小孩子闭嘴。你，西莉亚——还有你，惠特曼——现在，到了你们‘只许听不许说’的时候了。”他说，“只有一次，我得到了真正的启示。事情是这样的。那是去年夏天，天气很热，我正在猪圈旁边刨那棵大橡树根。我弯腰的时候，突然感觉后腰疼得厉害。我直起腰，周围一片漆黑。我用手捂着后腰，抬头望着天空，突然看见了那个小天使，是个白人小女孩天使——我觉得也就紫花豌豆那么大——头发是黄色的，穿着白长袍，就在太阳周围飞来飞去，然后我就进屋祈祷。我一连研究了三天《圣经》，后来才又出门到地里干活儿。”

科普兰医生觉得，心头又涌上那种熟悉的邪恶的愤怒，有些话涌上嘴边，却说不出来。他们都会听老人的，对于理性的话语他们却不会在意。这些都是我的家人，他努力说服自己——但因为他一言不发，这个想法现在对他并没有什么用处。他坐在那里，很紧张，闷闷不乐。

“这件事很奇怪。”外公突然说，“本尼迪克特·马迪，你是个好医生。有时候，我刨一阵子地或者种一阵子庄稼以后，后腰怎么会疼呢？为什么一直都有这个毛病？”

“您现在多大年纪了？”

“七八十岁吧。”

老人很喜欢药物和治疗。以前他跟家人来看黛西时，总是要检查检查身体，然后给全家人都带一些药和药膏回去。自从黛西离开他之后，老人就不再来了，只能用报纸广告里的泻药和肾丸聊以自慰。现在，老人望着他，眼里带着一种怯怯的渴望。

“多喝水。”科普兰医生说，“还要尽可能多休息。”

波西娅走进厨房准备晚饭，温暖的味道在屋子里弥散开来。人们安静地闲聊着，科普兰医生却没在听，也不说话。他不时地看一眼卡尔·马克思，或者汉密尔顿。卡尔·马克思在说乔·路易斯，汉密尔顿则大部分时间在说那场毁了很多庄稼的冰雹。他们碰到父亲的目光时会咧嘴一笑，拿脚在地上蹭着地板。他一直盯着他们，又生气又悲伤。

科普兰医生紧咬牙关。他一直想着汉密尔顿、卡尔·马克思、威廉和波西娅，想着他赋予他们的真正使命。他想得太多了，以至于一看到他们的面孔，他的心里便会涌上一种阴郁的感觉。如果他能再一次给他们讲讲这些事，从远古的开头一直讲到今天晚上，讲完这些也许会缓解他心头的这种刺痛。然而，他们不会听，也不会懂。

他硬下心来，身体的每一块肌肉都僵硬而紧张。周围的一切，他并没有听，也没有看。他坐在角落里，就像一个又聋又哑的人。很快，他们走到晚饭桌前就座，老人做了饭前祷告，但科普兰医生什么也没吃。海博埃拿出一瓶一品脱的杜松子酒，他们大笑着，传递着瓶子一口口地喝酒，他也不喝。他坐在那里，沉默着。最后他拿起帽子，没有道别便走出了那所房子。他如果不能说出所有那些冗长的真相，那么，他无话可说。

一整夜他都紧张地躺在床上，无法入睡。第二天是周日，他去看了五六个病人。半晌午的时候，他去了辛格先生的房间。这次拜访缓解了他心头的孤独感，道别时，他又可以跟自己和平相处了。

然而，还未及出门，这种平和便消失了。发生了一场意外。他下楼梯时，看见一个白人扛着一个大纸袋子，于是他紧贴栏杆扶手，这样可以让他俩错身而过。但这个白人正两步并作一步跑着奔上楼梯，看都没看，结果跟他重重地撞在了一起。科普兰医生被撞得有些恶心，险些喘不过气来。

“上帝！我没看见你。”

科普兰医生仔细看着他，没有回答。他以前见过这个白人，想起他身材矮小、野蛮残暴的样子，还有那双笨拙的大手。他突然带着一种临床的兴趣观察着白人男子的面容，在白人男子的眼睛里，他看到了一种奇怪的、固执的、孤僻的疯狂表情。

“对不起。”白人男子说。

科普兰医生抓住栏杆，从他身边走了过去。

4

“那人是谁啊？”杰克·布朗特问道，“刚从这里出去的那个瘦高个儿的黑人是谁啊？”

小房间里非常整洁。太阳照亮了桌上放的一碗紫色葡萄，辛格坐在那里，椅子稍微后倾，双手插在口袋里，望着窗外。

“我在楼梯上跟他撞在一起，他用那副眼神看着我——哎呀，从来没有人那么恶狠狠地看着我。”

杰克把那袋麦芽啤酒放在桌上。他惊奇地意识到，辛格并不知道他进屋了。他走到窗前，碰了碰辛格的肩膀。

“我不是故意撞到他的，他没有理由那么对我。”

杰克打了个哆嗦。尽管阳光灿烂，但屋里仍有种寒意。辛格举起食指，走到走廊里。回来时，他拿来一筐煤，还有一些引火柴。杰克望着他跪在炉膛前，熟练地把引火柴在膝盖上折断，摆放在铺好的纸上，又把煤块仔细地在上面排好。起初，火就是着不起来，火焰无力地摇晃着，然后熄灭了，冒出一阵黑烟。辛格在炉箅上铺上两层报纸。风让火重新活了起来，房间里响起呼呼的声音，报纸冒出火光，被火焰吞噬了，炉箅上满是噼啪作响的橘黄色火焰。

早晨的第一杯麦芽啤酒有一种上好的醇香味道。杰克很快将自己的酒大口喝完，然后用锉刀一样的手背抹了抹嘴巴。

“很久以前，我认识一位女士，”他说，“你有点让我想到她，克拉拉小姐。她在得克萨斯有个小农场，也做果仁糖到城里去卖。她又高又壮，长得很好看，穿着肥肥大大的长毛衣、土包子鞋，戴顶男人帽子。我认识她的时候，她丈夫已经死了，但我想说的意思是，如果不是因为她，我可能永远不会知道。我也许会跟数以百万计的不知道的那些人一样，继续过着生活。也许只能是个牧师，或者纺织工，或者推销员，也许我的一辈子就那么浪费掉了。”

杰克惊奇地摇摇头。

“要想听明白，你就必须得知道我以前的事情。你瞧，年轻时我住在加斯托尼亚。那时候我是个八字脚的小矮子，太小了，没法进工厂，只能去一家保龄球馆当球童，只管饭，没有工资。后来，我听说，离那儿不远有个反应灵敏的聪明男孩串烟叶，一天可以赚三毛钱。于是我就去了，去赚每天三毛钱的工钱，那时候我十岁。我就那么离开了家人，连封信都不写。我走了，他们其实很高兴，你明白那是怎么回事。再说，除了我姐姐，家里没人会看信。”

他在空中挥舞着一只手，仿佛要从脸上抹走什么东西。“但我的意思是，我最初信仰耶稣。有个家伙跟我在一个地方干活儿，他有个礼拜堂，每天晚上都去祷告。我也去了，听着听着便也有了这个信仰。我的心思一整天都放在耶稣身上，有空的时候我便研究《圣经》，祈祷。后来，有天晚上，我拿了把锤子，然后把手放在桌子上。我很愤怒，把钉子一直砸进手掌。我的手被钉在了桌子上，我望着它，手指颤动着，变成了青色。”

杰克伸出手掌，指着手心那个粗糙苍白的伤疤。

“我想当个福音传教士，想在这个国家四处周游，一边布道一边组织复兴会。同时，我从一个地方搬到另一个地方，快二十岁那年，我去了得克萨斯。我在一个山核桃果园干活儿，离克拉拉小姐住的地方非常近。我慢慢认识了她，有时候晚上会去她家，她跟我聊天。一定要明白，我不是一开始就什么都知道的，我们所有人都是这样，这个过程是逐渐发生的。我开始读书。我继续干活儿，这样就可以攒下钱，休息一阵子，可以学习，这就像重生一样。只有我们这些知道的人才能够理解这是什么意思。我们已经睁开了眼睛，可以看见了。我们这些人，就像来自遥远的地方一样。”

辛格同意他的说法。房间里很舒服，像家一样。辛格从壁橱里拿出一个铁盒子，里面放着饼干、水果和奶酪。他挑了一只橘子，慢慢剥开皮，又扯掉一缕缕的橘络，最后这只橘子在阳光下变成了透明的。他把橘子掰开，两人分着吃。杰克一口吃掉了两瓣橘子，噗的一下把果核吐进炉火中。辛格慢慢吃着自己的那一份，把种子整整齐齐地摆放在一只手的手心。他们又开了两瓶麦芽啤酒。

“在这个国家，像我们这样的人有多少？也许一万，也许两万，也许还要多。我去过很多地方，但像我们这样的人，我只遇到过几个。但是，比如说，一个人的确知道。他看到了这个世界的本质，回顾几千年前，明白这一切是怎么发生的。他观察着资本和权力缓慢积累，看到这种积累在今天达到顶点。他把美国看成一座疯人院。他看到人们为了活下去是如何被迫剥削自己的兄弟。他看到孩子几乎要饿死，看到女人每周要干六十个小时的活儿才能有口饭吃。他看到很多人失业，看到几十亿美元、几千英里土地被浪费掉。他看到战争来临。他看到人们遭受到艰苦磨难时会怎样变得刻薄丑陋，看到他们身上的一种东西是怎样死去的。然而，他看到的最重要的事情是，整个世界的体制是建立在一个谎言之上的。尽管这个谎言如同耀眼的太阳一样显而易见，但那些不知道的人已经在这个谎言里生活得太久了，他们就是看不见。”

杰克额头上的红色血管因为愤怒突了起来。他抓起炉膛上的煤筐，把煤块哗啦啦全部倒进炉子里。他的脚已经麻木了，他使劲跺着脚，地板都颤动起来。

“这个地方，我都走遍了。我四处走，跟人说话，拼命跟他们解释。但这么做有什么用呢？上帝！”

他盯着炉火，麦芽啤酒让他脸色发红，加上屋里的热气，他的脸更红了。脚上发麻的刺痛感顺着他的腿传上来，他昏昏欲睡，望着炉火的颜色，绿色、蓝色和燃烧的黄色。“你是唯一知道的人，”他精神恍惚地说，“唯一知道的人。”

他不再是个陌生人了。现在，他熟悉镇上大片贫民窟里的每条街道、每条小巷和每处栅栏。他还在迪克西阳光游乐场工作。秋天，游乐场从一块空地搬到另一块空地，但总是在城市的边缘。最后，游乐场转遍了小镇的每一个地方。地方变了，但背景都很相似——一片空地，周围是一排排破烂棚屋，紧靠工厂、轧棉机厂或者装瓶厂。顾客也都一样，大多是工厂的工人和黑人。一到晚上，游乐场的灯五颜六色，很花哨。旋转木马伴着机械音乐转个不停。秋千来回荡着，投硬币游戏周围的栏杆边总是挤满了人。有两个货亭出售饮料、血棕色汉堡和棉花糖。

在这里，他是个机修工，但慢慢地他的职责范围扩大了。他粗声大气的嗓门透过各种噪音大声喊叫着，他不停地在游乐场里到处转悠，额头上冒着汗珠，胡子上沾满啤酒。星期六，他得负责维持秩序。他矮胖结实的身体野蛮地大力挤过人群，只有一双眼睛没有沾染他身上的那种粗鲁暴力，深皱的眉头下面，这双眼睛睁得很大，透出一副孤僻沉默而又心烦意乱的神色。

凌晨十二点到一点之间，他回到家中。他住的房子被隔成了四个房间，每个人的租金是一块五毛钱。后面有间厕所，门廊里有个水龙头。他的房间里，墙壁和地板发出一股潮湿的酸臭味，窗子上挂着乌黑的廉价蕾丝窗帘。他把那身好西装装在袋子里，工装挂在钉子上。房间里没有暖气，也没有电。然而，窗外有一盏街灯亮着，使屋子里呈现一种淡绿色。床边的油灯他从来没点过，除非有时候他想看书。冰冷的房间里，燃烧的油散发出的那种刺鼻味道每每令他觉得恶心。

如果待在家里，他会坐立不安，走来走去。他坐在凌乱的床边，狠命啃着残破肮脏的手指甲，污垢的刺激味道在嘴巴里久留不去。他的孤独感如此强烈，让他满心恐惧。他经常会喝一品脱私酿威士忌，喝完这种原浆酒，他在白天便会觉得温暖而松弛。五点钟，工厂的哨声吹响，是第一班工人上班的时间。哨声制造出迷茫而怪异的回声，在哨声吹完之前，他无论如何都无法入睡。

然而，他通常并不待在家里。他出门，走到狭窄而空荡荡的大街上。在凌晨最初的几个小时里，天空一片漆黑，星星清晰而明亮。有时候，有些工厂还在开工，透着昏黄灯光的建筑物里传出机器的轰鸣声。他在工厂大门口，等待着换早班。穿着毛衣和印花裙的年轻姑娘们从家里出来，走到漆黑的大街上。男人们也出来了，提着饭盒。有些人总是先到一个街车咖啡馆喝杯可乐或咖啡，然后才回家，而杰克会跟他们一起去。在嘈杂的工厂里，人们能清楚地听见别人说的每句话，但从工厂出来的头几小时里，他们的耳朵几乎什么都听不到。

在街车咖啡馆，杰克喝着加了威士忌的可口可乐，跟别人聊天。冬天的清晨很冷，白茫茫一片，烟雾缭绕。他带着醉意的目光，急切地盯着男人们一张张憔悴蜡黄的脸。人们经常会嘲笑他，这时候他总是挺直自己矮小的身体，带着轻蔑的语气说些长而生僻的词。他从酒杯上翘起小拇指，傲慢地绕着自己的胡子。如果人们继续嘲笑他，他有时候会还击。他抡起硕大的褐色拳头，极其狂暴，还会大声地抽泣。

这样的早晨过后，他放松地回到游乐场。在拥挤的人群中挤来挤去，让他觉得很轻松。那些噪音、恶臭的味道，还有跟别人的摩肩接踵，都抚慰着他紧张的神经。

由于镇上实施“蓝法”，游乐场在安息日不营业。星期天，他早晨起床后，从手提箱里拿出那套毛哔叽西装，然后走到主街上。他先是走进纽约咖啡馆，买一袋麦芽啤酒，接着去辛格的房间。镇上的很多人，他尽管都知道名字或觉得脸熟，但只有哑巴是他唯一的朋友。他们会在安静的房间里打发时间，喝喝麦芽啤酒。他总是一直说话，在大街上或房间里独自度过的那些阴沉沉的清晨，他总有很多话要说。想起这些话并且说出来，是一件令人宽慰的事情。

炉火渐渐熄灭了。辛格正在桌前自己跟自己下棋。杰克已经睡着了，突然神经质地抖动一下，醒了过来。他抬起头，转身对着辛格。“是的，”他好像是在回答一个突如其来的问题，“我们有些人是共产主义分子，但并非我们所有人都是——我自己，我不是共产党员。因为，首先我只认识一名共产党员，你到处流浪那么多年，却碰不上共产主义分子。这周围也没有他们的办公室，你也没法过去说你要加入——如果有，我也从来没听说过。而且你也不能突然离开这里去纽约，去加入他们。刚才说过，我只认识一名共产党员——他是个邋遢的小个子禁酒主义者，嘴巴很臭，我们打过架。我倒不是因为这个就反对共产党，主要原因是，我不大看好斯大林和俄国，我痛恨所有的国家和政府。但即便如此，也许我应该首先加入共产党。我也拿不准哪条路是对的。你觉得呢？”

辛格皱起眉头，思考着。他伸手拿过银色铅笔，在便笺本上写道：我不知道。

“但就是这么回事。你瞧，我们一旦知道以后，便会坐卧不安，但我们得行动起来，然后我们当中有些人就疯掉了。要做的事情很多，你根本不知道从哪儿入手，简直让人发疯。即便是我——我做了很多事，再回过头去看时，这些事似乎都很不理性。我自己曾经建立过一个组织。我挑了二十个纺织工，跟他们交谈，最后我以为他们知道了。我们的座右铭只有两个字：行动。哈！我们就是要引发骚乱——尽最大力量搅起大麻烦。我们的最终目标是自由——真正的自由，只有人类从心灵深处感觉到公正，那么才有可能实现这种伟大的自由。我们的座右铭‘行动’意为彻底摧毁资本主义。在宪法（由我自己起草）中，有些条款规定，我们的工作一旦完成，我们的座右铭便从‘行动’改为‘自由’。”

杰克把火柴的末端弄尖，剔着一个讨厌的牙洞。过了一会儿，他继续说道：

“然后，等宪法都写完了，第一批追随者也组织起来了——我搭便车出去组织更多单位参加这个社团。三个月后我回到家，你猜我发现了什么？第一次英勇的行动是什么？是他们正义的愤怒压倒了精心策划的行动，然后他们丢下我先动手了吗？它是毁灭、谋杀或革命吗？”

杰克在椅子里向前倾着身体，停了一下，忧郁地说：

“我的朋友，他们从基金里偷走了五十七块三毛钱，去买了军帽，还享用了免费星期六晚餐。他们围坐在会议桌旁夸夸其谈，头上戴着帽子，手边放着火腿和一加仑杜松子酒，被我抓了现行。”

杰克放声大笑，辛格紧跟着露出一丝怯懦的微笑。过了一会儿，辛格脸上的笑容变得很紧张，然后消失了。杰克还在大笑，额头上青筋暴突，脸变成了暗红色。他笑了很久。

辛格抬头看看表，指了下时间——十二点三十分。他拿起手表、银色铅笔和纸，又从炉台上拿下烟和火柴，把这些东西分别装进口袋里。午饭时间到了。

但杰克还在大笑着，笑声里带着一种癫狂的味道。他在房间里踱来踱去，把口袋里的零钱晃得叮当作响，修长有力的胳膊僵硬而笨拙地挥动着，一一说着他要吃的食物。说到食物，他脸上现出热烈的激情，每说一个词都要抬起上唇，像一头饥饿的动物。

“烤牛肉加酱汁，米饭，卷心菜，白面包，一大块苹果派。我快饿死了。哦，强尼，我听说北方佬来了。说到吃饭，我的朋友，我有没有跟你说过克拉克·帕特森先生的事情？就是那个迪克西阳光游乐场的主人。他非常胖，都已经二十年没看见过自己的私处了。他一整天都坐在拖车里，玩纸牌，抽大麻卷烟。一日三餐，他从附近快餐店点外卖，他每天都会打破斋戒吃——”

杰克后退一步，让辛格离开房间。他跟哑巴在一起的时候，总是在门口磨磨蹭蹭，他总是跟在辛格后面，希望辛格领路。他们下楼梯时，他继续滔滔不绝地说着，带着一丝紧张感。他睁大棕色的眼睛，一直盯着辛格的面孔。

午后的天气柔和而又温暖，他们一直待在室内。回来时，杰克顺便买回一夸脱威士忌。他坐在床头苦思冥想，一言不发，不时斜一下身子拿起地下的酒瓶，给自己的杯子里倒满酒。辛格坐在窗前的桌子边，下着象棋。杰克有些放松了，他望着朋友的象棋，感觉到温暖安静的午后慢慢进入夜晚的黑暗。炉火在房间的墙壁上映出无声的黑色波浪。然而，到了晚上，他身上又恢复了那种紧张感。辛格已经把棋子收了起来，跟杰克面对面坐着。紧张令杰克的嘴唇剧烈抽搐着，他一个劲地喝酒，好让自己平静下来。坐立不安和欲望的余波袭遍他的全身。他喝完威士忌，又开始跟辛格说话。他心头有千言万语，从嘴里倾泻而出。他从窗户走到床，又从床走到窗户——一遍又一遍。终于，那些千言万语汇成洪流，他带着醉醺醺的强调语气一并将它们倾吐给哑巴：

“他们对我们干的那些好事！他们把真理变成谎言，他们玷污理想，败坏理想。就说耶稣吧，他是我们中的一员，他知道。耶稣说，骆驼要想穿过针眼，比富人要想进入上帝的王国还要难——他说的是真的。然而，看看过去两千年里，教会是怎么对待耶稣的，他们对耶稣干了什么。他们歪曲耶稣说的每一个字，以达到自己卑鄙的目的。今天，如果耶稣还活着，一定会遭到陷害，然后锒铛入狱。耶稣会是真正知道的那个人。我和耶稣会面对面坐在桌前，我看着他，他也看着我，我们都会明白对方是知道的。我，耶稣，还有卡尔·马克思，我们都会坐在一张桌子前面，然后——

“看看我们的自由变成了什么样子。那些为美国革命而战的男人不是‘美国革命女儿会’的太太们，就像我绝不是个大腹便便、浑身香气的哈巴狗一样。关于自由，他们说的都是真心话，他们为一场真正的革命而战斗。只有通过斗争，才能换来一个人人自由平等的国家。哈！这意味着在自然面前人人平等——人人机会均等。这并不意味着百分之二十的人可以肆意剥夺百分之八十的人的生计；这也不意味着一个富人可以通过压榨一万个穷人让自己富起来；这也不意味着暴君们可以任意让这个国家陷入困境当中，让数以百万计的人们可以为了混口饭吃、有个地方睡觉便为所欲为——欺诈、撒谎、打掉自己的右臂。他们亵渎了自由这个词。你听见我的话了吗？对于所有知道的人来说，他们让自由这个词散发出臭鼬一样的恶臭。”

杰克额头上的青筋剧烈跳动着，嘴巴抽搐起来。辛格坐直身体，有些惊慌，杰克还想继续说话，但那些话卡在了喉咙里，他的身体一阵发抖。他坐在椅子上，用手指压住哆嗦的嘴唇，然后哑声说道：

“就是这样，辛格，生气没有用。我们做的都没有用。在我看来，就是这样，我们所能做的就是四处传播真理。如果哪一天，有足够多的不知道的人明白了这个真理，便用不着斗争了。我们唯一能做的事情，就是让他们知道，只需要这样。但怎么才能做到呢，嗯？”

炉火的影子舔着墙面，黑色的波浪形影子越来越高，屋子似乎都动了起来。屋子升上去，又降下来，失去了平衡。杰克觉得自己一个人正在下沉，像波浪一样慢慢沉进阴影幢幢的大海里。他感到无助和恐惧，使劲睁着眼睛，但除了朝他拼命怒号的暗红色波浪，他什么都看不见。终于，他弄清了自己一直在寻找的东西。哑巴的脸依稀可辨，显得非常遥远。杰克闭上了眼睛。

第二天早晨，他很晚才醒过来。辛格已经走了好几个小时，桌上有面包、奶酪、一个橘子，还有一壶咖啡。他吃完早餐，已经到了上班时间。他抑郁地走在路上，低垂着脑袋，穿过镇子朝自己家走去。走到家附近，他穿过一条狭窄的街道，街道一侧有一幢砖房仓库，被烟熏得很黑。仓库的墙上有什么东西分散了他的注意力。他继续向前走，然后注意力被完全吸引住了。墙上用大红色粉笔写了一句话，字体很粗，样子很奇怪：

你必吃勇士的肉，喝地上首领的血。[15]

他把这两行字念了两遍，急切地往街道两端来回看，却并没有人。他困惑不已地认真考虑了几分钟，然后从口袋里掏出一支很粗的红色铅笔，在那行字下面认认真真地写道：

写上面这些字的人，不管你是谁，请明天中午在这里等我，十一月二十九日，星期三，或者后天。

第二天中午十二点，他来到墙跟前等待着。他心绪不宁，不时走到拐角处朝街道上四处张望。没有人来。一个小时之后，他必须赶往游乐场了。

第三天，他又来到这里，等待着。

到了星期五，开始下起一场冬雨，淅淅沥沥，下个不停。墙壁湿透了，上面的字花了，都分辨不出来了。雨一直下，灰暗，凄清，冰冷。

5

“米克，”巴伯说，“我觉得我们要被淹死了。”

的确，雨似乎永远停不下来。韦尔斯夫人开车来回接送他们上学，每天下午他们都只能待在门廊或者屋子里。她和巴伯玩飞行棋和“老处女”纸牌游戏，还在起居室的小地毯上玩弹珠。眼看圣诞节临近，巴伯开始念叨小主耶稣，念叨让圣诞老人送他一辆红色自行车。雨水浇在窗户上，银光闪闪的，天空湿冷而灰暗。河水涨得很高，有些工人不得不从家里搬了出来。后来，就在大家觉得这雨会无休无止永远下下去的时候，雨却突然停了。一天早晨，他们醒来发现艳阳高照。到了下午，天气暖和起来，像是到了夏天。米克放学回家很晚，巴伯、拉尔夫和斯波尔瑞巴斯正在门前的人行道上。孩子们看上去很热，汗腻腻的，身上的冬衣发出一股酸臭味。巴伯拿着弹弓，装了一口袋小石子。拉尔夫在手推车里坐起身子，帽子歪戴在头上，烦躁不安。斯波尔瑞巴斯拿着那把新来复枪。天空一片蔚蓝色，漂亮极了。

“我们等你很久了，米克，”巴伯说，“你去哪儿了？”

她三步并作一步跳上门前的台阶，把毛衣扔在衣帽架上。“一直在体操馆练钢琴。”

每天下午放学后，她都留在学校练习一小时钢琴。体操馆嘈杂拥挤，女子篮球队正在打比赛。今天，她的脑袋已经被篮球砸中两次了，但能有机会坐在钢琴面前，不管被砸多少次，不管有多少麻烦，都是值得的。她把音符组合到一起，总算弹出了她想要的声音，这比她预想的要容易。试了两三个小时之后，她在低音区摸索出了几组和弦，可以搭配右手弹奏的主旋律。现在，她几乎可以辨别出所有的音乐作品了，而且她还会自己创作新乐曲，这比只是模仿旋律好得多。她的双手捕捉到这些优美的乐声，让她觉得这是世间最美妙的感受。

她想学习如何看懂写下来的乐谱。德洛丽丝·布朗已经学了五年音乐，米克把每周用来吃午饭的五毛钱给了德洛丽丝，让她给自己上音乐课，这让米克一整天都饥肠辘辘。德洛丽丝会弹很多快而流畅的曲子——但德洛丽丝不知道该怎么回答她提出的所有那些问题，只能教给她不同音阶、大小调和弦、音符值，诸如此类的初级规则。

米克砰地关上厨房炉子的门。“我们就吃这些？”

“宝贝，我已经尽力了。”波西娅说。

只有玉米面包和人造奶油。她一边吃一边喝水，这样才能勉强咽下去。

“别这么狼吞虎咽，没人抢你的。”

孩子们仍然在家门前闲逛。巴伯把弹弓塞进了口袋，这会儿正在玩来复枪。斯波尔瑞巴斯十岁，他父亲上个月刚去世，这是他父亲留下的枪——所有小孩子都喜欢摆弄这支枪。每隔几分钟，巴伯就把枪抡到肩膀上，瞄准，然后大声发出“砰”的声音。

“别乱动扳机。”斯波尔瑞巴斯说，“我装上了子弹。”

米克吃完玉米面包，看看四周想找点事做。哈里·米诺维茨正坐在他家门廊的栏杆上看报纸。她很高兴看到他，想开个玩笑，于是举起一只胳膊，用纳粹的姿势冲他大喊：“嗨！”

哈里却没有把这个举动当成玩笑，他走进门厅关了门。他的感情很容易受伤。她很难过，因为她和哈里不久前还一直是好朋友。小时候，他们经常一起玩，但最近三年，他上了职业学校，而她还在文法学校。他在业余时间也干些兼职，好像突然之间他便长大了，再也不跟孩子们一起在前后院胡混了。有时候她看到他在卧室看报纸，或者深夜时分看见他脱衣服。在数学和历史方面，他是职业学校里最聪明的男孩。现在她也上了高中，他们经常会在放学回家的路上碰见，然后一起走回来。实践课上，他俩在一个班，有一次，老师让他俩搭档组装一辆摩托车。他读书，每天看报纸。世界政治无时无刻不在他的心头。他说话很慢，对一件事情特别认真的时候，额头上会冒出汗珠。而现在，她让他生气了。

“我想知道哈里是不是还有金币。”斯波尔瑞巴斯说。

“什么金币？”

“犹太男孩出生时，家人会为他在银行里存一枚金币。犹太人就是这么做的。”

“哪有的事，你弄混了。”她说，“你说的是天主教徒。天主教的婴儿一出生，家人就会买一把手枪。总有一天，天主教徒要发起战争，杀光所有人。”

“修女让我觉得很好笑，”斯波尔瑞巴斯说，“在街上看到修女，总是把我吓一跳。”

她在台阶上坐下，把头放在膝盖上，进入了“里屋”。对她来说，好像有两个地方——“里屋”和“外屋”。学校、家，还有每天发生的事情，这些属于“外屋”。辛格先生既属于“里屋”又属于“外屋”。国外、那些计划和音乐属于“里屋”，她日思夜想的那些歌也属于“里屋”，还有交响乐。她独自待在“里屋”时，那晚派对之后她听到的那首曲子便会回到她的脑海中。在她的心里，这首交响乐像一朵硕大的花，慢慢地绽放。白天有些时候，或者清晨刚醒来时，她脑子里会突然想起这首交响乐的一个新部分，然后她必须要进入“里屋”，翻来覆去地听着，想要把这部分加进这首交响乐她已经记住的那些部分中。“里屋”是个非常私密的地方，她在人满为患的屋子里，却仍然感觉到就像自己被单独关在了屋里一样。

斯波尔瑞巴斯把一只脏手伸到她眼前，因为她一直愣愣地盯着远方。她给了他一巴掌。

“修女是什么？”巴伯问。

“天主教的女士。”斯波尔瑞巴斯说，“是天主教的女士，穿着黑色大长裙，一直遮到脑袋。”

她厌倦了跟这帮孩子无所事事地混在一起，她想去图书馆看看《国家地理》杂志上的图片。照片里都是世界上其他国家的地方，法国巴黎、巨大的冰川，还有非洲的原始丛林。

“你们几个看着拉尔夫，别让他走到街上。”她说。巴伯把那支大来复枪扛在肩上。“回来的时候给我带本故事书。”

这个孩子似乎生来就知道怎么看书。他才上二年级，却特别喜欢自己看故事书——从来没让别人给他念过。“这次你想要什么书？”

“给我挑本里面有吃的东西的书。我特别喜欢那种德国孩子的故事，他们到森林里去，碰到一所房子，全都是各种各样的糖果做的，还有巫婆。我喜欢有吃的东西的故事。”

“我找找看。”米克说。

“但我有点厌烦糖果了。”巴伯说，“看看能不能给我找本故事书，里面有烤肉三明治什么的。如果实在找不到，我想看本有关牛仔的书。”

她正准备离开，突然停下了，看得出神。孩子们也都纷纷盯着看。他们站在那里一动不动，望着街对面的巴比·威尔逊从家门前的台阶上走下来。

“巴比太可爱了！”巴伯柔声说道。

也许是因为下了好几星期的雨，天气突然晴热起来的缘故。也许是因为在这样一个午后，他们身上暗淡的冬衣太难看的缘故，无论如何，巴比看上去就像个仙女，或者电影里的什么人。她穿着去年的晚会礼服——一条小小的粉色纱裙，微微朝外翘着，很挺括，一条粉色腰带，粉色舞鞋，甚至还拿了一个粉色小皮夹。除了头发是黄色，她全身是粉红、白色和金色——而且，她又娇小又干净，单单望着都怕会伤害到她。她娇美可爱，穿过街道，但不肯转过脸来看他们。

“到这里来，”巴伯说，“让我看看你那个粉色的小钱包——”

巴比沿着街道边缘从他们身边走过，头扭向一侧。她下定决心不跟他们说话。

人行道和街道之间有一小片草地，巴比走到草地的时候停住了，站了一会儿，然后做了一个前手翻。

“别去注意她，”斯波尔瑞巴斯说，“她总是要出风头。她要去布兰农先生的咖啡馆去买糖。布兰农是她姨夫，她不用付钱。”

巴伯把来复枪拄到地上，这支大枪对他来说太沉了。他一边望着巴比沿着街道走远，一边不断拽着自己散乱的刘海儿。“那真是个特别可爱的粉色小钱包。”他说。

“她妈妈总是说她多么有天赋，”斯波尔瑞巴斯说，“她觉得，她要把巴比送去演电影。”时间太晚，不能去看《国家地理》了，马上就要开晚饭了。拉尔夫抬起头哭了起来，她把他从手推车里抱出来，放到地上。现在是十二月，对于巴伯这个年龄的孩子来说，夏天还早呢。去年夏天，巴比出来时一直穿着那件晚会礼服，在大街中央跳舞。起初，孩子们会围拢过来看着她，但很快就厌倦了。后来她出来跳舞时，只剩下巴伯还会看。巴伯总是坐在路边，一有车来就冲她大喊。他看巴比穿着晚会礼服跳舞看了一百次——但夏天已经过去三个月了，现在对他来说一切又都是新的。

“我多希望自己也有一件礼服。”巴伯说。

“你想要什么样的？”

“一件很酷的礼服，非常漂亮的礼服，五颜六色，像蝴蝶一样。圣诞节我就想要这个，还有一辆自行车！”

“娘娘腔。”斯波尔瑞巴斯说。

巴伯又把那支大来复枪扛到肩膀上，瞄准街对面的一幢房子。“我如果有件礼服，我就会到处跳舞，我还要每天穿着去上学。”

米克坐在门前台阶上，看着拉尔夫。巴伯并不像斯波尔瑞巴斯说的那样是个娘娘腔，他只是喜欢漂亮的东西。斯波尔瑞巴斯居然这么说，她饶不了他。

“一个人不管是要什么东西，他都要努力争取。”她慢悠悠地说，“很多次我都注意到，一个孩子在家里越小越好。小一些的孩子都是最坚强的孩子，我就很坚强，因为我上面有好几个孩子。巴伯——他看上去病怏怏的，还喜欢漂亮东西，但他内心很勇敢。如果真是这样，那么等拉尔夫长大了可以四处走的时候，他肯定是最坚强的那一个。虽然拉尔夫现在只有十七个月，但我已经从他脸上看出了一种可称之为坚强和勇敢的东西。”

拉尔夫四处看看，知道是在说他。斯波尔瑞巴斯坐到地上，一把拿走拉尔夫的帽子，在他眼前晃着逗弄他。

“好吧！”米克说，“如果你把他惹哭了，你知道我怎么治你。你最好小心点。”

一切都静悄悄的。太阳落到了屋后，西边的天空一片紫红色，隔壁街区传来孩子们溜冰的声音。巴伯斜靠在一棵树上，似乎在幻想着什么东西。家里传来晚饭的香味，很快就该吃饭了。

“瞧，”巴伯突然说，“巴比又来了，她穿这身粉色衣服真漂亮。”

巴比慢慢朝他们这边走过来。她拿了一盒有奖品的爆米花糖果，正把手伸进盒子里拿奖品。她走起路来还是那样一本正经，那样文雅。看得出，她知道他们都在注视着她。

“嗨，巴比——”她经过他们身边时，巴伯说道，“让我看看你的粉色小钱包，摸摸你的粉色衣服。”

巴比自顾自地哼起歌来，并不听他说话。她经过巴伯身边，不让巴伯碰她。她只是迅速低下头，冲他笑了笑。

巴伯的肩上还扛着那支大来复枪，嘴里大声发出“砰”的声音，假装在射击。然后，他又对巴比喊了起来——声音柔和而又伤感，像是在呼唤一只小猫。“嗨，巴比——过来，巴比——”

他动作太快，米克根本来不及阻止他。她只看见他的手放在扳机上，随后突然传来“砰”的一声可怕的枪响，巴比瘫倒在人行道上。米克好像被钉在了台阶上，动弹不得，也叫不出声。斯波尔瑞巴斯抬起一只胳膊捂住了脑袋。

只有巴伯没有意识到发生了什么事情。“起来，巴比，”他喊道，“我没有生你的气。”

一切都发生在一瞬间。三个人同时冲到巴比身边。她瘫倒在肮脏的人行道上，裙子盖在头上，露出粉色衬裤和雪白的小腿。她双手张开——一只手里拿着糖果里的奖品，另一只手里拿着钱包。她的发带和头顶的黄色卷发上都沾满了血。她被打中了头部，脸朝下摔在地上。

一瞬间，发生了这么多事。巴伯惊声尖叫，扔下枪，跑了。米克站在那里，双手捂着脸，也尖叫起来。然后来了很多人。她爸爸第一个冲过来，把巴比抱到了屋里。

“她死了。”斯波尔瑞巴斯说，“她被打在两只眼睛中间，我看见了她的脸。”

米克在人行道上来回走着，她想问问巴比是不是死了，舌头却像卡在了嘴里一样。威尔逊太太从上班的美容院一路跑过来，冲进屋里，又冲了出来。她在街上来回走着，大哭着，把手指上的戒指摘下来又戴上。后来救护车来了，医生进去看巴比。米克跟在后面进了屋。巴比正躺在前屋的床上，屋子里安静得如同教堂。

巴比躺在床上，看上去像个漂亮的小洋娃娃，除了有血，看不出受伤的样子。医生俯下身查看她的头部，检查完毕，他们把巴比放上担架抬了出来。威尔逊太太和她爸爸跟着一起上了救护车。

屋里仍然一片寂静。所有人都忘了巴伯，他不见了踪影。一个小时过去了，她妈妈、黑兹尔、埃特，还有所有房客们都在前屋等着，辛格先生站在门口。

过了很长时间，她爸爸回来了。他说，巴比不会死，但颅骨骨折了。他要找巴伯，却没有人知道巴伯去了哪儿。外面已经黑了。他们到后院和街上去找，喊着巴伯的名字。他们又派斯波尔瑞巴斯和其他几个男孩出去找。巴伯似乎已经远远离开了这个地方。哈里去了一处房子，他们都觉得他也许会在那里。

她爸爸在门廊里来回踱步。“我从来没用鞭子抽过自己的孩子，”他不断地说，“我从来不相信鞭子，但等我抓住这个孩子，我一定要拿鞭子抽他。”

米克坐在栏杆上，望着黑暗的街道。“我治得了巴伯。等他回来，交给我就行。”

“你也出去找找，你比别人都更可能找到他。”

爸爸一说完，她突然想到巴伯去了哪里。后院有棵大橡树，夏天时，他们在树上建了个树屋。他们把一个大箱子拖到了橡树上，巴伯以前特别喜欢一个人坐在树屋里。米克离开门廊上的家人和房客，穿过小巷向黑乎乎的后院走去。

她在树下站了一会儿。“巴伯——”她小声说，“是米克。”

他没有吱声，但她知道他就在那里，她好像可以闻见他的味道似的。她跳起来，一下抓住最矮的一根树枝，慢慢向上爬。这个孩子真的让她很生气，她要好好教训他一通。她爬上树屋，又开口对他说话——依然没人回应。她爬进大箱子里，摸索着四周，终于摸到了他。他蜷缩在角落里，两条腿在打哆嗦。他一直屏住呼吸，当她摸到他的时候，抽泣声和呼吸声一下子爆发出来。

“我——我不是故意要打倒巴比的。她那么小，那么可爱——我只是想吓唬她一下。”

米克坐在树屋的地上。“巴比死了，”她说，“他们派了很多人找你。”

巴伯止住哭声，安静下来。

“你知道爸爸在家里干什么吗？”

她好像听到巴伯在认真倾听。

“你知道劳斯典狱长[16]——你在收音机里听到过他，你也知道辛辛监狱。嗯，咱爸爸正在给劳斯典狱长写信，让他们抓住你送到辛辛监狱的时候对你稍微好一点。”

黑暗中，这些话听起来非常可怕，她忍不住一阵战栗，她能感觉到巴伯在颤抖。

“他们那里有小电椅子——就是你那么大。他们一开开关，你就像一片烤肉一样烤干了，然后你就下地狱了。”

巴伯蜷缩在角落里，没有发出一丝声音。她爬到箱子边缘，要下去。“你最好待在这里，他们找了警察守着院子。也许再过几天，我可以给你带点吃的来。”

米克靠在橡树树干上。这就足以教训巴伯了。她总能对付得了他，她比任何人都了解这个孩子。有一次，大概是一两年前，他总是中途停下，跑到灌木丛后面撒尿，然后玩弄自己一会儿。她很快就明白了是怎么回事。后来每次这样的时候，她总会给他一巴掌，不到三天便治好了他的毛病。后来，他再也不像其他男孩那样撒尿了——总是把手背在身后。她得一直照顾这个巴伯，也总有办法对付他。再过一会儿，她会回到树屋，然后把他带回屋里。经历这件事后，他这辈子都不会再摸枪了。

屋子里还是一片死气沉沉的感觉，所有房客都坐在门廊里，没人聊天，也没人坐在摇椅上摇动。她的爸爸妈妈都在前屋。她爸爸用瓶子喝着啤酒，在屋里来回踱步。巴比会好起来的，所以这种焦虑跟她无关，而且似乎也没人为巴伯着急。是有别的事情。

“那个巴伯！”埃特说。

“以后，我从这座房子里走出去都会觉得丢人。”黑兹尔说。

埃特和黑兹尔走进中屋，关上了门。比尔待在后面自己的房间里。她不想跟他们说话。她站在前厅，独自考虑着这一切。

她爸爸的脚步停了下来。“这一切都是故意的，”他说，“这不像只是个孩子在摆弄这支枪，然后意外走火了。所有看见的人都说他是故意瞄准的。”

“不知道什么时候才能听到威尔逊太太的消息。”她妈妈说。

“我们会听到很多消息的，没错！”

“我觉得是这样。”

太阳下山后，夜里很冷，像十一月。人们从门廊走进来，坐在起居室里——却没有人生火。米克的毛衣挂在衣帽架上，她穿上毛衣，站在那里缩着肩膀，好让自己暖和一些。她想到巴伯一个人坐在冰冷黑暗的树屋里。他相信了她说的每个字，但他真的活该要担心。他差点打死那个巴比。

“米克，你难道想不到巴伯有可能去什么地方吗？”她爸爸问道。

“我觉得他就在附近。”

她爸爸手里拿着空啤酒瓶，来回踱着步，走路的样子就像盲人似的，脸上还挂着汗珠。“那个可怜的孩子吓得不敢回家。如果能找到他，我会好受些。我没动过巴伯一个手指头，他不该害怕我。”

她会再等一个半小时。到那个时候，巴伯会为自己的所作所为深表歉意。她总有办法对付这个巴伯，让他得到教训。

过了一会儿，屋子里骚动起来。她爸爸又给医院打了个电话，想打听巴比怎么样了。过了几分钟，威尔逊太太回了电话。她说想跟他们谈谈，要到家里来。

她爸爸仍然像个盲人似的，在前屋里走来走去。他又喝了三瓶啤酒。“发生这样的事，她完全可以去告我，让我连裤子都赔掉。她能得到的一切就是这座房子了，还得刨除掉抵押。但发生这样的事情，我们也没什么好说的了。”

突然，米克想到了什么。他们也许真的会把巴伯送上法庭，然后关进儿童监狱。威尔逊太太也许会把他送进劳改学校，他们也许真的会对巴伯做出可怕的事情来。她想立刻回到树屋，坐在他身边，让他不要担心。巴伯一直那么瘦，那么小，那么聪明。如果谁胆敢把这个孩子送走，她就杀了谁。她想要吻他，咬他，因为她那么爱他。

但她不能错过任何消息。再过几分钟，威尔逊太太就来了，她必须得知道事情的进展。然后她会跑出去，告诉巴伯她之前所说的话都是骗他的，而他也会真正得到应得的教训。

一辆廉价出租车驶上人行道。大家都在门廊等着，既安静又害怕。威尔逊太太跟布兰农先生一起从出租车里走了出来。他们走上台阶时，她听见她爸爸紧张得牙齿咬得咯咯作响。他们走进前屋，她紧跟在后面，站在门口。埃特、黑兹尔、比尔和房客们都在门外。

“我来跟你好好谈谈这件事。”威尔逊太太说。

前屋看上去俗气又邋遢，她看见布兰农先生注意到了这一切。拉尔夫玩的破赛璐珞洋娃娃、珠子和杂物散落了一地。她爸爸的工作台上有啤酒，爸爸妈妈床上用的枕头已经变成了灰色。

威尔逊太太不断把婚戒摘下来，再戴上去。在她身边，布兰农先生非常冷静。他跷着二郎腿坐在那里，下巴上青黑一片，看上去像电影里的黑帮成员。他对她一贯心存怨恨，跟她说话时声音粗暴，与跟别人说话时的声音不一样。是因为他知道那次她和巴伯从他柜台上偷了一包口香糖吗？她恨他。

“一切都归结到这一点，”威尔逊太太说，“你孩子故意打中了我家巴比的头部。”

米克一步迈到屋子中央。“不是，他没有。”她说，“我就在现场。巴伯当时正在用枪瞄准我、拉尔夫，还有周围的东西。他的枪碰巧对准了巴比，手指滑了一下。我就在现场。”

布兰农先生搓着鼻子，望着她，一副伤心的样子。她真的恨他。

“我理解你们的感受——所以，现在我想开门见山。”

米克的妈妈晃动着一串钥匙，她爸爸坐在那里一动不动，两只大手垂在膝盖上。

“巴伯之前没有成心想这么干，”米克说，“他只是——”

威尔逊太太把戒指猛地摘下来，又戴上去。“等一下，我知道一切是怎么回事。我要告上法庭，让你们赔光所有的钱。”

她爸爸脸上没有任何表情。“我告诉你一件事，”他说，“你告我们，我们也没有多少钱赔，我们所有的一切只是——”

“听我说，”威尔逊太太说，“我来这里，不是要带任何律师来控告你。巴塞洛缪——布兰农先生——和我来的时候，我们仔细讨论过这件事，对一些主要问题基本上意见一致。首先我想要公平诚实——其次，我不想让巴比在这个年龄就卷入非普通的诉讼案。”

没有人说话，房间里所有人都僵硬地坐在椅子上。只有布兰农先生朝米克似笑非笑，但她斜着眼睛非常强硬地回望着他。

威尔逊太太非常紧张，点烟的时候手一直在抖。“我不想告你或者怎么样，我想要的就是你们要公平。他们给巴比吃了什么东西让她睡过去之前，她经历了那么多折磨，哭了那么久，我不是要让你们为这些付出代价。没有任何代价可以弥补这一切，这会影响她将来的事业，会影响我们的计划，我也不是要让你们为这些付出代价。她要戴好几个月的绷带，也不能去晚会上跳舞了——也许头上甚至还会有块地方秃掉。”

威尔逊太太和她爸爸对视着，好像被催眠了似的。然后，威尔逊太太伸手拿过钱包，从里面取出一张纸条。

“你们要付的，就是我们需要支付的实际费用。巴比在医院里住单人病房，有私人护士，一直住到可以回家为止，还有手术室和医生的账单——这一次，我想立刻给医生付钱。而且，他们给巴比剃光了所有头发，你得付钱让我带她去亚特兰大做电烫发——等她头发长回原样之后，还要再做一次。还有她的服装费，以及类似其他小账单的钱。等我弄清楚，就立刻给你逐条写下来。我会尽最大可能公平诚实，我把账单拿来，你得一次付清。”

她妈妈抚平膝盖上的裙子，急促地喘了一口气。“我觉得，儿童病房要比单人病房好多了，上次米克得了肺炎——”

“我说过了，单人病房。”

布兰农先生伸出两只白皙、粗短的手掂量着，像是放在天平上一样。“或许，过一两天巴比会搬到双人房间，跟另一个孩子同屋。”威尔逊太太毫无表情地说，“你听见我说的话了。你孩子打伤我家巴比，她理所应当要享受优越的条件，直到康复的那一天。”

“你有权利要求。”她爸爸说，“天知道，我们现在一无所有——但我们可以积攒。我知道你不会趁机占我们的便宜，我很感激这一点。我们会尽最大努力。”

她想待在这里，听听他们还会说些什么，但她满脑子都是巴伯。一想到他坐在黑暗寒冷的树屋里担心辛辛监狱的事情，她便觉得心中不安。她走出屋子，穿过走廊朝后门走去。风在刮着，院子里一片漆黑，只有厨房的灯透出一方昏黄的亮光。她回过头，看见波西娅坐在桌前，修长瘦削的双手捧着脸，一动不动。院子里空无一人，黑暗中风刮得影子快速移动着，很吓人，还发出一种像是哀鸣的声音。

她站在橡树下面。然后，她刚要伸手去抓第一根树枝，脑子里突然闪过一个可怕的念头。她突然觉得，巴伯已经不见了。她大喊他的名字，他没有应声。她像只猫一样迅速无声地爬上去。

“嘿！巴伯！”

她不用到箱子里去摸，就知道他不在里面。为了确认一下，她走进箱子，摸遍了每一个角落。那个孩子不见了。肯定是她前脚刚离开，他后脚便爬下树来。现在他肯定已经跑了。像巴伯这么聪明的孩子，谁也不知道到哪里才能找到他。

她爬下树，跑到前面的门廊。威尔逊太太正要离开，他们都跟她一起来到门前的台阶上。

“爸爸！”她说，“我们得管管巴伯。他跑了，我肯定他已经不在我们街区了，我们都得出去找找。”

没有人知道该去哪里找，无从下手。她爸爸在街上走来走去，朝所有的小巷子里张望。布兰农先生打电话给威尔逊太太叫了辆便宜出租车，自己则留下来帮着一起找人。辛格先生坐在门廊的栏杆上，他是唯一保持冷静的人。他们都等着米克想出来去什么地方找巴伯才好。但是，镇子太大了，这个小孩又那么聪明，她实在不知道该怎么办。

也许他跑到糖山上，到波西娅家去了。她回到厨房，波西娅正坐在桌子前，两只手捧着脸。

“我突然想到，他可能跑到你家去了。帮我们找找他吧。”

“我怎么就没想到呢！我赌五分钱，我那个吓坏了的小巴伯一直待在我家里。”

布兰农先生借了一辆汽车。他、辛格先生、米克的爸爸带着她和波西娅，一起上了车。除了她，没人知道巴伯的感受是什么样的。没人知道，他逃跑实际上是为了逃命。

除了地上斑驳的月光，波西娅家里一片漆黑。他们一迈进门去，便感觉得到两个房间里都没有人。波西娅点亮前面的油灯。两个房间里散发着一种混杂的味道，墙上挤挤挨挨地贴满了剪贴画，桌上铺着蕾丝桌布，床上放着蕾丝枕头。巴伯并不在里面。

“他来过这里。”波西娅突然说，“我看得出有人来过这里。”

辛格先生在厨房桌子上找到一支笔和一张纸。他迅速看了一遍，然后他们都看着这张纸。字迹圆润但凌乱，除了一个单词，这个聪明的小孩其他的词都拼写得很正确。便条上写道：

亲爱的波西娅：

我去佛罗里达了。跟大家说一声。

你诚挚的，

巴伯·凯利

他们站在那里，大吃一惊，一筹莫展。她爸爸望着门外，焦虑地用大拇指挖着鼻子。他们都准备钻到车里，然后驱车前往南去的公路。

“等等，”米克说，“巴伯尽管只有七岁，但他很聪明，如果真要逃跑的话，他不会告诉我们他要跑到哪里去，关于佛罗里达的话只是个花招。”

“花招？”她爸爸说。

“是的。巴伯熟悉的地方只有两个，一个是佛罗里达，另一个是亚特兰大。巴伯、拉尔夫和我曾经去过通往亚特兰大的公路很多次。他知道从那里怎么走，他肯定去那里了。他以前一直说，如果有机会去亚特兰大他要做些什么。”

他们出门，又上了汽车。她正准备爬上后座，波西娅突然捏住她的胳膊肘。“你知道巴伯干了什么吗？”波西娅平静地说，“别告诉任何人，但我的巴伯把我的金耳环从梳妆台上拿走了。我从来没想到，我的巴伯能对我做出这种事来。”

布兰农先生发动了汽车。他们开得很慢，一边在街上仔细搜寻着巴伯，一边朝通往亚特兰大的公路开去。

的确，巴伯身上有一种强硬刻薄的特性。今天，他的举止跟以往迥然不同。在此之前，他一直是个安静的小孩，从来没干过真正刻薄的事情。如果伤害了谁的感情，他总会感觉羞愧和紧张。那么，他怎么能干出今天的这些事情来呢？

他们缓缓驶上通往亚特兰大的公路，经过最后一排房子来到漆黑的田野和树林边。一路上他们不断停下来，打听是否有人见过巴伯。“有没有一个穿灯芯绒裤子、光着脚的小孩经过这里？”然而，即便他们走了十英里，也没有人说见过或注意过他。风从开着的车窗吹进来，寒冷，强劲。已经是深夜了。

他们又往前开了一点，然后折返回镇上。她爸爸和布兰农先生想去问问所有二年级的孩子，但她让他们掉了头，又回到通往亚特兰大的公路上。她一直记得跟巴伯说过的那些话，巴比死了，辛辛监狱，劳斯典狱长，等等，还说过跟他个头儿一般大的小电椅，还有地狱。黑暗之中，这些话听起来非常可怕。

他们缓慢地开出镇子，走了约莫半英里，然后她猛然看见了巴伯。汽车的灯光清晰地照见了走在前面的他，样子很滑稽。他正沿着路边走，伸出大拇指，想要搭车。他腰带上别着波西娅的切肉刀，在宽阔漆黑的大路上他显得那么小，不像七岁，倒像个五岁的孩子。

他们停下车，他跑过来要钻进车里。他看不见车里是谁，脸上露出那种斜着眼睛的表情，跟以前玩弹珠瞄准时一样。她爸爸一把抓住他的领子，一通拳打脚踢。然后，他一把抓起那把切肉刀，他们的爸爸及时地一把从他手里夺过了刀子。他像中了圈套的小老虎那样挣扎着，但最终还是被他们拖进了车里。回去的路上，他们的爸爸把巴伯放在腿上，巴伯僵直地坐着，什么也不倚靠。

他们必须得把他拖进屋，所有邻居和房客都出来看热闹。他们把他拖进前屋，到了屋里，他退缩到角落里，紧攥着拳头，眯起眼睛，挨个儿看着屋里的人，好像随时要对抗整个人群。

自从进了屋子，他一句话都没说，最后他开始大声尖叫：“是米克干的！我没干，是米克干的！”

巴伯发出一种从未有人听过的尖叫声，他脖子上青筋暴突，两只拳头攥得像小石头一样。

“你们抓不住我！谁也抓不住我！”他一直在大叫。

米克晃晃他的肩膀，告诉他她之前说的话都是编的。他终于明白了她说的话，但他不肯停止尖叫，好像什么都无法阻挡那种尖叫。

“我恨所有人！我恨所有人！”

他们都站在旁边。布兰农先生搓着鼻子，看着地板。终于，他悄悄地出去了。辛格先生似乎是唯一知道怎么回事的人，也许这是因为他没有听见那种可怕的叫喊。他的脸上仍然很平静，巴伯每次看他，都似乎更安静了。辛格先生跟所有人都不一样，在类似今天这样的时候，如果人们让他来处理，会好得多。他更理智，他知道的事情很多普通人并不懂。他就那么望着巴伯，过了一会儿，孩子安静下来，他们的爸爸可以把他抱到床上去了。

他脸朝下趴在床上，哭个不停。他哭了很久，哭得很厉害，这让他全身颤抖。他哭了一个小时，三个房间里的人都没法入睡。比尔搬到了起居室的沙发上，米克跟巴伯一起躺在床上。他不让她碰他，也不让她挨着他。他一边哭一边打嗝，又过了一个小时，他睡着了。

她久久不能入睡。黑暗中，她用双臂搂着他，搂得很紧。她抚摸着他的全身，又吻遍他的全身。他那么柔软，那么小，身上散发着男孩子的那种咸味。她心中充满了对他强烈的爱，让她使劲搂着他，最后她的胳膊都麻了。在脑子里，她同时想着巴伯和音乐，仿佛她对他无论多好都不够。她再也不会打他，再也不会耍弄他了。她双手抱着他的头，就这样睡了一晚上。然后，她早晨醒来的时候，他不见了。

那晚之后，她再也没有多少机会耍弄他了——她或别人，都没有机会。打伤巴比之后，这个孩子再也不像小巴伯了。他总是沉默，不跟任何人打交道。大多时候，他就一个人那么坐在后院或者煤屋里。圣诞节越来越近。她真的想要一架钢琴，但关于这个，她自然什么也不会说。她跟所有人说，她想要一块米老鼠手表。他们问巴伯想让圣诞老人送他什么，他说什么都不要。他把弹珠和折叠刀藏了起来，也不让任何人动他的故事书。

那晚之后，没有人再叫他巴伯。邻居的大孩子们喊他巴比-杀手·凯利，但他不大跟别人搭腔，似乎也没有什么事情会烦扰到他。家人叫他的真名——乔治。起初，米克还是忍不住叫他巴伯，她也不想改。但很奇怪，大约一个星期后，她很自然地跟其他人一起叫他乔治了。但这个孩子——乔治——变了，他总是独来独往，老气横秋的样子，没有人知道他脑子里在想什么，即便是她，也是如此。

圣诞前夜，她跟他一起睡，他躺在黑暗中一言不发。“别再表现得这么奇怪了，”她对他说，“我们聊聊那些聪明人，还有，聊聊荷兰孩子是怎么不挂袜子而是挂木鞋的。”

乔治没应声。他睡着了。

早晨，她四点起床，叫醒所有家人。他们的爸爸在前屋生了火，然后让他们到圣诞树底下看看自己有什么礼物。乔治得到一套意大利西装，拉尔夫得到一个橡皮娃娃，家里其他人得到的都是衣服。她把自己的袜子翻了个遍，想找米老鼠手表，却没有发现。她的礼物是一双棕色牛津鞋，还有一盒樱桃糖果。尽管天还没亮，她和乔治已来到人行道上，砸巴西果，放鞭炮，又吃光了一整盒两层的樱桃糖果。天光大亮的时候，他们觉得肚子不舒服，也筋疲力尽了。她躺倒在沙发上，闭上眼进入“里屋”的世界。

6

八点钟，科普兰医生坐在桌前，借着窗户透进来的暗淡晨光，研究着一沓纸。在他身边是一株树冠浓密的雪松，一片深绿色一直伸向天花板。自从执业第一年起，他每年圣诞节都会办一次聚会，现在一切准备就绪。前面几个房间的墙边，放了一排排凳子和椅子。房子里弥漫着新烤蛋糕和热气腾腾的咖啡的那种香甜味道。波西娅也在办公室，跟他一起坐在墙边的凳子上，两只手托着下巴，身体向前趴着，几乎快对折起来了。

“父亲，你从五点开始就坐在桌子前面，你不用起得这么早，应该待在床上，有事再起也不晚。”

科普兰医生用舌头润润厚嘴唇。他心头的事情很多，无暇顾及波西娅，她在身边让他有点烦躁。

终于，他转身望着她，有些恼怒。“你坐在这里惆怅什么？”

“我就是担心。”她说，“第一，我担心我们的威利。”

“威廉？”

“你瞧，他每个周日都定期给我写信，我周一或周二就会收到他的信，但上周他没写信。当然，我不是很着急。威利一直善良温柔，我知道他会没事的。他已经从监狱被送进戴镣囚犯队，他们要到亚特兰大北部什么地方干活儿。两个星期以前，他写信来说，他们今天要去做礼拜，让我把那套衣服和红领带给他送过去。”

“威廉就说了这些？”

“他信上说，那个B.F.梅森也在监狱里，他还碰到了巴斯特·约翰逊，威利以前认识这个男孩。而且，他还让我把口琴给他送去，说没有口琴吹他觉得很不快乐。我把所有东西都送过去了，还有一副跳棋和一块白冰皮蛋糕。但我特别希望再过几天能收到他的信。”

科普兰医生的眼睛里闪着热切的光，两只手怎么也停不下来。“女儿，这件事我们以后再聊，时间紧迫，我得先把这些弄完。你到厨房去看看是不是都准备停当了。”

波西娅站起来，竭力装出一副明朗开心的样子。“那五块钱的奖金你是怎么决定的？”

“我还没有最后确定最明智的办法是什么。”他谨慎地说。

他的一个朋友是位黑人药剂师，每年都会提供五块钱的奖金，奖励命题作文中写得最好的高中生。这位药剂师让科普兰医生全权批阅这些作文，等到圣诞节聚会上宣布获奖者。今年，作文的题目是“我的志向：我该如何提升黑人在社会中的地位”。只有一篇文章真正值得考虑，但这篇文章太幼稚，没有明智的建议。因此，要把奖项颁给这篇文章，有点不太慎重。

科普兰医生戴上眼镜，全神贯注地重新看起这篇文章。

这就是我的志向。首先，我希望能够考上塔斯凯基大学，但我不想成为布克·华盛顿[17]或者卡弗博士[18]那样的人。等我认为自己的教育结束了，我希望成为一名好律师，就像为“斯科茨伯勒男孩们”[19]辩护的律师一样。我只接手黑人诉白人的案子。每天，在每个方面，以每一种方式，我们的同胞都感觉低劣卑微。不应该是这样的。我们是个正在崛起的民族，我们不会长久地在白人的重压之下流汗，我们不能只是播种，却让别人收获。

我想像摩西那样，领着以色列的子民离开压迫者之地。我想创立一个“黑人领袖和学者的秘密组织”。所有黑人都将团结在这些推选出的领导人身旁，在他们的指引之下，准备起义。世界上的其他国家，如果他们关注我们民族的困境，愿意看到美国分裂，那么他们就会来帮助我们。所有黑人都要团结起来，要进行革命。最终，黑人将占领密西西比河以东和波托马可河以南的领域。我会建立起一个强大的国家，由“黑人领袖和学者组织”来领导。我们坚决不给白人签发护照——他们如果进入这个国家，不会有任何法律权利。

我仇恨整个白人种族，我会一直努力，这样，黑人民族就可以为曾经遭受的所有苦难复仇。这就是我的志向。

科普兰医生感觉到血管里热血沸腾。桌上的钟表嘀嗒作响，声音很大，刺激着他的神经。这个男孩想法如此疯狂，他怎么能把奖项颁给他呢？他该怎么决定？

其他文章都没有实质性内容。这些年轻人不肯动脑子，他们写的只是自己的志向，完全忽略了论题的最后部分，只有一点内容还算有些意义。二十五个学生中，有九人在文章一开头便写道：“我不想做奴仆。”这句话写完之后，他们就写要开飞机，要成为职业拳击手，或者牧师，或者舞蹈家。一个女孩全部的志向就是要对穷人好一点。

让他纠结的这篇文章的作者叫兰西·戴维斯。他还没有翻到最后一页看到签名，便已经知道了作者是谁。兰西以前给他找过麻烦。他姐姐十一岁时到别人家里当奴仆，后来遭到年过半百的白人雇主强暴。大约一年之后，他接到紧急电话，要他去看看兰西。

科普兰医生走到卧室的档案柜前，那里头装着他所有病人的资料。他拿出一张卡片，上面写着“丹·戴维斯太太及家人”。他浏览着上面的记录，最后看到兰西的名字。日期是四年以前。他的相关条目是用墨水写的，比其他人的内容都详细：“十三岁，已发育。自行阉割未遂。性欲旺盛，甲状腺亢奋。尽管不太疼痛，但两次就诊均大声哭闹。健谈——尽管有些偏执，但很喜欢说话。除一次意外，成长环境尚可。参见露西·戴维斯——母亲，洗衣工。很聪明，值得观察，并尽可能给予帮助。保持联络。费用：一块钱（？）。”

“今年的结果很难判定，”他对波西娅说，“但我觉得必须要把这个奖颁给兰西·戴维斯。”

“如果你决定了，那么——来跟我说说这里的一些礼物吧。”

聚会上要分发的礼物都放在厨房里。有纸袋子装着的食品和衣物，上面都用一张红色圣诞卡标好了。愿意来的人都接到邀请来参加聚会，但想来参加聚会的客人之前已经来过这里，在走廊桌子上专门的会客簿上写下了（或请朋友代写）自己的名字。这些袋子堆在地上，大约有四十个，接受者的需求不一样，每个袋子的大小便也不一样。有些礼物只是几小包坚果和葡萄干，另一些是些很重的箱子，一个人几乎抬不动。厨房里塞满了好东西，科普兰医生站在门口，鼻孔骄傲地翕动着。

“我觉得你今年干得非常好。人们都这么善良。”

“哼！”他说，“这些连百分之一的需要都满足不了。”

“喏，又来了，父亲！我很明白，你其实非常高兴，但你就是不想表现出来，你总得找点事情来抱怨。这里大概有四袋豌豆，二十袋粗面粉，十五磅腊肉，有鲻鱼，六打鸡蛋，很多粗玉米粉，好几罐西红柿和桃子，有苹果，两打橘子，还有衣服，两个床垫，四条毯子。我觉得已经很多了！”

“大海里的一滴水罢了。”

波西娅指着角落里的一个大箱子。“这里——这些东西你想怎么处理？”

大箱子里装的只是些垃圾——没头的布娃娃、脏兮兮的蕾丝花边，还有一块兔子皮。科普兰医生仔细查看着每件物品。“别扔，每样东西都有用。这些都是客人送的，他们只有这些。以后我会发现它们的用途的。”

“你看看这些盒子和袋子吧，这样我就可以把它们包起来。厨房这里没地方放，很快他们就要挤进来吃茶点了。我要把这些礼物都放到后门台阶上，还有院子里。”

朝阳已经升起，这将是晴朗而寒冷的一天。厨房里传来各种香甜的味道，炉子上放着一大壶咖啡，壁橱架子上放着冰皮蛋糕。

“这些都不是白人捐的，都来自黑人。”

“不，”科普兰医生说，“不完全对。辛格先生捐了一张十二块钱的支票，用来买煤。今天我也请他来参加聚会了。”

“天哪！”波西娅说，“十二块钱！”

“我觉得，请他来是对的。他跟其他白人不一样。”

“你说得对，”波西娅说，“但我一直在想我的威利。我真希望他今天能来参加聚会，真希望能收到他的信，我心里老想着这些。但现在我们不能再聊下去了，得去准备下。客人们可能要来了。”

还有足够的时间。科普兰医生洗漱完毕，仔细地换好衣服。有一阵子，他想练习一下人们都来了之后他要说的话，但期待和不安让他无法集中注意力。十点钟，第一批客人到了，不到半小时人们都来了。

“圣诞快乐！”邮差约翰·罗伯茨说道。他在拥挤的屋子里欢快地挤来挤去，一只肩膀高，一只肩膀低，还一边用白色丝手帕抹着脸上的汗珠。

“大家都圣诞快乐！”

屋子前面很挤。客人们都堵在门口，在门廊和院子里三五成群。没有拥挤，也没有粗鲁的行为，这种热闹井然有序。朋友们彼此喊着名字，陌生人被介绍认识，然后握手，孩子和年轻人们聚在一起朝后面厨房移动着。

“圣诞礼物！”

科普兰医生站在前屋中央的圣诞树边上，感觉有些眩晕。他胡乱跟人们握手寒暄。给他个人的礼物纷纷塞进他的手里，有些用丝带包得非常精美，有些则用报纸包着。他一时不知道该把礼物放到哪里。空气厚重起来，人们的声音也越来越大，一张张面孔在他周围旋转，他谁也认不出来。他慢慢恢复了冷静，找到地方放下怀里的礼物。眩晕慢慢退去，房间清晰起来。他扶了扶眼镜，开始看着四周。

“圣诞快乐！圣诞快乐！”

药剂师马歇尔·尼克尔斯也来了。他穿着燕尾服，正跟开垃圾车的女婿交谈。至圣升天教会的牧师也来了，还有其他教堂的两位执事。海博埃穿着花哨的格子西装，在人群中穿梭自如。健壮结实、油头粉面的年轻人对穿着艳丽长裙的年轻女人鞠躬。母亲们带着孩子，小心翼翼的老人们往俗艳的手帕里吐着痰。屋子里温馨而又吵闹。

辛格先生站在门口，许多人盯着他看。科普兰医生不记得自己是否欢迎过辛格先生的到来。哑巴一个人站在那里，他的脸有点像斯宾诺莎的一幅照片，一张犹太人的脸。看见他真好。

门窗都开着，风吹进屋子里，炉火熊熊燃烧。嘈杂的声音平息下来，人们都已经就座，年轻人一排排地坐在前面的地上。走廊、门廊，甚至院子里，都挤满了沉默不语的客人们。他发言的时间到了——他该说点什么呢？恐慌扼住了他的喉咙。一屋子的人都在等待着。约翰·罗伯茨一示意，所有声音都止息了。

“我的同胞们。”科普兰医生茫然说道，又停住了，所有那些话突然涌上他的心头。

“我们共同聚集在这个屋子里，来庆祝圣诞节，今年已经是第十九年了。人们第一次听说耶稣基督降生的时候，是在黑暗的时代。我们的人民在这个镇上的法院广场被卖为奴隶。从那以后，我们不知道多少次听到并且讲述耶稣一生的故事。而今天，我们的故事将与以往不同。

“一百二十年前，有个人出生在今天我们叫作德国的地方——这个国家远在大西洋彼岸。这个人像耶稣基督一样明白事理，但他的思想跟天堂或逝者的未来无关。他的使命是为了活着的人，为了那些工作、受苦、工作一直到死的劳苦大众，为了那些以洗衣、做饭为工作的人们，为了那些摘棉花、在工厂滚烫染缸边工作的人们。他的使命是为了我们，这个人的名字叫卡尔·马克思。

“卡尔·马克思是个有智慧的人。他对周围的世界进行了观察、研究和琢磨。他说这个世界分成两个阶层：穷人和富人。对于每个富人，都有一千个穷人在为他工作，让他更富有。他没有把世界分成黑人、白人或中国人——对卡尔·马克思而言，一个人是成为数百万的穷人之一还是成为少数的富人之一，这似乎比他的肤色更重要。卡尔·马克思的终生使命，是要实现人类平等，要均分世界上的大笔财富，这样就不会再有贫富差距，每个人都有自己的份额。这就是卡尔·马克思留给我们的训示：‘人尽其才，按需分配。’”

走廊里有一只满是皱纹的蜡黄手掌怯懦地挥动了一下。“他是《圣经》里的马可吗？”

科普兰医生做了解释。他拼出了这两个名字，还提到了日期。“还有问题吗？我希望大家都畅所欲言，一起讨论。”

“我猜，马克思先生是基督教教会的人？”牧师问道。

“他相信人类的精神都是神圣的。”

“他是白人吗？”

“是的，但他不认为自己是个白人。他说：‘我觉得所有人跟我都是一样的。’他认为自己是所有人的兄弟。”

科普兰医生停顿了一下，这次停顿的时间更长了。周围，一张张面孔都在等待着。

“我们在商店里买的每样东西、每样商品，它的价值是什么？价值取决于一样东西——制造或者培育这件东西所花费的劳动。为什么一座砖房子比一棵卷心菜贵？因为建造一座砖房子需要很多人投入劳动。有人去制作砖和砂浆，有人去砍树做铺地的地板，有人负责整个砖房子的建造问题，有人把材料运到要建房子的地方去，有人制造手推车和卡车用来运送材料。最后，还有工人建造这座房子。一座砖房子涉及很多很多人的工作——而我们每个人都会在自家后院种一棵卷心菜。一座砖房比一棵卷心菜贵，就是因为它需要投入更多的劳动。因此，人们购买这座砖房时，他就是在为砖房所包含的劳动付钱。但是，谁拿到了这些钱，也就是利润呢？不是付出劳动的那些人，而是管理他们的那些老板们。你如果进一步仔细研究一下这件事，你会发现，老板上面又有老板，上面还有更大的老板——因此，劳动生产出有价值的物品，而控制这种劳动的人是极少数。这样说清楚了吗？”

“我们明白了！”

但他们真的明白了吗？他重新开始，把刚才的话又重复了一遍。这次大家有了问题。

“建造这些砖房子用的泥土难道不用花钱吗？而且租地种庄稼难道不用花钱吗？”

“这是个好问题，”科普兰医生说，“土地，泥土，木材——这些东西叫自然资源。人类不能制造这些自然资源——人类只能开发自然资源，只能利用它们来工作。因此，这些东西应该归哪个人或者哪个组织所有吗？人怎么能够拥有种庄稼需要的土地、空间、阳光和雨水呢？对于这些东西，一个人怎么能说‘这是我的’，并且拒绝别人来分享它们呢？因此，马克思说，所有这些自然资源应该归大家所有，不应该分成小块，而是应该按照人们的工作能力不同供所有人来使用。像这样。比如，一个人死了，把一头骡子留给了四个儿子，儿子们肯定不会把骡子分成四块然后每人拿一块。他们会共同拥有，共同使用这头骡子。按照马克思的观点，人们拥有自然资源也应该这样——不是归一群富人所有，而是全世界所有工人们作为一个整体去拥有它。

“我们这个屋子里的人，谁都没有私人财产，或许有一两个人住的房子是我们自己的，或者还存了一两块钱——但我们拥有的一切只够我们勉强维持生计，此外我们一无所有。我们所拥有的一切就是我们的身体，而我们活着的每一天都在出卖我们的身体。早晨，我们去上班的时候，或者我们一整天都在劳作的时候，我们就是在出卖自己的身体。我们会为了任何一点报酬，为了任何目的，随时出卖我们的身体。我们被迫出卖身体，仅仅是为了吃饭，为了活下来。我们出卖身体所得的报酬，只是为了让我们有力气进行更多的劳作，为别人赚取利润。今天，我们不再被放到法院广场的台子上出售，然而，在我们活着的每一个小时里，我们都被迫出卖我们的体力、我们的时间、我们的灵魂。我们从一种奴隶制中解放出来，却又被送进了另一种奴隶制。这就是自由吗？我们已经是自由人了吗？”

一个深沉的声音从前院传过来。“这就是真相！”

“就是这么回事！”

“而在这种奴役中，不只有我们，全世界还有其他很多人，数以百万计，不同肤色，不同种族，不同信仰。我们必须牢记这一点。我们民族的很多人仇恨贫穷的白人，而他们也仇恨我们，就是镇上那些住在河边、在工厂里干活儿的人，他们几乎跟我们一样贫穷。这种仇恨是一种极度的邪恶，不会产生好结果。我们必须牢记卡尔·马克思的话，按照他的教导寻找真理。这种贫困的不公平或许会将我们团结起来，而不是将我们分开。我们必须牢记，我们都是通过劳动在这个世界上制造着有价值的东西。卡尔·马克思所说的这些重要真理，我们必须铭记在心，永不忘记。

“但是我的同胞们！在这间屋子里，我们——我们黑人们——还有另外一个使命，那是我们独有的。在我们心中有一种强烈而真实的使命，如果我们辜负了这个使命，我们将会永远迷失。那么，让我们看看这种特殊使命到底是什么。”

科普兰医生松了松衬衫的领子，他的喉咙里有一种哽咽的感觉，他的心里有太多痛苦的爱。他环顾沉默的客人，他们在等待着。院子里、门廊里的那些人同样静静地站着，跟屋里的人一样聚精会神。一位失聪的老人向前倾着身子，一只手兜在耳朵上。一个女人用安抚奶嘴安慰着焦躁不安的婴儿。辛格先生专注地站在门口。大部分年轻人则坐在地板上，这里面便有兰西·戴维斯。这个男孩很紧张，嘴唇毫无血色。他用两只胳膊紧紧抱着膝盖，年轻的面庞上是一种郁郁寡欢的神情。屋子里所有的眼睛都注视着科普兰医生，眼睛里闪烁着对真理的渴望。

“今天，我们要把五块钱的奖金颁发给一个高中生，他就‘我的志向：我该如何提升黑人在社会中的地位’这个题目写出了最出色的文章。今年获得这个奖项的是兰西·戴维斯。”

科普兰医生从口袋里掏出一个信封。“我无须再告诉大家，这个奖项的价值不仅仅在于奖金的数目——而是其代表的神圣真理和信念。”

兰西笨拙地站了起来，郁郁寡欢的嘴唇一直在哆嗦。他鞠了躬，接过了奖金。“你想让我把自己的文章念一念吗？”

“不用了，”科普兰医生说，“但我希望你这周找个时间来跟我聊聊。”

“好的，先生。”屋里又安静下来。

“‘我不愿意做奴仆！’在这些文章里，我反复读到这样的愿望。奴仆？我们当中只有千分之一的人有机会做奴仆。我们没有工作！我们没机会服务！”

屋子里爆发出不安的笑声。

“听着！我们中有五分之一的人去做苦力修路，去负责这个城市的卫生，或者在锯木厂、农场工作。另有五分之一的人根本找不到工作，但其余五分之三的人——我们大多数人呢？我们为那些连自己吃的东西都不会做的人做饭，很多人一辈子侍弄花草，只是为了一两个人享乐，还有很多人在豪华的房子里擦亮打过蜡的地板，或者我们为那些懒到不肯自己开车的人当司机。我们耗费自己的生命，做了成千上万份工作，而这些工作却对人没有任何真正的用处。我们辛苦劳作，但所有的劳动都浪费了。这就是服务吗？不是，这是奴役。

“我们辛苦劳作，但我们的劳动浪费了，我们又没有机会去服务。今天上午到这里的这些学生们，你们代表了我们民族里面幸运的少数人。我们大多数人都根本上不了学。你们每一个人的背后，都有成打的年轻人连自己的名字都写不下来。我们被剥夺了学习和智慧的尊严。

“‘人尽其才，按需分配。’我们这里的所有人都知道真正的贫穷是种什么样的折磨，这就是一种严重的不公平。但有一种不公平更为严重——被剥夺了按自己能力去劳动的权利，终其一生，都在做无谓的工作，被剥夺了服务的机会。剥夺我们的精神和心灵财富比抢走我们钱包里的钱财更可怕。

“今天上午在这里的年轻人当中，有些也许想当教师、护士，或者当自己民族的领导者，但你们大多数人都会被剥夺这种机会。你们不得不为了无用的目的出卖自己，才能勉强活下去。你们会遭受挫折，会失败。年轻的化学家去摘棉花，年轻的作家不能学习认字，教师在熨衣板上遭受无谓的奴役。我们在政府部门没有代表，我们不能投票。在这个伟大的国家里，我们是最受压迫的民族。我们不能抬高声音，因为长久不用，我们的舌头已经烂在了嘴里。我们的心越来越空虚，丧失了实现使命的力量。

“黑人同胞们！我们身上有人类思想和灵魂的所有财富，我们贡献出最宝贵的天赋，但我们的贡献被蔑视，被嗤之以鼻。我们的天赋被践踏在泥里，一文不值，让我们去做的工作还不如牲畜的工作有意义。黑人们！我们必须站起来，重新变成一个整体！我们必须自由！”

房间里响起窃窃私语的声音，一种歇斯底里的情绪在慢慢积聚。科普兰医生哽咽着，握紧了拳头。他觉得好像自己已经膨胀为一个巨人，心里的爱让他的胸膛变成了发动机。他想要大喊，让全镇的人们都听到自己的声音。他想要跌倒在地板上，用巨人的声音呐喊。房间里充满了呻吟和叫喊。

“救救我们！”

“万能的主！带我们离开这片死亡的荒野！”

“哈里路亚！救救我们，主啊！”

他挣扎着控制住自己，挣扎着，最终恢复了自制力。他压下内心的呐喊，寻求着那种强大、真实的声音。

“注意！”他喊道，“我们要拯救自己，但不是通过哀悼的祈祷来拯救，不是通过好逸恶劳和烈酒，不是通过身体的愉悦和无知，不是通过顺从和谦卑，而是通过骄傲，通过尊严，通过变得坚强、强大，以此来拯救自己。我们必须为我们真正的使命积聚力量。”

他突然停住了，站得笔直。“每年这个时候，我们会用自己卑微的方式阐释卡尔·马克思的第一训示。今天来参加聚会的每个人都预先送来了礼物，你们很多人牺牲了自己的舒适，只是为了满足别人的需求。你们每个人都尽了自己最大的能力，从来没有想过将来会得到什么价值的礼物回报。我们彼此分享，这是非常自然的事情。我们很早便意识到，给予比接受更美好。我们心里早已记住了卡尔·马克思的话：‘人尽其才，按需分配。’”

科普兰医生沉默了很久，好像话已经说完了。然后，他又说道：

“我们的使命，就是在我们屈辱的每一天，都要带着力量和尊严前行。我们必须有强烈的骄傲之心，因为我们了解人类思想和灵魂的价值。我们必须要教给自己的孩子们，我们必须做出牺牲，这样他们才能够赢得学习和智慧的尊严。这个时刻终究会到来，我们心里的财富将不再被蔑视和嗤之以鼻；这个时刻终究会到来，我们可以有机会去服务、去劳动，我们的劳动不会再被浪费。我们的使命就是带着力量和信念静候这个时刻的来临。”

话讲完了。掌声响起来，屋里地板上有跺脚的声音，外面坚硬的冬日大地上也传来跺脚的声音。厨房里飘来热的浓咖啡的味道。约翰·罗伯茨分发礼物，叫着卡片上写的名字。波西娅从炉子上的大壶里舀出咖啡，马歇尔·尼克尔斯则分发着一块块蛋糕。科普兰医生在客人中间走动着，身边总是围着一小群人。

有人碰碰他的胳膊肘。“你儿子巴迪就是以他命名的？”他回答是的。兰西·戴维斯追着他问问题，不管什么问题，他都回答“是的”。这种快乐让他觉得有些醉意蒙眬。教育、劝解他的同胞，给他们做解释——还有，让他们明白真理，这就是最好的事情。说出真理，得到关注。

“这次聚会我们真的非常开心。”

他站在门厅里，跟人们道别，一一握手。他重重地斜靠在墙上，只有眼睛还能动弹，他太累了。

“我真的很感谢。”

辛格先生最后一个离开。他是个真正的好人，是个有才华、真正有知识的人，他的身上看不到刻薄的傲慢。所有人都离开了，他留到了最后。他等待着，似乎在期待最后的结束语。

科普兰医生伸手按住喉咙，因为喉咙很疼。“教师，”他声音沙哑地说，“是我们最缺乏的，还有领导者，得有人把我们团结起来，引导我们。”

庆祝活动结束了，所有房间看上去都空荡荡的，一片狼藉。屋里很冷。波西娅正在厨房洗杯子。圣诞树上的银色雪花被踩到了地上，有两件装饰品已经碎了。

他非常疲倦，但心里的快乐和狂热让他难以平静。他从卧室开始，动手整理屋子。文件柜上有一张掉出来的卡片——兰西·戴维斯的资料。他脑子里出现了要对兰西说的话，他有些心神不宁，因为这些话他现在没法说出来。他满脑子都是男孩那张郁郁寡欢的脸，挥之不去。他打开上层抽屉，把卡片放回原位，A、B、C——他紧张地翻动着这些字母，然后眼睛定格在自己的名字上：本尼迪克特·马迪·科普兰。

文件夹里有几张肺部的X光片，还有简短的病历。他把一张X光片放到光线底下。在左肺上部，有一处明亮的地方，像颗钙化的星星，再往下有一大块阴影区域，右肺上部有块一模一样的地方。科普兰医生迅速将X光片放回文件夹，只有他给自己写的简短记录还拿在手里，上面的字迹很大，很潦草，他自己都几乎认不出来了。“一九二〇年——淋巴结钙化——淋巴结明显增厚，病变已得到控制——功能恢复。一九三七年——病变复发——X光片显示——”记录看不下去了。起初，他看不清楚字迹，等看清后，他又不明白什么意思。最后，记录上有几个字：“预断：不得而知。”

那种熟悉的灰暗疯狂的感觉又传遍他的全身。他俯下身，猛地拉开下面的一个抽屉。一堆乱七八糟的信件——有色人种进步协会写来的几张便条。黛西写来的一封信，已经发黄了。汉密尔顿写的便条，要一块五毛钱。他在找什么？他的两只手在抽屉里乱翻一气，最后他僵直地站起身来。

浪费时间。已经过了一个小时了。

波西娅在厨房桌前削着土豆。她弯腰趴在那里，脸上一副悲伤的表情。

“把肩膀抬起来，”他生气地说，“别再发愁了，你整天发愁、发呆，我实在看不下去了。”

“我只是在想威利。”她说，“写信的话，只要三天就到了。但他没有理由让我这么担心，他不是那种男孩。我现在感觉很奇怪。”

“耐心点，女儿。”

“我觉得必须得耐心。”

“有几个病人我得去看看，很快就回来。”

“好的。”

“一切都会好的。”他说。

走到晴朗凉爽的正午阳光底下，他的快乐消失了一大半，脑子里都是病人的病情。肾肿胀，脊膜炎，脊椎结核病。他从后座拿起汽车的曲柄。通常，他会招呼大街上路过的黑人给自己用曲柄发动汽车，他的同胞们总是很乐意效劳。但今天，他自己把曲柄伸进去，猛力转动起来。他用大衣袖子抹抹脸上的汗珠，匆忙坐到方向盘后面，开车走了。

今天他说的那些话，人们听懂了多少？有多少东西可以有点价值？他回想着自己的措辞，那些词似乎都淡去了，没有了力量，而没说出口的那些话反而沉甸甸地压在心头。这些话涌上他的唇边，令他焦虑不安。他眼前浮现出同胞们遭受苦难的面孔，这些面孔越来越多。他开车沿着街道慢慢前行，心里因为这种愤怒、焦躁的爱而翻腾不止。

7

好多年来，这个小镇都没有经历过今年这么寒冷的冬天了。窗玻璃上结了霜冻，各家各户的屋顶也都变成了白色。冬天的午后，阳光呈现出一种曚昽的柠檬黄色，影子则是淡淡的蓝色。街道的水洼上，都结了一层薄薄的冰。圣诞节的第二天，有人说，北边十英里之外的地方下了一场小雪。

辛格的身上发生了变化。安东纳普勒斯离开之后的最初几个月里，辛格总是要出去散步很长时间。他散步的足迹覆盖了各个方向长达几英里的路程，几乎走遍了整个小镇。他走过河边拥挤的住宅区，自从这个冬天那些工厂的生意不景气之后，这些住宅区比以前更脏乱了，许多人的眼里都流露出一种阴沉的孤独感。人们出于无奈，只能无所事事，于是便生出一种焦躁不安的感觉，并且火热爆发出许多新的信仰。一个在工厂染缸处工作的年轻人突然宣布，他具有了一种伟大的神圣力量。他说，他的职责就是要把上帝的一套新戒律传递给大家。年轻人建起一个神龛，每天晚上都有成百上千人过来。他们在地上打滚，彼此摇晃，他们认为自己面对的是一种超人类的东西。还出现了谋杀案。一个女人赚的钱连吃饭都不够，她认定是工头在她的工作记录上做了手脚，于是用刀刺穿了他的喉咙。一户黑人家庭搬进了一条惨淡的街道末端的房子里，引起了公愤，邻居们烧掉了他家的房子，还打了这家的男主人。但这都是些小事件，并没有引起真正的变化。大家谈论的罢工从来没有实现过，因为人们并不能团结起来。一切如常。即便在最寒冷的夜晚，迪克西阳光游乐场也开放着。人们做梦，打架，睡觉，跟平常一样。出于习惯，他们简化了自己的思想，这样他们便不会迷失在明日之后的黑暗之中了。

辛格走过镇上那些乱七八糟的地方，觉得气味难闻，黑人们拥挤地住在这里。这里有更多快乐，也有更多暴力。巷子里经常飘荡着杜松子酒那种刺激好闻的味道。窗户上映着温暖静谧的炉火的火光。几乎每天晚上，教堂里都有集会。一块块棕褐色草地上坐落着一幢幢舒适的小房子——这些地方辛格也走过。这里的孩子们更结实，对陌生人也更友好。他走过富人的住宅区。那些房子非常宏伟古老，有白色烟囱，围着精美的铁艺栏杆。他走过那些高大的砖房子，汽车在门前车道上鸣着喇叭，烟囱里不断地飘出一股股烟。再向外走，便到了几条道路的边缘。这些路从镇上通往一些杂货店，每周六晚上都有农民到杂货店里围坐在火炉旁。他经常在四个主要商业区漫无目的地溜达，这些地方灯火通明，之后他又穿过后面黑乎乎、空荡荡的小街巷。这个镇上所有的地方，辛格都知道。他注视着上千扇窗户里投出来的一方方昏黄的灯光。冬天的夜晚很美，天空是种寒冷的蔚蓝色，星星格外明亮。

现在在他散步的过程中，经常会有人跟他说话，把他拦下来，各种各样的人都认识他。如果跟他说话的人是个陌生人，辛格会递上卡片，这样人家就理解他为什么沉默不语。他成为镇上家喻户晓的人。走路的时候他的肩膀挺得很直，两只手一直插在口袋里，一双灰色的眼睛似乎看到了周围的一切，脸上总是一副平和的神情，这种神情似乎只有特别智慧或者特别伤心的人身上才会有。如果有任何人想跟他为伴，他总是很乐意停下来。毕竟，他只是散步，哪儿也不去。

现在，关于哑巴的各种流言在镇上四散而起。以前跟安东纳普勒斯生活在一起的那些年，他们上下班都是一起走，但除此之外，他们便一直独自待在房间里。那时候没人来打扰他们——如果有人看他们的话，注意到的也是那个大块头希腊人。那些年里，辛格是被遗忘的人。

关于哑巴的传言丰富多彩。犹太人说他是个犹太人。主街两边的商人则称，他继承了大笔遗产，是个富人。一个被打压的纺织联盟里则有人背地里说，哑巴是美国产业组织委员会的组织者。好几年以前，一个孤单的土耳其人流落到镇上，跟家人一起开了家小店，靠卖家庭日用织品艰难度日，他跟妻子情绪激昂地说哑巴是土耳其人。他说，自己说土耳其语的时候，哑巴听得懂。他说这话时，声音温暖，忘了跟孩子吵嚷，充满了憧憬和活力。乡下来的一位老人说，哑巴是从他家乡附近来的，还说哑巴父亲种的烟草是全国最好的。人们对他众说纷纭。

安东纳普勒斯！辛格的心里永远留着对好友的记忆。晚上，他闭上眼睛，希腊人的音容笑貌便浮现在黑暗中——胖胖的，油光满面，带着睿智而温柔的笑容。在他的梦里，他们两人总是在一起。现在好友已经走了一年多。

今年似乎说长不长，说短不短，而且仿佛从普通的时间感里抽掉了一般——就像一个人喝醉了，或者半梦半醒的样子。在每个小时的背后，都有他好友的影子。跟安东纳普勒斯在一起的那段生活被埋葬了，然后又变化了、发展了，如同他周围的一切。在最初几个月里，他经常想起安东纳普勒斯被带走之前那几个糟糕的星期——想起他生病之后的麻烦事，想起逮捕的传票，想起努力控制好友异想天开时所经历的痛苦。他想起和安东纳普勒斯不愉快的那段过往。在久远的过去，有一个记忆反复闪现在他的脑海中。

他们没有朋友。有时候他们会去见其他哑巴——在十年间，他们认识了三个哑巴，但总是有这事或那事发生。有个哑巴在与他们相识后的第二周便搬到了另一个州。另一个哑巴结了婚，生了六个孩子，不再用手语说话了。但在好友离开之后，辛格记得最清楚的是与第三个哑巴熟人的关系。

这个哑巴叫卡尔，是个面色蜡黄的年轻人，在工厂里上班。他的眼睛是淡黄色的，牙齿很脆，是透明的，所以看上去也是淡黄色的。蓝色工装裤松松垮垮地挂在他骨瘦如柴的小身板上，让他看起来像个蓝黄色碎布拼的布娃娃。

他们邀请卡尔吃饭，跟他说好先到安东纳普勒斯工作的商店去会合。他俩到的时候，希腊人还在忙活着，正在商店后面的厨房里做一批焦糖奶油软糖，马上就要完工了。软糖在长长的大理石桌面上放着，色泽金黄，闪闪发光，空气里充满温暖醇厚的香甜味道。安东纳普勒斯很高兴卡尔在注视着他，他将刀子滑进温暖的糖果中，将其切成小方块。他把油乎乎的刀子边上留下的一角软糖递给他们的新朋友，又表演了一个小把戏。他如果想要讨好谁，都会表演这个把戏给人家看。他指着炉子上正在沸腾的一罐糖浆，用手扇着脸，斜眯起眼睛，好让人知道糖浆有多热。然后他把手放进一罐冷水里浸湿，一下伸进沸腾的糖浆里，又迅速将手抽出，重新放进冷水里。他瞪着眼睛，伸出舌头，似乎痛苦不堪的样子。他甚至绞着手，一只脚在地上跳着，整个房子都晃动起来。然后，他猛然笑起来，伸出那只手，显示这只是个玩笑，又打了一下卡尔的肩膀。

这是个暗淡的冬日夜晚，他们手挽手走在街上，呼出的气息在寒冷的空气中凝成了白雾。辛格走在中间，两度在人行道上离开他俩去商店里买东西。卡尔和安东纳普勒斯拿着食品袋，辛格紧紧挽着他们的胳膊，一路微笑着回家。他们的房间很舒适，他快乐地忙活着，一边跟卡尔交谈着。饭后，他们两人继续聊天，安东纳普勒斯则带着一种迟钝的微笑观望着。大块头希腊人不时笨拙地走到壁橱前，倒几杯杜松子酒。卡尔坐在窗前，只有当安东纳普勒斯把酒杯塞到他面前的时候，他才会喝，极其郑重地小口啜饮着。辛格不记得好友以前什么时候对陌生人如此亲近过，他很高兴地预想着什么时候卡尔可以经常来拜访他们。

时间已过午夜，突然有件事毁掉了他们的欢乐聚会。安东纳普勒斯又去了壁橱跟前，回来时脸上却带着一种愤怒的表情。他坐在床上，开始不断地盯着他们的新朋友，脸上一副生气和极度厌恶的表情。辛格努力急切地说着话，想掩饰他奇怪的表现，但希腊人很固执。卡尔缩在椅子上，抱着骨瘦如柴的膝盖，大块头希腊人脸上的痛苦表情让他既着迷又困惑。他脸色通红，怯懦地咽着口水。辛格无法继续漠视整个场面了。终于，他问安东纳普勒斯是不是肚子痛，或者是不是感觉不舒服想要睡觉。安东纳普勒斯摇摇头，指着卡尔，然后把知道的所有肮脏手势都做了个遍，脸上的厌恶表情简直不忍直视。卡尔缩成一团，很害怕。终于，大块头希腊人咬牙切齿地从椅子上站了起来。卡尔慌忙拿起帽子，走出了房间。辛格跟着他下了楼梯，不知道该如何跟这个陌生人解释好友的事情。卡尔缩着身子站在楼下的门口，一副无力的模样，鸭舌帽拉下来挡在脸上。最后，他们握握手，卡尔走了。

安东纳普勒斯告诉他，他们的客人趁他们不注意，去壁橱那里喝光了所有的杜松子酒。无论如何劝说都无法让安东纳普勒斯相信，是他自己喝干了那瓶酒。大块头希腊人坐在床上，那张圆脸阴沉忧郁，满是责备的表情，大滴的泪珠慢慢滚落下来，流到内衣的领子上，怎么哄他都无济于事。终于他睡了过去，但辛格在黑暗中久久无法入睡。他们从此再也没有见过卡尔。

多年以后，有一次，安东纳普勒斯从壁炉架上的花瓶里拿走了交房租的钱，全都喂了老虎机。还有一次，夏天的午后，安东纳普勒斯赤身裸体下楼去拿报纸。夏天的酷热让他难以忍受。他们分期付款买了一个电冰箱，安东纳普勒斯总是不断吸吮小冰块，甚至在睡觉时把几个小冰块放到床上慢慢融化。

有一次安东纳普勒斯喝醉了，把一碗通心粉扣到了辛格脸上。

最初那几个月里，这些难堪的记忆穿过他的思绪，就像难看的丝线穿过地毯一样。然后，这些记忆消失了，他们所有那些不愉快的记忆都忘记了。随着一年年过去，他对好友的思念与日俱增，最后，他心里想着的安东纳普勒斯只有他自己才认识。

这就是那位他会将所有心事都与之倾诉的好友，这就是那个除了自己没人知道他很聪明的安东纳普勒斯。岁月流逝，好友在他的心里似乎越长越大，在夜晚的黑暗中，好友的那张脸严肃而又机敏地向外望着。他脑子里对好友的记忆改变了，那些错误或愚蠢的记忆统统忘掉了——只留下好友聪慧而美好的记忆。

他看见安东纳普勒斯坐在他面前的一把大椅子上，安静地坐在那里，一动不动。他的圆脸神秘莫测，嘴巴挂着智慧的微笑，眼睛很深邃。他望着别人对他说话，而以他的智慧，他能懂。

这就是现在一直在他脑子里的安东纳普勒斯，这就是他想与之倾诉一切的那位好友。今年真的发生了一些事情。他被留在了一片陌生的土地上，一个人。他睁开眼睛，周围有那么多东西让他无法理解，他困惑不解。

他望着他们唇上拼出的那些词。

我们黑人想要一个最终获得自由的机会，自由只是做出贡献的权利。我们想要服务，想要分享，想要劳动，反过来，我们想要享用本该属于我们的东西。但在我遇见的白人当中，只有你意识到我的同胞们处于可怕的贫穷境地。

你明白吗，辛格先生？这首曲子一直在我心里，我一定要成为一名真正的音乐家。也许我现在什么都不懂，但等二十岁时我会懂的。明白吗，辛格先生？然后，我要到国外一个有雪的国家去旅行。

让我们干了这瓶。我想要一小瓶，因为我们正在思考自由，就是这个词，像我脑子里的一条虫子一样。是吗？不是？多少？多小？这个词意味着劫掠、盗窃和狡猾。我们会自由的，而最聪明的人又会奴役其他人。但是！但是这个词还有另外一层意思。在所有词汇中，这个词最危险。我们这些知道这一点的人必须要警惕。这个词让我们感觉良好——实际上这个词是个伟大的理想，但正因为有了这种理想，骗子们才为我们织就了最丑陋的网。

最后一个人搓着鼻子。他不太常来，也不太说话。他会问问题。

七个多月以来，这四个人一直到他屋里来。他们从不一起来——总是一个一个来。而他则无一例外，会站在门口带着真诚的微笑迎接他们。对安东纳普勒斯的想念一直伴随着他——跟好友走后最初的那几个月一样——跟其他人在一起总比长时间一个人待着强得多。就像很多年以前，他对安东纳普勒斯发誓（甚至把誓言写了下来，钉在床头上面的墙上）——发誓说，他会戒烟、戒酒、戒肉一个月。最初几天非常难熬，他坐卧不安，频繁去水果店找安东纳普勒斯，以至于查尔斯·帕克都对他没了好脸。他干完手上所有的雕刻活儿，会走到店铺前面闲逛，跟钟表匠和女售货员混一阵子，或者溜达到某个冷饮店喝杯可口可乐。那些日子里，靠近任何陌生人都比一个人待着想香烟、啤酒和肉要强。

最初，他根本不懂那四个人在说什么。他们说啊说啊——几个月的时间过去了，他们说得越来越多。他习惯了他们的嘴唇动作，能听懂他们说的每一个字。后来又过了一阵子，他们还没开口，他就已经知道他们每个人都想说些什么了，因为意思总是一模一样。

他的双手对他来说是个折磨，它们不肯消停。在睡梦中，两只手总会抽搐。有时候，他醒过来，发现两只手正在面前比画着梦里的一些词。他不喜欢看着自己的手，或者想到它们。它们纤细，棕褐色，非常结实。在之前的那些年里，他总是小心翼翼地呵护两只手。冬天，他抹上油，防止皲裂，他会把角质层磨掉，指甲总是用锉刀磨成跟指尖同样的形状。他喜欢清洗和保养自己的双手。但现在，他只是一天两次用刷子粗粗地刷一下，然后把它们插进口袋里。

他在屋里来回走动时，会把手指关节掰得嘎嘎作响，还会猛拽关节，直到把手指拽疼为止。或者，他会用一只拳头去打另一只手掌。有时候他一个人待着，脑子里又想到好友，两只手便不由自主地开始比画字词。然后，他意识到自己就像一个自言自语的人被人撞见了一样，好像犯了什么道德错误似的。羞愧与悲伤混杂在一起，他握起拳头放在背后，但双手依然让他不得安宁。

辛格站在街道上，面前是他和安东纳普勒斯曾经住过的房子。傍晚时分，空气里烟雾弥漫，一片灰暗。西边的天空有一道道冷冰冰的黄色和红粉色云霞。一只冬天的麻雀疲惫不堪，在烟雾弥漫的天空中飞着各种花样，最后落在房子的山墙上。街上空无一人。

他的眼睛定格在二楼右手边的窗户上。这是他们的前屋，后面是个大厨房，安东纳普勒斯就在那里做饭。从亮灯的窗户看去，他望见一个女人在房间里来回忙着。灯光下，她身材高大，身影有些模糊，戴着围裙。一个男人坐在那里，手里拿着晚报。一个男孩拿着一片面包走到窗前，把鼻子贴在窗玻璃上。辛格看到，这个房间跟他们离开时没有两样——安东纳普勒斯的大床，他自己的小铁床，松软的大沙发，还有那张轻便折椅。那只破糖碗当成了烟灰缸，天花板上因漏雨留下的那块潮湿地方还在，还有角落里放脏衣服的箱子。在这样一个傍晚，厨房里一般不会开灯，只有大炉子的燃油炉口闪着光。安东纳普勒斯总是把火苗调得很小，每个炉口里面只能看到一圈参差不齐的金色和蓝色的光。屋里很温暖，散发着晚餐的香味。安东纳普勒斯用木勺品尝着菜肴的味道，他们一起喝着红酒。在炉子前面的油毡垫上，炉口燃烧的火苗投下明亮的影子——五个小小的金色灯笼。乳白色的暮色渐浓，这些小灯笼便愈发明显起来，夜晚终于降临的时候，它们便欢快地燃烧着，非常清晰。到那个时候，晚饭也煮好了，他们打开灯，把椅子拖到桌前。

辛格低头望着昏暗的前门。他想起他们早晨一同出门，晚上一同回家。人行道上有个破损的地方，安东纳普勒斯在那里绊倒过一次，伤了胳膊肘。那个邮箱，电力公司每月的账单都送到那里去。他能够感觉到指尖碰到好友胳膊时的那种温暖。

现在街上一片漆黑。他又一次抬头望望那个窗户，看见那个陌生的女人、男人和孩子在一起。他心头一片空虚。一切都没了。安东纳普勒斯走了，不在这里了，也无从记忆，他对好友的思念在别处。辛格闭上眼睛，努力想着精神病院，还有安东纳普勒斯今晚住的房间。他想起那些窄小的白床，还有那些在角落里玩纸牌的老人们。他紧闭双眼，但脑子里那个房间却依然不清晰。心底的那种空虚感非常深重。过了一会儿，他抬头再次瞥了一眼窗户，便沿着漆黑的人行道迈步走开了。这条人行道他们曾经并肩走过那么多次。

这是周六的夜晚，主街上人流涌动。穿着工装瑟瑟发抖的黑人们在廉价商店的橱窗前徘徊，家人们在电影院售票处排着队，年轻姑娘和小伙子们则盯着外面贴的海报。往来穿梭的汽车非常危险，他不得不等了很长时间，然后才穿过马路。

他经过水果店。橱窗里的水果都很漂亮——香蕉、橘子、鳄梨、色泽艳丽的小金橘，甚至还有几个菠萝，但查尔斯·帕克正在里面招待一个顾客。在他看来，查尔斯·帕克的脸奇丑无比。有几次，查尔斯·帕克不在店里，他走进去，在里面待了很久，甚至还走进了后面安东纳普勒斯制作糖果的厨房。但如果查尔斯·帕克在店里，他绝对不进去。自从安东纳普勒斯乘汽车离开那一天起，他们俩便都小心翼翼地避免碰面。在街上遇见的时候，他们立刻扭过头去，连头都不点。有一次，他想给朋友送一罐他最喜欢的蓝果树蜂蜜，他用邮件从查尔斯·帕克店里订购，这样就不必面对他了。

辛格站在橱窗前，望着好友的表兄招呼客人。周六晚上的生意总是很好，安东纳普勒斯有时必须得工作到十点。那个很大的自动爆米花机就在门口附近。店员放进一份玉米粒，玉米粒便在里面旋转起来，像巨大的雪片一样。商店里散发出来的味道温暖而又熟悉，花生壳踩了一地。

辛格继续沿街朝前走去。他必须得小心翼翼地在人群中穿行，以免自己被撞到。因为是节假日，街上挂了很多彩灯，人们一群群站着，彼此搂抱着，大声说笑。年轻的父亲们把哭闹怕冷的孩子扛在肩头。一个戴着红蓝帽子的救世军女孩在街角摇着铃铛，当她望着辛格时，他觉得必须要在她身边的罐子里丢一枚硬币。路上还有乞丐，有黑人也有白人，他们伸出帽子或者粗糙的手。霓虹灯广告在人们的脸上投下一种橘黄色的光。

他走到一个街角。有一个八月份的下午，他和安东纳普勒斯曾经在这里见过一条疯狗。然后，他经过军需品商店上面的那间屋子，每到发工资的日子，安东纳普勒斯都要到这里来拍张照片。这会儿，他口袋里便装着很多这样的照片。他向西拐，朝河边走去。有一次他们带着午餐，过了桥，到河对岸的田野里野餐。

辛格沿着大街走了大约一个小时。在所有人群中，只有他形单影只。最后，他拿出手表，转身朝住的房子走去。也许，那几个人中有人今晚会到他屋里来。他希望如此。

他给安东纳普勒斯寄去一大箱子圣诞节礼物。他还给那四个人每人准备了一份礼物，凯利太太也有份。他给大家买了一台收音机，放在窗前的桌子上。科普兰医生没有注意到这台收音机。比夫·布兰农则立刻注意到了，抬了抬眉毛。杰克·布朗特只要在这里，便会一直开着收音机，总是听同一个台。他说话的时候，似乎在大声喊叫着好压过音乐声，额头上青筋暴突。米克·凯利看到收音机时，不明白怎么回事，她脸色通红，一遍遍地问收音机是不是真的是他的，问她能不能听。她调了好几分钟，然后才找到喜欢的台。她坐在椅子上，前倾着身体，双手放在膝盖上，张着嘴，太阳穴上的脉搏狂跳。不管听到的是什么，她好像都全力倾听着。整整一个下午她都坐在那里。她冲他咧嘴笑了一次，这时候她的眼睛湿润了，她忙用拳头揉着眼睛。她问他，她是否可以在他上班时偶尔进来听听收音机，他点头同意了。这样，后来的几天里，他无论什么时候打开门，都发现她坐在收音机前，一只手梳理着一头凌乱的短发，脸上的那种表情他以前从来没有见过。

圣诞节后不久，有天晚上四个人碰巧同时来看他，以前从来没有发生过这样的事情。辛格微笑着在房间里走动着，送上茶点，尽最大努力礼貌待客，让客人们感觉舒服。然而，还是有什么事情不对头。

科普兰医生不肯坐下，他站在门口，手里拿着帽子，对其他人只是冷淡地鞠了躬。他们望着他，好像很奇怪他为什么来这里。杰克·布朗特打开随身带来的啤酒，泡沫洒到胸前的衬衫上。米克·凯利听着收音机里的音乐。比夫·布兰农坐在床上，跷着二郎腿，一双眼睛扫视着面前的几个人，然后眯起眼睛盯住不动了。

辛格感觉困惑不解。平常，他们每个人都很健谈，而现在他们凑到一起，却沉默了。他们进来时，他还期待着会有一种爆发。朦胧之中，他期待着这是什么事情的终结。然而，屋子里只有一种紧张的气氛。他用两只手紧张地比画着，似乎是在从空气中拖拽看不见的什么东西，然后将它们捆绑到一起。

杰克·布朗特站在科普兰医生身边。“我记得你的长相，以前我们碰见过一次——在外面台阶上。”

科普兰医生小心地翕动嘴唇，好像在用剪刀剪裁自己的话一样。“我没意识到我们认识。”他说。然后，他僵直的身体似乎缩小了，他后退着，最后站到了门槛之外。

比夫·布兰农镇定地吸着烟，烟雾淡淡地飘散在屋子里。他转身对着米克，望着她，脸上升起红晕。他半闭起眼睛，很快，脸色又变得苍白起来。“你现在怎么样啊？”

“什么怎么样？”米克满脸怀疑地问。

“就是生活的事情啊，”他说，“学校——等等。”

“我觉得还行。”她说。

他们每个人都望着辛格，仿佛在期待着什么。他困惑了，送上茶点，微笑着。

杰克用手掌摩擦着嘴唇，他不再努力跟科普兰医生聊下去，而是挨着比夫坐在了床边。“以前用红色粉笔在工厂周围的篱笆和墙上写那些血淋淋的警告的人，你知道是谁吗？”

“不知道，”比夫说，“什么血淋淋的警告？”

“主要是《旧约》里的话。这件事我想了很长时间了。”

每个人的话都主要是对着哑巴说的，他们的想法似乎都在他的身上汇集到一起，就像车轮的辐条都通向中心毂一样。

“天气冷得非同寻常。”最终，比夫说道，“那天，我翻看以前的记录，发现一九一九年温度计低到过华氏十度。今天早晨气温只有十六度，自从那年的大严寒以来，这恐怕就是最冷的一天了。”

“今天早晨，煤屋屋檐上有垂下来的冰柱。”米克说。

“上周，我们赚的钱还不够开工资。”杰克说。

他们又谈论了一会儿天气。每个人似乎都在等着其他人先开口。然后，一冲动，他们又同时起来要走。科普兰医生先走，其他人紧跟其后。他们都走了，辛格一个人站在屋子里，他搞不清状况，于是想要干脆忘掉。那天晚上，他决定给安东纳普勒斯写封信。

安东纳普勒斯并不识字，但这不妨碍辛格给他写信。他一直知道好友弄不懂纸面上那些词的意思，但几个月过去了，他开始想，也许自己弄错了，也许安东纳普勒斯只是不想让别人知道自己是识字的。而且精神病院里很有可能有个聋哑人，可以为他读信，并解释给他听。辛格为自己的那些信想了好多个理由，因为当他感到困惑或伤心时，他总有一种迫切的需求，想给好友写信。然而，信一旦写完，又从来没有寄出过。他从晨报、晚报上剪下连环漫画，每个周六寄给好友，每个月还会寄出一张邮政汇票。然而，他写给安东纳普勒斯的那些长信则攒在他的口袋里，最后他会把这些信销毁了之。

四个人走了以后，辛格穿上那件暖和的灰色外套，戴上灰色毡帽出了屋子。他总是到店里去写信。而且，他答应第二天早晨去送一件活儿，他想现在干完，这样就不会耽搁了。夜晚寒冷，结了霜冻。月亮圆了，镶着一圈金边。在漫天星光下，屋顶都是黑色的。他一边走一边想着这封信如何开头，但等走到商店时，他连第一个句子都没想好。他拿出钥匙，开门走进漆黑的店里，打开了前面的灯。

他在商店的最里面工作，一块布帘子把他工作的地方隔了出来，这个地方就像个私密的房间。除了他的工作台和椅子，角落里有个很重的保险箱，还有一个洗手盆，上面装着一面发绿的镜子。此外，还有几个架子，上面放满了盒子和破旧的钟表。辛格把工作台上的盖布卷起来，然后从上面的毛毡盒子里拿出他答应要修好的银盘子。尽管店里很冷，他还是脱掉大衣，卷起蓝色条纹衬衫的袖子，这样工作起来便不会碍事了。

他花了很长时间整修盘子中央的那些花押字。他集中精力，用刻刀在银器上小心翼翼地移动着。工作时他的双眼有种犀利的饥渴神情，令人好奇。他还在考虑着给好友安东纳普勒斯要写的那封信。过了午夜，他的工作才做完。他把盘子收好，因为兴奋，额头都冒出了汗珠。他清理了工作台，开始写信。他喜欢用笔在纸上写下一个又一个字。这封信写得小心翼翼，就好像信纸就是银盘子似的。

我唯一的朋友：

我从咱们那本杂志上看到，协会今年要在梅肯开大会，会上有人发言，还要举行宴会，有四道主菜。我想象着这次会议。记得我们一直计划要去参加一次这样的大会，但从来没去过。现在，我多希望我们去过。我希望我们去参加这次大会，我一直在想象着那将是一幅什么样的场景。但是，当然，没有你我是不会去的。与会者来自各个州，他们都有很多话要说，心里有很多伟大的梦想。在一个教堂里还会举办一次特别仪式，进行一种什么竞赛，获奖的人会得到一枚金牌。我给你写信，告诉你我在想象着这一切。我想象着，又没有在想象。我的手已经很长时间没动了，几乎想不起来是怎么回事了。我想象着这次大会时，我会想到所有的客人都像是你，我的朋友。

前几天，我到咱们家门前站了一会儿，现在已经有人住在里面了。你还记得房前那棵大橡树吗？他们修剪了树枝，免得影响到电话线。后来这棵树却死了，树枝烂了，树干上出现了一个洞。而且，商店里的那只猫（你经常爱抚的那只猫）吃了有毒的东西，死掉了。真让人伤心。

辛格把笔停在纸上。他坐了很长时间，身体挺直紧绷着，没有再写下去。然后，他站起来，点上一根烟。房间里很冷，空气中有股酸腐的味道——一种煤油、银擦亮剂和烟草混合在一起的味道。他穿上外套、戴上围巾，慢慢定下心，又开始写起来。

你记得，上次我去看你时跟你说的那四个人。我给你画了他们的模样，那个黑人、年轻姑娘、留胡子的那个，还有开纽约咖啡馆的那个男人。关于他们的一些事情，我想跟你说说，但不知道该怎么说出来。

他们都很忙。实际上，他们太忙了，很难给他们画出像来。我不是说他们夜以继日地工作，而是说他们脑子里有很多事情，一刻也闲不下来。他们到我屋里来，一直跟我交谈。最后，我真的不明白一个人的嘴巴怎么能开合那么多次而不会感觉到疲惫。（然而，纽约咖啡馆的老板不一样——他跟别人不同。他的胡子很黑，每天必须得刮两次，他有那种电动剃须刀。他只是观望。其他人都有憎恨的东西。除了吃饭、睡觉、喝酒、交友之外，他们都有自己热爱的东西。这就是他们为什么那么忙的原因。）

留胡子的那个男人，我觉得他疯了。有时候他说话很清楚，像很久以前我上学时的老师一样，但有时候他说的话我完全听不懂。有时候他穿一套素净的西装，下次来的时候又浑身泥土，臭不可闻，穿着上班时的工装。他会晃着拳头说些难听的醉话，我不想让你听见。他觉得跟我有共同的秘密，但我不知道是什么。让我告诉你一件难以置信的事情吧。他能喝三品脱“幸福岁月”威士忌，之后还能说话，还能走路，还能保持清醒不睡觉。你不会相信，但千真万确。

我从那个女孩的妈妈那里租的房子，每月十六块钱。女孩以前像个男孩一样，穿着短裤，但现在她穿蓝裙子和宽松短衫。她还不算是个年轻女士。我愿意她过来看我。我给他们买了台收音机，这个女孩便总是过来。她喜欢音乐。我真希望知道她听的到底是什么。她知道我耳聋，但她以为我懂音乐。

那个黑人得了肺结核，但他在这里没有好医院可去，因为他是个黑人。他是个医生，比我认识的所有人工作得都辛苦，他说话根本不像黑人。其他黑人说话，我觉得很难听懂，他们的舌头发音时都不到位。这个黑人有时候让我害怕，他的眼睛炽热明亮。他请我去参加聚会，我去了。他有很多书，但没有悬疑故事书。他不喝酒，不吃肉，也不看电影。

自由和强盗啊，资本和民主啊，留胡子的那个丑男人这样说。然后他又自我矛盾，说自由是所有理想中最伟大的。我必须得找机会把我心里的音乐写出来，我要当音乐家，我必须得找机会，那个女孩这样说。我们没有机会服务，那个黑人医生这样说。这是我的同胞们神圣的需求。啊哈，纽约咖啡馆的老板说。他是个深思熟虑的人。

他们到我屋里来的时候，就是这样说话的。他们心里的那些话让他们不得安宁，所以他们总是很忙。你会觉得，他们如果碰到一起，肯定像这个星期在梅肯大会上那些协会成员碰到一起的场景一样。但并非如此。今天，他们同时来到我屋里，坐在那里就像不是一个城市里的人。他们甚至很失礼，你知道，我一直说有失礼貌、不照顾别人的感受都是不对的。他们就是这样。我搞不明白，我给你写信，因为我觉得你会明白。我的感觉很怪异。但这件事我写得够多了，我知道你会厌倦的，我也是如此。

现在，已经过了五个月零二十一天。这段时间，没有你我一直很孤单，我唯一能想象到的事情就是什么时候才能跟你再次团聚。如果不能很快去看你，我不知道该怎么办。

辛格把头放在工作台上，休息一下。木头的味道，还有下巴碰到木头的光滑的感觉，都让他想起上学的日子。他闭上眼睛，觉得很难受。他心里只有安东纳普勒斯的音容笑貌，他对好友的渴望如此强烈，让他无法呼吸。过了一会儿，辛格坐起来，拿过笔。

我为你订购的礼物没有按时送到，没能放进圣诞节给你寄过去的箱子里。我希望很快就到。我相信你会喜欢它，会很高兴的。我经常想起我们俩在一起的时光，想起一切。我想念你以前做的食物。纽约咖啡馆的食物比原来差远了。不久前，我在汤里发现了一只煮熟的苍蝇，混在蔬菜和面条里，像字母一样。但这都不算什么。我想念你，觉得很孤独，无法忍受，我很快会再去看你。我的假期还要再等六个月，但我觉得可以提前安排一下。我觉得必须这样，我不该这么孤单，不该没有你，只有你才懂我。

你永远的

约翰·辛格

他再次回到家中，已是深夜两点。那幢住满人的大房子一片漆黑，他小心摸索着，上了三段楼梯，并没有绊倒。他从口袋里掏出随身携带的卡片、手表和钢笔，然后把衣服整齐叠好，放到椅背上。灰色的法兰绒睡衣又暖和又柔软，他几乎刚把毯子拉到下巴底下，便立刻睡了过去。

在睡眠的黑暗之中，梦来了。一段漆黑的石头台阶上，点着几盏暗淡的黄色灯笼。安东纳普勒斯跪在台阶最上端，赤身裸体，摸索着他高高举过头顶的东西，凝视着它，像是在祈祷。他自己跪在这段台阶的中间位置，也是赤身裸体，很冷，眼睛一直盯着安东纳普勒斯，还有他举在头顶的东西。他身后的地上，他感觉到有留胡子的男人、那个女孩、黑人和第四个人，他们同样赤身裸体地跪着，他能感觉到他们的眼睛在盯着他。而在他们身后，有数不清的人在黑暗中跪倒在地。他自己的手成为巨大的风车，他兴致勃勃地盯着安东纳普勒斯手里不知名的东西。黄色灯笼在黑暗中摇曳着，其他的一切都静止不动。突然传来一阵骚动，在骚动中台阶坍塌了，他觉得自己一直向下跌落。他猛地一抖醒了过来。早晨的阳光已经照亮了窗户。他觉得很害怕。

这么长时间过去，好友也许发生了什么事情。安东纳普勒斯不给他写信，所以他也无从知晓。也许好友摔伤了。他有一阵强烈的冲动，想再去看他。他会不惜一切代价安排这件事——马上。

那天早晨，他在邮局自己的信箱里发现了一张通知：他的一个包裹到了。这个包裹正是他为圣诞节订购的礼物，之前没能及时送到。礼物非常精美，是他用两年分期付款的方式买的。它是架个人用的电影机，有六部《米老鼠》和《大力水手》的喜剧片，都是安东纳普勒斯很喜欢的。

那天早晨，辛格最后一个到店里。他递给珠宝商老板一封正式的书面申请，申请周五和周六请假。尽管那一周手头有四个婚礼的活儿，但珠宝商还是点头应允了。

这次行程他事先谁也没告知，但走的时候他在门上贴了条，说因为公事他要出去几天。他是晚上走的，火车到达他的目的地时，红彤彤的冬日黎明刚刚到来。

午后，离探视时间还差一会儿，他便去了精神病院。他怀里抱着带给好友的电影机的各个部件，还有一篮水果。他径直走进以前探望安东纳普勒斯的那个病房。

走廊，门，一排排的床铺，还是记忆中的样子。他站在门口，急切地寻找着好友。但立刻发现，尽管所有椅子上都坐着人，但安东纳普勒斯却不在那里。

辛格放下手里的大包小包，拿出一张卡片，在下面写道：“斯皮罗斯·安东纳普勒斯去哪儿了？”一个护士走进房间，他把卡片递给她。她不明白怎么回事，摇摇头，耸了耸肩膀。他又走到走廊，逢人便把卡片递上去。没有人知道。他的心头一阵恐慌，开始用两只手比画着。最后，他碰到一位穿白大褂的实习医生，他拉住实习医生的胳膊肘，递上卡片。实习医生认真看了看，然后领着他穿过好几个走廊，来到一个小房间。里面有个年轻女人坐在桌前，面前是一些纸张。她看完卡片，到抽屉的文件里翻动着。辛格的眼里涌出紧张和恐惧的泪水。年轻女人开始不慌不忙地在一本便笺上写字，他忍不住拧着身子，想立刻看到写的是关于他好友的什么事。

安东纳普勒斯先生已经转入医院。他患了肾炎。我让人给你带路。

穿过走廊时，他停下来，捡起之前放在病房门口的包裹。那篮水果已经被人偷走了，但其他的盒子原封未动。他紧跟实习医生走出大楼，穿过一片草地到医院去。

安东纳普勒斯！他们走到那个病房时，他一眼便看见了他。他的床在房间中央，他正靠着枕头坐在那里，身上穿着猩红色晨衣、绿色丝绸睡衣，戴着绿松石戒指。他的皮肤呈一种淡黄色，一双眼睛恍惚、忧郁，两鬓的黑发已经有了银白的痕迹。他正在编织着什么，肥胖的手指慢慢移动着那几根长长的象牙针。起初他并没有看见他的朋友，后来辛格站到他面前，他平静地笑了，并不吃惊，接着伸出那只戴着戒指的手。

辛格的心头涌上一种羞怯和拘束的感觉，以前从来没有过。他坐在床边，两只手交叠在一起放在床罩边缘。他脸色煞白，目光一刻都没有离开好友的脸。好友华丽的服装让他震惊。这套衣服，他是分好几次、一件件给他寄过来的，但从没想过成套穿起来会是什么样子。安东纳普勒斯的身躯比他记忆中更庞大了，丝质睡衣下显出肚皮上层层柔软的褶皱。他的头靠在枕头上，也奇大无比。他脸上那种平和镇定的表情如此深不可测，似乎根本没有注意到辛格就在他身边。

辛格怯怯地抬起手，开始说话。他结实的手指娴熟准确地比画着那些手势，充满了爱意。他说到寒冷的天气，又说到一个人过的这几个月如此漫长。他提到原来的记忆、死了的那只猫、商店，还有他住的地方。每次停顿的时候，安东纳普勒斯都彬彬有礼地点点头。他说到那四个人，说到他们经常去他屋里看他。好友的一双眼睛湿润了，很忧伤，在这双眼睛里，他看见了自己长方形的身影，是他曾经看过无数次的身影。他的脸上又恢复了温暖的血色，手势也加快了。他详细描绘着那个黑人、那个胡子一抖一抖的男人，还有那个女孩。他两只手的动作越来越快，安东纳普勒斯慢慢地郑重点头。辛格急切地俯过身子，呼吸也变得缓慢深沉起来，眼睛里闪着晶莹的泪光。

突然，安东纳普勒斯用圆滚滚的食指在空中慢慢画了一个圆，手指朝辛格绕过去，最后戳了戳好友的肚子。大块头希腊人的笑容变得灿烂起来，还伸出胖胖的粉红色舌头。辛格大笑起来，两只手疯狂地比画着一堆话，他的肩膀随着笑声颤动起来，头向后仰着。他为什么笑，自己也不知道。安东纳普勒斯翻着眼睛，辛格继续纵情大笑，直到最后气都喘不动了，手指也颤抖起来。他抓住好友的胳膊，努力稳住自己。他的笑声慢下来，很费力的样子，像是在打嗝。

安东纳普勒斯首先平静下来。他肥胖的小脚踢开床尾的被子，笑容渐渐消失，不屑一顾地踢着毯子。辛格赶紧帮他整理好，但安东纳普勒斯皱起眉头，威严地朝一个路过的护士伸出一根手指。等护士按照他的意思把床整理好，大块头希腊人非常从容地点着头，那样子不像是一般的点头致谢，更像是一种恩赐。然后他又转过头，严肃地望着好友。

辛格说话时，并没有注意到时间的流逝。一个护士给安东纳普勒斯用托盘端来晚饭，他这才意识到天色已晚。病房里的灯已经开了，窗户外面几乎黑了下来。其他病人面前也摆上了托盘盛好的晚餐，他们都放下手头的活计（有些在编篮子，有些在做皮革的活儿或者编织），无精打采地吃着饭。跟安东纳普勒斯相比，这些人都病恹恹的，毫无血色。大多数人都很久没有理发了，穿着后面开口的破旧灰色睡衣。他们盯着两个哑巴，满脸惊奇。

安东纳普勒斯掀开盘子盖，仔细检查着食物，有鱼，还有一些蔬菜。他拿起那条鱼，放在手掌上，举到亮光底下进行彻底检查，然后津津有味地吃起来。他一边吃饭，一边指着屋里的其他人。他指着角落里的一个人，做鬼脸，表示厌恶。那个人朝他咆哮起来。他又指着一个男孩，微笑着点点头，挥着一只圆滚滚的手。辛格非常快乐，并没有感觉到尴尬。他拿起地上的几个包裹放在床上，好吸引朋友的注意力。安东纳普勒斯打开包装，但对那个机器毫无兴趣，转身继续吃饭。

辛格递给护士一张纸条，解释了电影的事情。她叫来实习医生，然后他们又带进来一个医生。他们三个人一边商量，一边好奇地望着辛格。其他病人听到消息，纷纷用胳膊肘撑起身子，一脸兴奋。只有安东纳普勒斯不为所动。

辛格已经预先练习过放电影。他组装好屏幕，这样所有病人便都可以看了。然后，他鼓捣着投影仪和胶片。护士将晚餐托盘收走，病房里的灯也关上了。屏幕上闪出《米老鼠》的喜剧片。

辛格注视着朋友。起初安东纳普勒斯大为震惊，他坐起身子，好看得更清楚。如果不是护士按住了他，他都快从床上站起来了。然后，他看着，露出愉快的笑容。辛格看到其他病人彼此招呼着，哈哈大笑。护士和护工们也纷纷从走廊里进来，整个病房一片喧闹。《米老鼠》的片子放完后，辛格又装上一部《大力水手》的胶片。这部电影放完，他觉得第一次的娱乐时间已经够长了，便打开灯，病房里重新安静下来。实习医生把电影机放到辛格好友的床下，这时他看见安东纳普勒斯偷偷瞟着病房里所有的人，想确定大家都知道这个机器是他的。

辛格又开始用手说话了。他知道自己很快就得离开，但脑子里积攒的那些想法太多了，这么短的时间根本说不完，他说得极其匆忙。病房里有个老人，由于中风，头一直在晃动着，还一直无力地拽着自己的眉毛。他嫉妒这个老人，因为他每天都能跟安东纳普勒斯生活在一起，如果能跟他互换位置，辛格将会求之不得。

他的朋友在胸前摸索着找什么。是他一直戴着的那个小黄铜十字架，原来的脏绳子已经换成了一条红丝带。辛格想起他做的那个梦，也跟好友讲了。匆忙之中，有些手势做得模糊不清，他不得不摆摆手，重来一遍。安东纳普勒斯用一双忧郁无神的眼睛望着他，穿着明艳豪华的衣服安静地坐在那里，就像传说中的一位睿智的国王。

负责这个病房的实习医生允许辛格在探视时间过后又多待了半个小时。终于，实习医生伸出自己瘦弱的、毛茸茸的手腕，给他看表。病人们都安顿好，睡了。辛格的手颤抖起来，他抓住好友的胳膊，专注地盯着他的眼睛，就像以前他们每天早晨分开上班时那样。最后，辛格退出了病房。在门口，他用两只手比画了一个难过的再见，接着紧握成了拳头。

一月份，月光如水的夜晚，辛格只要没事，每天晚上都会沿着小镇的街道散步。关于他的传闻越来越离谱。一位老年黑人妇女跟成百上千的人说，他知道如何让死者的灵魂重返人间。一个计件工人则声称，他跟哑巴在这个州其他地方的一个工厂一起工作过——他讲的那些故事都非常独特。富人们觉得他很富，穷人们则认为他像他们一样也是穷人。没有什么办法打破这些传闻，因此传闻越来越神乎其神，几乎以假乱真。每个人都按照自己的想象来描述哑巴的样子。

8

为什么？

这个问题始终在比夫的心里翻涌，悄无声息，如同血管里的血液一样。他思考着人、物和观点，于是便有了这个问题。午夜，漆黑的凌晨，正午。希特勒，以及战争的传闻。猪里脊肉的价格，啤酒税。他尤其认真思考着谜一样的哑巴。比如，辛格为什么会坐火车离开，而当问他去了哪里时，他为什么会假装听不懂？而且，为什么每个人都坚持认为哑巴就是他们想象的那样——而很有可能一切都是个奇怪的错误？辛格一天三次坐在屋子中央的桌子前。不管给他上什么，他都吃——卷心菜和生蚝除外。在一堆吵闹的声音中，他独自沉默着。他最喜欢吃煮软的绿色小利马豆，会把豆子整整齐齐地摞在叉子的齿尖上，还会用饼干蘸着豆子汤吃。

比夫也思考死亡。一件奇怪的事情发生了。一天，他翻腾浴室橱柜时，找出一瓶佛罗里达香水。他当时把爱丽丝剩余的化妆品送给露西尔时，漏掉了这瓶香水。他若有所思地把香水拿在手里。现在，爱丽丝已经去世四个月了——每个月都那么漫长，那么空虚，仿佛像过了一年似的。他几乎不曾想起她。

比夫拔开瓶塞。他光着上身站在镜子前面，把香水点了一些在他黑乎乎、毛茸茸的腋下。香味让他身体僵硬。他与镜子里的自己交换了一个极其秘密的眼神，站在那里一动不动。香水一下子带回了那些记忆，让他惊诧，并非因为这些记忆很清晰，而是因为这些记忆将所有那些漫长的岁月都汇集起来，完整地呈现出来。比夫搓着鼻子，侧身看着自己。死亡的边界。他心里感觉到了跟她曾经度过的每一寸光阴。现在，他们在一起的生命完整了，仿佛只有过去才可能完整。比夫猛然转身走开了。

卧室已经重新收拾过，现在归他一个人用了。以前，卧室里俗气、杂乱、单调。屋里拉了一根绳子，上面总是晾着袜子、有破洞的粉色人造纤维内裤。那张铁床油漆已经脱落，锈迹斑斑，上面放着带着脏兮兮的蕾丝花边的枕头。楼下跑上来的一只猫，骨瘦如柴，会弓起后背，凄惨地在污水桶上蹭痒痒。

他把这些都换掉了。他把铁床换成了一张可以当床的长沙发，地上铺了一块厚厚的红色小地毯。他还买了一块很漂亮的中国蓝的布挂在一面墙上，好遮住最明显的那几道裂缝。他打开壁炉，里面放满了松木。炉台上，放着一张巴比的小照片，还有一张彩色照片，里面有个穿天鹅绒的小男孩，两只手捧着一个球。角落里的一只玻璃盒子里，装着他收集来的各色宝贝——蝴蝶标本、一个珍稀的箭头、一块类似人的轮廓的奇怪石头。长沙发上铺着蓝色丝绸垫子，他还借了露西尔的缝纫机，做了暗红色窗帘。他喜欢这间屋子，既奢华又静谧。桌子上有一个小小的日本塔，上面有玻璃坠子，风吹过的时候就会发出奇怪的叮叮当当的音乐声。

这间屋子里没有什么东西能唤起对她的记忆了，但他会经常拔出那瓶佛罗里达香水的瓶塞，用瓶塞点到耳垂或手腕上。香水的味道与他缓慢的沉思交融，过去的感觉便在他体内弥散开来。这些记忆就像是在建造大厦一般，有序地搭建起来。在他存放纪念品的一个盒子里，他找到婚前拍的一些老照片：爱丽丝坐在一大片雏菊中，爱丽丝跟他一起在河里划船。在这些纪念品中，还有一支很大的骨簪，那是他妈妈留下的。小时候，他特别喜欢看妈妈梳理长长的黑发然后挽起来的样子。那时候，他觉得那些发卡是弯成了一个女人的样子，有时候便会像玩洋娃娃一样玩这些发卡。那时候他还有个烟盒，装满了碎布，他喜欢那些漂亮碎布摸上去的感觉，喜欢它们的颜色。他会一坐好几个小时，在厨房桌子底下摆弄这些碎布。但他六岁那年，他妈妈把碎布拿走了。她是个高大结实的女人，有男人一样的责任感。她是最爱他的。即便现在，他有时还会梦到她，而且他一直戴着她那只旧的结婚金戒指。

除了那瓶佛罗里达香水，他还在壁橱里发现了爱丽丝之前用的一瓶柠檬洗发水。有一天，他自己试了一下这瓶洗发水，结果一头露着几缕白发的黑头发显得特别蓬松浓密，很让他喜欢。他扔掉了那瓶预防脱发的头油，经常用那瓶柠檬洗发水洗头。他过去嘲笑爱丽丝心血来潮，现在他也如此了。为什么？

每天早晨，楼下的黑人男孩路易斯会给他送上来一杯咖啡，他可以在床上喝。他经常靠在枕头上坐一个小时，然后才起床穿衣。他抽根雪茄，望着阳光投在墙上的图案。陷入沉思时，他用食指在修长弯曲的脚趾中间来回移动。他回忆着往事。

从中午一直到凌晨五点，他一直在楼下工作，星期天则要工作一整天。生意在赔钱，很多时候都不景气。尽管如此，一到吃饭时间店里通常还是人满为患。他每天守在收银台后，能见到几百个熟人。

“你一直站在这里想什么？”杰克·布朗特问他，“你像是在德国的犹太人。”

“我有八分之一的犹太血统。”比夫说，“我妈妈的祖父就是从阿姆斯特丹来的犹太人，但就我所知，家里其他人都是苏格兰—爱尔兰血统。”

星期天的早晨，客人们无精打采地坐在桌前，店里有烟草的味道，还有报纸的沙沙声。角落雅座里的几个人在掷骰子，但他们的游戏也很安静。

“辛格呢？”比夫问，“今天上午你不去他那里吗？”

布朗特的脸阴下来，闷闷不乐，他把头向前一抬。他们吵架了吗？——但一个哑巴怎么吵架？不对，之前也发生过类似的事情。布朗特有时候四处转悠，表现得好像正在跟自己吵架一样，但很快他就会去找哑巴——他总是如此——然后，他们两人会一起进来，布朗特还一边说着话。

“你过着优越的生活，就站在收银机后面，站在那里伸开手。”

比夫并没有生气。他俯下身子，用胳膊肘支着身子，眯起眼睛。“我们俩好好谈谈吧。你想要的到底是什么？”

布朗特两只手一下拍在柜台上，他的手温暖、厚实、粗糙。“啤酒，再来一小包奶酪饼干，里面夹花生酱的那种。”

“我不是那个意思。”比夫说，“但好吧，以后再谈。”

这个人是个谜，变化无常。他依然疯狂地喝酒，但跟其他男人不一样，他不会被酒撂倒。他的眼眶经常通红，他还有个神经质的把戏：扭过头去，露出一副惊吓的表情。他的脖子很细，头又大又沉。他这种人，孩子见了会嘲笑，狗见了都会咬。然而，当别人嘲笑他时，他又很容易受伤——他发脾气，大声叫嚷，像个小丑，而且他总是怀疑有人在嘲笑他。

比夫若有所思地摇摇头。“来，”他说，“你为什么一直待在那个游乐场啊？你能找份比那个好的工作。我可以让你在这里做兼职。”

“老天！你就算把这个地方都给我，把锁、存货、酒桶都给我，我也不会一直站在那个钱箱子后面。”

他又来了，这真让人生气。他永远不会有朋友，哪怕只是跟别人相处都够呛。

“别胡说。”比夫说，“认真点。”

一个顾客过来递上一张钞票，他找了零钱。店里仍然很安静。布朗特坐立不安。比夫觉得他要离开，便想留住他。他伸手从柜台后面架子上拿下两根A-I雪茄，递给布朗特一根。他在脑子里小心翼翼地摒除了一个又一个问题，然后终于问道：“如果让你选择生活在哪个历史阶段，你会怎么选？”

布朗特用他湿漉漉的宽大舌头舔了舔胡子。“如果可以让你选择做个傻瓜或者永远不问问题，你选哪个？”

“够了。”比夫坚持道，“认真想想。”

他把头歪到一边，视线越过自己的长鼻子，向下盯着看。他喜欢听别人谈论这个问题。他会选择古希腊。穿着拖鞋在蓝色的爱琴海边散步，宽松的长袍系在腰间。孩子们，大理石浴室，还有在寺庙中的冥想。

“或许到秘鲁去，跟印加人生活在一起。”

比夫的眼睛扫视着他的全身，像是剥光了他的衣服。他看到布朗特的皮肤被太阳晒成了深红棕色，脸上光滑干净，手腕上戴着一个金镯子，镶着珍贵的宝石。布朗特闭上眼睛时很像印加人，等比夫再细看他时，这幅画面却消失了。那撮神经质的胡子跟他的脸很不搭，还有他抖动肩膀的样子，细细脖子上的喉结，松松垮垮的裤子。而且，不止这些。

“或者，也许是一七七五年前后。”

“生活在那个时候挺不错。”比夫表示同意。

布朗特不自在地在地上搓着脚，脸上一副粗鲁、不高兴的样子，他准备要走。比夫很警觉，要留住他。“告诉我——你到底为什么要到这个镇上来？”他立刻意识到这个问题很冒失，他对自己很失望。然而，这个男人居然到这样一个地方来，真是件很奇怪的事情。

“这是上帝的真理，我也不懂。”

他们安静地站了一会儿，两人都斜靠在柜台上。角落里掷骰子的游戏结束了。客人点的第一份晚餐是长岛鸭肉特色菜，已经给A.&P.商店的老板送了上去。收音机正好调到教堂布道和摇摆舞乐队演出频道的中间。

布朗特突然向前探过身子，闻着比夫的脸。

“香水？”

“剃须水。”比夫镇定自若地说。

他没法再留住布朗特了，这家伙准备要走，稍后这家伙会跟辛格一起回来，每次都是这样。他想让布朗特畅所欲言，这样就能搞清楚他的一些情况了，但布朗特从来不正儿八经地说话——他只跟哑巴说话。这真是件非常奇怪的事情。

“多谢你的雪茄，”布朗特说，“再会。”

“再会。”

比夫望着布朗特朝门口走去，迈着摇摇摆摆的步子，像水手一样。然后，他开始忙活眼前的事情。他望着橱窗里的陈设。当日菜单贴在玻璃上，还摆着一盘特色菜，装饰着配菜以吸引顾客，但样子看上去很糟糕，可以说让人倒胃口。鸭肉里的汤汁流进了蔓越莓酱里，还有一只苍蝇落在甜点上。

“嗨，路易斯！”他喊道，“把这东西从橱窗里拿走，给我那个红色的陶瓷碗，再拿些水果来。”

他摆放着水果，特别讲究颜色和位置。最后，装饰效果令他满意。他去了趟厨房，跟厨师聊了一番，又打开锅盖，闻闻里面的食物，却并不是真心在意这件事。这活儿以前是爱丽丝干的，他不喜欢。看到油乎乎的洗碗池由于底下的食物残渣而泛起泡沫，他的鼻子灵敏起来。他写下第二天的菜单和订单，很高兴终于可以离开厨房，重新站到收银机后面。

露西尔和巴比星期天过来吃午饭。这个小孩现在还不太好，头上仍然缠着绷带，医生说到下个月才能拆。一叠纱布盖住了原来的黄色卷发，让她的头看上去有些光秃秃的感觉。

“跟比夫姨夫打个招呼，宝贝。”露西尔鼓励道。

巴比烦躁不安地昂起头。“跟比夫姨夫打个招呼，宝贝。”露西尔接着加油打气。

露西尔想要脱掉巴比的礼拜日大衣，她挣扎了一番。“喏，你要听话，”露西尔不停地说，“你得把大衣脱下来，否则，再出去的时候你会得肺炎的。喏，你要听话。”

比夫控制了这个局面。他用一粒软糖哄着巴比，慢慢把大衣从她肩膀上脱了下来。在跟露西尔挣扎的时候，她的裙子已经走了样。他把裙子给她拽平，前面的上衣抵肩便端端正正了。他又给她重新系好腰带，用手指把蝴蝶结调整成恰当的形状，然后拍了拍巴比小小的后背。

“今天，我们有草莓冰激凌。”他说。

“巴塞洛缪，你可以当一个相当好的母亲。”

“谢谢。”比夫说，“这是对我的恭维。”

“我们刚去了主日学校和教堂。巴比，把你学的《圣经》里的话说给比夫姨夫听听。”

孩子向后退着，噘起小嘴。“耶稣哭了。”她终于说话了，声音里透露出的那种蔑视让这两个词听上去像是一件可怕的东西。

“想去见见路易斯吗？”比夫问，“他就在后面厨房。”

“我想见威利，我想听威利吹口琴。”

“好了，巴比，别跟自己较劲了。”露西尔不耐烦地说，“你很清楚，威利不在这里，威利被送到监狱里去了。”

“但路易斯，”比夫说，“他也会吹口琴。去跟他说，准备好冰激凌，然后给你吹一曲。”

巴比走向厨房，一只脚跟拖在地上。露西尔把帽子放在柜台上，眼里含着泪水。“你知道，我总是说如果把一个孩子收拾得干干净净、漂漂亮亮的，照顾得好好的，那么这个孩子一般都会可爱又聪明。但如果一个孩子又脏又丑，那么你也不要对他有太大期望。我想说的是，巴比没了头发，头上还缠着绷带，她觉得很丢人，这好像让她对什么都失去了兴趣。她不练习朗诵了——什么也不做，她感觉非常糟糕，我也管不了她。”

“如果你不对她要求那么严格，她会好的。”

最后，他把母女俩安排到窗边的一个雅座。露西尔点了份特色菜，给巴比点的是鸡胸脯肉，切得很细，还有小麦粥和胡萝卜。巴比玩弄着自己的食物，把牛奶洒到了小裙子上。他跟她们坐在一起，后来客流高峰期到了，他不得不起身去照料生意。

人们吃着饭。一张张嘴巴张开，填塞着食物。这是什么来着？不久之前他刚看过一句话，生命就是摄入、吸收营养和繁殖。屋里很挤，收音机里播放着摇摆舞乐队的音乐。

然后，他等的那两个人走了进来。辛格先进门，脊背挺直，穿着剪裁得当的礼拜日西装，布朗特紧跟在他身后。他们走路的样子触动了他。他们坐在惯常的那张桌子前，布朗特起劲地又说又吃，而辛格礼貌地注视着他。吃完饭，他们在收银机前停留了几分钟。后来他们出去时，他又一次注意到他们一起走路的样子，这让他停下来，充满疑问。这可能是什么？他脑海深处的记忆之门猛然打开了，让他大为震惊。以前，辛格有时候会跟那个大块头聋哑傻子一起走路去上班，就是给查尔斯·帕克制作糖果的那个懒散的希腊人。希腊人总是走在前头，辛格跟在身后。他从来没怎么注意过他们，因为他俩从来不来店里。但他为什么没有想起来呢？这么长时间以来，他一直在琢磨这个哑巴，却没想到这件事。看到了所有的景色，唯独没有看到三只正在跳华尔兹的大象。但这又有什么关系呢？

比夫眯起眼睛。辛格以前是什么样子并不重要，重要的是，布朗特和米克把他变成了一种“自产”的神。因为他是哑巴，他们便可以按照自己的喜好随意赋予他各种品质。是的，但怎么会发生这种奇怪的事情呢？为什么会这样？

一个独臂男人走了进来，比夫免费请他喝了一杯威士忌，但他不想跟任何人说话。周日午餐是家庭聚餐。一到周日，那些平日里独自喝啤酒的男人们都会把太太和小孩子一起带过来。他们放在后面的高脚椅子经常能派上用场。已经两点半了，尽管很多桌子还占着，但人们基本已经吃完了。比夫已经站了四个小时，非常疲倦。他以前可以连续站十四到十六个小时，并没有什么感觉。但现在他老了，老了很多。这一点毋庸置疑。或者，更确切地说，是成熟了。不是老了——肯定不是——还不老。屋里的声浪在他耳畔起起落落。成熟了。他的眼睛疼起来，体内有种炽热的东西，好像让眼前的一切都明亮刺眼。

他喊过一个女招待。“替我照看一下好吗？我要出去。”

因为是周日，街上空无一人。太阳明晃晃地照着，很通透，却并不暖和。比夫把大衣衣领竖起来。独自一个人走在街上，他觉得有些无所适从。风从河上吹过来，很冷。他应该转身回到餐馆，那里才是他应该待的地方。他要去的地方，跟他并没有什么关系。在过去的四个星期天，他一直这么干。他到那个街区去散步，希望也许能看见米克。这件事本身就有点——不太对。是的，是错的。

他在她家对面的人行道上缓缓走动着。上个星期天，她在门前台阶上看那些连环漫画。但这一次，他快速朝她家瞥了一眼，她不在那里。比夫把呢帽的帽檐向下压了压，盖住眼睛。也许，她过会儿会去咖啡馆。星期天的晚饭后，她经常过来买杯热可可，会在辛格坐的桌前逗留一会儿。星期天，她穿的衣服跟平日里穿的蓝裙子和毛衣不一样，她星期天穿的裙子是酒红色丝绸的，带着褪色的蕾丝领子。有一次她还穿了长筒袜——上面有的地方抽了丝。他总想为她做点什么，给她点什么东西，不只是一个圣代或什么甜点——而是一件真正的东西。这就是他想让自己做的——给她点什么。比夫的嘴巴僵硬起来。他没有做错什么事，但心里却感觉到一种奇怪的罪恶感。为什么？所有男人心里的那种阴暗的罪恶感，莫名其妙，说不清楚。

回家的路上比夫发现水沟里有一分钱，被垃圾遮住了一半。他节俭地捡起硬币，用手绢擦干净，扔进随身携带的黑色钱夹里。他回到餐馆时已经四点了，店里很冷清，里面一个顾客都没有。

五点左右，生意有了好转。他最近雇来做兼职的那个男孩早早就来了。男孩叫哈里·米诺维茨，跟米克和巴比住在同一个街区。当时有十一个人应报纸上的广告前来应聘，但哈里似乎是最佳人选。对于他的年龄而言，他发育得很好，干净整洁。面试时，比夫一边跟他说话，一边注意到了他的牙齿。牙齿总是很好的标示。他的牙齿很大，又白又干净。哈里戴眼镜，但这并不妨碍工作。他妈妈给街上的一个裁缝做缝纫的活儿，一个星期赚十块钱，哈里是独子。

“嗯，”比夫说，“你已经跟我干了一个星期，哈里。你觉得喜欢这份工作吗？”

“当然，先生，我当然喜欢。”

比夫转动着手上的戒指。“让我想想。你什么时候放学？”

“三点，先生。”

“嗯，这样，你还有几个小时的时间可以学习和娱乐。然后你到这里，从六点干到十点。这样的话，你有足够的时间睡觉吗？”

“足够了。我不需要那么多睡眠。”

“你这个年龄，孩子，需要九个半小时的睡眠，纯粹、健康的睡眠。”

他突然觉得很尴尬。也许哈里会觉得这个不关他的事，无论如何，的确如此。他转过身去，接着又想起什么事。

“你上职业学校？”

哈里点点头，用衣袖擦着眼镜。

“我想想。那里很多男生女生我都认识。阿尔瓦·理查兹——我认识他父亲，还有玛吉·亨利，还有一个叫米克·凯利的孩子——”他觉得耳朵像着火了一样。他觉得自己是个傻瓜，想转身离开，却还是站在那里微笑着，用大拇指按着鼻子。“你认识她吗？”他轻声问道。

“当然认识。我就住在她家隔壁，但在学校里，我是毕业班学生，她是新生。”

比夫把这点微不足道的信息牢牢地存进了大脑，等以后独自一人时便可以拿出来细细咀嚼。“这里的生意会冷清一阵子，”他匆忙说，“我交给你了。现在你知道该怎么做这些事情了。对于喝啤酒的客人，盯着点，记住他们喝了多少，这样你就不用去问他们或按照他们说的来结账了。找零的时候别着急，仔细留意周围的情况。”

比夫将自己关进楼下的房间里。这是他存放档案的地方，屋子里只有一个小窗户，外面是条小巷。屋子里面的空气有一种发霉的味道，而且非常冷。一摞摞报纸堆得很高，顶到了天花板。一个自制的文件柜占满一面墙，门口旁边放着一把老式摇椅，还有一张小桌子，上面有一把大剪刀、一本字典，还有一把曼陀林。因为有一摞摞的报纸，所以无论朝哪个方向走，最多只有两步的空间。比夫坐在摇椅上摇晃着，漫不经心地拨弄着曼陀林的琴弦。他闭上眼睛，用一种忧郁的声音唱起来：

我走到动物市场。

那里有鸟有兽，

还有月光下的老狒狒

正在梳理它红褐色的毛发。

他最后弹了一个和弦，余音在冰冷的空气中颤抖着，消散了。

要收养几个小孩，一个男孩，一个女孩，三四岁，这样他们就会把他当作亲生父亲。他们的爸爸。我们的父亲。小女孩像米克（或者巴比？）这么大就好。圆脸蛋，灰眼睛，亚麻色头发。他会给她做衣服——粉色双绉裙，抵肩或袖子上带着精致的衣褶，穿着丝袜和白色鹿皮鞋。冬天，给她穿一件红色天鹅绒的小外套，戴帽子和皮手笼。男孩要黑黑的，长一头黑头发，跟在他后面学着他的样子做事。到了夏天，他们三个会到墨西哥湾的小屋去，他会给孩子们穿上防晒服，慢慢领着他们走进绿色的浅水中。然后他慢慢变老，他们也就长大了。我们的父亲。他们会找他问问题，他会给他们答案。

为什么不呢？

比夫又拿起曼陀林。“塔姆——啼——提姆——啼——提，啼——提，彩色布娃娃的婚礼。”曼陀林弹奏着这段副歌。他唱完所有的歌词，用脚打着拍子。然后，他又弹了《凯——凯——凯——凯蒂》和《爱是一首老情歌》。这些曲子就像那瓶佛罗里达香水，让他想起很多。一切。第一年，他很幸福。而她似乎也很幸福，那时候，三个月里床在他们身下塌过两次。那时候他并不知道，她脑子里一直想的就是怎么省吃俭用，节约出五分或一毛钱。然后，他先是和里奥混到一起，之后又有别的女孩占据了她的位置，基普、玛德琳和卢。后来他突然失去了兴趣，再也无法跟女人同床了。老天！这样，一开始便似乎一切都完了。

露西尔一直明白整个情况。她知道爱丽丝是什么样的女人，也许她也知道他是什么样的男人。露西尔鼓励两人离婚，费劲全力想帮他俩解决难题。

比夫突然皱起眉头，手从琴弦上猛地拿了下来，一段音乐戛然而止。他全身紧张地坐在椅子上，然后他突然无声地大笑起来。是什么让他遭遇了这一切？啊，上帝，上帝，上帝！他二十九岁生日那天，露西尔请他看完牙医后顺便到她公寓里坐坐。他以为会给他一点小纪念品——一盘樱桃蛋挞，或者一件好衬衫。她在门口迎接他，捂上他的眼睛才让他进门。然后，她说去去就回。在寂静的房间里，他倾听着她的脚步声，等她走到厨房的时候他放了个屁。他站在屋子里，被蒙着眼睛，就那么放了个屁。然后，他猛然恐惧地意识到他不是一个人在这里。先是一阵窃笑，然后是哄堂大笑，他的耳朵都快聋了。就在那时候，露西尔回来了，解开了他的眼罩。她端着一个盘子，上面放了一块焦糖蛋糕。屋子里都是人，勒罗伊和他那伙人，当然还有爱丽丝。他真想找个地缝钻进去。他站在那里，挂着一张没有表情的脸，全身火烧火燎。他们戏弄着他，随后的一个小时过得几乎跟他母亲去世时一样糟糕——他感觉就是这样。后来，那天晚上他喝了一夸脱威士忌。之后的几个星期——天哪！

比夫冷冷地轻声笑起来。他又在曼陀林上拨弄了几个和弦，开始弹唱一首欢快的牛仔歌曲。他的声音是一种圆润的男高音，唱歌的时候他闭着眼睛。屋子里几乎黑了下来，潮湿的寒气沁入骨髓，他患风湿病的腿疼了起来。

最后他收起曼陀林，在黑暗中慢慢地摇着。死亡。有时候，他几乎可以在这间屋子里感受到死亡，就在他身边。他在椅子里前后摇晃着。他明白了什么？什么也没有。他要去哪里？哪里也不去。他想要什么？要知道。什么？一个含义。为什么？一个谜。

残缺的画面浮现在他的脑海中，像是散落了一地的拼图。爱丽丝在浴室里打着肥皂。墨索里尼的杯子。米克推着手推车里的婴儿。橱窗里的烤火鸡。布朗特的嘴巴。辛格的面孔。他觉得自己在等待着。房间里已经完全黑了下来。他听到路易斯的歌声从厨房传过来。

比夫站起来，扶住摇椅的扶手让它停止摇晃。他打开门，外面的走廊温暖而又明亮。他想起来，也许米克会来的。他整整衣服，把头发向后抹平，身上又恢复了温暖和活力。餐馆里一片嘈杂，啤酒大战和周日晚餐已经开始了。他亲切地朝年轻的哈里笑了笑，自己站到了收银台后面。他的目光像套索一样，只一眼便将房间里的情况尽收眼底。屋子里拥挤不堪，嘈杂声四起。橱窗里的那碗水果是一种有品位又有艺术性的展示。他望着门口，继续用老练的目光留意着房间里的情况。他很警觉，专注地等待着。辛格终于来了，用银色铅笔写下他得了感冒，只想要汤和威士忌。然而，米克却没有来。

9

她身上连一枚五分硬币都没有。他们就是穷到了这个地步。钱是最主要的事情。一直以来，都是钱，钱，钱。他们要花很多钱支付巴比·威尔逊住私人病房和请私人护士的钱。但即便如此，那也只是其中一笔账单而已。付完一笔钱，另一件需要付钱的事情便又出现了。他们欠下了大约二百块钱的债务，必须马上偿还。他们失去了房屋。他们的爸爸卖房子得了一百块钱，让银行接管了抵押权，然后他又去借了五十块钱，辛格先生为他做了担保。后来，他们每个月都要担心房租，而不是担心交税了。他们几乎跟工厂的工人一样一贫如洗，只不过没有人轻视他们。

比尔在装瓶厂上班，一个星期可以赚十块钱。黑兹尔在一个美容院当助手，一个星期八块钱。埃特在电影院卖票，一个星期五块钱。他们每个人都上交一半收入当生活费。房子里还有六位房客，每人交五块钱的生活费，而辛格先生总是按时付房租。他爸爸能拿到手的，一个月总共大约二百块——而用这些钱，他们得给六位房客提供较好的伙食，养活全家人，付整个房子的房租，续交买家具的钱。

她和乔治现在没有午饭钱了，她不得不停掉音乐课。波西娅把晚上的剩饭菜攒起来，让她和乔治放学以后吃。一直以来，他们都在厨房吃饭。比尔、黑兹尔和埃特是跟房客们坐在一起吃还是在厨房吃，这要取决于食物的多少。在厨房，他们早餐吃粗玉米粉、黄油、腊肉，喝咖啡。晚饭他们吃同样的东西，再加上餐厅里剩下的东西。大孩子们每次必须到厨房吃饭时，都会发牢骚。有时候，她和乔治会连续两三天都饿着肚子。

但这都是“外屋”的事情，与音乐、外国以及她制订的那些计划毫无关系。这个冬天很冷，窗户上结着霜花。夜晚，起居室里的炉火噼啪作响，非常暖和。全家人跟房客们一起围坐在炉火旁边，所以她一个人独享中间的卧室。她穿着两件毛衣，一条比尔穿小的灯芯绒裤子，兴奋之情令她全身温暖。她会从床底下拖出自己的秘密盒子，坐在地上忙活。

大盒子里有几张画，是她在政府办的免费美术班上画的。她把这些画从比尔的房间里拿出来了。盒子里她还放了爸爸给她的三本悬疑小说、一个小化妆粉盒、一盒手表零件、一条水晶石项链、一把锤子和几个笔记本。有个笔记本上，用红色蜡笔在上面写着——“私密，勿动，私密”，上面还系了一根绳子。

整个冬天，她都在这个笔记本上研究着音乐。一到晚上，她便不再学习学校里的功课，便有更多时间花在音乐上。她写的主要是些小曲子——没有歌词的歌曲，甚至没有什么低音音符，都非常短。但即便这些曲子只有半页纸长，她也都一一取了名字，并在下面写上自己的姓名首字母。这个本子里的东西都称不上是真正的音乐或作曲，只是她脑海里的一些歌曲，她想要记下来。她取的名字就是这些歌曲会让她想到的东西——“非洲”“一场大战”“暴风雪”。

她无法按照曲子在她脑子里响起的样子把它如实写下来，必须要把曲子缩减成几个音符，否则就会乱成一团，无法继续下去。关于如何作曲，她有太多不懂的东西，但也许等她学会如何把这些简单的曲子写下来之后，很快便可以开始将脑海里完整的曲子记录下来了。

一月份，她开始写一首非常精彩的曲子，名字叫“我想要这件东西，却不知道是什么”。这是一首优美绝伦的歌曲——非常缓慢、柔和。一开始她想写首诗来搭配曲子，却想不出有什么东西可以搭配这首曲子，而且第三行很难找到一个词与“什么”押韵。这首新歌让她觉得既伤感又兴奋并幸福。如此优美的曲子写起来很难，任何歌曲写起来都很难。她用不了两分钟就可以哼完的东西，要想写在笔记本上，却意味着要埋头苦干整整一个星期——还不算她要弄明白音阶、时间和每一个音符。

她必须全神贯注，把曲子唱很多遍。她的嗓子一直是沙哑的，她爸爸说这是因为她小时候哭叫得太厉害的缘故。她跟拉尔夫那么大的时候，她爸爸每天晚上都得起来，抱着她到处走。他总是说，唯一能让她安静下来的办法，就是他拿着拨火棍敲打着煤斗给她唱“迪克西”。

她趴在冰冷的地板上，思考着。以后——等她二十岁的时候——她会成为一位世界闻名的作曲家，她会有一支完整的交响乐团，然后亲自指挥他们演奏自己的曲子。她会在一大群观众面前，站在指挥台上。指挥交响乐团时，她会穿男式晚礼服，或者缀满亮闪闪的水晶石的红色长裙。舞台的幕布将是红色天鹅绒的，上面写着烫金的两个大字：M.K.。辛格先生也会在场，过后他们会一起出来吃炸鸡。他会对她赞叹不已，视她为最好的朋友。乔治会到舞台上来给她献上大花环。演出将在纽约或者外国的什么地方举行。社会名流们都会对她指指点点——卡罗尔·隆巴德、阿图罗·托斯卡尼尼，还有海军上将伯德。

她会随心所欲地演奏贝多芬的交响乐。她在去年秋天听到的这首曲子里有一种奇特的东西，这支交响乐一直回荡在她的心里，一点点地生长着。原因是这样的：整首交响乐都在她的脑子里。一定是这样。她听到了每一个音符，在大脑深处的某个地方，整首曲子还停留在那里，跟演奏时一模一样。但她无法再把这首曲子呈现出来，她只能等待，准备着什么时候自己突然想起一个新的部分，等着它生长，就像等着一棵春天的橡树的枝杈慢慢长出叶子一样。

在“里屋”，除音乐之外，还有辛格先生。每天下午她在体操馆一弹完钢琴，便立刻沿着主街往回走，会经过他工作的那个店铺。从前窗望进去，她看不到辛格先生。他在后面工作，隔着一道帘子。但她望着他每天都在此工作的这间店铺，而且能看见他认识的一些人。每天晚上，她都在门廊里等着他回家。有时候她会跟着他上楼，她坐在床边，看着他收好帽子，看着他解开领口的纽扣，看着他梳理头发。不知道为什么，他们好像有一个共同的秘密，或者他们好像在等着要告诉对方一些以前从未说出口的话。

他是唯一在她“里屋”的人。很久以前，这里还有过其他人。她回顾过去，想起他来之前的事情。她想起很久以前，有个六年级的女孩，叫西莱斯特。这个女孩有一头顺直的金发，鼻子有些上翘，还有雀斑，穿一件红色羊毛针织衫和白色宽松上衣，走起路来有些内八字。每天她都带一个橘子在小课间吃，还带个蓝色的铁盒装着午饭，在大课间的时候吃。其他孩子趁小课间就把带的食物狼吞虎咽吃掉了，然后便饥肠辘辘——但西莱斯特不会这样。她揭下三明治外面的硬皮，只吃中间软和的部分。她还总是带一个煮得很老的填馅鸡蛋，把鸡蛋握在手里，用大拇指使劲压着蛋黄，把指纹印在上面。

西莱斯特从来不跟她说话，她也不跟西莱斯特说话。其实她非常想跟西莱斯特说话。夜晚她躺在床上不能入睡，想着西莱斯特。她会计划着她俩成为最好的朋友，想着什么时候西莱斯特可以跟她一起回家吃晚饭，一起睡觉，但这样的事情从来没有发生过。她对西莱斯特的那种感觉，让她绝不会像对其他人一样走上前去跟西莱斯特交朋友。一年以后，西莱斯特搬到了镇上另外一个地方，上了另外一所学校。

后来，还有个叫巴克的男孩。他个头高大，脸上有粉刺。早晨八点半，她站在他旁边排队入场时，他身上的味道难闻极了——好像裤子需要晾晒了。巴克有一次用头撞了校长，被勒令退学了。他大笑起来的时候上嘴唇会抬起，全身抖动。她想起他，就像想起西莱斯特一样。后来还有一位女士，她在火鸡抽奖活动上卖彩票。还有安格林小姐，是他们七年级的老师。还有电影里的卡罗尔·隆巴德。所有这些人。

然而，辛格先生与他们都不一样。她对他的感觉是慢慢产生的，回想起来，她不知道这种感觉是怎么发生的。其他人都很普通，但辛格先生与众不同。他第一天按门铃要一间屋子时，她便盯着他的脸看了好久。她打开门，仔细看着他递上来的卡片。然后她喊来妈妈，自己走到后面厨房去跟波西娅和巴伯说他的事。她又跟着妈妈和他上了楼，看着他按按床垫，之后他又卷起百叶窗看是不是好用。他搬来的那一天，她坐在门廊栏杆上，望着他从廉价出租车上下来，带着手提箱和棋盘。后来，她又听见他步履沉重地在房间里来回走动，不禁对他浮想联翩。其余的事情则是慢慢发生的。现在他们两人之间有了这种秘密的感觉。她跟他说的话比以往跟任何人说的都多。他如果能说话，也会跟她说很多事情。他就像一位了不起的老师，他不教书，只是因为他是个哑巴而已。晚上躺在床上，她会想象着如果她是个孤儿，她会跟辛格先生生活在一起——只有他们两个，住在国外的一所房子里，那里的冬天会下雪。也许住在瑞士的一个小镇上，周围都是高耸的冰川和大山。那里，房子上面都是岩石，房顶很尖、很陡。或者住在法国也可以，在那里人们从商店买了面包，根本不用包装便直接带回家去。或者也可以住在外国的挪威，临着灰色的、冬天的大海。

早晨，她想到的第一个便是他，还有音乐。她穿上裙子时，会想今天在哪里可以见到他。她用埃特的香水或一滴香草精，如果在走廊里碰上他的话，她浑身便会散发出一种好闻的味道了。她很晚才去上学，这样便可以看到他从楼上下来去上班。下午和晚上，如果他在家，她便从来不出门。

关于他，她了解到的每一件新鲜事都至关重要。他总是把牙刷和牙膏放在桌上的玻璃杯里，所以她不再把牙刷放在浴室，而是也放到了玻璃杯里。他不喜欢卷心菜，为布兰农先生工作的哈里曾经对她提到过。现在她也不吃卷心菜了。每次了解到他的一些新情况，或者跟他说话而他用银色铅笔写下几个词的时候，她都要一个人待很久，反复回味。她跟他在一起时，脑子里的主要念头就是要把一切都储存起来，这样以后便可以反复温习，牢记在心。

“里屋”有音乐和辛格先生，然而，“里屋”并非一切，“外屋”也发生了许多事情。她滚下楼梯，摔掉了一颗门牙。米娜小姐给她发了两张糟糕的英语成绩单。她在空地上丢了两毛五分钱，尽管她和乔治找了三天，却依然没有找到。事情是这样的：

一天下午，她正在后门台阶上学习，准备英语考试。哈里在栅栏那边他的家里砍木头，她冲他喊了一声，他过来用图解法给她讲了几个句子。他戴着角质框眼镜，那双眼睛很敏锐。他跟她解释完英语，便站起来，两只手在夹克衫口袋里反复地伸进去又掏出来。哈里总是精力充沛，紧张兮兮的，每时每刻都得说点什么或做点什么。

“你瞧，现在只剩下两件事。”他说。他喜欢语出惊人，有时候她不知道该怎么回答他。

“这是事实，现在只剩下两件事。”

“什么事？”

“激进民主，或者法西斯主义。”

“你不喜欢共和党吗？”

“呸，”哈里说，“我说的不是这个意思。”

有一天下午，他已经解释过法西斯主义的所有内容了。他讲了纳粹分子如何让犹太小孩趴在地上吃草。他还讲了自己如何计划着要刺杀希特勒，他已经制订了详细计划。他讲了在法西斯专制下如何没有正义和自由。他说报纸上蓄意刊登谎言，人们根本不知道世界上发生了什么。纳粹分子非常可怕——每个人都明白。她跟他一起策划如何杀死希特勒。在这个秘密计划里，如果有四五个人最好，这样万一一个人失手了，其他人照样还可以干掉希特勒。他们即便都死了，也会成为英雄。成为英雄，几乎可以与成为伟大的音乐家相媲美。

“要么战斗，要么死掉。尽管我不相信战争，但我随时准备为我认为的正义而战。”

“我也是。”她说，“我要与法西斯分子做斗争。我可以化装成男孩，没人能认得出来。比如，我可以剪掉头发。”

这是一个晴朗的冬日午后。天空是蓝绿色的，后院里那几棵橡树的树枝映衬在这种颜色之下，黑乎乎、光秃秃的。阳光很温暖。这样的日子让她觉得精力充沛，脑海里又浮现出音乐。为了找点事做，她捡起一枚三英寸长的钉子，猛砸几下钉进了台阶。他们的爸爸听到锤头的声音，裹着浴袍走出来站了一会儿。树下有两个锯木架，小拉尔夫正忙着把一块石头放到一个架子上面，接着再把石头搬过去，放到另一个架子上，来回折腾。他走路的时候，两只手向前伸着保持身体平衡。他有点罗圈腿，尿布都兜到了膝盖上。乔治正在玩弹球。他的头发好久没剪了，显得脸很瘦，他的几颗恒牙已经长了出来——但很小，而且发青，像吃了黑莓似的。他画一条弹球的线，然后趴在地上，瞄准第一个洞。他们的爸爸回去修表时，把拉尔夫一块带过去了。过了一会儿，乔治一个人去了小巷里。自从打伤巴比之后，他再也不跟任何人一起玩了。

“我得走了，”哈里说，“六点之前我得去上班。”

“你喜欢咖啡馆的工作吗？你有免费的好东西吃吗？”

“当然啦。到那个地方去的人五花八门。我以前做过的任何工作都不如这份让我喜欢，工资也更高。”

“我恨布兰农先生。”米克说。的确，尽管他从来没对她说过什么真正刻薄的话，但他说话的语气总是那么粗暴，那么好笑。他一定早就知道了那次她和乔治偷了那包口香糖。那么，他为什么还会问她的事情进展如何呢——就像在辛格屋里那一次？或许他以为他们经常偷东西。但他们没有，肯定没有。只有一次，他们从廉价商店拿了一小盒水彩笔，还拿过一只五分钱的削笔刀。

“我真受不了布兰农先生。”

“他还好。”哈里说，“有时候他看起来是有点古怪，但他并不暴躁，等你了解了他就好了。”

“有件事我想过了，”米克说，“在这方面，男孩比女孩有优势。我是说，男孩通常可以得到一份兼职，不用退学，还可以有些时间干别的。但女孩就没有这样的工作机会。如果女孩想要拥有一份工作，她必须得退学，做全职。我很想跟你一样，每个星期可以赚几块钱，但没有这种机会。”

哈里坐在台阶上，解开了鞋带，他拽着鞋带，竟然把其中一根拽断了。“咖啡馆里来了一个人，叫布朗特先生，杰克·布朗特先生。我喜欢听他说话。他喝了啤酒说的那些话，让我懂了很多事情，他让我了解了一些新思想。”

“我很熟悉他，他每个星期天都过来。”

哈里解下鞋带，把断掉的鞋带拉成同等长度，这样就可以重新打个结。“听着，”他紧张兮兮地在夹克衫上擦着眼镜，“你不要把我的话说给他听。我的意思是，我觉得他不记得我了。他不跟我说话，只跟辛格先生说话。他也许会觉得这很好笑，如果你——你知道我的意思。”

“好的。”她已经明白了他的言外之意，他对布朗特先生着了迷，她懂他的感受，“我不会提起的。”

夜色降临了。月亮如同牛奶一样白，挂在蔚蓝的天空中，天气很冷。她能听到拉尔夫、乔治和波西娅在厨房里的声音。炉子里的火把厨房的窗户照成了温暖的橙色，空气里弥漫着烟雾和晚饭的味道。

“你知道，这件事我从来没跟任何人说过。”他说，“我自己都不愿意想到这件事。”

“什么事啊？”

“你记得你第一次开始看报纸，并且开始思考看到的内容吗？”

“当然。”

“我过去是个法西斯分子。我以前觉得我是，就是这样。你知道那些照片，在欧洲我们这个年龄的人游行、唱歌，步伐一致。我过去以为这是很棒的事情。他们所有人都彼此宣誓，有共同的领袖，所有人有共同的理想，步伐一致地游行。我不太担心犹太少数民族会发生什么事情，因为我不愿去想，因为那时候我不愿去想自己就是犹太人。你瞧，我不知道。我只是看着那些照片，看着下面的文字，却并不明白。我从来不知道那是一件多么可怕的事情。我以为自己是个法西斯分子。当然，后来我发现并非如此。”

批评自己时，他的声音十分苦涩，不断地从男人的声音变成男孩的声音。

“嗯，你那时候没有意识到——”她说。

“这是个可怕的罪过。一个道德错误。”

他就是这样。一切都是黑白分明——没有中间地带。二十岁以下的人如果碰啤酒、白酒，或者吸烟，便是错的。一个人如果考试作弊，那是可怕的罪恶，但抄作业不算犯罪。女孩如果涂口红或穿露背裙，那是道德错误。如果买任何带有德国或日本商标的东西，不管多少钱，都是一种可怕的罪恶。

她想起小时候哈里的样子。有一次，他的眼睛变成了斗鸡眼，然后整整一年都是那个样子。他坐在前门台阶上，双手放在两个膝盖之间，望着一切，非常安静，眼睛向内斜视着。他在文法学校跳了两级，十一岁的时候就准备上职业学校了。但在职业学校里，当他们读到《艾凡赫》里的犹太人时，其他孩子便纷纷转过头来看着哈里，他便跑回家去哭。因此，他妈妈便不让他去上学了。他在家整整待了一年，长高了，也长胖了。她每次爬上栅栏，都会看到他在厨房里给自己弄吃的。他们俩会在附近一起玩，有时候还会一起摔跤。小时候，她喜欢跟男孩子们打架——不是真的打架，只是闹着玩。她用的是柔道和拳击的混合招数，两人各有胜负。哈里对别人从来不会动粗。小孩子们的玩具坏了，每次都来找他，他总会慢慢把玩具修好。他什么都能修。如果什么东西坏了，街上的女人们也会来找他，让他修电灯，或者修缝纫机。后来，他十三岁那年又回到职业学校，开始发奋努力。他送报纸，星期六工作，读书。很长时间以来，她不常见到他——一直到她举办那次聚会。他已经变了很多。

“就是这样，”哈里说，“过去，我一直有宏伟的抱负，要成为一名伟大的工程师，或了不起的医生，或律师，但现在我不再这样想了。我思考的只是这个世界现在发生的事情，关于法西斯主义和欧洲那些可怕的事情——另一方面，还有民主。我是说不能再想着自己在生活中要成为什么样子并为之努力，因为我对另一方面的东西想得太多了。我每天晚上都梦见刺杀希特勒，在黑暗中醒来时我口干舌燥，还对什么东西充满恐惧——又不知道是什么。”

她望着哈里的脸，一种深沉而严肃的感觉令她感到悲伤。哈里的头发垂在额头上，上嘴唇又薄又紧绷，但下嘴唇很厚，颤抖着，他看上去不像已经十五岁了。一阵冷风随着暮色吹过来。风在街边的那些橡树上唱着歌，把百叶窗吹得打在屋子的墙上，砰砰直响。街上，韦尔斯太太正在吆喝萨克回家。傍晚的暮色让她心里的那种悲伤更沉重了。“我想要一架钢琴——我想要上音乐课。”她自言自语。她望着哈里，他正在变换着花样交叉自己瘦削的手指，他的身上散发出一种温暖的男孩子的味道。

是什么让她突然这样？也许是因为想起了他们小时候的时光，也许是因为悲伤让她感觉很怪异。但无论如何，她突然推了哈里一下，差点把他从台阶上推下去。“你奶奶的！”她冲他大嚷一声，然后跑开了。街上的孩子要找碴打架时，经常这样说。哈里站起来，一脸吃惊。他把鼻子上的眼镜扶好，看了她一会儿，然后跑到巷子里。

寒冷的空气让她觉得像力士参孙一样强壮。她大声笑起来，传来短促的回声。她用肩膀撞了哈里一下，他一把抓住她。他们拼力扭到一起，大声笑着。她个头最高，但他的两只手很有劲。他打得不怎么样，被她摔倒在地上。他突然停住不动，她也停了下来。他的气息吹在她的脖子上，暖暖的，他一动不动。她坐在他身上的时候，感觉到自己的膝盖正抵在他的肋骨上，他的呼吸很急促。他们一起站起来，没有笑。巷子里悄然无声。他们穿过黑乎乎的后院。不知为什么她觉得很好笑，并没有什么东西让她感觉奇怪，但突然就这么发生了。她轻轻推了他一下，他也推了她一下，然后她又大笑起来，感觉一切回归如常。

“再见。”哈里说。他大了，不能再翻栅栏，所以跑着穿过小巷，朝家门口去了。

“天啊，太热了！”她说，“在这里快闷死了。”

波西娅正在炉子上给她热晚饭。拉尔夫用勺子敲着高脚椅上的托盘。乔治用脏兮兮的小手拿着一片面包，用它搅着他的粗玉米粥，两只眼睛眯着，似乎在望着远方。她拿过白肉、肉汁、粗玉米粥和几粒葡萄干，把它们在自己的盘子里混到一起。她吃了三份，一直到把所有粗玉米粥都吃光了，却还是饿。

一整天，她都在想着辛格先生。一吃完晚饭，她便上了楼。但走到三楼，她看见他的屋门敞开着，房间里漆黑一片。这让她感觉心里很空。

在楼下，她没法安静地坐下来准备英语考试，仿佛她太强壮了，无法像其他人一样坐在房间的椅子上。她好像可以推倒屋里所有的墙壁，然后像个巨人一样在街道上前进。

最后，她从床底拿出她的私密盒子。她趴着翻看那个笔记本。现在里面已经有大约二十首歌曲了，但她并不满足。要是她能写一首交响乐就好了！让一整个交响乐团来演奏——但交响乐怎么写呢？有时候几件乐器同时演奏一个音符，所以谱子尺寸必须特别大才行。她在一页大试题纸上画下五条横线——中间都间隔一英寸。如果是小提琴、大提琴或长笛的音符，她会写下乐器的名字来表示；如果是所有乐器同时演奏一个音符，她便用圆圈把所有乐器都圈起来。在这页纸的顶部，她用大写字母写下“交响乐”，下面又写上“米克·凯利”。然后，她便一筹莫展了。

要是她能上音乐课该多好！

要是她能有一架真正的钢琴该多好！

过了很长时间，她才得以动笔。那些曲调就在她的脑子里，她却不知道该怎么写出来，就像这是世界上最难的戏剧一样。但她不断地想，直到后来埃特和黑兹尔走进屋子，上了床，并且让她必须关灯，因为已经十一点了。

10

六个星期以来，波西娅一直在等着威廉的消息。每天晚上她都会来家里，问科普兰医生同一个问题：“你有没有见过谁收到威利的信？”每天晚上他都不得不告诉她，他没有听到任何消息。

终于，她不再问这个问题了。她总是来到走廊上，望着他，一言不发。她开始喝酒，上衣经常敞着一半纽扣，鞋带也没系好。

二月份来了。天气暖和了些，接着开始热了。太阳猛烈照射着，非常刺眼。鸟儿在光秃秃的树上唱着歌，孩子们在街上玩耍，都光着脚，赤裸着上身。夜晚酷热难耐，像仲夏一般。过了几天，冬天重回小镇。温暖的天空阴了下来，下起了冷雨，天气变得很阴湿，并且极其寒冷。镇上，黑人最为受罪。储备的燃料已经用完，所有人都在拼命寻求温暖。湿冷狭窄的街上，肺炎肆虐，整整一个星期的时间，科普兰医生都没有睡过囫囵觉，而且全都是和衣而眠。依然没有威廉的消息，波西娅写过四封信，科普兰医生写过两封。

白天和夜晚的大部分时间，他根本无暇思考。但偶尔他可以抽空回家休息片刻。他会坐在火炉旁，喝一壶热咖啡，这时心头便会涌上一种深深的不安。他已经有五个病人死了，其中一个就是那个聋哑小孩奥古斯塔斯·本尼迪克特·马迪·路易斯。人们请他去葬礼仪式上讲话，但他的原则是不参加葬礼，因此无法接受这个邀请。这五个病人的死绝不是因为他的疏忽，罪魁祸首是背后多年的贫穷。食物总是玉米面包、腌猪肉和糖浆，四五个人挤在一间小屋子里。死于贫穷。他思考着这件事情，喝着咖啡好保持清醒。他经常用手托着下巴，因为最近，只要他一累，脖子上的神经便会微微颤抖，让他不由自主地点头。

二月的第四周，波西娅来到家里。刚刚清晨六点，他正坐在厨房的火炉旁，用锅热牛奶当早饭。她喝得烂醉。他闻到了杜松子酒那种浓烈的甜味，不由厌恶地翕动着鼻孔。他没看她，只顾忙着自己的早餐。他把面包掰碎放到碗里，然后倒上热牛奶。他准备好咖啡，摆好桌子。

坐下来吃早餐时，他严厉地望着波西娅。“你吃过早饭了吗？”

“我不吃早饭。”她说。

“你需要吃，如果你今天还想上班的话。”

“我不去上班。”

他感到一阵害怕，不想再追问了。他盯着自己的牛奶碗，用勺子喝着，手有些发抖。吃完，他抬头看着她头顶上的墙。“你的舌头打结了吗？”

“我会告诉你的。你会听到的。等我能说话了，我马上就告诉你。”

波西娅坐在椅子上，一动不动，眼睛慢慢地从一个墙角挪到另一个墙角，两条胳膊软塌塌地垂着，两条腿松垮地扭在一起。

他从她身上移开视线的时候，有一瞬间感到一种危险的轻松和自由，这种感觉很强烈，因为他知道它很快就要土崩瓦解了。他添了添火，烤了烤手，然后卷了一支烟。厨房里纤尘不染，整洁有序。墙上的平底锅映着炉火的光，每一只后面都有一个圆形的黑影。

“是关于威利的。”

“我知道。”他在两手之间小心翼翼地搓着烟，两只眼睛愣愣地瞟着四周，贪婪地享受着最后的甜美幸福时刻。

“我有一次跟你提到过，那个巴斯特·约翰逊跟威利一起在监狱里，我们以前认识他。昨天，他被送回家了。”

“然后呢？”

“巴斯特这辈子都残废了。”

他的头颤抖了一下，他用手按住下巴让自己稳定下来，但顽固的颤抖很难控制住。

“昨天晚上，有几个朋友到我家来，说巴斯特回家了，而且有关于威利的消息要告诉我。我一路跑了过去，然后他就把这些告诉我了。”

“嗯。”

“他们三个人，威利、巴斯特，还有另外一个男孩，他们是朋友。然后麻烦就来啦。”波西娅停住，用舌头舔舔手指，然后用手指滋润着干燥的嘴唇，“是这么回事，那里的白人看守一直找他们的碴。有一天，他们出去干修路的活儿，巴斯特顶了嘴，后来另一个男孩想跑到树林里去，看守就把他们三个都抓了起来，把三个人带到营地，关进了那个冰冷的屋子里。”

他又说“嗯”，但头颤抖着，这个字从喉咙里发出来像咯咯的响声。

“这件事发生在大约六个星期以前，”波西娅说，“你还记得最冷的那段时间，他们就把威利和另外两个男孩关到那间冰窟窿一样的房间里。”

波西娅的声音很小，中间既没有停顿，脸上的悲伤也没有减少。她的声音就像一首低沉的歌曲。她说着，他却听不懂。这些声音在他耳朵里非常清晰，却不能成形或者表达出什么意义，就好像他的脑袋是船头，而那些声音是水，水撞在船头，却又流了过去。他觉得必须回过头去，去寻找之前已经说过的那些话。

“……他们的脚冻肿了，他们躺在那里，在地上挣扎着，大声喊叫着，却没有一个人去。他们在那里喊了三天三夜，没有一个人去。”

“我聋了。”科普兰医生说，“我听不懂。”

“他们把我们的威利和那两个男孩关到那间冰冷的屋子里，天花板上有条绳子垂下来。他们脱掉他们三个的鞋子，用绳子拴住光脚。威利和那两个男孩就那么躺在那里，后背在地上，脚在空中。他们的脚冻肿了，他们在地上挣扎着，叫喊着。屋子里冰冷冰冷的，他们的脚冻僵了。他们的脚肿了，他们大声喊叫了三天三夜。没有一个人去。”

科普兰医生两只手按住脑袋，但那种顽固的颤抖就是不肯停下来。“我听不见你说什么。”

“最后终于有人去接他们了。他们很快把威利和那两个男孩送到病房，他们的腿都肿了，冻僵了，坏死了。他们把我们威利的两只脚都锯掉了。巴斯特·约翰逊失去了一只脚，另一个男孩治好了。但我们的威利——现在他一辈子都残废了，两只脚都锯掉了。”

话说完了，波西娅俯过身子，把头撞在桌子上。她没有哭，没有呻吟，但她一次又一次地把头重重地撞在坚硬的桌面上，上面的碗和勺子哗哗作响，他把它们收进了水槽里。那些话在他脑子里散乱一片，但他并没有想要把它们拼接到一起。他用热水烫了碗和勺子，又洗干净擦盘巾。他从地上捡起一样什么东西，又把它放到了什么地方。

“残废了？”他问，“威廉？”

波西娅用头撞着桌子，一下下的，节奏像缓慢的鼓点，他的心也随着这节奏跳动着。那些话悄无声息地活了过来，回归了原意。他明白了。

“他们什么时候把他送回来？”

波西娅低垂的头伏在胳膊上。“这个，巴斯特不知道。后来，他们三个很快就被分到不同的地方去了。他们把巴斯特送到了另外一个营地。威利只剩下几个月就服刑期满了，所以巴斯特觉得他应该很快就回来了。”

他们喝着咖啡，望着对方的眼睛，坐了很长时间。他的杯子与牙齿碰得咯咯直响。她把咖啡倒进一个碟子里，咖啡洒到了她的腿上。

“威廉——”科普兰医生说道。他说出这个名字时，牙齿深深地咬进舌头里，他痛苦地动着下巴。他们坐了很久，波西娅握着他的一只手。黯淡的晨曦照得窗户发灰。外面雨还在下。

“如果我还想上班，那现在得走了。”波西娅说。

他跟着她穿过走廊，在衣帽架那里停下，穿上大衣，戴上围巾。打开门，一股湿冷的风吹进来。海博埃坐在外面的路边石上，顶着一张报纸挡雨，报纸已经湿透了。人行道边有一溜栅栏，波西娅一边走一边斜靠在栅栏上，科普兰医生跟在她后面走了几步，他的手也扶着栅栏的木板，才能稳住自己的身体。海博埃跟在他们两人身后。

他等着那种阴郁可怕的愤怒爆发出来，仿佛等着一头野兽从黑夜中蹿出来。然而，它却并没有到来。他的肠胃似乎像装了铅一样沉重，他走得很慢，不时靠在栅栏上，或者靠在沿路房子湿冷的墙上。一路跌到最谷底，直到最后，下面再也没有深渊了。他触摸到了坚实的绝望之底，在那里苟延残喘。

这时，他感觉到一种强烈而神圣的喜悦。受压迫的人放声大笑，黑奴在皮鞭下用自己愤慨的灵魂歌唱。此刻，他的心里也有一首歌——尽管说不上是音乐，只是一种歌曲的感觉。一种平和的沉重负担压得他四肢动弹不得，他只有凭借那种坚强的真正使命感才能向前挪动。他为什么要继续向前？他为什么不能在这极端羞辱的谷底停歇下来，苟且活着？

然而，他终究还是继续向前了。

“叔叔，”米克说，“你觉得喝点热咖啡会感觉好些吗？”

科普兰医生望着她的脸，好像根本没有听到似的。他们已经穿过小镇，最终来到凯利家后边的小巷。波西娅先走了进去，他也随后跟了进去。海博埃还是在外面台阶上等着。米克和她的两个小弟弟已经在厨房里了。波西娅跟他们说了威廉的事情。科普兰医生没听她说的什么，只觉得她的声音很有节奏——开头，中间，结尾。她说完后，又从头开始说了一遍。其他人都跑进来听。

科普兰医生坐在角落里的一张凳子上。他的大衣和围巾搭在火炉旁的一张椅子背上，正在冒着热气。他把帽子放在膝盖上，两只修长的黑手在破损的帽檐边上紧张地动来动去，黄色的手心出汗了，他偶尔用手帕擦一下。他的头颤抖着，全身肌肉僵硬，拼命要让头部停止抖动。

辛格先生来到屋里，科普兰医生抬起头看着他。“你听说这件事了吗？”他问道。辛格先生点点头，眼睛里没有恐惧，也没有怜悯或者憎恨。在所有那些知道的人当中，只有他的眼睛没有表现出这种反应，因为只有他明白这件事情。

米克低声对波西娅说：“你爸爸叫什么名字？”

“他叫本尼迪克特·马迪·科普兰。”

米克斜过身子，靠近科普兰医生，对着他的脸大喊一声，好像他是个聋子。“本尼迪克特，你不觉得喝点热咖啡会感觉好些吗？”

科普兰医生吓了一跳。

“别那么喊。”波西娅说，“他跟你一样，听得见。”

“哦。”米克说。她倒掉壶里的残渣，然后把咖啡放到炉子上重新烧开。

哑巴在门口徘徊。科普兰医生仍然望着他的脸。“你听说了？”

“他们会怎么处理那些监狱看守？”米克问道。

“亲爱的，我不知道。”波西娅说，“我不知道。”

“我要做点什么。我肯定要为这件事做点什么。”

“我们做什么都没用，我们能做的最好的事情，就是把嘴巴闭上。”

“应该用他们对待威利和那两个男孩的办法对待他们，还要更狠一些。我希望能召集一群人，亲手杀了那些人。”

“这样说不像基督教徒。”波西娅说，“我们还是算了，反正知道他们早晚会被撒旦用叉子叉碎，扔到油锅里不停地炸干。”

“不管怎么样，威利还能吹口琴。”

“两只脚都锯掉了，他也只能干这个。”

屋子里一片嘈杂和不安。厨房顶上的房间里有人在搬动家具，餐厅里挤满了房客。凯利太太在早餐餐桌和厨房之间急匆匆地来回忙碌着，凯利先生穿着一条肥大的裤子和一件浴袍转来转去，凯利家的小孩子们在厨房里狼吞虎咽地吃着饭。家里到处都能听到砰砰的关门声和人们的说话声。

米克给科普兰医生递上一杯咖啡，里面加了淡牛奶，因此咖啡呈现出一种灰蓝色的光泽。盘子里洒了一些咖啡，他先拿出手绢，把盘子和咖啡杯沿擦干净。他根本不想喝咖啡。

“真希望我能杀了他们。”米克说。

房子里安静下来。餐厅里的人都去上班了，米克和乔治去上学了，而婴儿被关进了前面的一个房间里。凯利太太头上裹着一块毛巾，拿着一把笤帚上了楼。

哑巴仍然站在门口。科普兰医生抬头凝视着他的脸。“你知道这件事？”他又问道。这些话没有出声——卡在了他的喉咙里——但他的眼睛在问着这个问题。然后哑巴走了，只剩下科普兰医生和波西娅。他在角落里的凳子上坐了一会儿，最后他站起来要走。

“你坐下，父亲。今天早晨，我们要待在一起。我煎些鱼，还有鸡蛋面包和土豆，当午饭。你待在这里，我给你端上来一顿热饭。”

“你知道我还要巡诊。”

“就今天一天。求你了，父亲。我感觉真的要崩溃了，而且我不想让你一个人到街上转悠。”

他犹豫了，摸摸外套的领子，还是湿的。“女儿，很抱歉，你知道，我得去巡诊。”

波西娅把他的围巾放在炉子上方，一直烤到羊毛围巾发热。她给他扣好大衣，又把领子给他竖起来。他清清嗓子，拿出口袋里随身带着的四方纸巾，把痰吐在里面，然后扔到炉子里烧掉了。往外走的时候，他停下来跟台阶上的海博埃说话。他建议，海博埃如果可以安排请一天假，最好陪着波西娅。

天气寒冷刺骨。低沉压抑的天空一直飘着蒙蒙细雨，雨水渗入垃圾桶，巷子里飘散着湿垃圾的恶臭味道。他一边走，一边扶着栅栏支撑着自己，阴郁的目光一直盯着地面。

他去看了所有那些必须看的病人，从中午到下午两点，他又回办公室接诊病人。之后，他坐在办公桌前，紧紧攥着两只拳头。然而，对于这件事情，再努力思考都是徒然。

他再也不想看见人的面孔，但与此同时，他又无法独自一人待在空荡荡的屋子里。他穿上外套，又走到湿冷的街道上。他的口袋里有几份药方，要送到药房去，但他不想跟马歇尔·尼克尔斯说话。他走进店里，把药方放在柜台上。正在称药粉的药剂师转过身来，伸出两只手，厚嘴唇无声地翕动了好一会儿，然后才恢复镇定。

“医生，”他郑重地说，“你一定要知道，我和所有同事、我的所有家人，还有教堂里所有的人，我们都深切感受到你的悲恸，希望你能接受我们最诚挚的同情。”

科普兰医生猛地转过身，一句话没说便走了出去。这些根本无济于事，他需要更多的东西，那种强烈的真正使命，还有对正义的追求。他僵硬地走着，胳膊紧贴在身体两侧朝主街走去。他思考着，却没有结果，他想不出这个镇上有哪个白人既勇敢又正直。他想着所熟悉的每一名律师、每一位法官、每一个官员，但想到这些白人只会让他的心痛苦不堪。最终，他决定去找最高法院的法官。到了法院，他丝毫没有犹豫，快步走了进去，决定那天下午一定要见到法官。

宽敞的前厅空荡荡的，只有通往两端办公室的门口有几个无所事事的人在那里闲逛。他不知道法官的办公室在哪儿，便边踌躇地在楼里穿行，边看着门上的牌子。最后，他走到一条狭窄的走廊上。这条走廊的中间有三个白人男子站在一起聊天，堵住了去路。他紧贴墙壁，想要走过去，但其中一个白人却转身拦住了他。

“你要干什么？”

“能麻烦您告诉我法官的办公室在什么地方吗？”

白人用大拇指朝走廊尽头晃了一下。科普兰医生认出了他，是副警长。他们见过几十次，但副警长并不记得他。对黑人而言，所有白人都长得一个模样，但黑人会特别注意区分他们的不同。而另一方面，对白人而言，所有黑人也长得很相似，但白人通常并不费心在脑子里去记一个黑人的模样。于是，这个白人说：“你想干什么，牧师？”

这种熟悉的戏谑头衔惹怒了他。“我不是牧师，”他说，“我是名医生，一名医生，我叫本尼迪克特·马迪·科普兰，我想立刻见到法官，有要紧事。”

副警长跟其他白人一样，一番表述清晰的话便惹火了他。“是吗？”他嘲讽道，朝朋友们递了个眼色，“那么，我是副警长，你可以叫我威尔逊先生，我告诉你，法官很忙。改天再来吧。”

“我必须要见法官。”科普兰医生说，“我等着。”

走廊入口处有条长凳，他坐了下来。三个白人继续聊天，但他知道副警长在盯着他。他下定决心不会离开。半个多小时过去了。几个白人悠闲地在走廊里走来走去，他知道副警长正在盯着他，他僵直地坐在那里，两只手紧紧夹在膝盖中间。他的谨慎告诉他应该离开，下午晚些时候再回来，到时副警长就不在这里了。他这一辈子跟这些人打交道时一直谨小慎微，但现在，他心里有什么东西不让他退缩。

“过来，你！”终于，副警长说话了。

他的头抖起来，起身时没有站稳。“什么事？”

“你刚才说见法官有什么事？”

“我没说过，”科普兰医生说，“我只是说，我找他有要紧事。”

“你站都站不直了，喝酒了，对吗？我从你嘴里闻出来了。”

“胡说，”科普兰医生缓缓地说，“我没有——”

副警长一拳打在他的脸上，他跌撞在墙上。两个白人抓住他的胳膊，拖着他下了台阶，来到一楼。他没有反抗。

“这就是这个国家的问题，”副警长说，“有他这样一些该死的傲慢的黑鬼。”

他一言不发，任他们摆布。他等着那种可怕的愤怒到来，然后感觉到愤怒从心底升起。愤怒令他十分虚弱，他踉跄起来。他们将他推进囚车，又进去两个警卫。他们把他带到警察局，扔进监狱里。直到他们走进监狱，愤怒的力量才涌上他的全身。他突然挣脱他们的束缚，然后被他们逼到墙角。他们用警棍对着他的脑袋和肩膀一通乱打。他心里有种光荣的力量，他一边反抗，一边听见自己在放声大笑。他又哭又笑，两只脚疯狂地乱踢一通。他用拳头回击着，甚至还用脑袋去撞他们。然后他们紧紧抓住了他，让他动弹不得，随后将他一步步拖过监狱的走廊。牢房的门打开了，身后有人踹了他屁股一脚，他双膝着地摔倒在地上。

在这个逼仄的小房间里，还有五个囚犯——三个黑人，两个白人。其中一个白人年龄很大，醉醺醺的，正坐在地上抓痒。另一个白人囚犯是个男孩，最多十五岁。三个黑人都很年轻。科普兰医生躺在铺位上，抬头望着这几个人的脸，认出了其中一个。

“你怎么到这里来了？”一个年轻人问，“你不是科普兰医生吗？”

他说：“是的。”

“我叫达里·怀特，去年你帮我姐姐摘了扁桃体。”

冰冷的牢房里弥漫着一股腐烂的味道，角落里放着一只桶，里面的尿液都快溢出来了，墙上爬满蟑螂。他闭上眼睛，一定是立刻睡了过去，因为当他再次抬起头来的时候，带铁栅栏的窗户已经漆黑一片，走廊里开着一盏明晃晃的灯。地上放着四只空空如也的铁盘子，他那份卷心菜和玉米面包的晚饭摆在身边。

他坐在铺位上，剧烈地打了好几个喷嚏，呼吸时胸腔中有痰呼噜作响。过了一会儿，那个年轻的白人男孩也开始打喷嚏。科普兰医生的方纸巾用完了，只得从口袋里掏出笔记本，撕了纸页来用。白人男孩前倾着身体，趴在角落里那个桶的上方，任由鼻涕流到他的衬衫前胸，眼睛瞪得很大，光洁的双颊通红，他蜷缩在铺位的边缘呻吟着。

很快他们被领出牢房，去盥洗室，回来后立即准备就寝。他们六个人，只有四个铺位。那个老人躺在地上，鼾声如雷。达里和另一个男孩挤在一张床上。

时间过得真慢。走廊里的灯光刺眼，牢房里的味道让每一次呼吸都变成一种折磨。他觉得很冷，牙齿咯咯作响，整个人在寒冷中颤抖不已。他裹着脏乎乎的毯子坐了起来，前后摇晃着身体。白人男孩嘟囔着，在睡梦中把两只胳膊伸了出来，他两次伸出手去，替男孩盖好毯子。他摇晃着身体，双手捧着脑袋，喉咙里发出一种唱歌似的呻吟。他没法去想威廉，也没法去思考那种强烈的真正使命感，并从中汲取力量，他只能感觉到内心的悲哀。

然后他的高烧退了，一股暖流传遍全身。他躺下去，似乎陷入一个温暖、火红、非常舒适的地方。

第二天早晨，太阳出来了，这个奇怪的南方冬天结束了。科普兰医生被释放了。监狱外面有一小群人正等着他，有辛格先生，还有波西娅、海博埃和马歇尔·尼克尔斯。他们的面孔模糊不清，他看不真切。阳光非常刺眼。

“父亲，你难道不知道这样肯定救不了我们的威利吗？到白人的法院去胡闹？我们能做的最好的事情，就是闭上嘴，等着。”

她响亮的声音在他耳畔疲惫地回荡着。他们钻进一辆廉价出租车。到家后，他的脸紧紧贴在干净的白色枕头上。

11

米克一整夜都辗转反侧。埃特病了，她不得不睡在起居室。沙发又窄又短。她梦到了威利，是个噩梦。波西娅跟她说到威利发生的事情，几乎已经是一个月之前的事情了，但她依然无法忘记。这一夜，她做了两次这种噩梦，醒来时发现自己在地板上，额头上多了一个包。到了六点，她听见比尔到厨房给自己弄早饭。天已经亮了，但由于百叶窗还拉着，所以房间里还是一片昏暗。在起居室里醒过来，她觉得有些怪异，不喜欢这样。床单乱七八糟地裹在身上，一半在沙发上，一半在地上，枕头跑到了屋子中央。她起了身，打开通往走廊的门。楼梯上没有人，她穿着睡衣跑回后面的房间。

“闪开，乔治。”

这个孩子躺在床的正中央。晚上很暖和，他光着身子，像只松鸦一样。他紧紧攥着拳头，即便在睡梦中眼睛还在眯着，像是在思考一件非常棘手的事情。他张着嘴巴，枕头上有块地方湿乎乎的。她推推他。

“等会儿——”他在睡梦中说。

“到你那边去。”

“等会儿——让我做完这个梦——这个——”

她把他拖到先前的地方，挨着他躺下。等她再次睁开眼睛时，时间已经不早了，太阳从后窗照了进来，乔治不见了踪影。她听见院子里传来孩子们的声音，还有流水的声音。埃特和黑兹尔正在中间的屋子里聊天。她正穿着衣服，突然有了一个想法。她在门口听着，却听不见她们在说什么。她猛地打开门，要吓她们一跳。

她俩正在看一本电影杂志。埃特还在躺在床上，一只手半挡着下面一张演员的照片。“从这个角度看，你不觉得他特别像那个男孩吗？那个以前约会过——”

“今天早晨你觉得怎么样啊，埃特？”米克问道。她看看床底下，自己的私密盒子仍然好好地待在原来的位置。

“你倒挺操心的。”埃特说。

“你不要总想挑起战争。”

埃特的脸瘦了。她的肚子疼得厉害，卵巢有问题，跟她来例假有关。医生说必须得立刻把她的卵巢切掉，但她们的爸爸说，他们必须得等等。家里没有钱。

“你到底想让我怎么样？”米克说，“我问你一个礼貌的问题，你就开始指责我。因为你病了，所以我觉得应该替你难过，但你就是不肯让我做个规矩人，我自然会生气。”

她把刘海儿拢到后面，仔细照了照镜子。“好家伙，看我摔的这个包！我敢打赌，我的头都摔坏了。昨天晚上我掉下来两次，我觉得好像是撞到沙发旁边的桌子上了。我不能睡在起居室里了，沙发太挤了，我睡不开。”

“小点声，声音太大了。”黑兹尔说。

米克跪在地上，拖出那个大盒子。她仔细看看捆在外面的绳子。“嘿，你们俩有没有摆弄过这个啊？”

“胡说！”埃特说，“我们摆弄你那个破东西干吗？”

“你们最好没动，谁要是想动我的私人物品，我就杀了谁。”

“听着，”黑兹尔说，“米克·凯利，我觉得你是我见过的最自私的人，你对世界上所有人都漠不关心，除了——”

“噢，放屁！”她狠狠摔上了门。她恨她俩。这么想很可怕，但事实就是如此。

她爸爸跟波西娅待在厨房里。他穿着浴袍，正在喝咖啡，眼睛通红，杯子和碟子碰得叮当响。他绕着餐桌走来走去。

“几点了？辛格先生出门了吗？”

“他出门了，先生，”波西娅说，“已经快十点了。”

“十点！天哪！我以前从来没睡到过这么晚。”

“你搬来搬去的那个大帽盒子，里面装的什么东西？”

米克把手伸进炉子，拿出半打饼干。“别问了，我又不会跟你撒谎。谁要偷看，没有好下场。”

“如果还有剩牛奶的话，我想拿来泡碎面包。”她爸爸说，“‘墓地汤’，也许能让我的胃舒服些。”

米克掰开饼干，把煎过的几片白肉夹到里面，然后坐到后面的台阶上，吃着早饭。上午的天气温暖而又晴朗，斯波尔瑞巴斯和萨克正跟乔治在后院玩耍。萨克穿着防晒服，另外两个孩子脱得只剩下短裤。他们拿着水龙头互相追着喷水，水流在阳光底下闪闪发光，风吹出一些水花，像薄雾一样，里面出现了彩虹的颜色。绳子上挂的衣服在风里扑啦啦地飞动着——白床单，拉尔夫的蓝衣服，一件红色罩衫，还有睡衣——湿漉漉的，很干净，被吹成了各种形状。天气几乎跟夏天一样，毛茸茸的小黄蜂围着胡同栅栏上的忍冬花嗡嗡地飞着。

“看我把它举到头顶上！”乔治大声喊着，“看看水怎么流下来。”

她精力充沛，没法再安静地坐下去了。乔治曾把一个面粉袋装满土，挂在一根树枝上当沙袋。她开始击打这个沙袋。嘭！嘭！她击打着沙袋，正好合着今早醒来时脑子里的那首曲子的节奏。乔治在土里还掺了一块尖锐的石头，她的指关节都打青了。

“嗷！你把水喷到我耳朵里了，把我耳膜弄破了，我听不见了。”

“给我，让我喷一会儿。”

水花溅到她的脸上，孩子们还拿水龙头转而去喷她的腿。她担心弄湿盒子，所以拿起盒子，穿过胡同到前面门廊去了。哈里正坐在他家台阶上看报纸。她打开盒子，拿出笔记本，却很难集中注意力去琢磨她想写下来的那首歌。哈里朝她这边望过来，她没法思考了。她和哈里最近聊了很多。

他俩几乎天天一起放学回家。他们谈论上帝。有时候她半夜醒来，想起他们说过的话，不禁瑟瑟发抖。哈里是个泛神论者，那也是一种宗教，如同浸礼教、天主教，或者犹太教。哈里相信，人死了被埋葬之后，会变成植物、火、尘土、云彩和水。几千年后，你最终会成为世界的一部分。他说，他觉得这比只当个天使好多了。无论如何，这比什么都没有好多了。

哈里把报纸扔进家里的门厅，走了过来。

“今天跟夏天一样热。”他说，“这才三月。”

“是啊，我希望我们可以去游泳。

“如果有什么可以游泳的地方，我们就去。”

“没有什么可以游泳的地方，只有那个乡村俱乐部的泳池。”

“我当然想干点什么——走出家门，去个什么地方。”

“我也是。”她说，“等等，我知道一个地方，就在乡下，约莫

十五英里的路程。树林里有条河，又深又宽。女童子军团在那里有个夏天的营地。去年有一次，韦尔斯太太带着我、乔治、皮特和萨克去那里游过泳。”

“如果你想去，我弄两辆自行车，我们可以明天去。我一个月可以休一个星期天。”

“我们骑车去，然后到那里野餐。”米克说。

“好的，我去借自行车。”

他该上班了。她望着他沿着大街走去，甩着两只胳膊。在街区中间的地方有一棵月桂树，枝叶很低。哈里紧跑几步跳起来，抓住一根树枝，做了个引体向上。她的心里涌上一种幸福的感觉，因为他们的确是要好的朋友，而且他很帅。明天，她要跟黑兹尔借蓝色项链，穿上那条丝绸裙子。至于午饭，他们要带果酱三明治和汽水。也许哈里会带些稀奇古怪的东西，因为他们吃的是传统犹太人的食物。她一直望着他，直到他拐过弯去。的确，他已经长成了一个非常英俊的小伙子了。

到了乡下的哈里跟坐在后门台阶上看报纸、思考希特勒的哈里完全不一样。他们一大早便出发了。他借的自行车都是男孩子骑的那种，两腿中间有大梁。他们把午饭和游泳衣捆在挡泥板上，九点以前就出发了。早晨天气很热，阳光灿烂。不到一个小时，他们就出了镇子，走上一条红色土路。田野里一片明艳的绿色，空气中弥漫着松树浓郁的味道。哈里非常激动地说着话，暖风吹在他们的脸上。她的嘴里很干，也觉得饿了。

“看见那边山上的房子了吗？我们到那里停一下，喝点水。”

“别了，我们最好等等，井水会让人得伤寒。”

“我已经得过伤寒了，还得过肺炎，断过腿，脚上还感染过。”

“我记得。”

“是的，”米克说，“我和比尔得伤寒发高烧的时候，就待在前屋里。皮特·韦尔斯从人行道上经过时，一边抬头望着我们的窗户，一边捂着鼻子从边上跑过去。比尔觉得非常难堪。我的头发都掉了，变成了秃子。”

“我敢打赌，我们已经离开镇子十英里了。我们骑了一个半小时，也骑得很快。”

“我真的很渴，”米克说，“也很饿。你袋子里装的是什么午饭？”

“冷肝馅布丁，鸡肉沙拉三明治，还有馅饼。”

“真是美味的野餐。”她很为自己带的东西感到羞愧，“我带了两颗水煮蛋，填了馅料，还分别用小袋子装了盐和胡椒，还有三明治，抹了黑莓酱和黄油，都用油纸包好了，还有餐巾纸。”

“我没想让你带任何东西，”哈里说，“我母亲给我们俩都准备了午饭，我请你出来，这就够了。我们很快就到一个商店了，可以买冷饮。”

他们又骑了半个小时，终于来到一个加油站的商店。哈里支好两人的自行车，她先走了进去。从外面炫目的阳光底下走进来，商店里面显得很黑，架子上堆着厚厚的白肉块、一桶桶油，还有一袋袋面粉。柜台上放着一大罐黏糊糊的散糖，上面苍蝇乱飞。

“你这里有什么饮料？”哈里问道。

店主一一道出名字。米克打开冰柜，看看里面。她的双手放在冰水里，感觉好极了。“我要一瓶巧克力味的汽水，有吗？”

“我也是，”哈里说，“来两瓶。”

“不，等等，这里有冰啤酒。如果你请得起的话，我想要一瓶啤酒。”

哈里也为自己点了一瓶啤酒。他觉得，不到二十岁的人喝啤酒简直就是犯罪——但也许，他突然想寻找刺激。第一口下肚，他脸上露出一副苦相。他们坐在商店前面的台阶上。米克的两条腿累坏了，腿上的肌肉一跳一跳的。她用手抹了抹瓶颈，慢慢地喝了一大口冰凉的啤酒。马路对面有一大片空荡荡的草地，草地那边有一排松树，呈现出深深浅浅的绿色——从明亮的黄绿色到接近黑色的深绿色，不一而足。天空蔚蓝，天气很热。

“我喜欢啤酒，”她说，“我以前经常用爸爸剩下的啤酒蘸面包吃，我喜欢一边喝，一边舔手上的盐粒。这是我独自喝的第二瓶啤酒了。”

“第一口发酸，后面的味道很好。”

店主说他们离小镇已经十二英里了。他们还要再走四英里。哈里付了钱，他们又走到外面炽热的阳光底下。哈里大声说着话，一直在哈哈大笑，毫无缘由。

“老天，喝完啤酒，再加上这炽热的阳光，让我觉得有点头晕眼花，但我真的感觉很美妙。”他说。

“我简直等不及要游泳了。”

路上有沙子，他们只得把全身重量都压在脚踏板上，免得陷进去。哈里的衬衫被汗水湿透了，贴在后背上，他还在不停地说话。道路变成红土路，沙子路被抛到了身后。她脑海中浮现出一首和缓的黑人歌曲——波西娅的弟弟曾经用口琴吹过这首歌。她按着歌曲的节拍踩着自行车踏板。

终于，他们到了她一直在寻找的地方。“就是这里！看见那个写着‘私有’的牌子了吗？我们得先爬过铁丝网栅栏，然后再顺着那条路上去——看！”

树林里非常安静，地上铺着光滑的松针。几分钟后，他们到了那条小河边。河水是棕色的，流得很急，很清凉。除了水声和松树梢传来的风的歌唱，周围鸦雀无声。幽深安静的树林似乎让他们有些胆怯，他们沿着河堤悄悄地走着。

“是不是很美啊。”

哈里大笑起来。“你为什么窃窃私语啊？听这里！”他用手拍着嘴巴，发出一声长长的印第安人的呐喊声，接着传来回声。“来吧，我们跳到水里，凉快凉快。”

“你不饿吗？”

“好吧，那我们就先吃东西。我们现在把午餐吃一半，留着一半，等从水里上来以后再吃。”

她打开果酱三明治。吃完以后，哈里把包装纸紧紧团成一个球，塞进一个空树桩里。然后他拿起短裤，顺着小路走下去。她躲到灌木丛后面，脱掉衣服，挣扎着把自己塞进黑兹尔的游泳衣里。泳衣太小了，紧紧勒着她的屁股。

“准备好了吗？”哈里大声喊道。

她听到水花四溅的声音，等赶到堤岸时，哈里已经在水里游了起来。“先别跳水，我看看有没有突出的石块，或者很浅的地方。”他说。她望着他的脑袋在水里一起一伏。无论如何，她都没打算跳水，她甚至连游泳都不会。她这辈子只游过几次泳——而且总是一直戴着游泳圈，或者待在水不会没过头顶的地方，但如果告诉哈里，就显得太娇气了。她有些尴尬。突然，她编起故事来：

“我再也不跳水了。我以前跳过，高台跳水，一直跳。但有一次我把脑袋摔破了，所以再也不跳了。”她想了一会儿，“我那天跳的是双飞身镰刀式，等上来时，水里都是血，但我没多想，便开始练游泳技巧了。那些人都冲我大喊大叫，我这才明白水里那些血是从哪里来的，从那以后我再也没好好游过泳。”

哈里爬上河堤。“天哪，我以前从来没听说过。”

她还想添油加醋好让这个故事听上去更合理一些，但是，她只是那么望着哈里。他的皮肤是浅棕色的，沾了水，闪闪发光。他胸前和腿上都有毛发，游泳裤很紧，让他看上去像是赤身裸体的样子。他没戴眼镜，脸显得更宽了，也更英俊了。他的眼睛是蓝色的，湿漉漉的。他也正在望着她，突然之间，他们好像尴尬起来。

“这里的水大约十英尺深，对岸那边很浅。”

“我们游起来吧。我敢打赌，冰凉的水让人感觉很好。”

她并不害怕。她觉得自己就像困在了一棵很高的大树树顶，她别无选择，只能小心翼翼地爬下来——一种死一般平静的感觉。她爬下堤岸，进到冰冷的水里。她抓着一条树根，但树根最后断掉了，她便开始游了起来。她呛了一次水，没了一次顶，但她坚持游着，没给自己丢脸。她游到了对岸，在那里她可以探到底，然后感觉好多了。她用两只拳头砸着水面，大声胡乱喊着，制造回声。

“看这里！”

哈里摇摇晃晃地爬上一棵很高很细的小树，树干很软，等他爬到树顶时，小树带着他一起倒了下来，他掉到了水里。

“我也要！看我的！”

“这是棵小树苗。”

她像别的住在一个街区的孩子一样，很擅长爬树。她模仿着他的每一个动作，重重地砸到水面上。她也会游泳，现在游得还不错。

他们玩着模仿游戏，在河堤上跑来跑去，又跳进冰冷的褐色河水里。他们又喊，又跳，又爬，玩了大约两个小时。然后他们站在河堤上，看着对方，似乎没有什么新把戏可以玩了。突然，她说：

“你裸泳过吗？”

林间一片安静，有一会儿的时间他没有回答。他很冷，乳头变成了紫色，很硬，嘴唇也发紫，牙齿咯咯作响。“我——我想没有。”

她心里一阵兴奋，然后脱口而出：“你敢，我就敢。你敢不敢？”

哈里把湿漉漉的黑色刘海儿抹到后面。“好。”

他俩都脱掉了泳衣。哈里背对着她，他脚步踉跄，耳朵都红了，然后他俩转过身，面对着对方。也许，他们在那里站了半个小时——也许并不超过一分钟。

哈里从一棵树上扯下一片树叶，撕成碎片。“我们还是穿上衣服吧。”

午餐过程中，两人都一言不发。他们把午餐摆在地上。哈里把所有东西都一分为二。夏日的午后炽热得让人有种昏昏欲睡的感觉。在树林深处他们听不到任何声音，只有缓缓的流水声，还有鸟叫的声音。哈里拿着他那颗填馅水煮蛋，用大拇指把蛋黄碾碎。这让她想起了什么？她听见自己的呼吸声。

然后哈里抬起头来，望着她背后的地方。“听着，我觉得你非常漂亮，米克。我以前从来没有这样想过，不是说我以前觉得你很丑——只是说——”

她朝水里扔了一颗松果。“如果想天黑之前回到家的话，我们最好现在就往回赶。”

“不，”他说，“我们躺下，就躺一会儿。”

他弄来一捧捧松针、树叶和灰色苔藓。她吸吮着膝盖，望着他，两只拳头攥得紧紧的，好像全身上下都很紧张。

“现在，我们可以睡一会，养足精神，好回家。”

他们躺在松软的“床”上，抬头望着一丛丛深绿色的松树直入云霄。有只鸟儿唱着一首哀婉清越的歌，她以前从来没有听过。有个很高的音符像是双簧管发出来的——接着降了五个调，然后又响了起来。这首歌如此哀婉，像是一个无言的问题。

“我喜欢这只鸟。”哈里说，“我觉得是只绿鹃。”

“我希望我们是在海上，在沙滩上，望着远处海上的船只。有一年夏天你去海边了——那到底是种什么感觉？”

他的声音粗哑而低沉。“嗯，有海浪，有时候是蓝的，有时候是绿的，在灿烂的阳光下海浪看起来像玻璃一样。沙滩上可以捡到小贝壳，就像我们用雪茄盒带回来的那种。水面上还有白色的海鸥。我们去过墨西哥湾——海湾的凉风一直吹着，从来不像这里这么热，像烤箱一样。一直——”

“雪，”米克说，“这是我想看的。寒冷的白色雪花，像电影里一样。暴风雪。寒冷的白色雪花一直轻轻地飘着，整个冬天都在一直飘啊飘啊，像阿拉斯加的雪一样。”

他们两人同时转过身来，紧紧靠在了一起。她感觉到他在颤抖，她的两只拳头攥得都快裂开了。“噢，上帝。”他一遍遍地说。她的头好像从身体上掉了下来，被扔掉了。她的眼睛向上直视着刺目的阳光，一边在心里数着什么。然后，就是这样了。

就是这样。

他们沿着小路缓缓推着车子。哈里耷拉着脑袋，弓着肩膀。土路上，他们的影子很长很黑，已是傍晚时分了。

“听着。”他说。

“嗯。”

“我们必须弄明白这件事，必须弄明白，你——懂吗？”

“我不知道，我觉得不懂。”

“听着。我们必须得做点什么。坐一会儿吧。”

他们扔下自行车，坐在路边的水沟旁，两人离得很远。黄昏的阳光照在他们头上，周围都是不堪一击的棕色蚂蚁窝。

“我们必须弄明白这件事。”哈里说。

他哭了起来。他坐在那里一动不动，眼泪从白皙的脸上滚落下来。她想不出他为什么事情而哭。一只蚂蚁咬了一口她的脚踝，她用手指把蚂蚁捏起来，拿近了细看。

“是这样，”他说，“我以前从来没有亲吻过女孩。”

“我也没有，我从来没有亲吻过男孩，家里人除外。”

“我过去满脑子想的都是这件事——去亲吻某一个女孩。以前，上学时我会在脑子里盘算，夜里还会梦见这件事。后来有一次，她约了我。我看得出，她想让我亲她。我只是在黑暗中望着她，却不能亲她。我以前满脑子都是这个——亲她——但事到临头，我却做不到。”

她用手指在地上挖了个洞，埋掉了那只死蚂蚁。

“这都是我的错。不管怎么看，通奸都是一种可怕的罪恶。你比我小两岁，还是个孩子。”

“不，我不是孩子，绝不是个孩子，但现在我希望自己是。”

“听着，如果你觉得应该的话，我们可以结婚，秘密地结婚，或者用别的什么方式。”

米克摇摇头。“我不喜欢那样，我绝不跟任何男孩结婚。”

“我也绝不结婚。我知道这一点，而且也不只是说说而已——是真的。”

他脸上的表情让她害怕，他的鼻子颤抖着，下嘴唇咬得颜色斑驳，有些血淋淋的。两只眼睛很明亮，含着泪光，闪着怒气。那张脸比她见过的任何面孔都要苍白。她别过头去，不看他。如果他不再说话，一切可能会好得多。她慢慢环顾四周——望着水沟里的红白相间的黏土，望着一个碎掉的威士忌瓶子，望着他们对面的一棵松树，上面挂了个牌子，为一个竞选乡村治安官的男人做宣传。她想就这样永远静静地坐下去，不思考，也不说话。

“我要离开小镇，我还算是个不错的技工，可以到其他地方找份工作。如果待在家里，母亲会从我的眼神里察觉这件事。”

“告诉我。你看着我，能看出异样吗？”

哈里盯着她的脸，看了很长时间，点点头表示能看出来，然后又说：

“还有一件事。过一两个月，我会把我的地址发给你，你给我写信，告诉我你是不是一切都好。”

“你是什么意思？”她缓缓问道。

他跟她做了解释：“你只需要写个‘好’字，我就明白了。”

他们继续推着自行车，往家走去，影子在路上拉得很长，像巨人似的。哈里弓着身子，像个苍老的乞丐，不断地用衣袖擦鼻子。有一瞬间，一切都闪耀着明亮金黄的光芒，然后太阳落到了树木背后，他们眼前路上的影子消失了。她觉得非常苍老，就像心里有什么沉重的东西一样。现在不管自己愿不愿意，她已经是个大人了。

他们走了十六英里，到了家旁边漆黑的小巷里，她看见家里厨房透出昏黄的灯光。哈里家则漆黑一片——他母亲还没有回来。他母亲在一条小街上给一个裁缝干活儿，有时候甚至连周日也要上班。你从窗户里望进去，能看到她趴在后面的机器上，或者用一根长针缝着一些厚重的东西。你望着她时，她从来不会抬头。到了晚上，她会为哈里和自己煮一顿传统的晚饭。

“听着——”他说。

她在黑暗中等着，但他没有继续说下去。他们握了握手，哈里顺着房子之间黑乎乎的小巷走了。他走到人行道上，转过头，望望身后。一束灯光照在他的脸上，他的脸色苍白、冷峻。然后，他走了。

“我有个谜语。”乔治说。

“我听着呢。”

“两个印第安人正在小路上走着。前面那个是后面那个的儿子，但后面那个却不是他的父亲。他俩什么关系？”

“我想想。是他的继父。”

乔治冲波西娅笑了，露出一口方方正正、细小的青色牙齿。

“那就是他叔叔。”

“你猜不出来的。是他妈妈。里面的花招就是，你觉得印第安人不会是女的。”

她站在屋子外面，望着他们。从门口看过去，厨房就像一幅画。里面干净舒适。只有水槽旁边的灯开着，房间里影影绰绰。比尔和黑兹尔在桌上玩“黑杰克”纸牌，用火柴当钱。黑兹尔用胖乎乎的粉红手指抚摸着发辫，比尔则吸着两颊，非常认真地打着手中的牌。水槽边，波西娅正用一块干净的方格毛巾擦干碗碟。她看上去很瘦，皮肤是一种金棕色，抹了油脂的黑色头发梳得很整齐光滑。拉尔夫安静地坐在地板上，乔治正努力把用圣诞节旧金属箔丝线做的挽具往他身上套。

“这里还有一个谜语，波西娅，如果钟表的指针指向两点半——”

她走进屋子。她似乎以为他们看见她时会向后退去，然后围成一圈站在那里看着她，但他们只是瞥了她一眼。她坐在桌前，等待着。

“大家都吃完晚饭了，你才拖拖拉拉地回来。我好像永远也下不了班了。”

没有人注意她。她吃完了一大盘子卷心菜和鲑鱼，最后又吃光了乳冻甜食。她心里想着妈妈。门开了，妈妈走了进来，告诉波西娅，布朗小姐说房间里发现了臭虫。要去把汽油拿出来。

“别那么皱着眉头了，米克，你这个年龄应该好好收拾一下，尽量保持最好的样子。慢着——我跟你说话时，别急着往外窜——我是说，睡觉前你用海绵好好给拉尔夫擦洗下身体，好好洗洗他的鼻子和耳朵。”

拉尔夫柔软的头发上沾着燕麦粥。她用抹布把燕麦片擦掉，又在水槽跟前给他洗了脸和手。比尔和黑兹尔结束了扑克游戏。比尔拿起火柴时，长指甲刮在桌面上。乔治抱着拉尔夫去睡觉。厨房里，只剩下她和波西娅两个人。

“听着！看着我，你看出有什么地方不一样吗？”

“我当然看出来了，亲爱的。”

波西娅戴上红帽子，换了鞋子。

“嗯——”

“你得弄点油脂抹抹脸，你的鼻子都脱皮了，脱得很厉害。他们说油脂治疗晒伤最好了。”

她独自站在漆黑的后院里，用指甲从那棵橡树上抠下一块块树皮。情况更糟糕了。也许如果他们能够看着她，看出端倪，她会感觉好得多。他们要是知道就好了。

她爸爸在后门台阶上喊她：“米克！哦，米克！”

“在，长官！”

“电话。”

乔治挤过来，想听听，但她把他推开了。米诺维茨太太的嗓门很大，很激动。

“我家哈里现在应该在家的。你知道他去哪儿了吗？”

“不知道，夫人。”

“他说你们俩要骑自行车出去。现在他会在哪儿呢？你知道他在哪儿吗？”

“不知道，夫人。”米克又重复了一遍。

12

天气重新热了起来，迪克西阳光游乐场也随之热闹起来。三月的风平息下来，树木的枝叶郁郁葱葱，一片黄绿色。天空碧蓝，没有一丝云彩，阳光越发强烈了，空气湿热难耐。杰克·布朗特痛恨这种天气。他晕晕乎乎地想到未来几个月漫长酷热的夏季，感觉很糟糕。近来他不断受头痛困扰，体重增加了，肚子有点鼓了出来，他只好不扣裤子最上面的一颗纽扣。他知道是因为喝酒导致的发胖，却还是一直喝酒。酒精有助于缓解头痛，他只要喝一小杯，头痛就好多了。现在，对他而言，一杯跟一夸脱没有分别。让他兴奋的不是当时的酒——而是第一口酒下肚后，引发了过去几个月中储存在他血液中的所有酒精的反应。一勺啤酒会帮助他缓解头痛，但一夸脱威士忌却不会让他喝醉。

他完全戒了酒。几天以来，他只喝水，还有橘子汁。那种疼痛就像脑子里有条虫子在爬。他在漫长的午后和夜晚工作着，疲惫不堪。他无法入睡，想要读点东西，这简直就是一种痛苦。房间里潮湿酸腐的味道令他恼火。他躺在床上辗转反侧，终于睡过去的时候已是天光大亮。有个梦总是挥之不去。四个月之前，他第一次做这个梦，醒来时非常恐惧——但奇怪的是，他从来记不住这个梦的内容。睁开眼睛时，只有那种感觉还存留下来。每一次醒来时的恐惧感都一模一样，他毫不怀疑这些梦都是同样的内容。他习惯了做梦，酒后的那些稀奇古怪的噩梦让他陷入一个疯子似的混乱境地。但清晨的阳光一来，这些荒诞的梦便消失不见，他也记不起来了。

这个茫然、诡秘的梦全然不同。他醒来后什么都不记得，但心里会有一种威胁的感觉久久不能散去。后来他有天早晨醒过来，又是那种熟悉的恐惧感，却依稀记得背后的那种黑暗。他走在一群人当中，怀里抱着什么东西，他只能确定这些内容。他偷东西了吗？他是要拼命保护什么财产？周围的那些人都在追他吗？好像不是。他越想这个简单的梦，越觉得不明白。后来有一段时间，他不再做这个梦了。

他遇到了那个写标语的人，去年十一月，他看见这个人用粉笔写的那些话。从他们第一次见面起，这个老人就像个邪恶的天才一样缠着他。他叫西姆斯，经常在人行道上布道。冬天太冷，他只好待在室内，但到了春天，他会一整天都待在大街上。他的头发很软，胡乱地垂在脖子上。他总是随身带着一个很大的女式丝绸提包，里面装满粉笔和耶稣宣传单。他的眼睛明亮，眼神疯狂。西姆斯想要让他皈依。

“逆境中的孩子，我闻到了你气息中罪恶的啤酒臭味，而且你还抽烟。如果上帝想让我们抽烟，他就会在《圣经》里说了。你的眉头上有撒旦的印记，我看见了。忏悔吧。让我指给你光明吧。”

杰克向上翻翻眼珠，慢慢在空中划出一个虔诚的符号，然后张开油迹斑斑的手。“我只把这个给你看。”他用一种低低的舞台剧的声音说道。西姆斯低头看着他手掌上的伤口。杰克俯身过来，低声说：“还有另外一个符号，你知道的符号，我生来就带着它们。”

西姆斯向后靠在栅栏上，用女人一般的姿势把一缕银发从额头撩起来，理顺到头顶上抚平，舌头紧张地舔着嘴角。杰克哈哈大笑起来。

“亵渎神明的人！”西姆斯尖叫起来，“上帝会抓到你的，你和你们这帮人。上帝会记住嘲笑者，他在我身后关注着，上帝关注每个人，但他特别关注我，就像他关注摩西一样。上帝在晚上跟我说了很多事情。上帝会抓到你的。”

他把西姆斯带到街角的一家商店，请他喝可口可乐，吃抹了花生酱的饼干。西姆斯又开始在他身上下功夫了。他起身去游乐场的时候，西姆斯一路小跑紧跟在他身后。

“今晚七点，到这个街角来。耶稣有专门给你的启示。”

四月，最初有几天刮风，却很暖和。白云飘在湛蓝的天空上，风里有河流的味道，还有镇子外面的田野散发出来的更清新的味道。从早晨四点一直到午夜，游乐场里都人满为患，这都是些粗人。随着新春的到来，他隐隐感觉到有一种麻烦的味道。

一天晚上，他正在检修秋千的机械装置，突然被一阵愤怒的声音惊得回过神来。他迅速挤过人群，看到旋转木马售票亭旁边一个白人女孩正跟一个黑人女孩打架。他使劲把两人拽开，但她俩还是拼命要扑向对方。围观人群各有偏袒，吵闹声震天。白人女孩是个驼背，一只手里紧紧握着一个什么东西。

“我见过你，”黑人女孩喊道，“我要把那个罗锅从背上给你打下来。”

“闭嘴，你这个黑鬼。”

“下流的工厂货，我付了钱就要坐。白人，你让她把票还给我。”

“黑鬼骚货！”

杰克看看这个，再看看那个。人群挤得更紧了，两边都有人嘟嘟囔囔地发表着意见。

“我看见卢里掉了票，然后这个白人女孩捡了起来。就是这样。”一个黑人男孩说。

“任何黑鬼都不许用手碰任何一个白人女孩，而——”

“你别再推我了，即便你的皮肤的确是白的，我也要一拳打回去了。”

杰克粗鲁地挤进密不透风的人群。“好了！”他大声喊道，“走吧——散了吧，你们这些该死的。”看到他的两只大拳头，人们悻悻地散开了。杰克转身望着两个女孩。

“事情就是这样。”黑人女孩说，“我敢确定，在这里没几个人能像我一样，直到星期五晚上才攒够五毛钱。这个星期我做了两倍熨衣服的活儿。她手里拿的那张票，我花了五分钱，现在我一定要坐木马。”

杰克很快解决了问题。他让驼背女孩留着那张有争议的票，又给了黑人女孩一张新票。那天晚上，没有再出现争吵。但杰克在人群中穿来穿去，很警惕。他忧心忡忡，心神不宁。

游乐场里，除了他还有五位员工——两个男人开秋千、收票，三个女孩负责售票亭。这没算上帕特森。这位游乐场主大多数时间都在拖车里跟自己打牌。他眼神迟钝，瞳孔缩着，脖子上的皮肤堆成层层黄色的褶皱，软软的。在过去的几个月中，杰克的工资涨了两次。到了半夜，他负责跟帕特森汇报，并上交当晚的收入。有时候，他在拖车里待上好几分钟，帕特森才会注意到他。帕特森总是一直盯着牌，陷入恍惚之中。拖车里弥漫着浓重的食物和大麻烟卷的刺鼻味道。帕特森伸手捂住肚子，好像保护着肚子不受什么东西的伤害。他对账目审查得非常仔细。

杰克和两个操作员发生过一次口角。这两个人以前都在工厂里当落纱工。起初他试图跟他们聊天，想帮他们看清真相，有一次还邀请他俩去台球室喝酒。但是，他们非常愚钝，他帮不了他们。此后不久，他无意间听到两人的对话，才引发了这场麻烦。那是周日凌晨，大概两点钟，他在跟帕特森核对账目。他走出拖车时，场地上似乎空荡荡的，月光非常明亮。他想着辛格和接下来空闲的一天，经过秋千时他听到有人提到他的名字。那两个操作员干完活儿，正凑在一起抽烟。杰克侧耳细听。

“如果说有什么东西比黑鬼还让我讨厌，那就是赤色分子。”

“他让我发笑，我根本不把他当回事。看他趾高气扬的样子，我从来没见过这么五短身材的小矮子。你觉得他有多高？”

“大概五英尺吧，但他觉得自己有那么多东西要跟别人讲。他该进监狱，那才是他该待的地方，这个红色布尔什维克。”

“他让我发笑，一看见他我就忍不住笑。”

“他不用跟我装什么大头。”

杰克望着他们朝织工巷走去。他的第一个反应就是冲出去质问他们，但某种畏缩又把他拉了回来。有好几天的时间，他默默地生闷气。后来有天晚上下班后，他跟着那两个男人走了好几个街区，他们转过一个弯时，他挡在了他们面前。

“我听见你们说的话了，”他喘着粗气说，“上个星期六晚上，我碰巧听到你们说的每个字。当然，我是个赤色分子，至少我认为自己是，但你们是什么？”他们站在一盏街灯下，两个人朝后退了一步，附近空无一人。“你们这些脸色苍白、小肚鸡肠、没骨气的小老鼠！我可以伸出手掐断你们细瘦的脖子，一手一个。别管是不是小矮子，我可以把你们打倒在人行道上，到时候得用铲子才能把你们铲起来。”

两个男人面面相觑，吓住了，想要走开，但杰克不放过他们。他随着他们的步子，倒退着，脸上现出愤怒的讥笑。

“我要说的就是：我建议，以后你们什么时候想评论我的身高、体重、口音、举止，或者思想，尽管来找我。特别是最后一点，我要特别提醒你俩——免得你们不知道。我们可以一起讨论讨论。”

后来，杰克用愤怒的鄙视态度对待这两个人。在他背后，他们对他冷嘲热讽。一天下午，他发现秋千的引擎遭到了蓄意破坏，他不得不加班三个小时才修好。他一直觉得有人在嘲笑他。每次听到那几个女孩在一起聊天，他都会挺直身子，漫不经心地一个人大笑起来，好像想到了某个私密的笑话。

墨西哥湾吹来温暖的西南风，带着浓浓的春天气息。白天越来越长，阳光灿烂。这种令人懒洋洋的温暖让他情绪低落，他又开始喝酒了。工作一干完，他便回家躺在床上。有时候他待在那里，不脱衣服，一动不动，一待便是十二三个小时。几个月前，让他哭泣、啃指甲的那种坐立不安似乎消失了，但在这种怠惰背后，杰克感觉到了原来的那种紧张感。在他去过的所有地方当中，这是最孤独的小镇，或者如果没有了辛格，它将是最孤独的小镇。只有他和辛格懂得真理。他知道，却无法让那些不知道的人明白，就像在跟黑暗、跟空气中的炎热或臭味搏斗一样。他阴郁地望着窗外。街角有棵矮小的树，被烟熏黑了，已经抽出黄绿色的新叶。天空总是一种深邃硬朗的蓝色。有条发臭的小河流经镇上的这片区域，里面滋生的蚊子在他房间里嗡嗡乱飞。

他抓着发痒的地方。他把硫黄和猪油混在一起，每天早晨抹在身体上。他把自己抓得浑身红肿，瘙痒似乎永远不能消停。有天晚上，他崩溃了。他独自坐了好几个小时，喝了掺在一起的杜松子酒和威士忌，醉得厉害。时间已是凌晨。他从窗口探出身子，望着漆黑无声的街道，想起周围的人们。他们在睡觉。这些不知道的人。突然，他大声叫骂起来：“这就是真理！你们这些畜生，什么都不知道，你们不知道，你们不知道！”

整条街上的人都愤怒地醒了过来，灯亮了，人们带着睡意大声地骂他。住在同一幢房子里的男人们愤怒地猛砸他的门，街对面妓院里的姑娘们都把头伸出了窗外。

“你们这些愚蠢愚蠢愚蠢愚蠢的杂种。你们这些愚蠢愚蠢愚蠢愚蠢的——”

“闭嘴！闭嘴！”

走廊里的家伙正在推门。“你这头醉鬼公牛！等我们进去有你好看的。”

“外面有多少人？”杰克咆哮道。他把一只空酒瓶砰的一声砸在窗框上，“来吧，所有人。来吧，一起上吧。我一次可以解决你们三个。”

“好啊，甜心。”一个妓女喊道。

门被推开了。杰克从窗户里跳了出去，钻进一条偏僻小巷。“嘿嚯！嘿嚯！”他醉醺醺地大喊着。他光着脚，赤裸着上身。一个小时以后，他跌跌撞撞走进了辛格的房间，四肢伸展瘫在地上，哈哈大笑，笑着笑着便睡着了。

一个四月的早晨，他发现了一个被暗杀的男人的尸体，是个年轻的黑人。杰克在一条水沟里发现了这具尸体，离游乐场大约有三十码的距离。黑人的喉咙被割开了，脑袋向后仰着，角度令人惊诧。太阳炽热地照在他睁开的呆滞双眼上，胸前干掉的血迹上苍蝇乱飞。死者手里握着一根拐杖，红黄相间，带流苏，像游乐场汉堡摊上卖的那种一样。杰克难过地低头盯着这具尸体，看了好一会儿。然后，他报了警。没有发现任何线索。两天后，死者的家属到太平间认领了尸体。

在迪克西阳光游乐场经常有人打架、争吵。有时候，两个好朋友手挽手走进游乐场，大笑着，喝着饮料，等离开时则会扭作一团，气得直喘粗气。杰克一直很警觉。在游乐场花哨的欢乐、明亮的灯光、懒洋洋的大笑之下，他总觉得有一种闷闷不乐的东西，非常危险。

在这恍恍惚惚、支离破碎的几个星期中，西姆斯一直四处奔走。老人喜欢随身带着一个肥皂箱、一本《圣经》，然后在人群中站好，开始布道。他讲耶稣的第二次降临，说审判日是一九五一年十月二日。他会指着某些酒鬼，用伤感而疲惫的声音冲他们喊叫。由于兴奋，他嘴里流满口水，每说一句话便会发出一种湿漉漉的、汩汩的声音。他一旦走进人群站定，任凭别人怎么说，他都不会让步。他给了杰克一本基甸国际《圣经》做礼物，让他每天晚上跪地祈祷一个小时，并且把别人给他的啤酒和香烟全部扔掉。

他们因为墙壁和栅栏争吵起来。杰克也开始在口袋里随身装着粉笔，写一些简单的句子。他很注意措辞，这样才有路人停下来认真琢磨意思，才会有人好奇，才会有人思考。此外，他还写些简短的小册子到大街上分发。

杰克知道，如果不是因为辛格，他也许已经离开小镇了。只有星期天跟朋友在一起的时候，他才会感觉到宁静。有时候他们会一起散散步，或下下棋——但大多数时候，他们一整天都安静地待在辛格的屋子里。如果他想说话，辛格总是很专心地听着。如果他闷闷不乐地坐一整天，哑巴也会理解他的感受，并不吃惊。在他看来，现在似乎只有辛格能帮得了他。

有个星期天，他爬上台阶，看见辛格的房门开着，里面空无一人。他一个人在那里坐了两个多小时。终于，他听见辛格上楼的脚步声。

“我正在想着你呢。你去哪儿了？”

辛格微笑着，用手帕扫了扫帽子，将帽子收好，从容地从口袋里掏出银色铅笔，伏在壁炉上写了一张便条。

“你是什么意思？”杰克看完哑巴写的东西，问道，“谁的腿被锯掉了？”

辛格拿回便条，又写了几句话。

“哈，”杰克说，“这个不奇怪。”

他思考着这张纸上的话，然后在手里把它揉作一团。过去一个月里的精神不振消失了，他紧张而且不安。“哈！”他又说道。

辛格将咖啡壶放在炉子上，拿出棋盘。杰克把便条撕碎，在两只汗乎乎的手里揉搓着这些纸片。

“但是，这件事我们可以做点什么。”过了一会儿，他说，“你知道吗？”

辛格犹疑地点点头。

“我想见见那个男孩，听听完整的事情经过。你什么时候可以带我过去？”

辛格认真思考了一下，然后在便笺本上写道：“今晚。”

杰克用一只手捂住嘴巴，开始在屋里不安地踱步。“我们可以做点什么。”

13

杰克和辛格在门廊等着。他们按了门铃，但漆黑的屋子里并没有门铃声响起。杰克不耐烦地敲敲门，把鼻子贴在纱门上。辛格呆站在他身边，微笑着，双颊带着红晕，他俩刚才一起喝了一瓶杜松子酒。这个夜晚很安静，漆黑一片。杰克看着走廊里亮起一束柔和的黄色灯光。波西娅为他们开了门。

“我希望你们没等太长时间。来的人太多了，我们觉得还是把门铃摘下来比较好。先生们，把帽子给我吧——父亲病得很厉害。”

杰克踮着脚，步履沉重地跟在辛格后面，穿过空荡荡的狭窄走廊。在厨房门口，他突然停下了。房间里又挤又热，一个小小的木头炉子里正生着火，窗户紧闭，烟雾混合着一种黑人的味道。炉子里的火光是屋里唯一的亮光，他在走廊里听到的那些低沉的声音静默了。

“来了两位白人绅士，他们想问问父亲的情况。”波西娅说，“我觉得他也许能见见你们，但我最好先进去帮他准备下。”

杰克用手指摸着厚厚的下嘴唇，鼻尖印着前面纱门的格子痕迹。“不是这么回事，”他说，“我来是想跟你弟弟聊聊。”

屋里的黑人们都站了起来，辛格示意他们都落座。两位头发花白的老者坐在火炉旁边的凳子上，一个四肢松弛的混血儿懒洋洋地靠在窗户上。角落里的一张宿营用的床上躺着一个男孩，没有双腿，裤子叠了起来固定在大腿残肢底下。

“晚上好。”杰克有些局促地说，“你叫科普兰？”

男孩双手捂住残肢，向后缩着紧贴到墙边。“我叫威利。”

“亲爱的，别担心。”波西娅说，“这位是辛格先生，你听父亲提起过他。另一位白人绅士是布朗特先生，他是辛格先生的好朋友。他们只是好心过来关心下我们的问题。”她转身对着杰克，指指屋子里另外三个人，“靠在窗户上的这个男孩也是我弟弟，叫巴迪。坐在火炉边的这两位，都是我父亲的好朋友，马歇尔·尼克尔斯先生和约翰·罗伯茨先生。我觉得，先认识下屋子里的人比较好。”

“谢谢。”杰克说，又转向威利，“我只想让你给我说说这件事，这样我就可以理出个头绪来。”

“是这样的，”威利说，“我觉得两只脚还在疼，这种可怕的疼痛一直疼到脚指头，但如果两只脚还在腿上的话，这种疼痛会一直传到原来长脚的那个地方，而不是我的脚现在待的地方。这件事情很难理解。我的脚一直疼得厉害，但我不知道我的脚在哪里，他们没有把脚还给我，它们也许在离我一百英——英里之外的什——什么地方。”

“我是说，想听听这件事情发生的始末。”杰克说。

威利抬头看看姐姐，很不安。“我不记得了——记不清了。”

“你当然记得，亲爱的。你跟我们说过一遍又一遍。”

“嗯——”男孩的声音怯怯的，郁郁寡欢。“我们都在外面的路上，那个巴斯特跟警卫说了什么。那个白——白人拿棍子打他，然后另一个男孩想要逃跑，我紧跟着他。一切发生得很突然，我记不清到底是怎么回事了。然后他们把我们带回了营地，并且——”

“其他的情况我知道了。”杰克说，“告诉我另外两个男孩的名字和地址，还有警卫的名字。”

“听着，白人，我觉得你好像要给我惹麻烦。”

“麻烦！”杰克粗鲁地说，“看在耶稣的分上，你觉得你现在的处境怎么样？”

“我们冷静一下，”波西娅紧张地说，“是这样，布朗特先生。他们提前让威利离开了营地，他的刑期还没满，但他们对他再三强调，不要——我相信你明白我们的意思。威利自然很害怕，我们自然要非常小心——因为这是我们最好的选择了。我们的麻烦已经够多了。”

“那些警卫怎么处理了？”

“那些白——白人被开除了，他们是这么跟我说的。”

“你的朋友现在在哪里？”

“什么朋友？”

“哎呀，就是那两个男孩。”

“他们不——不是我朋友，”威利说，“我们都大吵了一架。”

“你是什么意思？”

波西娅拽着耳环，耳垂像橡胶一样被拽得很长。“威利的意思是这样的，你看，在他们遭受折磨的三天里，他们开始争吵。威利再也不想见他俩了。父亲和威利因为这件事情已经争论过。这个巴斯特——”

“巴斯特装了一条木腿，”窗边的男孩说，“今天我在街上看见他了。”

“这个巴斯特没有家人，父亲想让他搬来跟我们住。父亲想把这几个男孩都笼络到一起。我真的不知道，他为什么觉得我们养得起他们。”

“这不是个好主意，而且我们从来就不是什么好朋友。”威利用黝黑结实的双手抚摸着两条残肢，“我只是希望能知道我的脚——脚——脚在哪里，这是最让我发愁的事情。那个医生没有把它们还给我。我特别想知道它们在哪儿。”

杰克环顾四周，眼神恍惚，醉意蒙眬。一切都很模糊，很奇怪。厨房里的热气让他头晕，那些声音在他耳畔回荡着，烟雾令他窒息。天花板上吊下来的灯亮了，但为了降低亮度，灯泡用报纸包上了，大部分光亮还是来自炽热火炉的缝隙中透出来的光。他周围，一张张黑色面孔都闪着红光。他觉得心神不安，觉得孤独。辛格已经离开了这间屋子，去看波西娅的父亲。杰克想让他赶紧回来，可以一起回家。他笨拙地走到另一边，坐在马歇尔·尼克尔斯和约翰·罗伯茨中间。

“波西娅的父亲在哪里？”他问道。

“科普兰医生在前面的房间，先生。”罗伯茨说。

“他是个医生？”

“是的，先生，他是个医生。”

外面台阶上传来吵闹声，后门开了，一阵温暖新鲜的风稀释了空气里的凝重。先是一个穿着亚麻西装和镀金鞋子的高个男孩走了进来，怀里抱着一个袋子。后面跟进来一个男孩，大约十七岁的样子。

“嗨，海博埃。嗨，兰西。”威利说，“你们给我带了什么？”

海博埃规矩地给杰克鞠躬，然后把两罐用水果坛装的酒放在桌上。兰西在旁边又放下一个盘子，上面盖着一张干净的白色餐巾。

“这些酒是协会给的礼物，”海博埃说，“兰西的母亲送来一些桃子泡芙。”

“医生怎么样了，波西娅小姐？”兰西问道。

“亲爱的，这些天他病得很厉害。让我担心的是，他很强壮。一个像他这样的病人，突然这么强壮起来，不是个好兆头。”波西娅转向杰克，“你不觉得是个坏兆头吗，布朗特先生？”

杰克神情恍惚地盯着她。“我不知道。”

兰西面带愠色地瞥了一眼杰克，放下已经过小的衬衫袖口。“请把我家人的问候带给医生。”

“我们真的非常感谢。”波西娅说，“那天父亲还说起过你。他有本书想送给你。等一下，我去找找，再把这个盘子洗干净还给你母亲。她这样做真是太好心了。”

马歇尔·尼克尔斯朝杰克俯过身来，似乎要跟他说话。老人穿一条条纹裤子，一件晨衣，纽扣眼处别着一朵花。他清清嗓子说：“抱歉，先生——但我们不可避免地听到了你跟威廉的一部分谈话，就是关于他现在的麻烦的。必然地，我们已经考虑过最好的办法。”

“你是他的亲戚，还是他教堂的牧师？”

“都不是，我是个药剂师。你左边的约翰·罗伯茨受雇于政府的邮政部门。”

“邮差。”约翰·罗伯茨重复一遍。

“请您允许——”马歇尔·尼克尔斯从口袋里掏出一条丝质黄手帕，小心翼翼地擤了擤鼻子，“我们自然已经深入地谈论了这个问题。无疑，作为在美国这个自由国度里的黑人种族的一员，我们急切地想要作出努力，希望发展我们的友好关系。”

“我们一直希望能够做些正确的事情。”约翰·罗伯茨说。

“我们理应小心抗争，不要危及已经建立起来的友好关系。然后，慢慢地情况就会好转了。”

杰克看着这个，再看看那个。“我似乎没明白你的意思。”热气令他窒息，他想出去。他的眼球上像是蒙了一层薄膜，周围的面孔都模糊不清。

房间那头，威利吹起口琴，巴迪和海博埃都在听着。曲调阴郁而悲伤。一曲吹完，威利在衬衫前襟上擦着口琴。“我又饿又渴，嘴里的口水把曲子都弄湿了。我真的很高兴尝尝这种‘布基伍基’[20]。能有点好酒喝，是唯一能让——让我忘掉悲伤的事情了。如果能知道我的脚这会儿在哪里，能每天晚上喝一杯杜松子酒，那就没什么了不起的了。”

“别着急，亲爱的。你会有的。”波西娅说。

“布朗特先生，您想来块桃子泡芙，再来一杯酒吗？”

“谢谢。”杰克说，“那太好了。”

波西娅快速在桌子上铺了桌布，放了一个盘子和一把叉子。她倒了一大杯酒，“在这里，尽管随意。如果不介意，我去招呼下其他人。”

两个水果坛子在人们嘴边传来传去。海博埃把坛子传给威利之前，跟波西娅要了一支口红，画了一条红线，标出饮酒的边界。传来咕咚咕咚的声音，还有人们的欢笑声。杰克吃完泡芙，端着酒杯又回到两位老人中间的位置。自酿的酒醇厚，浓烈，像白兰地一样。威利又开始用口琴吹奏低沉悲伤的曲调。波西娅把手指关节掰得噼啪作响，拖着脚步在屋里走来走去。

杰克转身看着马歇尔·尼克尔斯。“你说，波西娅的父亲是个医生？”

“是的，先生。是的，的确如此，一位医术高超的医生。”

“他出了什么事？”

两个黑人彼此谨慎地对视一眼。

“他出了场事故。”约翰·罗伯茨说。

“什么事故？”

“严重的事故，很恶劣。”

马歇尔·尼克尔斯把丝绸手帕折起来，再打开。“刚才我们还在说，不要损害现在这些友好的关系，这很重要，还要尽可能用各种办法来真正促进友好关系。我们作为黑人，必须想方设法激励我们的公民。那边的那位医生尝试了各种方法。但有时候，我觉得他没有完全认清不同种族中的一些特定因素，没有认清局势。”

杰克迫不及待地一口喝掉最后几口酒。“看在上帝的分上，伙计，直说吧，你说的话我一句都听不懂。”

马歇尔·尼克尔斯和约翰·罗伯茨交换了一下受伤的眼神。房间那头，威利仍然坐在那里吹奏着音乐，他的嘴唇在口琴的方洞上来回移动，就像有褶皱的胖毛毛虫。他的肩膀宽阔结实，大腿残肢随着音乐抖动着。海博埃跳着舞，巴迪和波西娅和着节奏拍着手。

杰克站起来，而一站起来，他才发现自己喝醉了。他摇摇晃晃，仇恨地瞥了一眼周围的人，但似乎并没有人注意到。“辛格在哪里？”他粗声粗气地问波西娅。

音乐声停了。“哎呀，布朗特先生，我以为你知道他已经走了。你坐在桌前吃桃子泡芙的时候，他来到门口，伸出手表让你看，意思是他该走了。你径直看了他一眼，摇摇头。我以为你知道的。”

“也许我当时在考虑别的事情。”他转向威利，生气地对他说，“我根本不用跟你说我为什么到这里来，我来这里不是要求你做任何事情，我只是想——我想要的就是这个，你和另外两个男孩要证明发生了什么事，我会解释为什么。为什么，这是唯一重要的事情——而不是什么。我应该用车子推着你们到各处去，你们应该讲讲自己的经历，然后我会解释为什么。也许这有很大的意义，也许这——”

他感觉他们都在嘲笑他，困惑之中他忘了要说什么。房间里到处都是黝黑、陌生的面孔，空气凝重，简直无法呼吸。他看见一扇门，跌跌撞撞走了过去。他走进一个黑乎乎的壁橱里，里面散发着药物的味道，然后他的手又去转动另一扇门的把手。

他站在一个白色小房间的门槛上，房间里只有一张铁床、一个橱柜、两把椅子。床上躺着一个可怕的黑人，就是他在辛格家楼梯上碰见过的那个人。在硬挺的白色枕头的映衬下，这个人的脸非常黑，一双黑眼睛里燃烧着憎恨，厚重的嘴唇发青，却很镇静。他的脸一动不动，像个黑色面罩，只有每次呼吸时，鼻孔才缓慢地翕动着，张得很大。

“出去。”黑人说道。

“等等——”杰克无助地说，“你为什么这么说话？”

“这是我家。”

杰克无法将视线从黑人可怕的脸上挪开。“但是，为什么？”

“你是个白人，而且是个陌生人。”

杰克没有离开。他笨拙而又小心地走到一张白色直背椅子跟前，坐了下来。黑人的手在床单上动着，黑色眼睛里闪着狂热的光。杰克注视着他，两人都在等待着。房间里有一种感觉，像阴谋一样紧张，又像大爆炸之前的死寂一般。

时间早已过了午夜。春日凌晨那种温暖、黑暗的空气搅动着屋子里一层层的蓝色烟雾。地上有一个个纸团，还有半瓶杜松子酒。烟灰散落在床单上，灰乎乎的一片。科普兰医生把头紧紧靠在枕头上，他已经脱掉了晨衣，棉布睡衣的袖子卷到胳膊肘上。杰克在椅子上向前倾着身子，领带已经松了，衬衫的领子被汗水浸得发软。在过去的几个小时里，他们两人之间进行了一场漫长的谈话，令人筋疲力尽，现在谈话停顿了一会儿。

“那么，是时候——”杰克开口了。

但科普兰医生打断了他。“现在，也许我们必须——”他声音沙哑地低声说道。他们住了口，望着对方的眼睛，等待着。“抱歉。”科普兰医生说。

“对不起，”杰克说，“您继续。”

“不，您继续。”

“嗯——”杰克说，“不说刚才的话题了。关于南方，我们再说几句吧。被扼杀的南方，被荒废的南方，被奴役的南方。”

“还有黑人。”

为了让自己平静下来，杰克拿起脚边地上那个瓶子，喝了一大口烈酒。然后，他缓缓走到橱柜跟前，拿起一个廉价的小地球仪，这原本是做镇纸用的。他把地球仪拿在手里，慢慢转动着。“我能说的就是这个：这个世界充满了刻薄和邪恶。哈！这个地球上，四分之三的地方要么是战争，要么是压迫。骗子和恶魔联合起来，那些知道的人都被孤立了，毫无防御能力。但是！但是，如果让我指出这个地球表面最野蛮的地方，我会指这里——”

“看仔细，”科普兰医生说，“你指到海上去了。”

杰克又转了一下地球仪，把笨拙、肮脏的大拇指小心翼翼地按在选好的那个地方。“这里，这十三个州。我知道自己在说什么。我看过书，也去过很多地方。这十三个该死的州，每个州我都去过，在每个州都工作过。我之所以有这样的想法，是因为：我们生活在世界上最富有的国家，物产丰富，却不肯分给那些一无所有的男人、女人和孩子。而且我们的国家本来建立在一个伟大真实的原则之上——自由、平等，每个人都有权利。哈！但结果如何呢？有些公司价值几十亿元——而成千上万的人却没有饭吃。在这十三个州，对人类的盘剥如此厉害——这样的事情，你必须要亲眼看到才能明白。我这一辈子看到的东西足以让人发疯。至少有三分之一的南方人活得连任何一个欧洲法西斯国家里最底层的农民都不如。农场里的佃农平均一年的工资只有七十五块钱。注意，这是平均工资！佃农们的工资从每人三十五块到九十块不等。一年三十五块钱，意味着干整整一天只能拿到一毛钱。到处都有陪拉格病、钩虫病、贫血症，还有赤裸裸的饥饿。但是！”杰克用脏手的指关节搓着嘴唇，额头上沁出汗珠。“但是！”他重复道，“这些只是可以看得见、摸得着的邪恶，还有一些事情更糟糕。我说的是，人们被蒙蔽了，看不见真相。他们听到的那些话，只是为了不让他们看到真相，都是恶毒的谎言，所以他们没有知道的机会。”

“还有黑人，”科普兰医生说，“要想了解我们身上发生的事情，你必须——”

杰克野蛮地打断他。“谁是南方的主宰？北方的工厂拥有四分之三的南方。他们说，这头年老的奶牛到处吃草——在南部、西部、北部和东部，但只在一个地方挤奶。她的老奶头胀满的时候，只在一个地方晃荡。她到处吃草，却只在纽约挤奶。比如说，我们的棉纺厂、纸浆厂、挽具厂和床垫厂，都是北方人的。然后呢？”杰克的胡子愤怒地抖动着，“这里有个例子。地点就是按照伟大的美国工业的父权体系建起来的工厂村，遥领制。村子里有一个庞大的砖厂，也许便会有四五百个小棚屋，那些房子根本不适合人类居住，而且这些房子一开始便是按贫民窟建的。这些棚屋往往只有两三个房间，加一个厕所——建这些房子比建关牲口的棚子还要仓促，比建猪圈还要随意。因为在这样的体制之下，猪比人值钱。工厂里那些骨瘦如柴的小孩子，你是没法拿他们去做猪排和香肠的，现在有一半的人也不能再买卖了，但是猪——”

“打住！”科普兰医生说，“你跑题了，而且你也没有关注黑人这个特殊的问题。我在旁边一句话都插不上。我们以前谈论过这个问题，但如果不把黑人包括进来，便不可能明白全部的局势。”

“回到我们的工厂村。”杰克说，“一个年轻人这个时候如果能找到工作的话，每星期可以挣八到十块钱，还不错。他要结婚，生完第一个孩子，妻子也必须要到工厂干活儿。他们两人的工资加起来，每星期能挣到十八块钱。哈！他们拿出四分之一付工厂租给他们的棚屋钱，然后到公司开办或主管的商店购买食品和衣物，而商店里每一样东西都非常贵。如果生上三四个孩子，他们就被套住了，跟戴了枷锁差不多。这就是农奴制的全部原理。然而，在这里，在美国，我们声称自己是自由的。好笑的是，这种观念深深根植在佃农、年轻人，还有其他所有人的脑子里，他们都信以为真。但是为了阻止他们知道，别人不知道用了多少谎言。”

“只有一条出路——”科普兰医生说。

“两条出路，只有两条出路。曾经有一段时间，这个国家大肆扩张，每个人都觉得自己有机会。哈！但那段时期已经过去了——永远过去了。不到一百家公司几乎吞并了一切，剩下的寥寥无几。这些公司已经吸干了人们的血汗，榨干了人们的骨头。曾经扩张的日子已经结束了。整个资本主义民主体系——烂透了，腐败了。未来只有两条出路。第一：法西斯主义；第二：改革，最革命和最持久的那种改革。”

“还有黑人。别忘了黑人。就我和我们的同胞而言，南方现在实行的就是法西斯主义，一直都是。”

“是的。”

“纳粹分子剥夺了犹太人的法律、经济和文化生活。在这里，黑人同样被剥夺了这些东西。如果说这里没像德国一样发生钱财和物品的大规模、戏剧性掠夺的话，只是因为一开始黑人便没有机会拥有财富。”

“这就是体制。”杰克说。

“犹太人和黑人，”科普兰医生痛苦地说，“我们黑人的历史与犹太人不堪的历史旗鼓相当——只会更血腥、更暴力，就像一种特别的海鸥。如果你抓住其中一只，在它腿上缠上一根红线，其他海鸥就会把它啄死。”

科普兰医生摘下眼镜，重新用金属线绑了一下坏掉的折合处，然后用睡衣擦擦镜片。他的手因为焦虑不安而颤抖着。“辛格先生便是犹太人。”

“不是，这点你错了。”

“但我肯定他是，辛格这个名字就是。我第一眼见到他，就看出了他的种族。从他眼睛里可以看出来，而且他也是这么跟我说的。”

“啊，他不可能是。”杰克坚持道，“依我看，他是纯种盎格鲁-撒克逊人，爱尔兰-盎格鲁-撒克逊人。”

“但是——”

“我肯定，绝对是。”

“好吧，”科普兰医生说，“我们别争了。”

外面，漆黑的空气很凉，屋子里都有了一股寒气。黎明马上就要来了。凌晨的天空是一种深邃的丝绸般的蓝色。月亮从银色变成了白色。一切都寂静无声。唯一的声音，是一只春天的小鸟在外面的夜色中歌唱，声音清越而孤独。尽管窗户里吹进一丝微风，但屋里的空气仍然发酸和凝重的，有一种令人既紧张又疲惫的感觉。科普兰医生从枕头上向前微微倾着身子，双眼充血，两只手抓着床单，睡衣的衣领滑到了瘦骨嶙峋的肩膀之下。杰克的脚跟在他坐的椅子横档上保持着平衡，两只大手叠在一起，夹在两膝之间，像个孩子似的等待着。他的眼底下有深黑色的眼圈，头发蓬乱。他们彼此望着，等待着。沉默的时间越长，两人之间的那种紧张感便越是一触即发。

终于，科普兰医生清清嗓子，说道：“我肯定，你无事不登门。我也肯定，我们彻夜讨论这些话题是有目的的。我们现在已经讨论了所有的事情，但最重要的一个话题还没有讨论——出路。必须要做些什么。”

他们仍旧彼此对视着，等待着，每个人的脸上都有期待。科普兰医生靠在枕头上，坐得笔直。杰克则用一只手托着下巴，前倾着身体。继续沉默。然后，他们又迟疑着同时开口说话了。

“抱歉，”杰克说，“您继续。”

“不，您，您先说的。”

“继续。”

“咳！”科普兰医生说，“您继续。”

杰克盯着他，眼神蒙眬而神秘。“是这样，我是这样看的。唯一的解决办法，就是让人们知道。他们一旦知道了真相，便不会再受压迫了。只要有一半人知道，这场战争就打赢了。”

“对，他们一旦了解了这个社会的运行机制就好了，但你觉得应该怎么告诉他们呢？”

“听着，”杰克说，“考虑下连环信。如果一个人给十个人发一封信，然后这十个人再分别给十个人发一封信——你明白了吗？”他结结巴巴地说，“不是说我要写信，但想法是一样的，我会到处宣讲。如果在一个镇上，我可以给十个不知道的人讲明真相，那么我就觉得已经产生了一些作用。明白了吗？”

科普兰医生望着杰克，很吃惊。然后，他哼了一声。“别幼稚了！你不能只是四处宣讲。还什么连环信！知道的人和不知道的人！”

杰克的嘴唇哆嗦着，皱着眉头，火冒三丈。“好吧，你有什么好点子？”

“要我说，首先在这个问题上，我以前跟你的感觉一样，但我已经明白这种态度是个很大的错误。半个世纪以来，我一直觉得忍耐是很明智的做法。”

“我没说要忍耐。”

“面对暴行，我很谨慎。面对不公正，我保持平和。我牺牲掉拥有的东西，去换取假想中的整体利益。我相信舌头的力量，而不是拳头的力量。我教给人们要在心里有忍耐和信念，以此作为抵御压迫的铠甲。现在，我知道自己以前是大错特错了。我做了自己和同胞们的叛徒。一切都烂透了。现在，到了行动的时候了，要立刻行动。以牙还牙，以眼还眼。”

“但怎么做呢？”杰克问，“怎么做？”

“哎呀，出去，行动起来，呼吁人民大众团结起来，让他们去游行。”

“哈！最后一句话泄露了你的秘密——‘让他们去游行。’如果对于一件事情他们根本不知道，让他们为此去游行又有什么用处呢？你这简直就是妄想从屁眼里给猪喂东西啊。”

“语言如此粗俗，让我生气。”科普兰医生大惊失色。

“看在上帝的分上！我不在乎这话是不是让你生气。”

科普兰医生举起一只手。“我们不要过于激动，”他说，“尽量谋求一致。”

“这正合我意，我不想跟你吵架。”

他们沉默了。科普兰医生的眼睛从天花板的一角挪到另一角。好几次，他润润嘴唇想说话，但每次话到嘴边又咽了下去。终于，他说道：“我给你的建议是这样的：不要试图孤军作战。”

“但是——”

“但是，没有但是。”科普兰医生一副不容争辩的口吻，“一个人所做的最致命的事情，就是试图孤军作战。”

“我明白你的意思。”

科普兰医生把睡衣领子从瘦骨嶙峋的肩膀下拽上来，紧紧拢在喉咙上。“你认可我的同胞为了人权而进行的抗争吗？”

医生的焦躁不安，还有他温和而沙哑的问题让杰克突然间热泪盈眶。一种突如其来的强烈的爱意让他一把抓住床单上那只骨瘦如柴的黑手，紧紧握着。“当然。”他说道。

“我们极度的贫困？”

“是的。”

“缺乏正义？严重的不平等？”

科普兰医生咳嗽起来，从枕头底下掏出方形纸巾，把痰吐在里面。“我有个计划，一个非常简单明确的计划。我只想集中考虑一个目标。今年八月份，我计划带领这个地方的一千多名黑人去游行，游行到华盛顿。我们所有人万众一心。你看看那边的橱柜，会看见一摞信件，是我这个星期刚写的，我会亲自发送出去。”科普兰医生的两只手在小床的床沿上紧张地来回滑动着，“你记得我刚刚跟你说过的话吗？你一定能想起来，我给你的唯一建议是：不要试图孤军作战。”

“我明白。”杰克说。

“但你一旦参与其中，必须要全情投入，这是最最重要的。你要从一而终地干下去，必须毫无保留地奉献自己的全部，不求个人回报，永不停歇，也不祈望停歇。”

“为了南方黑人的权利。”

“在南方，在这个县，要么全情投入，要么一无所有。要么是，要么不是。”

科普兰医生向后靠在枕头上，似乎只有眼睛还是活的。两只眼睛在他的面孔上像烧得通红的煤块，这种狂热让他的两颊呈现一种可怕的紫色。杰克皱起眉头，把指关节塞进柔软、宽大、颤抖的嘴巴里，脸上飞起一片红色。窗外，第一缕苍白的晨曦照了进来。黎明中，悬在天花板上的那盏电灯泡发出难看刺目的光。

杰克站起来，僵直地站在床尾。他直截了当地说：“不，这不是正确的角度，我敢百分之百肯定，这不是。首先，你们永远出不了镇子，他们会说这是危害公共安全，从而把你们解散——或者随便编个类似的理由。他们会把你们抓起来，然后不了了之。即便发生了奇迹，你们到了华盛顿，也没有任何用处。哎，整个想法都很疯狂。”

科普兰医生喉咙里发出清晰的痰的呼噜声，他的声音很严厉。“你嘲讽和批评起来倒是很迅速，那你有什么好法子？”

“我没有嘲讽。”杰克说，“我只是说，你的计划很疯狂。我今晚来到这里，有个想法比这个好得多。我想让你的儿子威廉，还有其他两个男孩，允许我用车子推着他们到处转转，他们可以说说发生的事情，之后我再解释为什么会这样。换句话说，我要讲讲资本主义的辩证法——揭露它所有的谎言。我会解释这些东西，让大家都明白为什么这些孩子的腿会被锯掉，并且让每个目睹的人都理解。”

“啐！啐啐！”科普兰医生愤怒地说，“我觉得你的脑子不正常。如果我还能大笑的话，我肯定会因此大笑起来。我以前从来没机会亲耳听到这样的胡言乱语。”

他们盯着彼此，心里充满痛苦的失望，还有愤怒。外面街上传来手推车的嘎吱声。杰克咽了口唾沫，咬住嘴唇，终于说道：“哈！你是唯一发疯的那个人。你让一切都倒退了。在资本主义体制下，解决黑人问题的唯一办法，就是把所有州里一千五百万黑人都阉割掉。”

“你那套关于正义的夸夸其谈背后，原来藏的就是这番高见。”

“我可没说应该这么做，我只是说你一叶障目不见森林。”杰克说得很慢，小心翼翼，很痛苦，“这个事情必须从根本做起，摧毁旧传统，然后建立新传统，打造一种新的世界模式。首先让人成为社会动物，生活在一个有序和自制的社会中，不必为了生存而被迫牺牲公正。一种社会传统，其中——”

科普兰医生讽刺地拍着手。“很好，”他说，“但织布以前必须得先摘棉花才行。你和你古怪的无为理论能——”

“嘘！你跟你那一千个黑人是否能游荡到那个叫华盛顿的臭水坑，谁会在乎呢？这又有什么分别？几个人能有什么重要性——了了千把人，不管是白人还是黑人，好人还是坏人？我们的整个社会都是建立在险恶谎言的基础之上。”

“一切！”科普兰医生喘息着，“一切！一切！”

“什么都不是！”

“这个地球上，在正义的眼中，我们当中最刻薄、最邪恶的灵魂也值得更——”

“哦，见鬼去吧！”杰克说，“胡说八道！”

“亵渎者！”科普兰医生尖叫起来，“肮脏的亵渎者！”杰克摇晃着床上的铁栏杆，额头上青筋暴突，几乎要爆炸了，他脸色阴郁，充满愤怒。“目光短浅，冥顽不化！”

“白——”科普兰医生的嗓子发不出声来，他挣扎着，却没有任何声音发出来。最后，他得以吐出一个哽咽的低语：“魔鬼。”

窗外迎来了亮黄色的清晨。科普兰医生的头向后垂到枕头上，脖子扭着，像断了似的，嘴唇上沾着一点血沫。杰克又看了他一眼，猛烈抽泣着，一头冲出了房间。

14

现在，她无法待在“里屋”了，必须得一直待在别人身边才行，每时每刻都要做点事情。如果是一个人待着，她便数数，或者算数。她数过起居室墙纸上有多少玫瑰花，算过整幢房子的面积有多少立方米，数过后院有多少片草叶，还数过某棵灌木上到底有多少片叶子。她如果不用这些数字来占据自己的脑子，那种可怕的恐惧感便会袭上来。五月份的午后，她走在放学回家的路上，突然间便会觉得必须要考虑点什么紧急的事情才好，想的往往是件好事——很好的事情。也许她会想起一段急促的爵士乐，或者想起回家时会在冰箱里看见一碗果冻，或者计划藏到煤屋后面抽支烟。也许她会想到很久以后的事情，比如她去了北方，看到了雪，或者甚至到国外的什么地方去旅行。但关于这些好事情的思绪并不能持久。不到五分钟，果冻就不见了，香烟也抽完了。在那之后，又有什么呢？那些数字也会在她脑子里混为一谈，雪和外国则是很久很久以后的事情。那么，还剩下什么？

只剩下辛格先生。她想跟着他随便去哪里。早晨，她望着他走下门前台阶去上班，然后她会跟着他走半个街区。每天下午只要一放学，她便到他工作的那个商店附近，在街角徘徊。四点钟，他出来喝可口可乐。她望着他穿过街道，走进杂货店，最后又出来。她尾随着他下班回家，有时候甚至他出来散步，她也会跟在后面。她总是远远地跟在后面，他并不知情。

她会上楼，到房间里去看他。最初，她总是仔细擦洗脸颊和双手，在裙子前面洒上香草味的香水。现在她每周只去看他两次，因为不想让他厌烦。每次她推门进去时，他几乎都是坐在那个既奇怪又好看的棋盘前面。然后，她就那么跟他坐在一起。

“辛格先生，你有没有去过一个冬天会下雪的地方啊？”

他把椅子向后斜靠在墙上，点点头。

“不是这个国家——外国的地方？”

他又点点头，表示肯定，然后用银色铅笔在便笺本上写字。他曾经去过加拿大的安大略湖——从底特律过河。加拿大非常靠北，白皑皑的雪会飘落到房顶，五大湖和圣劳伦斯河就在那个地方。那边的人在街上跑来跑去，说的都是法语。再往北去，有幽深的森林，还有白色的冰屋，北极地区有很美的北极光。

“你在加拿大的时候，是不是会出来找新鲜的雪然后掺着奶油和糖一起吃啊？有一次，我看到书上说，那么吃味道非常美。”

他把头转到一边，因为他听不懂。她也没法再问一遍这个问题，因为突然之间，这样的问题听上去很傻。她只是望着他，等待着。他的头在身后的墙上投下一个很大的黑影。电风扇冷却着厚重闷热的空气，一切都寂静无声。他们好像在等着要向对方倾诉一些从来没有说过的话似的。她要说的话很可怕，令人恐惧，但他要跟她说的话却都那么真实，会理顺一切事情。也许这样的事情根本无法用词汇说出来，或者写出来，也许他会用另外一种方式让她明白这件事。这就是他给她的感觉。

“我问的只是加拿大的事情——但并不重要，辛格先生。”

楼下，家里各个房间里都麻烦不断。埃特依然病得厉害，三个人挤在一张床上，她根本无法入睡。百叶窗拉了下来，黑乎乎的屋子里弥漫着一股难闻的病人的味道。埃特的工作丢了，这意味着除了需要支付医生的账单之外，家里每个星期还少了八块钱的收入。有一天，拉尔夫在厨房里走动时被滚烫的炉子烧伤了，绷带让他的手很痒，必须有人一刻不离地看着他，不然他就会抓破水泡。乔治生日那天，他们给他买了一辆红色的小自行车，车把上有铃铛，还有车筐。为买这辆自行车，大家都凑了钱。但埃特丢了工作，他们付不起钱了，有两次未能按时分期付款，商店便派了个人过来，推走了自行车。乔治眼睁睁望着那个人把自行车推出门廊，经过他身边时乔治踢了一脚后面的挡泥板，然后走进煤屋，关上了门。

钱，钱，总是钱。他们欠杂货店的钱，有些家具的尾款也欠着。现在他们失去了房子，便又欠着房租了。房子里的六个房间一直都有房客，但没人能够按时付房租。

有一阵子，他们的爸爸天天出去找工作。他没法再干木工活儿了，因为再到离地超过十英尺的地方干活儿让他紧张不安。他申请了很多份工作，却没人肯雇他。最后，他产生了这样的想法。

“是广告，米克。”他说，“我得出结论，现在我的修表生意最重要的就是广告。我得自己推销自己，我得出去让人们知道我会修表，修得又好又便宜。你尽管记住我的话。我要把这个生意做起来，这样，余生我就可以让家人生活得好一些。只有通过广告才行。”

他带回家一打铁皮，还有一些红色油漆。接下来的一星期他很忙。在他看来，这是个绝佳的主意。那些招牌摆满了前屋的地面。他跪在地上，小心翼翼地涂着每一个字母。他一边干活儿，一边吹着口哨晃着脑袋。好几个月以来，他从来没有如此开心过。隔一阵子，他就要穿上那身好西装，拐过街角，去喝杯啤酒平静下心情。一开始，他在牌子上写道：

威尔伯·凯利

修表

经济　专业

“米克，我想让这几个词一下子抓人眼球，不管在哪里看到都能很醒目。”

她给他帮忙，然后他给了她三个五分硬币。起初，这些招牌还不错，然后他继续加工，结果过了头反而适得其反了。他一再想添加更多内容——边角处加字，在上面和下面也加字。还没等他做完，牌子上已经涂满了类似的话：“非常经济”“立刻光临”“随便给我一块表，我都能让它跑起来”。

“你想在牌子上写的东西太多了，那样反而没人能看到任何东西了。”她告诉他。

他又带回家一些铁皮，把设计的活儿交给了她。她涂写的内容很简单，用很大的大写印刷体字母写的，又画了一个钟表。很快，他就有了一沓招牌。他认识的一个伙计开车把他拉到乡下，他把牌子钉到树上和篱笆桩上。在他家街区的两端，他各竖起一块牌子，上面有一只黑色的手指向他家的方向，在房子的前门上也有一块牌子。

做完这些广告的第二天，他在前屋等待着，穿着干净的衬衫，打着领带。没有什么动静。有个钟表商经常把做不完的活儿以半价给他，这次送来了几块钟表。仅此而已。他觉得难以接受这个现实。他不再出去找别的活儿，但每一分钟都在家里里外外地忙活着。他把门都一一摘下来，给铰链上了油——不管需不需要。他替波西娅搅拌人造奶油，擦洗楼上的地板。他鼓捣出一个小装置，让冰箱里的水直接从厨房窗子里排走。他给拉尔夫刻了一些非常漂亮的字母积木，还发明了一种小小的穿针器。在手头要修的那几块表上，他花费了巨大的心思。

米克仍然跟着辛格先生，但她并不想这么做。在他不知情的情况下跟着他，似乎有些不太好。有两三天，她逃了学。他去上班时，她跟在他身后，然后一整天都在商店附近的街角徘徊。他去布兰农先生的咖啡馆吃饭，她也走进去花五分钱买一袋花生。到了晚上，她则会跟在他身后，一起在黑乎乎的街道上长久地散步。她会走在街道的另一侧，离他整整一个街区远。他停住的时候，她也停住——他快步走的时候，她便一路小跑跟上他。只要能看见他，靠近他，她便是幸福的。但有时候她会有种奇怪的感觉，她知道自己的做法不对。因此，她拼命让自己在家里不得空闲。

她和爸爸现在在这方面如出一辙，必须要一直摆弄点什么东西才行。她了解家里和邻里所发生的一切。斯波尔瑞巴斯的大姐姐在电影院的一个活动中抽中了五十块钱。巴比·威尔逊头上的绷带现在已经拆掉了，但头发剪得很短，像个男孩。今年她不能到晚会上跳舞了，她妈妈带她去看晚会，巴比在一支舞曲中间大喊大叫，乱闹一通，他们不得不把她从剧院里拽了出来。到了人行道上，威尔逊太太为了让她规矩点，还动手打了她，威尔逊太太也哭了。乔治痛恨巴比，她从家门前路过时，他总要捂住鼻子，塞住耳朵。皮特·韦尔斯离家出走了，走了三个星期，回来的时候光着脚，饥肠辘辘。他还吹牛说自己如何一路走到了新奥尔良。

因为埃特，米克仍然睡在起居室。那张短沙发实在太挤了，她不得不在学校的自修室补觉。每隔一天晚上，比尔会跟她换一下，她跟乔治一起睡。后来，他们有了幸运的转机。住在楼上的一个家伙搬走了。一个星期过去了，没人回应报纸上的广告。这时他们的妈妈告诉比尔，他可以搬到楼上的空房间去住。有了自己独立的地方，可以远离家人，这让比尔非常高兴。她搬去跟乔治一起住，乔治睡觉的时候像只温暖的小猫，呼吸非常轻。

她又熟悉了那种夜晚的时光，但跟去年夏天不一样了。那时候她独自走在夜色里，听着音乐，做着计划。现在，她换了一种方式来认识夜晚。她躺在床上难以入睡，心里涌上一股怪异的恐惧感，感觉天花板就像正在慢慢朝她的脸压下来似的。如果房子倒了，会是什么样子？他们的爸爸有一次说过，整个这片地区都应该被宣告为危房。他是说，也许哪天夜里他们睡着的时候，墙壁会裂开，房子会倒塌吗？把他们都埋在灰浆、碎玻璃和破家具之下？让他们无法动弹，也无法呼吸？她清醒地躺在那里，肌肉僵硬。夜晚，有吱吱嘎嘎的声音响起。是有人在走路吗？——除她之外，还有人没睡——是辛格先生吗？

她从来没有想过哈里。她已经下定决心要忘掉他，她的确做到了。他写信来，说在伯明翰的一家汽修厂找了份工作。她按照两人计划好的，回了一张卡片，写上“好”。他每周给他妈妈寄来三块钱。他们一起去森林里，似乎已经是很久很久以前的事情了。

白天，她在“外屋”忙碌着，但到了晚上，她独自一人躺在黑暗中，数数已经远远不够。她需要某个人。她努力不让乔治睡觉。“不睡觉，在黑夜里聊天，真的很有意思。我们一起聊会儿吧。”

他迷迷糊糊地答应着。

“瞧窗外的星星。真的很难想到，每一颗小星星都是一颗像地球那么大的行星。”

“他们是怎么知道的？”

“他们就是知道。他们有办法测量，这是科学。”

“我不信。”

她试图怂恿他，让他跟自己争论，这样他就会兴奋，就不会困了。而他则随她怎么说，并不在意。过了一会儿，他说：

“看，米克！你看见那根树枝了吗？像不像一个清教徒祖先躺在地上，手里拿着枪？”

“真的很像，的确很像。看看那边书桌上，那个瓶子像不像个很滑稽的人，还戴着帽子？”

“不像，”乔治说，“我觉得一点都不像。”

她拿起地上的水杯，喝了一口。“我们俩玩个游戏吧——名字游戏。愿意的话，可以你说我猜，怎么样都行，随你选。”

他的两只小拳头放在脸上，平静均匀地呼吸着，他马上就要睡着了。

“等等，乔治！”她说，“这很有意思。我是一个人，名字是M打头的，猜猜我是谁。”

乔治叹了口气，声音很疲惫。“你是哈勃·马克思吗？”

“不是，我根本没有在电影里出现过。”

“我不知道。”

“你肯定知道。我的名字首字母是M，我住在意大利，你应该能猜出来。”

乔治翻了个身，侧躺着，蜷缩成球状。他没有应声。

“我的名字以M开头，但有时候，人们也叫我以D[21]开头的那个名字，住在意大利，你猜猜。”

房间里很安静，漆黑一片，乔治睡着了。她又掐他，又扭他的耳朵，他呻吟着，却没醒。她靠近他，把脸紧紧贴在他裸露的热乎乎的小肩膀上。一整夜他都在安睡，而她则在数数。

辛格先生也在楼上房间里醒着吗？天花板的吱嘎声，是他在小心翼翼地走来走去喝冰橘子汁、研究桌上摆开的棋子吗？他曾经感觉到过这样的恐惧吗？不会。他从来没有做过错事。他从来没有犯过错，夜里他的心是平静的。但他还是会理解的。

要是她能把这些跟他说说，那就好多了。她想着该如何开口跟他说。辛格先生——我认识的这个女孩，跟我年龄一般大——辛格先生，不知道你能否理解这样的事情——辛格先生。辛格先生。她一遍遍地说着他的名字。她爱他胜过爱家里所有的人，甚至胜过爱乔治、爱爸爸。这是一种不一样的爱，跟以前在生命中体验到的任何东西都不一样。

早晨，她和乔治一起穿衣服、聊天。有时候，她特别想亲近乔治。他已经长高了，小脸尖尖的，脸色苍白，柔软的淡红色头发参差不齐地垂在小耳朵上面，一双锐利的眼睛一直眯着，让脸上总带着一种紧张的表情。他的恒牙已经长了出来，却是青色的，跟乳牙一样稀稀拉拉。他的下巴经常歪着，因为他有个习惯，总用舌头去舔那颗疼痛的新牙。

“听着，乔治，”她说，“你爱我吗？”

“当然了，我爱你。”

期末最后一周，这天早晨天气炎热，阳光灿烂。乔治穿好了衣服，趴在地上做算术题。他的小脏手紧紧捏着铅笔，总是把铅笔头别断。等他做完，她抓着肩膀把他拽起来，紧紧盯着他的脸。“我是说，很多爱，很多很多。”

“放开我，我当然爱你。你不是我姐姐吗？”

“我知道，但假如我不是你姐姐，那你还爱我吗？”

乔治后退一步。他没有干净的衬衫穿了，穿了件脏兮兮的套头毛衣。他的手腕很细，露着青色血管。毛衣袖子拽得很长，松松地垂下来，让他的手显得非常小。

“如果你不是我姐姐，我也许都不认识你，所以不能爱你。”

“如果你认识我，而我又不是你姐姐。”

“但你怎么知道我认识你？你没法证明。”

“嗯，就当是这样，假装。”

“我觉得还会喜欢你，但我还是要说，你没法证明——”

“证明！你脑子里只有这个词。证明和花招。什么事情要么是个花招，要么需要证明。我真受不了你，乔治·凯利，我恨你。”

“好吧，那我也不喜欢你了。”

他爬到床底下找什么东西。

“你到那底下找什么？你最好别动我的东西。如果让我抓住你乱动我的私密盒子，我就在那面墙上把你的脑袋撞破，我说到做到。我还会把你的脑浆踩出来。”

乔治从床底下爬出来，拿着他的拼写本。他的小脏手伸进床垫的一个洞里，他在那里面藏了弹珠。什么事都吓不住这个孩子。他不急不忙，挑出三颗棕色玛瑙纹弹珠带在身上。“啊，没什么，米克。”他答道。乔治太小了，太难管教，爱他没有任何意义，他懂的事情还没有她懂的多。

学校放假了，她通过了所有功课的考试——有些得了A+，有些勉强过关。日子漫长，天气炎热。终于，她又可以埋头研究音乐了。她开始写小提琴和钢琴的曲子，也写歌曲，她的脑子里总是装着音乐。她听着辛格先生的收音机，在房子周围闲逛，一边思考着听过的那些节目。

“米克哪里不舒服啊？”波西娅问，“她的舌头让什么猫叼走了？她四处乱转，一句话不说。她甚至不像以前那么狼吞虎咽了，这些天她变得越来越淑女了。”

她好像在用什么方式等待着——但在等什么，她自己也不清楚。骄阳似火，明晃晃地照在大街上，很热。白天，她要么埋头研究音乐，要么跟小孩子们混在一起。她在等待着。有时候她快速扫视一下四周，心头涌上那种恐慌感。六月底突然发生了一件重要的事情，改变了一切。

那天晚上，他们都来到外面门廊。暮色朦胧，柔和。晚饭快好了，卷心菜的味道从敞开的门厅传了出来。他们都在这里，唯独缺黑兹尔和埃特。黑兹尔还没下班，而埃特依然病怏怏地躺在床上。他们的爸爸靠坐在一张椅子上，两只脚穿着袜子搭在栏杆上，比尔和孩子们在台阶上，他们的妈妈坐在秋千上，用报纸扇着风。街道对面，附近新来的一个女孩穿着轮滑鞋在人行道上来回滑着。街区的路灯刚刚开始亮起来，远处有个男人在喊着谁的名字。

然后，黑兹尔回家了。她踩着高跟鞋“噔噔”地上了台阶，懒洋洋地向后靠在栏杆上。在半黑的暮色中，当摸着后脑勺编起来的头发时，她肥胖柔软的双手显得煞白。“我真希望埃特能去上班，”她说，“今天我听说了这样一份工作。”

“什么样的工作？”他们的爸爸问道，“我什么都能干，只能女孩干吗？”

“只能女孩干。伍尔沃斯店[22]的一个职员下周要结婚了。”

“那个廉价商品店——”米克说。

“你有兴趣？”

这个问题让她大吃一惊。她刚才一直在想前一天刚从那里买的那袋冬青糖。她感觉又热又紧张。她把刘海儿从额头撩了上去，数着刚出来的几颗星星。

他们的爸爸把香烟弹到人行道上。“不行，”他说，“我们不想让米克在这个年纪就承担太多责任，让她先长大吧。无论如何，让她先长大再说。”

“我同意，”黑兹尔说，“我的确觉得如果让米克固定地上班，那不合适，我觉得那样不好。”

比尔把拉尔夫从膝头放下来，在台阶上踱来踱去。“不到十六岁左右，谁也不应该去工作。米克还应该再过两年，完成职业学校的学业——如果我们应付得了的话。”

“即便我们必须得放弃这座房子，搬到工厂区去，”他们的妈妈说，“我也要让米克在家里再待一阵子。”

有一瞬间，她很害怕，担心他们会逼她接受这份工作，那样她就会说她要离家出走。但他们实际的态度感动了她，让她觉得很兴奋。他们都在谈论她——那么和善。她为自己起初的恐惧感到羞愧。突然，她很爱所有的家人，觉得喉咙一阵发紧。

“那份工作大约能拿多少钱？”她问道。

“十块钱。”

“一个星期十块钱？”

“当然了，”黑兹尔说，“你以为一个月只有十块钱？”

“波西娅都赚不了那么多钱。”

“哦，黑人——”黑兹尔说。

米克用一只拳头揉搓着头顶。“那是一大笔钱，很多。”

“不用咧嘴，”比尔说，“我也挣这么多。”

米克的舌头发干。她把舌头在嘴里转了转，沾些唾液好说话。“一个星期十块钱，大概可以买十五只炸鸡、五双鞋子，或者五条裙子，或者分期付款买一台收音机。”她想了想钢琴，但没有大声说出来。

“倒可以帮助我们渡过难关，”他们的妈妈说，“但话说回来，我还是宁愿让米克在家里再待一阵子。现在，埃特又——”

“等等！”她觉得燥热，有些不顾一切，“我想干这份工作，我能干得了，我知道我能。”

“听小米克说。”比尔说道。

他们的爸爸用火柴剔着牙，把脚从栏杆上放了下来。“这会儿，我们都不要急着做决定。我想让米克慢慢来，考虑清楚。她不用去上班我们也能想办法撑下去。我是说，我很快会把修表的活儿增加百分之六十——”

“我忘了，”黑兹尔说，“好像每年圣诞节还发奖金。”

米克皱起眉头。“但到那时候，我就不在那里工作了，我要上学，我只想趁假期上班，然后回学校上学。”

“当然了。”黑兹尔立即说道。

“但明天我跟你一块去，如果人家要我的话，我就干这份工作。”

全家人仿佛赢得了一次大胜利，紧张感悄然消失了。夜色中，他们笑着，聊着。他们的爸爸用火柴棒和手帕给乔治耍着把戏，然后又给了这个孩子五毛钱，让他到街角的店里买可口可乐，留待晚饭以后喝。门厅里的卷心菜味更浓了，锅里正在煎猪排。波西娅在喊他们，房客们已经就座了。米克到餐厅吃晚饭，她盘子里的卷心菜软不拉耷，颜色发黄，她吃不下。她伸手去拿面包，却把桌上的冰茶壶打翻了。

之后，她独自一人来到门廊里，等着辛格先生回家，她迫不及待想要见到他。前一刻的兴奋之情已经消退，她觉得心里很难受。她就要到廉价商品店工作了，而她并不想到那种地方上班，她好像是被诱骗着做了什么事情。这份工作不会只持续这个夏天——而是要干很长时间，长到她能预见到的未来。他们一旦习惯了这笔进账，再不干便不可能了。事情往往都是如此。她站在夜色中，紧紧抓着栏杆。过了很久，辛格先生却依然没有回来。十一点，她走到门外想看看是否能找到他，但突然之间黑夜让她觉得很害怕，她立即跑回家去。

早晨，她仔细地沐浴、着装。黑兹尔和埃特把衣服借给她穿，精心把她打扮得漂漂亮亮的。她穿着黑兹尔的绿色丝绸裙，戴着一顶绿色帽子，穿着长筒丝袜和高跟浅口皮鞋。她们给她抹了腮红、口红，还给她修了眉毛。等她们忙活完毕，米克看上去至少像十六岁。

现在要反悔为时已晚。她真的长大了，要自己挣饭吃。但她如果去找爸爸，告诉他自己的感受，他会让她再等一年的。即便现在，黑兹尔、埃特、比尔和他们的妈妈也都会说她不是必须要去。但她不能这样做，不能这样丢脸。她上楼去见辛格先生，一股脑儿地把这些话倒出来：

“听着——我相信自己可以得到这份工作。你觉得呢？你觉得这是个好主意吗？你觉得我现在可以辍学去工作吗？你觉得这样好吗？”

起初他不明就里，一双灰眼睛半闭着，站在那里，双手深深地插进口袋里。又是那种熟悉的感觉，好像他们在等着要向对方倾诉以前从来没说过的那些话。她现在要说的并不多，但他跟她说是对的才行——如果他说这份工作听上去不错，那么她就会感觉好多了。她又慢慢重复了一遍那些话，然后等待着。

“你觉得这样好吗？”

辛格先生想了想，然后点点头表示肯定。

她得到了这份工作。经理把她和黑兹尔带到后面的一间小办公室，跟她俩谈话。后来，她完全想不起来那个经理长的是什么模样，或者说过什么话了。她被录用了。从店里回来时，她给乔治买了一毛钱的巧克力，还有一小盒橡皮泥。六月五号她就要开始工作了。她在辛格先生工作的首饰店窗前站了很久，然后走到街角，徘徊着。

15

又到了辛格去看安东纳普勒斯的时间了。路程很长。尽管两人之间的距离还不到二百英里，但火车迂回地绕了很远，而且到了夜间会在一些小站停靠好几个小时。辛格总是下午离开小镇，在火车上过一夜，直到第二天清晨才到。像往常一样，他早早便准备妥当。这一次，他打算跟好友待上整整一个星期。他已经把衣服送去了洗衣店，楦好了帽子，大包小包也已经准备停当。他要带的礼物都用彩色薄纸包着——此外，还有一个豪华果篮，装饰着玻璃纸，还有一箱刚刚运来的草莓。早晨出发前，辛格打扫了房间。他在冰箱里发现了一点剩下的鹅肝，拿出来放到巷子里，给邻居家的猫吃。他在门上挂上以前挂过的那个牌子，说他要出差几天。准备这些东西的时候，他轻松自在地走来走去，双颊带着两抹生动的红晕，脸上是一副肃穆的表情。

终于，动身的时刻到了。他站在月台上，提着手提箱和各色礼物，望着火车沿轨道慢慢驶来。他在硬座车厢找了一个座位，把行李放到头顶的架子上。车厢里很挤，大多是母亲带着孩子。绿色毛绒座位有种脏乎乎的味道，车窗很脏，地上散落着最近往新婚夫妇身上扔的稻米。辛格诚挚地对同行乘客微笑着，然后靠坐在座位上。他闭上眼睛，睫毛在凹陷的双颊上形成黑色弯曲的两道缘饰。他的右手在口袋里紧张地挪动着。

有一阵子，他的思绪停留在回身后的小镇上。他看见了米克、科普兰医生、杰克·布朗特和比夫·布兰农，他们的面孔从黑暗中浮现在面前，挤作一团，让他觉得窒息。他想起布朗特和那个黑人之间的争吵。这次争吵的本质让他脑子里混乱无序，令人绝望——但有好几次，趁对方不在，他们两人都对对方进行过长篇大论的激烈指责。他轮番同意他们的观点，尽管并不知道他们到底想让他认可什么。还有米克——她脸上一副紧迫的表情，说了一大堆，他却根本听不懂。还有纽约咖啡馆的比夫·布兰农。布兰农下巴上黑乎乎一片，像铁一样，一双眼睛很警觉。还有大街上跟着他的那些陌生人，不知道为什么，他们总是强行拦下他，跟他说话。日用纺织品店的那个土耳其人，两只手几乎甩到了他的脸上，叽里呱啦说了一大堆，那些词的口型辛格以前从来没有见过。还有工厂的工头和那位老年黑人妇女，以及主街上的一个商人和那个把大兵拉到河边妓院的小乞丐。辛格不安地扭动着肩膀。火车晃动着，令人感到平稳、闲适。他的头慢慢垂到了肩膀上，有一阵子他睡了过去。

等他再次睁开眼睛的时候，小镇已经被远远地抛在了身后。小镇被遗忘了。脏乎乎的窗户外面是绚丽的仲夏乡村。太阳斜射下来，古铜色的阳光猛烈照着绿色的新棉花田。有大片的烟草田，植株壮硕，郁郁葱葱，像是一些巨大的丛林杂草。桃子园里，矮墩墩的树上挂满沉甸甸的果实。有绵延数英里的牧场，还有几十英里荒废的贫瘠土地，长满了生命力顽强的杂草。火车穿过深绿色的松林，地上铺满顺滑的褐色松针，原始的树木高耸入云。再往前走，到了离小镇很远的南边，便出现了柏树沼泽——盘根错节的树根蜿蜒着伸进半咸的水中，灰色杂乱的苔藓从树枝上一路蔓延下去。热带的水中花朵在阴冷潮湿之处怒放。之后，火车又驶进太阳照射下的开阔地，驶进靛蓝色的天空下。

辛格坐在那里，严肃而怯懦，完全扭过脸去望着窗外。大片土地一闪而过，还有那些强烈粗犷的色调，都令他眼花缭乱。万花筒般的景色，众多的生机和色彩，不知为什么都让他想起好友。他的思绪一直在安东纳普勒斯身上，与他重逢的喜悦几乎令他喘不上气来。他有些鼻塞，便微张着嘴巴迅速急促地喘息着。

安东纳普勒斯见到他一定会很高兴，他会喜欢这些新鲜的水果和礼物。现在他应该出院了，可以跟他出去看电影，然后再去他初次探望时吃晚饭的那个旅馆。辛格给安东纳普勒斯写过很多信，却都没有寄出去。他完全沉浸在对好友的思念之中。

上次见完好友之后的这半年时间，说长不长，说短不短。每一个清醒的时刻背后，总有他的好友。在心底跟安东纳普勒斯的这种交流慢慢成长、变化，仿佛他们已经血肉相连了一样。有时候他想到安东纳普勒斯，会有一种敬畏和自卑的感觉，有时候又会充满骄傲——但无一例外，都带着爱，这种爱不会被批评所阻碍，不会为意志所控制。夜晚做梦时，好友的面容总是浮现在他面前，他的脸硕大却温柔。醒着的时候，他在心里总觉得他俩是永远连在一起的。

夏日的夜晚姗姗来迟。太阳落到了远处参差不齐的树顶之下，天空泛起白色，暮色懒散而又柔和。一轮白色的满月升起来，地平线上低垂着一层紫色云彩。大地、树木和原色的乡村房屋，都慢慢笼上阴影。间或，空中会闪过一道温和的夏日闪电。辛格专注地望着这一切。终于，夜幕降临了，面前的玻璃上映出了他自己的面孔。

孩子们在通道里跌跌撞撞地来回跑动，手里端着纸杯子，水洒了一路。辛格的前面坐着一位老人，穿着工装，不时从可口可乐的瓶子里喝着威士忌。不喝的时候，他用一个纸团小心翼翼地塞住瓶口。右边，一个小女孩正用一根黏糊糊的红色棒棒糖梳着头发。闷罐似的车厢打开，一盘盘晚餐从餐车车厢送了进来。

辛格没吃晚餐。他靠在座位上，漫不经心地望着周围发生的一切。终于，车厢里安静了下来。孩子们躺在宽大的毛绒座位上睡着了，男人和女人们蜷缩着靠在枕头上，尽可能舒服地休息一会儿。辛格没有睡。他把脸紧贴在窗户玻璃上，使劲看着外面的夜色。夜色浓重，又像天鹅绒般柔软。有时候，沿途人家的窗户里，会映出一方月光或闪出一丝灯光。从月亮来看，他知道火车已经不再向南了，转了方向，正朝东方驶去。他内心的渴望如此急切，鼻塞得无法呼吸，两颊也变成绯红色。在漫漫长夜的旅程中，他大部分时间都坐在那里，脸紧贴在冰冷乌黑的车窗玻璃上。

火车晚点一个多小时，到站时正赶上清新明朗的夏日早晨。辛格立即赶到旅馆，那是个很好的旅馆，他已经提前预订好了。他打开各色包裹，把要带给安东纳普勒斯的礼物摆在床上。他从行李员给他的菜单上点了一份奢华早餐——烤青鱼、玉米粥、法式吐司和热黑咖啡。吃过早餐，他穿着内衣裤在电扇跟前休息了一会儿。到了中午，他开始穿衣服。他洗澡，刮胡子，摊开干净的亚麻衬衣，还有他最好的泡泡纱西装。三点，医院的探视时间到了。这天是周二，七月十八号。

到了精神病院，他先去病房找安东纳普勒斯，好友以前就是住在这里的。但到了房间门口，他一下子看到好友并不在里面。接着，他一路穿过走廊，找到上次被领去的那个办公室。他已经把问题写在了随身携带的卡片上。办公桌后面的人换了，现在是个年轻人，几乎就是个男孩，长着一张还没定型、不成熟的面孔，一头蓬乱的直发。辛格把卡片递给他，静静地站着，怀里抱着一大堆包裹，全身的重量都压在了脚跟上。

年轻人摇摇头，伏在桌上，在便笺本上潦草地写着什么。辛格看完他写的内容，两颊立时变得苍白。他久久地盯着这张纸条，两只眼睛斜视着，脑袋耷拉着。纸条上写着安东纳普勒斯已经死了。

回旅馆的路上，他小心保护着随身带的水果，免得挤烂。他把包裹带回房间，然后又溜达着回到楼下大厅。在一棵盆栽棕榈树后面，有个老虎机。他塞进一枚五分硬币，使劲去拉手柄，这才发现机器卡住了。就因为这件事，他大动肝火。他堵住店员，愤怒地演示着刚才发生的事情，脸色白得吓人，无法自控，眼泪顺着鼻梁流了下来。他奋力挥舞双手，甚至抬起穿着优雅鞋子的修长双脚，在毛绒地毯上使劲跺了一下。人家归还了他的硬币，但他仍旧不依不饶，坚持要立刻退房。他打好包，费尽力气才把箱子重新合上。除了带来的东西之外，他还带走了三条毛巾、两块肥皂、一支钢笔、一瓶墨水、一卷厕纸，还有一本《圣经》。他付了钱，走到火车站，寄存了行李。火车到晚上九点才开，他有整整一个下午无事可做。

这个镇子比他生活的镇子还要小。商业街纵横交叉，形成一个十字的形状。商店看起来都是土里土气的模样，一半橱窗里摆的都是挽具和饲料袋子。辛格垂头丧气地走在人行道上，觉得喉咙肿胀，他想咽口唾沫，却咽不下去。为了缓解这种窒息的感觉，他到一家杂货店买了杯饮料。他到理发店闲逛了一圈，又去廉价商店买了几样小东西。他并不抬头看人，脑袋朝一边耷拉着，像一只生病的动物。

下午就快过去的时候，辛格突然碰上了一件奇怪的事情。他一直沿着路边缓缓走着，毫无目的。天阴沉着，空气潮湿。辛格没有抬头，但经过镇上的台球室时，斜刺里却瞥见一样东西，让他不安。他走过台球室，然后在街道中间停了下来，然后又无精打采地折回去，站到台球室敞开的门前。里面有三个哑巴，正在一起用手语交谈。三人都没穿外套，戴着圆顶硬礼帽，系着鲜艳的领带，每人都用左手拿着一杯啤酒。他们之间有种兄弟般的相似性。

辛格走了进去。好一阵子，他费了很大力气才把手从口袋里抽出来，然后笨拙地比画了一个问候语。有人拍他的肩膀，给他点了一杯冰啤酒。他们围着他问他问题时，手指就像活塞一样频频伸出来。他跟他们说了自己的名字，说了生活的那个小镇的名字，之后想不出对于自己还能说些什么。他问他们是否认识斯皮罗斯·安东纳普勒斯，他们并不认识。辛格站在那里，两只手松松地垂着，头仍然歪向一边，目光都是斜的。他那么无精打采，那么冷淡，那三个戴圆顶硬礼帽的哑巴奇怪地看着他。过了一阵子，他们便自顾聊起天来。他们付完所有的啤酒钱，准备要离开，这时并没有邀请他一起走。

整整半天时间，辛格只是在街上闲逛，却依然差点误了火车。他自己也不清楚这是怎么回事，不清楚之前几个小时他是怎么度过的。就在火车离站前的两分钟，他才赶到车站，勉强来得及把行李拖上车，然后去找座位。他选择的车厢几乎是空的。等他坐定，便打开那箱草莓，很挑剔地挑选着。草莓的个头很大，核桃般大小，完全熟透了，颜色饱满的果实顶上带着绿叶，仿佛小巧的花束一样。辛格把一个草莓放进嘴里，尽管汁液里有一种丰富饱满的香甜，但已经隐隐透出腐烂的味道。他一直吃，最后味蕾都对这种味道麻木起来。然后他把箱子包好，又放回头顶的架子上。午夜，他拉下遮光帘，躺在座位上。他蜷缩成一个球，拉起大衣盖住脸和头。他就以这个姿势躺在那里，精神恍惚，半睡半醒，一直保持了大约十二个小时。到站的时候，列车员不得不过来推醒他。

辛格把行李留在车站中央的空地上。然后他走回店里，无精打采地转了一下头，算是对珠表商老板打了招呼。等他再出来时，口袋了多了一件很重的东西。他低着头，沿着街道漫无目的地走了一阵子，但太阳的直射和潮湿的闷热压迫着他。他回到自己的房间，双眼红肿，内心疼痛。休息了一阵子后，他喝了一杯冰咖啡，抽了一根烟。然后，他洗干净烟灰缸和玻璃杯，从口袋里掏出一把手枪，把一颗子弹射进了自己的胸口。

第三部分

1

一九三九年八月二十一日

清晨

“别催我。”科普兰医生说，“别管我。发发善心，让我在这里清静地坐一会儿。”

“父亲，不是我们催你，到时间了，该离开这里回家了。”

科普兰医生固执地摇晃着，灰色围巾紧紧绕在肩膀上。尽管早晨的空气温暖而清新，炉子里还是烧着一小块木头。厨房里什么家具都没有，只有他坐的这把椅子。其他房间也空了。大部分家具都已经搬到了波西娅家里，其余的则捆在外面的汽车上。一切就绪，唯独他自己的思想没有准备好。然而，他的脑子里没有开始，也没有结束；没有真理，也没有使命。他怎么能就这样离开呢？他抬起一只手，按住摇晃的头部，继续在吱吱嘎嘎的椅子里缓缓地摇晃着。

关着的那扇门后面，他听到了他们的声音：

“我尽力了。他坚持要坐在那里，等他好了，准备好再走。”

“巴迪和我已经包好了那些瓷盘子，还有——”

“我们要赶在露水干掉之前离开，”老人说，“不然，还没到家天就黑了。”

他们的声音安静下来。空荡荡的走廊里回荡着脚步声，听不到他们的声音了。他脚边的地板上放着一只杯子和碟子，他用炉子上的咖啡壶把杯子里倒满咖啡。他一边摇着，一边喝着咖啡，用蒸汽暖和着手指头。不能真的就这样结束。他的心里，还有其他的一些声音在无声地呐喊。耶稣的声音，约翰·布朗的声音。伟大的斯宾诺莎和卡尔·马克思的声音。还有那些曾经战斗过的人，曾经肩负使命的人，他们呐喊的声音。他的同胞们饱含悲痛的声音。还有逝者们的声音。哑巴辛格的声音，他是个正直、通情达理的白人。弱者的声音，强者的声音。他的同胞们发出的洪亮呐喊声一直在聚积，越来越响亮，越来越强大。强大的、真正的使命的声音。作为回应，那些话在他的双唇上颤抖着——那些“真的是人类所有悲哀根源”的话——他几乎要大声说出来：“万能的主啊！宇宙的终极力量！我做的都是些不该做的事情，而应该去做的事情我又没做到，所以真的不能就这么结束。”

他第一次住进这幢房子，是跟他爱着的她一起来的。黛西穿着新娘礼服，戴着白色蕾丝面纱。她的皮肤是漂亮的深蜜糖色，笑声甜美。夜晚，他把自己关进灯火通明的房间里，一个人学习。他努力认真思考，严格规束自己学习。但身边有了黛西，他便产生了一种强烈的欲望，即使学习也无法使其消散。因此，有时候他干脆顺从这种情感，然后再咬着嘴唇彻夜思考着那些书。后来有了汉密尔顿、卡尔·马克思、威廉和波西娅。全都失去了。一个也没有留下来。

还有马迪本、班尼·梅、本尼迪恩·马迪恩和马迪·科普兰，这些人都带着他的名字。还有他劝导过的那些人。然而，在这千千万万人当中，哪个才是他可以托付使命然后让自己安歇的人呢？

在他的一生中，他始终强烈地知道这种使命。他知道自己如此努力的原因，心底也非常笃定，因为他了解眼前的每一天。他背着箱子，走街串巷，跟他们聊所有的事情，耐心地给他们解释。到了晚上，他知道这一天是为完成使命而奋斗的一天，便会感觉很幸福。即便身边没有黛西、汉密尔顿、卡尔·马克思、威廉和波西娅，他也会独自坐在炉火旁，因为这个而高兴。他会喝杯萝卜叶汁，吃块玉米面包，心底生出一种深深的满足感，因为这一天过得非常美好。

这样满足的时刻有过千千万万个，但又有什么意义呢？在这么多年里，他实在想不出做过的事情中有哪样具有持久的价值。

过了一会儿，走廊的门开了，波西娅走了进来。“我觉得必须得像给孩子穿衣服一样给你穿好，”她说，“这是你的鞋和袜子，我帮你把拖鞋脱下来，穿上鞋袜。我们必须马上动身了。”

“你为什么要这么对我？”他愤愤不平地说。

“我现在怎么对你了？”

“你很清楚，我不想离开。你趁我状态不好不能做决定的时候，逼着我答应了。我希望待在一直待的地方，你明白。”

“你又来了！”波西娅生气地说，“你那么多牢骚，我都快受不了了。你不是生气，就是大惊小怪，我真为你感到羞愧。”

“哼！随你怎么说。你在我面前不过是只小虫子。我知道自己想要什么，谁也不能让我做不对的事情。”

波西娅脱掉他的拖鞋，打开一双卷着的干净黑色棉袜。“父亲，我们不要再吵了，我们都已经尽了最大努力。你跟外公、汉密尔顿和巴迪一起走，这是最好的计划。他们会好好照顾你，你会康复的。”

“不，我不走。”科普兰医生说，“我在这里也会康复的，我知道。”

“你觉得谁能为这幢房子付租金啊？你觉得我们怎么照顾你吃饭啊？在这里，你觉得谁能照顾你啊？”

“我一直都应付得了，以后也可以应付。”

“什么事你都要唱反调。”

“哼！你在我面前就是只小虫子，我不理睬你。”

“我在这里给你穿鞋袜，你却这么说我，真是太好了。”

“抱歉，原谅我，女儿。”

“你当然得抱歉，”她说，“我们俩当然都得抱歉，我们再也经不起争吵了。而且等我们把你在农场上安顿好，你立刻就会喜欢那里的。那儿的菜园是我见过最漂亮的，只是想想都让我流口水了，还有鸡、两头育种母猪和十八棵桃树。你会爱上那个地方的，真希望有机会去那儿的是我。”

“我也这么希望。”

“你为什么要这么难过呢？”

“我只是觉得自己失败了。”他说。

“你说失败了，是什么意思？”

“不知道。别管我，女儿。让我在这里静静地坐一会儿。”

“好吧，但我们必须马上动身。”

他要安静，他要静静地坐着，在椅子里摇着，直到心里恢复平静为止。他的头颤抖着，脊椎疼痛起来。

“我真的希望这样，”波西娅说，“我真的希望，等我死了，走了，为我伤心的人能赶上为辛格先生伤心的人那么多。我真的很想知道，我的葬礼是不是会跟他的一样让人伤心，有同样多的人——”

“嘘！”科普兰医生粗暴地说，“你的话太多了。”

然而，那个白人的死的确在他心里蒙上了一层阴郁的悲伤。他跟辛格交谈过，跟别的白人他从来没有这样交谈过，而且他信任他。他的自杀之谜令他困惑不已，感到孤立无助。这种悲哀，无头无尾，令人费解。他在脑海里总是想到这个白人。这个白人不张狂，不傲慢，公平待人。逝者如果仍然活在生者的心里，那他怎么能算真的逝去了呢？但是，他不能再想这些了。从现在开始，他要把这些统统抛开。

他现在需要的是约束。在过去的一个月中，那种阴郁可怕的感觉又出现了，折磨着他的精神。这里面有憎恨，连续多天让他陷入死亡一般的境地。跟那位午夜访客布朗特先生争吵过后，他心里一直有一团残暴的黑暗。但现在，他已经记不清当时是因为什么而引起的纷争。然后当他望着威利的残肢时，心头又涌上一股异样的愤怒。爱与恨不断冲突——爱他的同胞，恨压迫他同胞的人——这让他心力交瘁，精神萎靡。

“女儿，”他说，“给我拿手表和外套，我要走了。”

他扶着椅子扶手站起身来。地板似乎离他的脸非常遥远，卧床太久，他的两条腿非常虚弱。有一瞬间，他觉得自己要摔倒了。他头晕眼花地走过空荡荡的房间，然后倚在门框上，咳嗽起来。他从口袋里拿出一块方形纸巾，捂住嘴巴。

“给你大衣。”波西娅说，“但外面很热，不用穿。”

他最后一次走过空荡荡的房子。百叶窗紧闭，黑乎乎的屋子里有股尘土的味道。他靠在门厅的墙上歇一歇，随后走出门外。清晨天空晴朗，天气温暖。前一天晚上和今天一早，很多朋友都已经来道过别了——现在，门廊只有他们家自己人。外面街道上停着那辆骡车和汽车。

“喏，本尼迪克特·马迪，”老人说道，“我估计头几天你会有点想家，但很快就好了。”

“我没有家了，怎么还会想家？”

波西娅紧张地舔舔嘴唇说：“等他身体好了，准备好了，随时都可以回来。巴迪会很愿意开车把他送回镇上来，巴迪喜欢开车。”

汽车装得满满当当。一箱箱的书捆在脚踏板上，后座上塞了两把椅子、一个档案柜。他的办公桌四条腿朝天，拴到了车顶上。汽车不堪重负，骡车却几乎是空的。那头骡子耐心地站在那里，缰绳系在一块砖头上。

“卡尔·马克思，”科普兰医生说，“仔细看看，检查一遍家里，确保别落下什么东西。把我放在地上的茶杯，还有我的摇椅都拿来。”

“我们动身吧。我急着赶在晚饭前到家。”汉密尔顿说。

他们终于准备好了。海博埃用摇柄发动了汽车，卡尔·马克思坐到方向盘后面，波西娅、海博埃和威廉一起挤在后座上。

“父亲，建议你坐到海博埃的腿上，我觉得这样一定比跟我们和这些家具挤在一起要舒服。”

“不行，太挤了，我宁愿坐骡车。”

“但你不习惯坐骡车，”卡尔·马克思说，“路非常颠簸，而且可能要走一整天。”

“不要紧，我以前坐过很多次骡车。”

“那让汉密尔顿过来吧，他肯定更愿意坐汽车。”

外公是前一天赶着骡车来镇上的。他们带了一些土特产，有桃子、卷心菜和胡萝卜，让汉密尔顿到镇上来卖。除了一袋桃子，其他的都卖光了。

“喏，本尼迪克特·马迪，你跟我一起坐骡车回家吧。”老人说。

科普兰医生爬进骡车的后座。他很疲倦，浑身的骨头都像灌了铅似的。他的头颤抖着，突然感到一阵恶心，不得已赶紧平躺到粗糙的木板上。

“我很高兴你来了，”外公说，“你知道，我对文化人从来都充满深深的敬意。如果一个人是文化人，这种深深的敬意会让我忘记很多其他的事情。我很高兴我们家又来了一个你这样的文化人。”

骡车的轮子吱嘎作响。他们出发了。“我很快就回来。”科普兰医生说，“过一两个月，我就回来。”

“汉密尔顿，他也是个很好的文化人，我觉得他有点像你。他替我记账，念报纸。还有惠特曼，我觉得他也会变成一个文化人。现在他尽管还是个孩子，但已经可以给我念《圣经》了，也可以干些记账的活儿。我对文化人总是有种深深的敬意。”

骡车走着，颠着他的后背。他仰望着头顶的树枝，之后到了没有树荫的地方，他用手帕挡住脸，免得阳光刺眼。不可能就这样结束了。那种强烈真实的使命感一直埋在他的心底。四十年来，他的使命便是他的生命，他的生命便是他的使命。然而，一切还都没有做，什么都没有完成。

“是的，本尼迪克特·马迪，我很高兴让你又跟我们住在一起。我一直等着，想问问你我的右脚为什么感觉这么奇怪，感觉很怪异，就像右脚睡着了。我吃了六六六，还用搽剂按摩。我希望你能给我个好方子治治。”

“我会尽力。”

“是的，我很高兴你来。我相信所有亲人都应该团结在一起——血亲和姻亲。我相信我们大家应该一起努力，互帮互助，总有一天我们会在来生得到回报。”

“哼！”科普兰医生愤愤地说，“我相信现在的正义。”

“你说你相信什么？你的声音哑了，我听不见。”

“相信我们会拥有正义，我们黑人的正义。”

“是的。”

他感觉到心中有一团火，无法平静。他想坐起来，大声呐喊——但当他努力要坐起来时，却发现没有力气。心里的那些话越来越响，不肯沉默下去。但是，老人已经不再听他说话了，没有人听他说话。

“驾，李·杰克逊。驾，宝贝。抬起脚来，别在这儿磨蹭了。我们还有很远的路要走。”

2

午后

杰克一路拼命跑着，步子笨拙。他穿过织工巷，斜插进一条小巷，翻过一道栏杆，急匆匆地向前跑去。他胃里一阵恶心，喉咙里感觉到呕吐的味道。一只狗狂吠着追在他的身后，最后他停下来，拿着石头吓唬了它好一阵子。他眼睛圆睁，满是恐惧，一只手紧紧捂住张开的嘴巴。

天哪！这就算结束了。争吵。骚乱。他跟所有人打架。一个个的脑袋，一双双的眼睛，都被破瓶子划得鲜血淋漓。天哪！旋转木马上气不接下气的音乐在嘈杂声里响着。汉堡和棉花糖掉了一地，孩子们尖叫着。还有他。飞扬的尘土和炫目的阳光下，他乱打一气。尖牙利齿咬在他的手指关节上。哗笑声。天哪！他从心底释放出一种狂野强烈的韵律，无法停止。近距离盯着那张死去的黑人的脸，陷入意识的空白，甚至不知道他是否杀了人。但是，等等。天哪！没有人能够阻止这一切。

杰克慢下脚步，紧张地扭头望着身后。巷子里空无一人。他呕吐起来，然后用衬衫袖子擦擦嘴巴和额头。之后他歇了一会儿，感觉好些了。他已经跑了大概八个街区，抄近路的话大约还有半英里的路程。他的脑袋渐渐不那么晕眩了，从所有狂乱的感觉中他慢慢想起一些事实。他又跑起来，这次跑得很慢，很稳。

没有人能够阻止这一切。整整一个夏天，他都在扑灭它们，就像扑灭突如其来的大火，但只有这次除外。这场混战，没有人能够阻止。它好像凭空便突然熊熊燃烧起来。他当时正在修理秋千的机械装置，停下来去拿杯水。他经过游乐场时，看见一个白人男孩和一个黑人在绕着对方走来走去，他们都喝醉了。那天下午，一半的人群都喝醉了，因为那天是星期六，各个工厂已经连轴转了一个星期。炎热和阳光让人不舒服，空气中飘散着浓重的臭味。

他看见那两个打架的人互相逼近，但他知道这不是开始。很长时间以来，他一直感觉到一场大战即将来临。好笑的是，他居然有时间想起这些。他站在那里，观望了大约五秒钟，然后挤进了人群。在那短短的瞬间，他想到了很多事情。他想到了辛格，想到了这个阴沉的夏日午后，还有漆黑炎热的夜晚，想到了他阻拦过的所有混战、平息下的所有争吵。

然后，他看见了一把小折刀在阳光下闪着光。他挤开一堆人，一下跳到拿刀的那个黑人的背上，那个男人跟他一起摔倒在地。黑人身上的汗味混合着浓重的尘土味道，冲进他的肺里。有人踩在他的腿上，还有人踢他的头。等他再次站起来时，这次打架已经成了混战。黑人们正在撕扯着白人，白人在撕扯着黑人。一秒一秒地，他看得非常清楚。挑起战争的那个白人男孩似乎是个头儿，他领的那帮人经常到游乐场来。他们十六岁上下，穿着白色帆布裤和花哨的人造丝球衣。黑人们拼力反抗。有些人手里拿着剃须刀。

他开始大喊：秩序！救命！警察！但这就像冲着决堤的大坝喊叫一样。他耳朵里充斥着一种可怕的声音——说可怕，因为是人的声音，却没有言语。这种声音越来越大，成为一种轰鸣，他的耳朵都聋了。他被人一拳打在脑袋上，他看不清周围的情况，只看见眼睛、嘴巴、拳头——怒目圆睁的眼睛，半闭的眼睛，湿漉漉的、张着的嘴巴，紧闭的嘴巴，黑色的拳头，白色的拳头。他从一只手里夺过刀子，抓住一只举起来的拳头，然后尘土和阳光刺得他睁不开眼睛。他心里唯一的念头就是要冲出去，找到电话报警。

然而，他被困住了。不知道从什么时候起，他也加入混战之中。他用拳头打出去，感觉撞在湿漉漉的嘴巴上，很柔软。他闭着眼睛乱打一通，低着脑袋，喉咙里发出疯狂的声音。他拼尽全力打着，低着头像公牛一样向前冲，脑子里全是些混乱的话语，他在大笑着。他不知道打中了谁，也不知道谁打中了他，但他知道战斗的阵线已经变了，现在每个人都在为自己而战。

突然，一切都结束了。他绊了一下，朝后倒去，不省人事。也许过了一分钟时间，也许过了很长时间，他才睁开眼睛。几个醉汉仍然在打，但两个警察很快把他们拉开了。他看清了是什么东西绊倒了他。他半躺在一个黑人男孩的尸体上。只看了一眼，他便知道这个男孩已经死了，他脖子一侧有道刀口，但不知道为什么他死得这么快。他认识这张面孔，却想不起到底是谁。男孩的嘴巴张着，眼睛也睁着，一副吃惊的表情。地上散落着纸片、碎瓶子，还有踩扁的汉堡。有个木马的脑袋掉了下来，一个售货亭已经毁掉了。他坐了起来，看见那些警察，他惊慌失措地抬腿就跑。现在他们肯定追不上他了。

前面还有四个街区，然后他就百分之百安全了。恐惧让他呼吸急促，他气喘吁吁。他握紧拳头，低着头跑着。突然他慢了下来，停住了。他来到了主街旁边的一条小巷里，只有他一个人。一边是一座建筑物的墙壁，他颓然靠在墙上，喘息着，额头上青筋暴突，像要着火一样。混乱之中，他穿过镇子，一路跑到了他朋友的住处。但是，辛格已经死了。他放声大哭，大声抽泣着，鼻涕流下来，弄湿了胡子。

一面墙，一段楼梯，前面的一条路。炽热的太阳像一副重担，压迫着他。他开始原路折回。这次他走得很慢，用油腻的衣袖擦着满脸的泪水。他的嘴唇止不住地哆嗦，他使劲咬着，直到最后尝到了血的味道。

在下一街区的拐角，他碰上了西姆斯。这个老头正坐在一个箱子上，腿上放着《圣经》。他身后有一道高高的木板栅栏，上面用紫色粉笔写着一则信息：

上帝为救你而死

听听上帝的爱与恩典的故事

每晚7:15

街上空无一人。杰克想穿过街道，走到对面的人行道，但西姆斯一把抓住了他的胳膊。

“来吧，你这颗孤独疼痛的心。放下你的罪恶和烦恼，伏到神圣的上帝脚下，他是为了救你而死的。你为何要走啊，布朗特兄弟？”

“回家拉屎，”杰克说，“我得去拉屎。救世主难道连这个也管吗？”

“罪人！主会记得你所有的罪过，主今天晚上有启示给你。”

“主记不记得我上个星期给你的那一块钱？”

“今晚七点十五分，主有启示给你。你准时到这里来，听听主的圣言。”

杰克舔舔胡子。“每天晚上你这里都太挤了，我根本靠近不了，听不见。”

“总有地方给嘲笑者留着。而且我接到启示，救世主希望让我很快为他造一幢房子，就在十八大道和第六大街路口的那块地方，建个大教堂，足够容纳五百人。你们这些嘲笑者等着瞧吧。主会当着我的敌人的面，在我面前准备一张桌子，他会把油涂在我的头顶，我的杯里淌着——”

“我今晚可以替你召集一群人。”杰克说。

“怎么召集？”

“把你那支漂亮的彩色粉笔给我，我保证，一大群人。”

“我已经看到了你的标语。”西姆斯说，“‘工人们！美国是世界上最富有的国家，但我们有三分之一的人在挨饿。我们什么时候才能团结起来争取我们的那一份？’——都是那样的东西。你的标语太激进，我不让你用我的粉笔。”

“但我没打算写标语。”

西姆斯抚弄着《圣经》的纸页，等待着，满心狐疑。

“我要给你召集一大群人。在街区两头的人行道上，我给你画几个漂亮的裸体妓女，都画上彩色箭头，指引方向。可爱，丰满，光着屁股——”

“巴比伦人！”老人尖叫起来，“罪恶之地的子民！上帝会记住这一切的。”

杰克穿过大街，走到对面的人行道上，朝住处走去。“再见了，兄弟。”

“罪人，”老人喊道，“七点十五准时到这里来，听听耶稣的启示，会给你信仰，拯救你。”

辛格死了。他听说他是自杀身亡的，第一感觉不是悲伤——而是愤怒。他站在一面墙跟前。他想起跟辛格说过的所有内心的想法。辛格死了，他觉得这些想法也随之消失了。辛格为什么要结束自己的生命？也许，他精神失常了。但无论如何，他死了，死了，死了。再也看不见他，摸不着他，再也没法跟他说话了。他们一起度过那么多时光的那间屋子，已经租给了一个女孩，是个打字员。他再也不能到那里去了。他形单影只。一面墙，一段楼梯，一条大路。

杰克随手锁上房间门。他饥肠辘辘，却没有什么可吃的。他很渴，桌上的壶里却只剩下几滴温水。床铺没叠，地上布满毛茸茸的灰尘，房间里到处散落着纸张，因为最近他写了很多小告示，在镇上到处发送。他闷闷不乐地瞟了一眼其中的一张纸，上面写着“纺织工人组织委员会是你最好的朋友”。有些告示只有一句话，有些则长一些。有张告示写了满满一页纸，标题是“我们的民主与法西斯主义之间的关联”。

整整一个月，他都在忙着写这些告示，上班的时候匆忙写完，到纽约咖啡馆用打字机打出来，做出复印件，再亲手一份份地发出去。他日夜忙碌着，但有谁读它们呢？这些东西有什么用处？这个规模的小镇，对于一个人而言还是太大了。现在他要离开了。

但这一次，他又该去哪儿呢？那些城市的名字呼唤着他——孟菲斯、威尔明顿、加斯托尼亚、新奥尔良。他要去某个地方，但不会离开南方。那种熟悉的不安和饥渴仍然留在他的心里。这次不一样了。这次，他不再渴望开阔的天地和自由——恰恰相反。他想起那个黑人科普兰跟他说过的话：“不要试图孤军作战。”有些时候，这样反而最好。

杰克把床搬到房间的另一头。床挪走之后，地板上露出个手提箱，还有一堆书和脏衣服。他急不可待地开始打包。那个老年黑人的脸闪现在脑海中，他又想起他们之前谈过的一些话。科普兰简直疯了，他是个狂热分子，因此，想要跟他讲道理是不理智的。然而，那天晚上他们感受到的那种可怕的愤怒仍然难以理解。科普兰知道。而知道的那些人，就像一小群赤身裸体的士兵面对着一支武装部队。他们做了些什么？他们后来吵了起来。科普兰错了——是的——他简直疯了。但毕竟，在有些问题上他们也许能够齐心协力。如果他们没有说那么多话就好了。他会再去看看他。他突然觉得有一种紧迫感，要赶紧行动。也许，这毕竟是最好的事情。也许这就是那个征兆，就是他长久以来等待着的那只手。

他没来得及洗净脸上和手上的污垢，便捆好箱子出了门。外面的空气湿热难耐，街上有一股恶臭。乌云在天上积聚起来，空气里没有一丝风，附近一个工厂冒出的烟成为一条连续的直线。杰克走路的时候，手提箱笨重地磕碰着他的膝盖，他不时猛地扭过头望望身后。科普兰住在镇子的另一头，因此他必须加快步伐。天空中的乌云越来越浓，看样子，天黑之前要有一场夏天的大雨。

他赶到科普兰家的房子，看到百叶窗紧闭。他走到后面，透过窗子仔细望着空荡荡的厨房。空虚、绝望的失望让他的手心出汗，他的心跳都乱了。他走到左边的那户人家，也没人在家。别无他法，他只能去凯利家，问问波西娅。

他厌恶再次走近那幢房子。他无法忍受看见前厅的衣帽架，还有他爬了那么多次的那段长长的楼梯。他转回头，步履缓慢地再次穿过镇子，却正好经过那条小巷。他走进了后门。波西娅正在厨房里，那个小男孩跟她在一起。

“不，先生，布朗特先生，”波西娅说，“我知道你是辛格先生非常好的朋友，你也知道父亲是怎么看他的，但我们今天早晨把父亲送回乡下了。我心里明白，我不该告诉你他到底去了哪儿。如果不介意的话，我宁愿有话直说，不绕圈子。”

“对任何事你都没必要绕圈子。”杰克说，“但这是为什么啊？”

“那次你来看我们之后，父亲病得很厉害，我们以为他要死了。我们花了很长时间才让他能够坐起来。他现在情况还不错，到了现在的地方他恢复得会更快些。但不管你能不能理解，他现在特别恨白人，非常容易生气。而且如果你不介意我直说的话，你找我父亲到底有什么事？”

“没什么，”杰克说，“你不懂。”

“我们黑人跟任何人一样，都有感情。我说的是真心话，布朗特先生。父亲只是个生病的老黑人，他的烦恼已经够多了。我们得照顾好他，而且他并不着急见你——我知道。”

他重新回到大街上，看见乌云变成一种深沉、愤怒的紫色，凝滞的空气中有一种暴风雨的味道。人行道旁，郁郁葱葱的树木似乎悄悄融进了空气里，大街上闪着一种奇怪的绿光。一切都寂静无声，杰克停下来，嗅嗅空气，朝四周张望了一会儿。然后他把手提箱夹在腋下，朝主街的那些雨篷底下跑去。但他的速度还是不够快。一个雷声如金属炸裂般响过，空气瞬间寒冷起来。大颗大颗的银色雨点嘶嘶地打在人行道上，大雨如注，倾泻而下，挡住了他的视线。等他跑到纽约咖啡馆的时候，衣服已经湿透了，皱巴巴地紧贴在身上，鞋子里灌满了水，吱吱作响。

布兰农推开报纸，把胳膊肘靠在柜台上。“喏，这真奇怪，刚一下雨，我就预感到你要来。我从骨子里就知道你要来，而且知道你会来晚一步。”他用大拇指按着鼻子，把鼻子都按平了，泛起白来。“还带着箱子？”

“它看上去像个箱子，”杰克说，“感觉像个箱子。因此，如果你相信真有箱子的话，那好吧，我觉得这就是个箱子。”

“你不应该这么站着。上楼，把衣服扔下来，路易斯会用热熨斗给你烫烫。”

杰克走到后面雅座的一张桌子前坐下，双手捧住脑袋。“不了，谢谢。我只想坐在这里歇歇，喘口气。”

“但你的嘴唇都青了，你看上去快要累垮了。”

“我很好。我想吃点晚饭。”

“再过半小时晚饭才能好。”布兰农耐心地说道。

“剩饭就可以，只消把它们放到盘子里，甚至都不用费心加热。”

他内心空虚，心里隐隐作痛。他既不想向后看，也不想向前看。他用两根粗短的手指在桌面上划动着。距离第一次坐到这张桌子跟前，已经过去了一年多。现在他比那时候有什么进展呢？没有。他交了一个朋友，又失去了他，此外什么都没有发生。他对辛格付出了一切，而这个人却自杀了。他孤立无援。现在要走出这个局面重新开始，都要靠他自己了。一想到这里，一种恐慌感涌上心头。他累了。他把头靠在墙上，两只脚放在旁边的座位上。

“给你，”布兰农说，“这应该会有所帮助。”

他放下一杯热饮和一盘鸡肉馅饼。那杯饮料有一种香甜浓重的味道。杰克吸着冒出的热气，闭上了眼睛。“里面是什么？”

“用糖搓过的柠檬皮，加了热水，还有朗姆酒。很好喝。”

“我欠你多少钱？”

“这会儿说不上来，但你走之前我会算出来的。”

杰克喝了一大口热甜酒，在嘴里涮了一圈，然后才咽下去。“你永远别想拿到钱，”他说，“我没有钱付账——即便有钱，我也许无论如何都不会付给你。”

“嗯，我催过你吗？我给你开过账单，或要求你清过账吗？”

“没有，”杰克说，“你一直很理智。我认真想过，你是个非常体面的家伙——从个人角度来说，就是这样。”

布兰农坐在他桌子的对面，脑子里正想着什么东西，把盐罐来来回回地挪动着，不断地理头发。他闻起来似乎有香水的味道，蓝色条纹衬衫干净整齐，袖子挽了起来，用蓝色的旧式袖箍固定住。

终于，他犹豫不决地清清嗓子说：“你来之前，我在翻看下午的报纸，你们那个地方今天似乎遇上大麻烦了。”

“是的。上面怎么说？”

“等等，我去把报纸拿来。”布兰农从柜台上抓过报纸，斜靠在雅座的隔板上。“头版上说，迪克西阳光游乐场，在什么什么位置，出现了群体骚乱。两名黑人被刀子刺伤，不幸死亡。另有三人受轻伤，已经被送往市医院治疗。两名死者为吉米·梅西和兰西·戴维斯。受伤的是约翰·哈姆林，白人，来自中央工厂区；维尔瑞尔斯·威尔逊，是个黑人；等等等等。原文说：‘多人被捕。据称，这次骚乱是由劳工煽动而起，在骚乱地点及周围发现颠覆性内容的传单。稍后，更多人有望被捕。’”布兰农上下牙碰在一起，发出咔嗒声，“这些报纸印得一天不如一天，‘颠覆性’的第二个音节居然写成了字母‘u’，‘逮捕’漏掉了一个‘r’。”

“他们很聪明，很好，”杰克嘲讽地说，“‘由劳工煽动而起’，太棒了。”

“无论如何，整个事情很不幸。”

杰克用一只手捂住嘴巴，望着面前的空盘子。

“你现在想怎么办？”

“我要走了。今天下午我就离开这里。”

布兰农在手心里磨着指甲。“嗯，这当然不必要——但这样也许是个好事。不过，为什么这么轻率呢？这个时间动身没有什么道理。”

“我愿意。”

“我觉得你不适合重新开始。再有，你为什么不听听我对这件事给你的建议呢？我自己——我是个保守派，当然觉得你的意见很激进，但话又说回来，对于一件事我喜欢进行全面了解。无论如何，我想看到你能重回正轨。那么你为什么不找个地方，可以碰见几个多少跟你志同道合的人？然后，安定下来？”

杰克恼怒地推开盘子。“我不知道自己要去哪儿。别管我，我累了。”

布兰农耸耸肩膀，回到柜台后面。

他真的累了。热朗姆酒和大雨的噪音令他昏昏欲睡。安然坐在雅座里，刚刚饱餐一顿，感觉真好。如果愿意，他可以靠着打个盹儿——很快地打个盹儿。他感觉脑袋又大又沉，闭上眼睛就舒服多了，但睡的时间不能太长，因为很快他就必须离开这里。

“这雨还要下多长时间啊？”

布兰农的声音透着昏昏欲睡的感觉。“说不准——热带暴雨，也许立刻便会放晴——或者——也许会小一点，然后下一晚上。”

杰克把脑袋枕在胳膊上。雨声就像大海的涨潮声。他听到钟表的嘀嗒声，还有远处碗碟的哗啦声。他的两只手慢慢松弛下来，在桌面上张开了，手心朝上。

布兰农摇晃着他的肩膀，盯着他的脸。他做了个可怕的梦。“醒醒吧，”布兰农说，“你做了个噩梦。我朝这边看，你嘴巴张着，呻吟着，两只脚在地上搓来搓去，我从来没见过这种样子。”

脑海中，那个梦依然让人很沉重。他又感觉到了之前醒来时经常会有的那种恐惧。他推开布兰农，站起身来。“我做噩梦，用不着你告诉我，我记得怎么回事儿。这个梦，我以前做过大概十五回了。”

这会儿，他的确想起来了。每隔一段时间，他醒来后脑子里便记不清这个梦境。他穿行在一大群人中间——好像是在游乐场，但周围的人好像有些东方人的样子。太阳非常灿烂，人们都是半裸。他们沉默无语，行动迟缓，脸上有种饥饿的表情。到处都没有声音，只有太阳，还有沉默的人群。他走在人群中间，拿着一个硕大的篮子，篮子是盖着的。他要把篮子带到什么地方去，却找不到放篮子的地方。在梦里，他在人群里面穿来穿去，不知道把怀里抱了这么长时间的东西放到哪里去，让他有种特别的恐惧感。

“怎么回事儿？”布兰农问道，“有魔鬼在追你吗？”

杰克站起来，走到柜台后面的镜子跟前。他脸上很脏，汗涔涔的，眼睛下面有黑眼圈。他把手绢放到水龙头底下打湿，擦擦脸，然后从口袋里掏出梳子，把胡子梳理整齐。

“这个梦没什么。你得先睡着，然后才能明白为什么会做这样的噩梦。”

钟表的指针指到五点三十分，雨几乎停了。杰克拿起手提箱，走到前门。“再会，我也许会给你寄张明信片的。”

“等等，”布兰农说，“你现在不能走，还在下小雨。”

“只是雨篷上滴下来的水而已，天黑前我得出镇子。”

“但等等，你有钱吗？够维持一个星期吗？”

“我不需要钱，以前我就不名一文。”

布兰农已经备好一个信封，里面有两张二十块钱的钞票。杰克把两张钞票翻来覆去看了看，然后塞进了口袋里。“天知道你为什么这么干，以后你连它们的味儿都闻不到了。但谢谢，我会记住的。”

“祝你好运。给我写信。”

“再见。”[23]

“再见。”

门在他的身后关上了。他走到街区尽头，回头张望，布兰农还站在人行道上看着他。他一直走，最后走到了铁路旁边。铁路两侧有一排排破败不堪的房子，都只有两间屋子。狭窄的后院里，有个破烂的厕所，绳子上晾晒着烟灰色的衣服，也都破烂不堪。两英里范围内，没有一处地方让人觉得舒适、敞亮、干净，即便是泥土，都让人觉得肮脏，是废弃的。不时会看到有人曾经种过一畦菜地的迹象，但只剩几颗打蔫儿的羽衣甘蓝还苟延残喘。此外，还有几棵没结果的无花果树，脏兮兮的。孩子们纷纷涌进这片肮脏的地方，小一点的孩子都光着屁股。这种贫穷的景象如此残酷，如此无望，杰克低吼一声，握紧了拳头。

他走到小镇边缘，拐上了一条公路。汽车从他身边经过。他的肩膀太宽，两臂太长，他实在太强壮、太丑陋了，没有人愿意搭载他，但也许不久会有一辆卡车停下来。傍晚时分的太阳又出来了，因为天热，湿乎乎的人行道上冒出了蒸汽。杰克稳步前行。他一离开镇子，身上便焕发出一股新的能量。这是逃避还是进攻？无论如何，他要走了。所有这一切，换个时间再重新开始吧。前方的道路向北延伸出去，稍微偏西。但他不会走得太远，他不会离开南方，这一点很清楚。他心里存有希望，也许他的行程方向很快便会清晰起来。

3

晚上

这有什么用呢？她想知道这个问题。这到底有什么用。她所做的那些计划，还有音乐。所有的一切到头来都是个圈套——商店，回家睡觉，再回商店。辛格先生以前上班的那个店铺前面，钟表指着七点。她刚要下班。无论什么时候需要加班，经理总会让她留下，因为她比别的女孩都能站的时间更长，工作更努力。

大雨过后，天空变成静谧的浅蓝色，夜色正在降临。灯火已经亮了起来，街道上响着汽车喇叭，报童叫喊着报纸的头条消息。她不想回家。如果现在回家，她会躺在床上号啕大哭。她就是这么疲倦。如果她走进纽约咖啡馆，吃点冰激凌，也许会感觉好些。再抽根烟，一个人待一会儿。

咖啡馆的前部挤满了人，她走到最后一个雅座。她的腰背和面容都疲惫不堪。他们的座右铭应该是“时刻警惕，保持微笑”。她一走出商店，必须皱很长时间眉头才能让脸部恢复自然状态。就连她的耳朵都疲惫不堪，她摘下垂着的两个绿色耳环，捏着耳垂。这是她上个星期买的耳环——还买了一个银手镯。起初她在炊事用品区干活儿，但现在他们把她调到了配饰珠宝区。

“晚上好，米克。”布兰农说。他用餐巾擦拭着一个水杯的杯底，然后把杯子放在桌上。

“给我一个巧克力圣代，一杯五分钱的生啤。”

“一起上？”他放下菜单，用那个戴着女式金戒指的小拇指点着，“瞧——这里有很好吃的烤鸡或炖小牛肉。你为什么不在这儿一块简单吃个晚饭呢？”

“不用了，谢谢。我只想要圣代和啤酒，两个都要特别凉的。”

米克理了下额前的头发。她的嘴巴张着，双颊似乎凹陷下去。有两件事情，她永远都无法相信。辛格先生自杀了，死了；还有，她长大了，必须得到伍尔沃斯店里上班。

是她发现他死了。他们还以为那个声音是汽车回火了，直到第二天他们才知道真相。她进去开收音机。他的脖子上都是血。她爸爸赶了过来，把她推出房间。她跑出家门，心中万分震惊，无法平静。她跑进黑暗中，用拳头猛打自己。第二天晚上，他躺进了起居室的棺材里。殡仪员给他抹了胭脂和口红，让他的面容显得自然一些。但是，他的样子并不自然。他死气沉沉。混合着花香，有种另类的味道，让她无法待在屋子里。但在那些痛苦的日子当中，她还是保住了工作。她包好商品，从柜台上递过去，然后把钱放进收银机的抽屉。她该走路的时候走路，该吃饭的时候吃饭。只是一开始，她晚上上床之后无法入睡。但现在，她也该睡就睡了。

米克斜坐在座位上，跷起二郎腿。她的长袜有个地方抽线了。她走路上班的时候，袜子开始抽线，她朝上面吐了口唾沫。后来脱线越来越厉害，她用一块口香糖粘在了脱线的末端，即便如此也无济于事。现在，她得回家缝缝了。她真不知道该怎么穿长袜，她的袜子破得很快，除非她像那些普通女孩子一样穿棉袜子。

她不该到这里来。她的鞋底都已经完全磨穿了，她该省下这两毛钱，好补一副新的前掌。如果她穿着一双脚底有洞的鞋子一直站在那里，会发生什么事？脚上会磨出泡的。那她就得把针烧了，挑破水泡，她就必须请假在家，那样就要被开除了。那时候，会发生什么事呢？

“给你。”布兰农先生说，“但我以前从来没听说过这种搭配。”

他把圣代和啤酒放在桌上。她假装在清洁手指甲，因为如果她看他一眼，他就会开始说个不停。他对她没了那种怨恨，那么他肯定已经忘了那包口香糖的事。现在他总想跟她说话，但她不想说话，想一个人待着。圣代很好吃，上面浇满了巧克力、坚果、樱桃。啤酒让人放松。吃完冰激凌再喝啤酒，啤酒便有一种很好喝的苦味，让她醉意蒙眬。除了音乐，啤酒是最好的东西。

但现在，她脑子里已经没有了音乐。这很有意思，就像她“里屋”的门已经关上了似的。有时候，一首短促的小曲子会一闪而过——但她从来没像以前那样走进“里屋”，与音乐为伴，仿佛是她太紧张了。或者，也许是因为商店似乎消耗了她全部的精力和时间。伍尔沃斯跟学校不同。以前她放学回家时，感觉非常好，随时准备着要研究她的音乐。但现在，她总是很疲倦。在家时她吃完晚饭便睡觉，然后吃完早饭便走出家门又去店里。她两个月前在私密笔记本上开始写的一首歌，现在依然没有完成。她很想待在“里屋”，却不知道如何做到，仿佛“里屋”已经被锁在了离她很远的地方。这件事情真的令人费解。

米克用大拇指推推那颗断掉的门牙。但她的确得到了辛格先生的收音机。分期付款还没有付完，她接过了这个担子。能获得一件原本属于他的东西，真的太好了。也许这几天，她可以攒点钱买架二手钢琴，比如一个星期省下两块钱。除了她自己，谁也不允许碰这架私人钢琴——她也许还可以教乔治弹几首小曲子。她会把钢琴放到后面的房间里，每天晚上都要弹，到了星期天她要弹一整天。但是，假如哪个星期她付不起钱了怎么办？那样的话，他们会来把钢琴抬走，就像那辆红色小自行车一样？假如她不让他们抬走呢。假如她把钢琴藏到屋子下面，或者她在前门堵住他们，跟他们拼命。她会把那两个人都打倒在地，打得他们眼圈发黑，打断他们的鼻子，打得他们晕倒在门厅的地上。

米克皱起眉头，用拳头使劲来回搓着额头。事情就是这样。她仿佛一直都很愤怒，不是像孩子那样无端地生气然后又很快忘记——而是另外一种样子。只是，没有什么事情可以为之生气，商店的事情除外。但商店并没有要求她干这份工作，因此也没什么可生气的。她仿佛是被欺骗了似的，只是没有任何人欺骗她，因此也没有任何人可以让她发泄怒火。然而，她仍然有这种感觉，被欺骗的感觉。

但钢琴的事情也许会成真，会一切顺利。她也许很快便会有机会了。否则，这一切还有什么意义——她对音乐的感受，还有她在“里屋”所做的那些计划？不管任何东西，如果要有道理，那就必须要有点意义才行。这件事也是如此，也是如此，也是如此，也是如此。这件事有点意义。

好吧！

好的！

有点意义。

4

深夜

万籁俱寂。比夫擦干手和脸，一阵微风吹来，桌上那个日本小塔上的玻璃坠子叮当作响。他刚打了个瞌睡醒过来，抽完了每夜必抽的那根烟。他想起布朗特，很想知道他现在是否已经走远了。一瓶佛罗里达香水放在浴室架子上，他用瓶塞涂了下太阳穴。他用口哨吹起一首老歌，走下狭窄的楼梯时，嘴里的曲子在身后留下断断续续的回音。

路易斯应该在柜台后面值班才对，但他开了小差。店里空无一人，大门开着，外面是空荡荡的街道。墙上的钟表指着十一点四十三分，收音机开着，里面的人正在谈论希特勒给但泽带来的危机。他回到厨房，发现路易斯在椅子上睡着了。这个男孩脱掉了鞋子，解开了裤子的纽扣，脑袋垂在胸前，衬衫上湿了长长的一片，说明他已经睡了好一会儿了。他的两条胳膊直直地从两侧耷拉下来，他居然没有脸朝前摔下来，真是个奇迹。他睡得很沉，根本没法叫醒他。这将是个寂静的夜晚。

比夫蹑手蹑脚地穿过厨房，走到一个架子跟前，上面放着一篮子的茶桂花，还有满满两大水壶的鱼尾菊。他把这些花拿到餐馆前面，然后从橱窗里取下上面用玻璃纸盖着的大浅盘，里面是上一餐的特色菜。他厌倦了食物。一橱窗的新鲜夏季花卉——那会很美。他闭上眼睛，想象着应该怎样摆放这些花。下面铺上一层茶桂花，清爽，葱绿。上面用陶瓷盆装满灿烂的鱼尾菊。这些就够了。他开始认真地布置橱窗。这些花里有一株很奇怪，这棵鱼尾菊有六个古铜色花瓣和两个红色花瓣。他仔细看看这件稀罕物，先留到了一边。橱窗布置完毕，他站到街上，欣赏着自己的手艺。那些笨拙的茎干被弯曲得恰到好处，营造出一种闲适的松散。电灯破坏了效果，等太阳出来以后，这个布置会展现最佳效果。完美的艺术品。

星光熠熠的黑暗夜空似乎离地面非常近。他沿着人行道缓步前行，中间停下一次，用脚把一块橘子皮踢进了排水沟。在下个街区的远端，有两个男人手挽手地站在一起，从远处看很小，一动不动的。周围空无一人。这条街上，只有他家的店大门洞开，灯火通明。

为什么？镇上所有其他的咖啡馆都关了门，只有他的店彻夜开放，到底是为了什么？经常有人问他这个问题，他却说不出答案。不是为钱。有时候，一伙人进来喝啤酒，要盘炒鸡蛋，花上五块或十块。但这种情况少之又少。大多数情况下，他们一个一个地进来，几乎不点什么东西，却会逗留很久。有些夜里，十二点到五点之间没有一个客人进来。店里没有盈利——这显而易见。

但他夜晚永远不会关门——只要他还干这一行，就不会关门。夜晚才正是时候。如果不是夜晚，有些人他永远见不到。有几个人每星期都会固定过来几次，有些人则只来过一次，喝杯可口可乐，然后便再也没有出现过。

比夫把胳膊交叠在胸前，走得更慢了。在弧形的街灯下，他的影子棱角分明，黑乎乎的。夜晚的安宁与静谧占据了他的身心，这是休息和冥想的好时候。也许，这就是他为什么会一直待在楼下不去睡觉的原因。他最后快速地瞥了一眼空荡荡的街道，走进店里。

收音机里的声音还在谈论着危机，天花板上的风扇旋转着，令人舒适。厨房里传来路易斯的鼾声。他突然想到可怜的威利，决心找个时间尽快给他送一夸脱威士忌过去。他转身拿起报纸，看着上面的字谜游戏。中间是个女人的照片，让猜名字。他认出了这个女人，在横着的第一栏里写下名字——蒙娜·丽莎。竖着的第一列是个表示乞丐的词，“m”打头，有九个字母。托钵僧[24]。横着的第二栏，这个词的意思是远远地挪开，有六个字母，“e”打头。消逝[25]？他大声试着各种字母组合。移至远处[26]。但他很快兴致索然。没有这种字谜，他的谜也已经够多了。他叠好报纸收了起来。以后再做吧。

他仔细看着特意留下的那枝鱼尾菊。他把花放在手心里凑近灯光，这朵花也不是多么新奇的标本，不值得保存。他摘下柔软艳丽的花瓣，最后一个花瓣因爱而开。但爱谁呢？他现在爱着谁？没有谁。任何一个穿着体面的人都可以从街上走进来坐下，待上一个小时，喝一杯，却没有哪个是他爱的人。他明白自己的所爱，但一切都结束了。爱丽丝、玛德琳，还有基普。都结束了，留下他，不好也不坏。到底是怎么样？随你怎么看。

还有米克。最近几个月，她在他的心里挥之不去，感觉很奇怪。那种爱也完结了吗？是的，完了。傍晚时分，她会进来喝杯冷饮，或吃个圣代。她已经长大了，身上那种粗野和孩子气没有了。相反，现出一种淑女般、很精致的东西，很难说清楚。耳环、悬着的手镯以及她跷二郎腿的新样子，她还会把裙边拽下来盖住膝盖。他注视着她，只感觉到一种温柔。他心里原来的那种感觉消失了。有一年的时间，这种爱以奇怪的方式盛开在他的心里。他质疑过无数次，却没有找到答案。现在一切都完结了，犹如夏日的花朵凋零在九月。没有人了。

比夫用食指轻叩着鼻子。收音机里，一个外国人正在说话。他无法确定说的到底是德语、法语，还是西班牙语，但它听上去像厄运来临一般，让人心神不宁。他关掉收音机，随之而来的是深沉的寂静，绵延无尽。他能感受到外面的夜色。孤独扼住了他的喉咙，呼吸都变得急促起来。时间太晚了，不能给露西尔打电话，跟巴比说话了。他也不指望这个时候还有顾客上门。他走到门口，看了看左右的街道。空无一人，漆黑一片。

“路易斯！”他喊道，“你醒了吗，路易斯？”

没人答话。他把胳膊肘支在柜台上，双手捧着头。他长满黑胡子的下巴左右挪动着，他慢慢皱起眉头。

那个谜。那个问题已经在他心里生根发芽，不肯让他安生。辛格的谜，其他人的谜。距离这一切的开始已经过去一年多了。距离布朗特第一次来到这里喝得酩酊大醉，并且第一次见到哑巴，已经过去一年多了。距离米克开始跟着他进进出出，已经过去一年多了。而现在，距离辛格去世和下葬，已经一个月了。而那个谜，却依然在他心底，让他不得安生。这一切，有种不自然的东西——这种东西像个丑陋的笑话。他想到这里便觉得不安，不知道为什么还有些害怕。

他操持了葬礼。他们把所有的事情都交给了他处理。辛格的事情一团糟。他所有的东西都有分期付款到期，而其人寿险的受益人已经过世。剩下的钱只勉强够给辛格下葬。葬礼安排在中午。他们站在一个开阔的阴冷墓地周围，太阳无遮无拦地炙烤着，那些花儿在太阳底下打了卷，变成棕褐色。米克哭得很伤心，几乎喘不上气来，她爸爸不得不使劲拍打她的后背。布朗特望着墓地，怒容满面，一只拳头抵在嘴巴上。镇上的那个黑人医生好像跟可怜的威利有什么关系，他站在人群边上，暗自垂泪。还有以前从没见过、从没听说过的一些陌生人，天知道他们是从哪儿来的，或者他们为什么到这里来。

屋里的寂静如同夜色一般深沉。比夫定定地站着，陷入沉思。突然，他感觉心跳加速，一阵晕眩，他向后靠在柜台上支撑住自己。眼前有亮光瞬间闪过，他瞥见了人类的奋斗，还有英勇；瞥见了人类在无穷无尽的时间中无穷无尽的流动；瞥见了那些劳作的人，还有那些——一个字——爱着的人，他的灵魂自由驰骋。但只是短短的一瞬间。他在心里感觉到一种警告，一阵恐惧。他被悬吊在了两个世界之间。他看到，他正盯着面前柜台玻璃上自己的那张脸，太阳穴上闪着汗珠，脸庞扭曲，一只眼睛睁得大，一只眼睛睁得小。左眼眯着，深深地看着过去；而右眼圆睁，惊恐地凝视着黑暗、错误、毁灭的未来。他被悬吊在光明和黑暗之间，在辛辣的讽刺和信念之间。他猛地扭过头去。

“路易斯！”他喊道，“路易斯！路易斯！”

依然没有回应。但是，天哪，他是神志正常，还是已经疯了？他甚至不清楚这种恐惧到底从何而来，但为什么它会这样令他感觉窒息？他要一直像个神经质的傻瓜一样站在这里，还是要振作起来，做个清醒的人？他究竟是神志正常，还是已经疯了？比夫在水龙头底下打湿手帕，然后用湿手帕拍拍疲惫紧张的脸。不知怎的，他想起遮雨棚还没有支起来。他朝门口走去，步子逐渐恢复了稳定。等终于又回到屋里的时候，他定下神来，等待着早晨太阳升起。

PART ONE

1

In the town there were two mutes, and they were always together. Early every morning they would come out from the house where they lived and walk arm in arm down the street to work.The two friends were very different.The one who always steered the way was an obese and dreamy Greek.In the summer he would come out wearing a yellow or green polo shirt stuffed sloppily into his trousers in front and hanging loose behind.When it was colder he wore over this a shapeless gray sweater.His face was round and oily, with half-closed eyelids and lips that curved in a gentle, stupid smile.The other mute was tall.His eyes had a quick, intelligent expression.He was always immaculate and very soberly dressed.

Every morning the two friends walked silently together until they reached the main street of the town. Then when they came to a certain fruit and candy store they paused for a moment on the sidewalk outside.The Greek, Spiros Antonapoulos, worked for his cousin, who owned this fruit store.His job was to make candies and sweets, uncrate the fruits, and to keep the place clean.The thin mute, John Singer, nearly always put his hand on his friend's arm and looked for a second into his face before leaving him.Then after this good-bye Singer crossed the street and walked on alone to the jewelry store where he worked as a silverware engraver.

In the late afternoon the friends would meet again. Singer came back to the fruit store and waited until Antonapoulos was ready to go home.The Greek would be lazily unpacking a case of peaches or melons, or perhaps looking at the funny paper in the kitchen behind the store where he cooked.Before their departure Antonapoulos always opened a paper sack he kept hidden during the day on one of the kitchen shelves.Inside were stored various bits of food he had collected—a piece of fruit, samples of candy, or the butt-end of a liverwurst.Usually before leaving Antonapoulos waddled gently to the glassed case in the front of the store where some meats and cheeses were kept.He glided open the back of the case and his fat hand groped lovingly for some particular dainty inside which he had wanted.Sometimes his cousin who owned the place did not see him.But if he noticed he stared at his cousin with a warning in his tight, pale face.Sadly Antonapoulos would shuffle the morsel from one corner of the case to the other.During these times Singer stood very straight with his hands in his pockets and looked in another direction.He did not like to watch this little scene between the two Greeks.For, excepting drinking and a certain solitary secret pleasure, Antonapoulos loved to eat more than anything else in the world.

In the dusk the two mutes walked slowly home together. At home Singer was always talking to Antonapoulos.His hands shaped the words in a swift series of designs.His face was eager and his gray-green eyes sparkled brightly.With his thin, strong hands he told Antonapoulos all that had happened during the day.

Antonapoulos sat back lazily and looked at Singer. It was seldom that he ever moved his hands to speak at all—and then it was to say that he wanted to eat or to sleep or to drink.These three things he always said with the same vague, fumbling signs.At night, if he were not too drunk, he would kneel down before his bed and pray awhile.Then his plump hands shaped the words“Holy Jesus，”or“God，”or“Darling Mary.”These were the only words Antonapoulos ever said.Singer never knew just how much his friend understood of all the things he told him.But it did not matter.

They shared the upstairs of a small house near the business section of the town. There were two rooms.On the oil stove in the kitchen Antonapoulos cooked all of their meals.There were straight, plain kitchen chairs for Singer and an over-stuffed sofa for Antonapoulos.The bedroom was furnished mainly with a large double bed covered with an eiderdown comforter for the big Greek and a narrow iron cot for Singer.

Dinner always took a long time, because Antonapoulos loved food and he was very slow. After they had eaten, the big Greek would lie back on his sofa and slowly lick over each one of his teeth with his tongue, either from a certain delicacy or because he did not wish to lose the savor of the meal—while Singer washed the dishes.

Sometimes in the evening the mutes would play chess. Singer had always greatly enjoyed this game, and years before he had tried to teach it to Antonapoulos.At first his friend could not be interested in the reasons for moving the various pieces about on the board.Then Singer began to keep a bottle of something good under the table to be taken out after each lesson.The Greek never got on to the erratic movements of the knights and the sweeping mobility of the queens, but he learned to make a few set, opening moves.He preferred the white pieces and would not play if the black men were given him.After the first moves Singer worked out the game by himself while his friend looked on drowsily.If Singer made brilliant attacks on his own men so that in the end the black king was killed, Antonapoulos was always very proud and pleased.

The two mutes had no other friends, and except when they worked they were alone together. Each day was very much like any other day, because they were alone so much that nothing ever disturbed them.Once a week they would go to the library for Singer to withdraw a mystery book and on Friday night they attended a movie.Then on payday they always went to the ten-cent photograph shop above the Army and Navy Store so that Antonapoulos could have his picture taken.These were the only places where they made customary visits.There were many parts in the town that they had never even seen.

The town was in the middle of the deep South. The summers were long and the months of winter cold were very few.Nearly always the sky was a glassy, brilliant azure and the sun burned down riotously bright.Then the light, chill rains of November would come, and perhaps later there would be frost and some short months of cold.The winters were changeable, but the summers always were burning hot.The town was a fairly large one.On the main street there were several blocks of two-and three-story shops and business offices.But the largest buildings in the town were the factories, which employed a large percentage of the population.These cotton mills were big and flourishing and most of the workers in the town were very poor.Often in the faces along the streets there was the desperate look of hunger and of loneliness.

But the two mutes were not lonely at all. At home they were content to eat and drink, and Singer would talk with his hands eagerly to his friend about all that was in his mind.So the years passed in this quiet way until Singer reached the age of thirty-two and had been in the town with Antonapoulos for ten years.

Then one day the Greek became ill. He sat up in bed with his hands on his fat stomach and big, oily tears rolled down his cheeks.Singer went to see his friend's cousin who owned the fruit store, and also he arranged for leave from his own work.The doctor made out a diet for Antonapoulos and said that he could drink no more wine.Singer rigidly enforced the doctor's orders.All day he sat by his friend's bed and did what he could to make the time pass quickly, but Antonapoulos only looked at him angrily from the corners of his eyes and would not be amused.

The Greek was very fretful, and kept finding fault with the fruit drinks and food that Singer prepared for him. Constantly he made his friend help him out of bed so that he could pray.His huge buttocks would sag down over his plump little feet when he kneeled.He fumbled with his hands to say“Darling Mary”and then held to the small brass cross tied to his neck with a dirty string.His big eyes would wall up to the ceiling with a look of fear in them, and afterward he was very sulky and would not let his friend speak to him.

Singer was patient and did all that he could. He drew little pictures, and once he made a sketch of his friend to amuse him.This picture hurt the big Greek's feelings, and he refused to be reconciled until Singer had made his face very young and handsome and colored his hair bright yellow and his eyes china blue.And then he tried not to show his pleasure.

Singer nursed his friend so carefully that after a week Antonapoulos was able to return to his work. But from that time on there was a difference in their way of life.Trouble came to the two friends.

Antonapoulos was not ill any more, but a change had come in him. He was irritable and no longer content to spend the evenings quietly in their home.When he would wish to go out Singer followed along close behind him.Antonapoulos would go into a restaurant, and while they sat at the table he slyly put lumps of sugar, or a pepper-shaker, or pieces of silverware in his pocket.Singer always paid for what he took and there was no disturbance.At home he scolded Antonapoulos, but the big Greek only looked at him with a bland smile.

The months went on and these habits of Antonapoulos grew worse. One day at noon he walked calmly out of the fruit store of his cousin and urinated in public against the wall of the First National Bank Building across the street.At times he would meet people on the sidewalk whose faces did not please him, and he would bump into these persons and push at them with his elbows and stomach.He walked into a store one day and hauled out a floor lamp without paying for it, and another time he tried to take an electric train he had seen in a showcase.

For Singer this was a time of great distress. He was continually marching Antonapoulos down to the courthouse during lunch hour to settle these infringements of the law.Singer became very familiar with the procedure of the courts and he was in a constant state of agitation.The money he had saved in the bank was spent for bail and fines.All of his efforts and money were used to keep his friend out of jail because of such charges as theft, committing public indecencies, and assault and battery.

The Greek cousin for whom Antonapoulos worked did not enter into these troubles at all. Charles Parker（for that was the name this cousin had taken）let Antonapoulos stay on at the store, but he watched him always with his pale, tight face and he made no effort to help him.Singer had a strange feeling about Charles Parker.He began to dislike him.

Singer lived in continual turmoil and worry. But Antonapoulos was always bland, and no matter what happened the gentle, flaccid smile was still on his face.In all the years before it had seemed to Singer that there was something very subtle and wise in this smile of his friend.He had never known just how much Antonapoulos understood and what he was thinking.Now in the big Greek's expression Singer thought that he could detect something sly and joking.He would shake his friend by the shoulders until he was very tired and explain things over and over with his hands.But nothing did any good.

All of Singer's money was gone and he had to borrow from the jeweler for whom he worked. On one occasion he was unable to pay bail for his friend and Antonapoulos spent the night in jail.When Singer came to get him out the next day he was very sulky.He did not want to leave.He had enjoyed his dinner of sowbelly and cornbread with syrup poured over it.And the new sleeping arrangements and his cellmates pleased him.

They had lived so much alone that Singer had no one to help him in his distress. Antonapoulos let nothing disturb him or cure him of his habits.At home he sometimes cooked the new dish he had eaten in the jail, and on the streets there was never any knowing just what he would do.

And then the final trouble came to Singer.

One afternoon he had come to meet Antonapoulos at the fruit store when Charles Parker handed him a letter. The letter explained that Charles Parker had made arrangements for his cousin to be taken to the state insane asylum two hundred miles away.Charles Parker had used his influence in the town and the details were already settled.Antonapoulos was to leave and to be admitted into the asylum the next week.

Singer read the letter several times, and for a while he could not think. Charles Parker was talking to him across the counter, but he did not even try to read his lips and understand.At last Singer wrote on the little pad he always carried in his pocket：

You cannot do this.Antonapoulos must stay with me.

Charles Parker shook his head excitedly. He did not know much American.“None of your business，”he kept saying over and over.

Singer knew that everything was finished. The Greek was afraid that some day he might be responsible for his cousin.Charles Parker did not know much about the American language—but he understood the American dollar very well, and he had used his money and influence to admit his cousin to the asylum without delay.

There was nothing Singer could do.

The next week was full of feverish activity. He talked and talked.And although his hands never paused to rest he could not tell all that he had to say.He wanted to talk to Antonapoulos of all the thoughts that had ever been in his mind and heart, but there was not time.His gray eyes glittered and his quick, intelligent face expressed great strain.Antonapoulos watched him drowsily, and his friend did not know just what he really understood.

Then came the day when Antonapoulos must leave. Singer brought out his own suitcase and very carefully packed the best of their joint possessions.Antonapoulos made himself a lunch to eat during the journey.In the late afternoon they walked arm in arm down the street for the last time together.It was a chilly afternoon in late November, and little huffs of breath showed in the air before them.

Charles Parker was to travel with his cousin, but he stood apart from them at the station. Antonapoulos crowded into the bus and settled himself with elaborate preparations on one of the front seats.Singer watched him from the window and his hands began desperately to talk for the last time with his friend.But Antonapoulos was so busy checking over the various items in his lunch box that for a while he paid no attention.Just before the bus pulled away from the curb he turned to Singer and his smile was very bland and remote—as though already they were many miles apart.

The weeks that followed didn't seem real at all. All day Singer worked over his bench in the back of the jewelry store, and then at night he returned to the house alone.More than anything he wanted to sleep.As soon as he came home from work he would lie on his cot and try to doze awhile.Dreams came to him when he lay there half-asleep.And in all of them Antonapoulos was there.His hands would jerk nervously, for in his dreams he was talking to his friend and Antonapoulos was watching him.

Singer tried to think of the time before he had ever known his friend. He tried to recount to himself certain things that had happened when he was young.But none of these things he tried to remember seemed real.

There was one particular fact that he remembered, but it was not at all important to him. Singer recalled that, although he had been deaf since he was an infant, he had not always been a real mute.He was left an orphan very young and placed in an institution for the deaf.He had learned to talk with his hands and to read.Before he was nine years old he could talk with one hand in the American way—and also could employ both of his hands after the method of Europeans.He had learned to follow the movements of people's lips and to understand what they said.Then finally he had been taught to speak.

At the school he was thought very intelligent. He learned the lessons before the rest of the pupils.But he could never become used to speaking with his lips.It was not natural to him, and his tongue felt like a whale in his mouth.From the blank expression on people's faces to whom he talked in this way he felt that his voice must be like the sound of some animal or that there was something disgusting in his speech.It was painful for him to try to talk with his mouth, but his hands were always ready to shape the words he wished to say.When he was twenty-two he had come South to this town from Chicago and he met Antonapoulos immediately.Since that time he had never spoken with his mouth again, because with his friend there was no need for this.

Nothing seemed real except the ten years with Antonapoulos. In his half-dreams he saw his friend very vividly, and when he awakened a great aching loneliness would be in him.Occasionally he would pack up a box for Antonapoulos, but he never received any reply.And so the months passed in this empty, dreaming way.

In the spring a change came over Singer. He could not sleep and his body was very restless.At evening he would walk monotonously around the room, unable to work off a new feeling of energy.If he rested at all it was only during a few hours before dawn—then he would drop bluntly into a sleep that lasted until the morning light struck suddenly beneath his opening eyelids like a scimitar.

He began spending his evenings walking around the town. He could no longer stand the rooms where Antonapoulos had lived, and he rented a place in a shambling boarding-house not far from the center of the town.

He ate his meals at a restaurant only two blocks away. This restaurant was at the very end of the long main street, and the name of the place was the New York Café.The first day he glanced over the menu quickly and wrote a short note and handed it to the proprietor.

Each morning for breakfast I want an egg, toast, and coffee—$0.15

For lunch I want soup（any kind），a meat sandwich, and milk—$0.25

Please bring me at dinner three vegetables（any kind but cabbage），fish or meat, and a glass of beer—$0.35

Thank you.

The proprietor read the note and gave him an alert, tactful glance. He was a hard man of middle height, with a beard so dark and heavy that the lower part of his face looked as though it were molded of iron.He usually stood in the corner by the cash register, his arms folded over his chest, quietly observing all that went on around him.Singer came to know this man's face very well, for he ate at one of his tables three times a day.

Each evening the mute walked alone for hours in the street. Sometimes the nights were cold with the sharp, wet winds of March and it would be raining heavily.But to him this did not matter.His gait was agitated and he always kept his hands stuffed tight into the pockets of his trousers.Then as the weeks passed the days grew warm and languorous.His agitation gave way gradually to exhaustion and there was a look about him of deep calm.In his face there came to be a brooding peace that is seen most often in the faces of the very sorrowful or the very wise.But still he wandered through the streets of the town, always silent and alone.

2

On a black, sultry night in early summer Biff Brannon stood behind the cash register of the New York Café.It was twelve o’clock.Outside the street lights had already been turned off, so that the light from the café　made a sharp, yellow rectangle on the sidewalk.The street was deserted, but inside the café　there were half a dozen customers drinking beer or Santa Lucia wine or whiskey.Biff waited stolidly, his elbow resting on the counter and his thumb mashing the tip of his long nose.His eyes were intent.He watched especially a short, squat man in overalls who had become drunk and boisterous.Now and then his gaze passed on to the mute who sat by himself at one of the middle tables, or to others of the customers before the counter.But he always turned back to the drunk in overalls.The hour grew later and Biff continued to wait silently behind the counter.Then at last he gave the restaurant a final survey and went toward the door at the back which led upstairs.

Quietly he entered the room at the top of the stairs. It was dark inside and he walked with caution.After he had gone a few paces his toe struck something hard and he reached down and felt for the handle of a suitcase on the floor.He had only been in the room a few seconds and was about to leave when the light was turned on.

Alice sat up in the rumpled bed and looked at him.“What you doing with that suitcase?”she asked.“Can't you get rid of that lunatic without giving him back what he's already drunk up?”

“Wake up and go down yourself. Call the cop and let him get soused on the chain gang with cornbread and peas.Go to it, Misses Brannon.”

“I will all right if he's down there tomorrow. But you leave that bag alone.It don't belong to that sponger any more.”

“I know spongers, and Blount's not one，”Biff said.“Myself—I don't know so well. But I'm not that kind of a thief.”

Calmly Biff put down the suitcase on the steps outside. The air was not so stale and sultry in the room as it was downstairs.He decided to stay for a short while and douse his face with cold water before going back.

“I told you already what I'll do if you don't get rid of that fellow for good tonight. In the daytime he takes them naps at the back, and then at night you feed him dinners and beer.For a week now he hasn't paid one cent.And all his wild talking and carrying-on will ruin any decent trade.”

“You don't know people and you don't know real business，”Biff said.“The fellow in question first came in here twelve days ago and he was a stranger in the town. The first week he gave us twenty dollars'worth of trade.Twenty at the minimum.”

“And since then on credit，”Alice said. Five days on credit, and so drunk it's a disgrace to the business.And besides, he's nothing but a bum and a freak.”

“I like freaks，”Biff said.

“I reckon you do！I just reckon you certainly ought to, Mister Brannon—being as you're one yourself.”

He rubbed his bluish chin and paid her no attention. For the first fifteen years of their married life they had called each other just plain Biff and Alice.Then in one of their quarrels they had begun calling each other Mister and Misses, and since then they had never made it up enough to change it.

“I'm just warning you he'd better not be there when I come down tomorrow.”

Biff went into the bathroom, and after he had bathed his face he decided that he would have time for a shave. His beard was black and heavy as though it had grown for three days.He stood before the mirror and rubbed his cheek meditatively.He was sorry he had talked to Alice.With her, silence was better.Being around that woman always made him different from his real self.It made him tough and small and common as she was.Biff's eyes were cold and staring, half-concealed by the cynical droop of his eyelids.On the fifth finger of his calloused hand there was a woman's wedding ring.The door was open behind him, and in the mirror he could see Alice lying in the bed.

“Listen，”he said.“The trouble with you is that you don't have any real kindness. Not but one woman I've ever known had this real kindness I'm talking about.”

“Well, I've known you to do things no man in this world would be proud of. I've known you to—”

“Or maybe it's curiosity I mean. You don't ever see or notice anything important that goes on.You never watch and think and try to figure anything out.Maybe that's the biggest difference between you and me, after all.”

Alice was almost asleep again, and through the mirror he watched her with detachment. There was no distinctive point about her on which he could fasten his attention, and his gaze glided from her pale brown hair to the stumpy outline of her feet beneath the cover.The soft curves of her face led to the roundness of her hips and thighs.When he was away from her there was no one feature that stood out in his mind and he remembered her as a complete, unbroken figure.

“The enjoyment of a spectacle is something you have never known，”he said.

Her voice was tired.“That fellow downstairs is a spectacle, all right, and a circus too. But I'm through putting up with him.”

“Hell, the man don't mean anything to me. He's no relative or buddy of mine.But you don't know what it is to store up a whole lot of details and then come upon something real.”He turned on the hot water and quickly began to shave.

It was the morning of May　15，yes, that Jake Blount had come in. He had noticed him immediately and watched.The man was short, with heavy shoulders like beams.He had a small ragged mustache, and beneath this his lower lip looked as though it had been stung by a wasp.There were many things about the fellow that seemed contrary.His head was very large and well-shaped, but his neck was soft and slender as a boy's.The mustache looked false, as if it had been stuck on for a costume party and would fall off if he talked too fast.It made him seem almost middle-aged, although his face with its high, smooth forehead and wide-open eyes was young.His hands were huge, stained, and calloused, and he was dressed in a cheap white-linen suit.There was something very funny about the man, yet at the same time another feeling would not let you laugh.

He ordered a pint of liquor and drank it straight in half an hour. Then he sat at one of the booths and ate a big chicken dinner.Later he read a book and drank beer.That was the beginning.And although Biff had noticed Blount very carefully he would never have guessed about the crazy things that happened later.Never had he seen a man change so many times in twelve days.Never had he seen a fellow drink so much, stay drunk so long.

Biff pushed up the end of his nose with his thumb and shaved his upper lip. He was finished and his face seemed cooler.Alice was asleep when he went through the bedroom on the way downstairs.

The suitcase was heavy. He carried it to the front of the restaurant, behind the cash register, where he usually stood each evening.Methodically he glanced around the place.A few customers had left and the room was not so crowded, but the set-up was the same.The deaf-mute still drank coffee by himself at one of the middle tables.The drunk had not stopped talking.He was not addressing anyone around him in particular, nor was anyone listening.When he had come into the place that evening he wore those blue overalls instead of the filthy linen suit he had been wearing the twelve days.His socks were gone and his ankles were scratched and caked with mud.

Alertly Biff picked up fragments of his monologue. The fellow seemed to be talking some queer kind of politics again.Last night he had been talking about places he had been—about Texas and Oklahoma and the Carolinas.Once he had got on the subject of cat-houses, and afterward his jokes got so raw he had to be hushed up with beer.But most of the time nobody was sure just what he was saying.Talk—talk—talk.The words came out of his throat like a cataract.And the thing was that the accent he used was always changing, the kinds of words he used.Sometimes he talked like a linthead and sometimes like a professor.He would use words a foot long and then slip up on his grammar.It was hard to tell what kind of folks he had or what part of the country he was from.He was always changing.Thoughtfully Biff fondled the tip of his nose.There was no connection.Yet connection usually went with brains.This man had a good mind, all right, but he went from one thing to another without any reason behind it at all.He was like a man thrown off his track by something.

Biff leaned his weight on the counter and began to peruse the evening newspaper. The headlines told of a decision by the Board of Aldermen, after four months'deliberation, that the local budget could not afford traffic lights at certain dangerous intersections of the town.The left column reported on the war in the Orient.Biff read them both with equal attention.As his eyes followed the print the rest of his senses were on the alert to the various commotions that went on around him.When he had finished the articles he still stared down at the newspaper with his eyes half-closed.He felt nervous.The fellow was a problem, and before morning he would have to make some sort of settlement with him.Also, he felt without knowing why that something of importance would happen tonight.The fellow could not keep on forever.

Biff sensed that someone was standing in the entrance and he raised his eyes quickly. A gangling, towheaded youngster, a girl of about twelve, stood looking in the doorway.She was dressed in khaki shorts, a blue shirt, and tennis shoes—so that at first glance she was like a very young boy.Biff pushed aside the paper when he saw her, and smiled when she came up to him.

“Hello, Mick. Been to the Girl Scouts?”

“No，”she said.“I don't belong to them.”

From the corner of his eye he noticed that the drunk slammed his fist down on a table and turned away from the men to whom he had been talking. Biff's voice roughened as he spoke to the youngster before him.

“Your folks know you're out after midnight?”

“It's O. K.There's a gang of kids playing out late on our block tonight.”

He had never seen her come into the place with anyone her own age. Several years ago she had always tagged behind her older brother.The Kellys were a good-sized family in numbers.Later she would come in pulling a couple of snotty babies in a wagon.But if she wasn't nursing or trying to keep up with the bigger ones, she was by herself.Now the kid stood there seeming not to be able to make up her mind what she wanted.She kept pushing back her damp, whitish hair with the palm of her hand.

“I'd like a pack of cigarettes, please. The cheapest kind.”

Biff started to speak, hesitated, and then reached his hand inside the counter. Mick brought out a handkerchief and began untying the knot in the corner where she kept her money.As she gave the knot a jerk the change clattered to the floor and rolled toward Blount, who stood muttering to himself.For a moment he stared in a daze at the coins, but before the kid could go after them he squatted down with concentration and picked up the money.He walked heavily to the counter and stood jiggling the two pennies, the nickel, and the dime in his palm.

“Seventeen cents for cigarettes now?”

Biff waited, and Mick looked from one of them to the other. The drunk stacked the money into a little pile on the counter, still protecting it with his big, dirty hand.Slowly he picked up one penny and flipped it down.

“Five mills for the crackers who grew the weed and five for the dupes who rolled it，”he said.“A cent for you, Biff.”Then he tried to focus his eyes so that he could read the mottoes on the nickel and dime. He kept fingering the two coins and moving them around in a circle.At last he pushed them away.“And that's a humble homage to liberty.To democracy and tyranny.To freedom and piracy.”

Calmly Biff picked up the money and rang it into the till. Mick looked as though she wanted to hang around awhile.She took in the drunk with one long gaze, and then she turned her eyes to the middle of the room where the mute sat at his table alone.After a moment Blount also glanced now and then in the same direction.The mute sat silently over his glass of beer, idly drawing on the table with the end of a burnt matchstick.

Jake Blount was the first to speak.“It's funny, but I been seeing that fellow in my sleep for the past three or four nights. He won't leave me alone.If you ever noticed, he never seems to say anything.”

It was seldom that Biff ever discussed one customer with another.“No, he don't，”he answered noncommittally.

“It's funny.”

Mick shifted her weight from one foot to the other and fitted the package of cigarettes into the pocket of her shorts.“It's not funny if you know anything about him，”she said.“Mister Singer lives with us. He rooms in our house.”

“Is that so?”Biff asked.“I declare—I didn't know that.”

Mick walked toward the door and answered him without looking around.“Sure. He's been with us three months now.”

Biff unrolled his shirt-sleeves and then folded them up carefully again. He did not take his eyes away from Mick as she left the restaurant.And even after she had been gone several minutes he still fumbled with his shirt-sleeves and stared at the empty doorway.Then he locked his arms across his chest and turned back to the drunk again.

Blount leaned heavily on the counter. His brown eyes were wet-looking and wide open with a dazed expression.He needed a bath so badly that he stank like a goat.There were dirty beads on his sweaty neck and an oil stain on his face.His lips were thick and red and his brown hair was matted on his forehead.His overalls were too short in the body and he kept pulling at the crotch of them.

“Man, you ought to know better，”Biff said finally.“You can't go around like this. Why, I'm surprised you haven't been picked up for vagrancy.You ought to sober up.You need washing and your hair needs cutting.Motherogod！You're not fit to walk around amongst people.”

Blount scowled and bit his lower lip.

“Now, don't take offense and get your dander up. Do what I tell you.Go back in the kitchen and tell the colored boy to give you a big pan of hot water.Tell Willie to give you a towel and plenty of soap and wash yourself good.Then eat you some milk toast and open up your suitcase and put you on a clean shirt and a pair of britches that fit you.Then tomorrow you can start doing whatever you're going to do and working wherever you mean to work and get straightened out.”

“You know what you can do，”Blount said drunkenly. You can just—”

“All right，”Biff said very quietly.“No, I can't. Now you just behave yourself.”

Biff went to the end of the counter and returned with two glasses of draught beer. The drunk picked up his glass so clumsily that beer slopped down on his hands and messed the counter.Biff sipped his portion with careful relish.He regarded Blount steadily with half-closed eyes.Blount was not a freak, although when you first saw him he gave you that impression.It was like something was deformed about him—but when you looked at him closely each part of him was normal and as it ought to be.Therefore if this difference was not in the body it was probably in the mind.He was like a man who had served a term in prison or had been to Harvard College or had lived for a long time with foreigners in South America.He was like a person who had been somewhere that other people are not likely to go or had done something that others are not apt to do.

Biff cocked his head to one side and said，“Where are you from?”

“Nowhere.”

“Now, you have to be born somewhere. North Carolina—Tennessee—Alabama—some place.”

Blount's eyes were dreamy and unfocused.“Carolina，”he said.

“I can tell you've been around，”Biff hinted delicately.

But the drunk was not listening. He had turned from the counter and was staring out at the dark, empty street.After a moment he walked to the door with loose, uncertain steps.

“Adios，”he called back.

Biff was alone again and he gave the restaurant one of his quick, thorough surveys. It was past one in the morning, and there were only four or five customers in the room.The mute still sat by himself at the middle table.Biff stared at him idly and shook the few remaining drops of beer around in the bottom of his glass.Then he finished his drink in one slow swallow and went back to the newspaper spread out on the counter.

This time he could not keep his mind on the words before him. He remembered Mick.He wondered if he should have sold her the pack of cigarettes and if it were really harmful for kids to smoke.He thought of the way Mick narrowed her eyes and pushed back the bangs of her hair with the palm of her hand.He thought of her hoarse, boyish voice and of her habit of hitching up her khaki shorts and swaggering like a cowboy in the picture show.A feeling of tenderness came in him.He was uneasy.

Restlessly Biff turned his attention to Singer. The mute sat with his hands in his pockets and the half-finished glass of beer before him had become warm and stagnant.He would offer to treat Singer to a slug of whiskey before he left.What he had said to Alice was true—he did like freaks.He had a special friendly feeling for sick people and cripples.Whenever somebody with a harelip or T.B.came into the place he would set him up to beer.Or if the customer were a hunchback or a bad cripple, then it would be whiskey on the house.There was one fellow who had had his peter and his left leg blown off in a boiler explosion, and whenever he came to town there was a free pint waiting for him.And if Singer were a drinking kind of man he could get liquor at half price any time he wanted it.Biff nodded to himself.Then neatly he folded his newspaper and put it under the counter along with several others.At the end of the week he would take them all back to the storeroom behind the kitchen, where he kept a complete file of the evening newspapers that dated back without a break for twenty-one years.

At two o'clock Blount entered the restaurant again. He brought in with him a tall Negro man carrying a black bag.The drunk tried to bring him up to the counter for a drink, but the Negro left as soon as he realized why he had been led inside.Biff recognized him as a Negro doctor who had practiced in the town ever since he could remember.He was related in some way to young Willie back in the kitchen.Before he left Biff saw him turn on Blount with a look of quivering hatred.

The drunk just stood there.

“Don't you know you can't bring no nigger in a place where white men drink?”someone asked him.

Biff watched this happening from a distance. Blount was very angry, and now it could easily be seen how drunk he was.

“I'm part nigger myself，”he called out as a challenge.

Biff watched him alertly and the place was quiet. With his thick nostrils and the rolling whites of his eyes it looked a little as though he might be telling the truth.

“I'm part nigger and wop and bohunk and chink. All of those.”

There was laughter.

“And I'm Dutch and Turkish and Japanese and American.”He walked in zigzags around the table where the mute drank his coffee. His voice was loud and cracked.“I'm one who knows.I'm a stranger in a strange land.”

“Quiet down，”Biff said to him.

Blount paid no attention to anyone in the place except the mute. They were both looking at each other.The mute's eyes were cold and gentle as a cat's and all his body seemed to listen.The drunk man was in a frenzy.

“You're the only one in this town who catches what I mean，”Blount said.“For two days now　1　been talking to you in my mind because I know you understand the things I want to mean.”

Some people in a booth were laughing because without knowing it the drunk had picked out a deaf-mute to try to talk with. Biff watched the two men with little darting glances and listened attentively.

Blount sat down to the table and leaned over close to Singer.“There are those who know and those who don't know. And for every ten thousand who don't know there's only one who knows.That's the miracle of all time—the fact that these millions know so much but don't know this.It’s like in the fifteenth century when everybody believed the world was flat and only Columbus and a few other fellows knew the truth.But it’s different in that it took talent to figure that the earth is round.While this truth is so obvious it’s a miracle of all history that people don’t know.You savvy.”

Biff rested his elbows on the counter and looked at Blount with curiosity.“Know what?”he asked.

“Don't listen to him，”Blount said.“Don't mind that flat-footed, blue-jawed, nosy bastard. For you see, when us people who know run into each other that's an event.It almost never happens.Sometimes we meet each other and neither guesses that the other is one who knows.That's a bad thing.It's happened to me a lot of times.But you see there are so few of us.”

“Masons?”Biff asked.

“Shut up, you！Else I'll snatch your arm off and beat you black with it，”Blount bawled. He hunched over close to the mute and his voice dropped to a drunken whisper.“And how come?Why has this miracle of ignorance endured?Because of one thing.A conspiracy.A vast and insidious conspiracy.Obscurantism.”

The men in the booth were still laughing at the drunk who was trying to hold a conversation with the mute. Only Biff was serious.He wanted to ascertain if the mute really understood what was said to him.The fellow nodded frequently and his face seemed contemplative.He was only slow—that was all.Blount began to crack a few jokes along with this talk about knowing.The mute never smiled until several seconds after the funny remark had been made；then when the talk was gloomy again the smile still hung on his face a little too long.The fellow was downright uncanny.People felt themselves watching him even before they knew that there was anything different about him.His eyes made a person think that he heard things nobody else had ever heard, that he knew things no one had ever guessed before.He did not seem quite human.

Jake Blount leaned across the table and the words came out as though a dam inside him had broken. Biff could not understand him any more.Blount's tongue was so heavy with drink and he talked at such a violent pace that the sounds were all shaken up together.Biff wondered where he would go when Alice turned him out of the place.And in the morning she would do it, too—like she said.

Biff yawned wanly, patting his open mouth with his fingertips until his jaw had relaxed. It was almost three o'clock, the most stagnant hour in the day or night.

The mute was patient. He had been listening to Blount for almost an hour.Now he began to look at the clock occasionally.Blount did not notice this and went on without a pause.At last he stopped to roll a cigarette, and then the mute nodded his head in the direction of the clock, smiled in that hidden way of his, and got up from the table.His hands stayed stuffed in his pockets as always.He went out quickly.

Blount was so drunk that he did not know what had happened. He had never even caught on to the fact that the mute made no answers.He began to look around the place with his mouth open and his eyes rolling and fuddled.A red vein stood out on his forehead and he began to hit the table angrily with his fists.His bout could not last much longer now.

“Come on over，”Biff said kindly.“Your friend has gone.”

The fellow was still hunting for Singer. He had never seemed really drunk like that before.He had an ugly look.

“I have something for you over here and I want to speak with you a minute，”Biff coaxed.

Blount pulled himself up from the table and walked with big, loose steps toward the street again.

Biff leaned against the wall. In and out—in and out.After all, it was none of his business.The room was very empty and quiet.The minutes lingered.Wearily he let his head sag forward.All motion seemed slowly to be leaving the room.The counter, faces, the booths and tables, the radio in the corner, whirring fans on the ceiling—all seemed to become very faint and still.

He must have dozed. A hand was shaking his elbow.His wits came back to him slowly and he looked up to see what was wanted.Willie, the colored boy in the kitchen, stood before him dressed in his cap and his long white apron.Willie stammered because he was excited about whatever he was trying to say.

“And so he were　1-1-lamming his fist against this here brick w-w-wall.”

“What's that?”

“Right down one of them alleys two d-d-doors away.”

Biff straightened his slumped shoulders and arranged his tie.“What?”

“And they means to bring him in here and they liable to pile in any minute—”

“Willie，”Biff said patiently.“Start at the beginning and let me get this straight.”

“It this here short white man with the m-m-mustache.”

“Mr. Blount.Yes”

“Well—I didn't see how it commenced. I were standing in the back door when I heard this here commotion.Sound like a big fight in the alley.So I r-r-run to see.And this here white man had just gone hog wild.He were butting his head against the side of this brick wall and hitting with his fists.He were cussing and fighting like I never seen a white man fight before.With just this here wall.He liable to broken his own head the way he were carrying on.Then two white mens who had heard the commotion come up and stand around and look—”

“So what happened?”

“Well—you know this here dumb gentleman—hands in pockets—this here—”

“Mr. Singer.”

And he come along and just stood looking around to see what it were all about. And Mr.B-B-Blount seen him and commenced to talk and holler.And then all of a sudden he fallen down on the ground.Maybe he done really busted his head open.A p-p-p-police come up and somebody done told him Mr.Blount been staying here.”

Biff bowed his head and organized the story he had just heard into a neat pattern. He rubbed his nose and thought for a minute.

“They liable to pile in here any minute.”Willie went to the door and looked down the street.“Here they all come now. They having to drag him.”

A dozen onlookers and a policeman all tried to crowd into the restaurant. Outside a couple of whores stood looking in through the front window.It was always funny how many people could crowd in from nowhere when anything out of the ordinary happened.

“No use creating any more disturbance than necessary，”Biff said. He looked at the policeman who supported the drunk.“The rest of them might as well clear out.”

The policeman put the drunk in a chair and hustled the little crowd into the street again. Then he turned to Biff：“Somebody said he was staying here with you.”

“No. But he might as well be，”Biff said.

“Want me to take him with me?”

Biff considered.“He won't get into any more trouble tonight. Of course I can't be responsible—but I think this will calm him down.”

“O. K.I'll drop back in again before I knock off.”

Biff, Singer, and Jake Blount were left alone. For the first time since he had been brought in, Biff turned his attention to the drunk man.It seemed that Blount had hurt his jaw very badly.He was slumped down on the table with his big hand over his mouth, swaying backward and forward.There was a gash in his head and the blood ran from his temple.His knuckles were skinned raw, and he was so filthy that he looked as if he had been pulled by the scruff of the neck from a sewer.All the juice had spurted out of him and he was completely collapsed.The mute sat at the table across from him, taking it all in with his gray eyes.

Then Biff saw that Blount had not hurt his jaw, but he was holding his hand over his mouth because his lips were trembling. The tears began to roll down his grimy face.Now and then he glanced sideways at Biff and Singer, angry that they should see him cry.It was embarrassing.Biff shrugged his shoulders at the mute and raised his eyebrows with a what-to-do?expression.Singer cocked his head on one side.

Biff was in a quandary. Musingly he wondered just how he should manage the situation.He was still trying to decide when the mute turned over the menu and began to write.

If you cannot think of any place for him to go he can go home with me.First some soup and coffee would be good for him.

With relief Biff nodded vigorously.

On the table he placed three special plates of the last evening meal, two bowls of soup, coffee, and dessert. But Blount would not eat.He would not take his hand away from his mouth, and it was as though his lips were some very secret part of himself which was being exposed.His breath came in ragged sobs and his big shoulders jerked nervously.Singer pointed to one dish after the other, but Blount just sat with his hand over his mouth and shook his head.

Biff enunciated slowly so that the mute could see.“The jitters—”he said conversationally.

The steam from the soup kept floating up into Blount's face, and after a little while he reached shakily for his spoon. He drank the soup and ate part of his dessert.His thick, heavy lips still trembled and he bowed his head far down over his plate.

Biff noted this. He was thinking that in nearly every person there was some special physical part kept always guarded.With the mute his hands.The kid Mick picked at the front of her blouse to keep the cloth from rubbing the new, tender nipples beginning to come out on her breast.With Alice it was her hair；she used never to let him sleep with her when he rubbed oil in his scalp.And with himself?

Lingeringly Biff turned the ring on his little finger. Anyway he knew what it was not.Not.Any more.A sharp line cut into his forehead.His hand in his pocket moved nervously toward his genitals.He began whistling a song and got up from the table.Funny to spot it in other people, though.

They helped Blount to his feet. He teetered weakly.He was not crying any more, but he seemed to be brooding on something shameful and sullen.He walked in the direction he was led.Biff brought out the suitcase from behind the counter and explained to the mute about it.Singer looked as though he could not be surprised at anything.

Biff went with them to the entrance.“Buck up and keep your nose clean，”he said to Blount.

The black night sky was beginning to lighten and turn a deep blue with the new morning. There were but a few weak, silvery stars.The street was empty, silent, almost cool.Singer carried the suitcase with his left hand, and with his free hand he supported Blount.He nodded good-bye to Biff and they started off together down the sidewalk.Biff stood watching them.After they had gone half a block away only their black forms showed in the blue darkness—the mute straight and firm and the broad-shouldered, stumbling Blount holding on to him.When he could see them no longer, Biff waited for a moment and examined the sky.The vast depth of it fascinated and oppressed him.He rubbed his forehead and went back into the sharply lighted restaurant.

He stood behind the cash register, and his face contracted and hardened as he tried to recall the things that had happened during the night. He had the feeling that he wanted to explain something to himself.He recalled the incidents in tedious detail and was still puzzled.

The door opened and closed several times as a sudden spurt of customers began to come in. The night was over.Willie stacked some of the chairs up on the tables and mopped at the floor.He was ready to go home and was singing.Willie was lazy.In the kitchen he was always stopping to play for a while on the harmonica he carried around with him.Now he mopped the floor with sleepy strokes and hummed his lonesome Negro music steadily.

The place was still not crowded—it was the hour when men who have been up all night meet those who are freshly wakened and ready to start a new day. The sleepy waitress was serving both beer and coffee.There was no noise or conversation, for each person seemed to be alone.The mutual distrust between the men who were just awakened and those who were ending a long night gave everyone a feeling of estrangement.

The bank building across the street was very pale in the dawn. Then gradually its white brick walls grew more distinct.When at last the first shafts of the rising sun began to brighten the street, Biff gave the place one last survey and went upstairs.

Noisily he rattled the doorknob as he entered so that Alice would be disturbed.“Motherogod！”he said.“What a night！”

Alice awoke with caution. She lay on the rumpled bed like a sulky cat and stretched herself.The room was drab in the fresh, hot morning sun, and a pair of silk stockings hung limp and withered from the cord of the window-shade.

“Is that drunk fool still hanging around downstairs?”she demanded.

Biff took off his shirt and examined the collar to see if it were clean enough to be worn again.“Go down and see for yourself. I told you nobody will hinder you from kicking him out.”

Sleepily Alice reached down and picked up a Bible, the blank side of a menu, and a Sunday-School book from the floor beside the bed. She rustled through the tissue pages of the Bible until she reached a certain passage and began reading, pronouncing the words aloud with painful concentration.It was Sunday, and she was preparing the weekly lesson for her class of boys in the Junior Department of her church.“Now as he walked by the sea of Galilee, he saw Simon and Andrew his brother casting a net into the sea：for they were fishers.And Jesus said unto them，‘Come ye after me, and I will make you to become fishers of men.'And straightway they forsook their nets, and followed him.”

Biff went into the bathroom to wash himself. The silky murmuring continued as Alice studied aloud.He listened.“……and in the morning, rising up a great while before day, He went out, and departed into a solitary place, and there prayed.And Simon and they that were with Him followed after Him.And when they had found Him, they said unto Him，‘All men seek for Thee.'”

She had finished. Biff let the words revolve again gently inside him.He tried to separate the actual words from the sound of Alice's voice as she had spoken them.He wanted to remember the passage as his mother used to read it when he was a boy.With nostalgia he glanced down at the wedding ring on his fifth finger that had once been hers.He wondered again how she would have felt about his giving up church and religion.

“The lesson for today is about the gathering of the disciples，”Alice said to herself in preparation.“And the text is，‘All men seek for Thee.'”

Abruptly Biff roused himself from meditation and turned on the water spigot at full force. He stripped off his undervest and began to wash himself.Always he was scrupulously clean from the belt upward.Every morning he soaped his chest and arms and neck and feet—and about twice during the season he got into the bathtub and cleaned all of his parts.

Biff stood by the bed, waiting impatiently for Alice to get up. From the window he saw that the day would be windless and burning hot.Alice had finished reading the lesson.She still lay lazily across the bed, although she knew that he was waiting.A calm, sullen anger rose in him.He chuckled ironically.Then he said with bitterness：“If you like I can sit and read the paper awhile.But I wish you would let me sleep now.”

Alice began dressing herself and Biff made up the bed. Deftly he reversed the sheets in all possible ways, putting the top one on the bottom, and turning them over and upside down.When the bed was smoothly made he waited until Alice had left the room before he slipped off his trousers and crawled inside.His feet jutted out from beneath the cover and his wiry-haired chest was very dark against the pillow.He was glad he had not told Alice about what had happened to the drunk.He had wanted to talk to somebody about it, because maybe if he told all the facts out loud he could put his finger on the thing that puzzled him.The poor son-of-a-bitch talking and talking and not ever getting anybody to understand what he meant.Not knowing himself, most likely.And the way he gravitated around the deaf-mute and picked him out and tried to make him a free present of everything in him.

Why?

Because in some men it is in them to give up everything personal at some time, before it ferments and poisons—throw it to some human being or some human idea. They have to.In some men it is in them—The text is“All men seek for Thee.”Maybe that was why—maybe—He was a Chinaman, the fellow had said.And a nigger and a wop and a Jew.And if he believed it hard enough maybe it was so.Every person and everything he said he was—

Biff stretched both of his arms outward and crossed his naked feet. His face was older in the morning light, with the closed, shrunken eyelids and the heavy, iron-like beard on his cheeks and jaw.Gradually his mouth softened and relaxed.The hard, yellow rays of the sun came in through the window so that the room was hot and bright.Biff turned wearily and covered his eyes with his hands.And he was nobody but—Bartholomew—old Biff with two fists and a quick tongue—Mister Brannon—by himself.

3

The sun woke Mick early, although she had stayed out mighty late the night before. It was too hot even to drink coffee for breakfast, so she had ice water with syrup in it and cold biscuits.She messed around the kitchen for a while and then went out on the front porch to read the funnies.She had thought maybe Mister Singer would be reading the paper on the porch like he did most Sunday mornings.But Mister Singer was not there, and later on her Dad said he came in very late the night before and had company in his room.She waited for Mister Singer a long time.All the other boarders came down except him.Finally she went back in the kitchen and took Ralph out of his high chair and put a clean dress on him and wiped off his face.Then when Bubber got home from Sunday School she was ready to take the kids out.She let Bubber ride in the wagon with Ralph because he was barefooted and the hot sidewalk burned his feet.She pulled the wagon for about eight blocks until they came to the big, new house that was being built.The ladder was still propped against the edge of the roof, and she screwed up nerve and began to climb.

“You mind Ralph，”she called back to Bubber.“Mind the gnats don't sit on his eyelids.”

Five minutes later Mick stood up and held herself very straight. She spread out her arms like wings.This was the place where everybody wanted to stand.The very top.But not many kids could do it.Most of them were scared, for if you lost your grip and rolled off the edge it would kill you.All around were the roofs of other houses and the green tops of trees.On the other side of town were the church steeples and the smokestacks from the mills.The sky was bright blue and hot as fire.The sun made everything on the ground either dizzy white or black.

She wanted to sing. All the songs she knew pushed up toward her throat, but there was no sound.One big boy who had got to the highest part of the roof last week let out a yell and then started hollering out a speech he had learned at High School—“Friends, Romans, Countrymen, Lend me your ears！”There was something about getting to the very top that gave you a wild feeling and made you want to yell or sing or raise up your arms and fly.

She felt the soles of her tennis shoes slipping, and eased herself down so that she straddled the peak of the roof. The house was almost finished.It would be one of the largest buildings in the neighborhood—two stories, with very high ceilings and the steepest roof of any house she had ever seen.But soon the work would all be finished.The carpenters would leave and the kids would have to find another place to play.

She was by herself. No one was around and it was quiet and she could think for a while.She took from the pocket of her shorts the package of cigarettes she had bought the night before.She breathed in the smoke slowly.The cigarette gave her a drunk feeling so that her head seemed heavy and loose on her shoulders, but she had to finish it.

M. K.—That was what she would have written on everything when she was seventeen years old and very famous.She would ride back home in a red-and-white Packard automobile with her initials on the doors.She would have M.K.written in red on her handkerchiefs and underclothes.Maybe she would be a great inventor.She would invent little tiny radios the size of a green pea that people could carry around and stick in their ears.Also flying machines people could fasten on their backs like knapsacks and go zipping all over the world.After that she would be the first one to make a large tunnel through the world to China, and people could go down in big balloons.Those were the first tilings she would invent.They were already planned.

When Mick had finished half of the cigarette she smashed it dead and flipped the butt down the slant of the roof. Then she leaned forward so that her head rested on her arms and began to hum to herself.

It was a funny thing—but nearly all the time there was some kind of piano piece or other music going on in the back of her mind. No matter what she was doing or thinking it was nearly always there.Miss Brown, who boarded with them, had a radio in her room, and all last winter she would sit on the steps every Sunday afternoon and listen in on the programs.Those were probably classical pieces, but they were the ones she remembered best.There was one special fellow's music that made her heart shrink up every time she heard it.Sometimes this fellow's music was like little colored pieces of crystal candy, and other times it was the softest, saddest thing she had ever imagined about.

There was the sudden sound of crying. Mick sat up straight and listened.The wind ruffled the fringe of hair on her forehead and the bright sun made her face white and damp.The whimpering continued, and Mick moved slowly along the sharp-pointed roof on her hands and knees.When she reached the end she leaned forward and lay on her stomach so that her head jutted over the edge and she could see the ground below.

The kids were where she had left them. Bubber was squatting over something on the ground and beside him was a little black, dwarf shadow.Ralph was still tied in the wagon.He was just old enough to sit up, and he held on to the sides of the wagon, with his cap crooked on his head, crying.

“Bubber！”Mick called down.“Find out what that Ralph wants and give it to him.”

Bubber stood up and looked hard into the baby's face.“He don't want nothing.”

“Well, give him a good shake, then.”

Mick climbed back to the place where she had been sitting before. She wanted to think for a long time about two or three certain people, to sing to herself, and to make plans.But that Ralph was still hollering and there wouldn't be any peace for her at all.

Boldly she began to climb down toward the ladder propped against the edge of the roof. The slant was very steep and there were only a few blocks of wood nailed down, very far apart from each other, that the workmen used for footholds.She was dizzy, and her heart beat so hard it made her tremble.Commandingly she talked out loud to herself：“Hold on here with your hands tight and then slide down until your right toe gets a grip there and then stay close and wiggle over to the left.Nerve, Mick, you've got to keep nerve.”

Coming down was the hardest part of any climbing. It took her a long time to reach the ladder and to feel safe again.When she stood on the ground at last she seemed much shorter and smaller and her legs felt for a minute like they would crumple up with her.She hitched her shorts and jerked the belt a notch tighter.Ralph was still crying, but she paid the sound no attention and went into the new, empty house.

Last month they had put a sign out in front saying that no children were allowed on the lot. A gang of kids had been scuffling around inside the rooms one night, and a girl who couldn't see in the dark had run into a room that hadn't been floored and fallen through and broken her leg.She was still at the hospital in a plaster parish cast.Also, another time some tough boys wee-weed all over one of the walls and wrote some pretty bad words.But no matter how many Keep Out signs were put up, they couldn't run kids away until the house had been painted and finished and people had moved in.

The rooms smelled of new wood, and when she walked the soles of her tennis shoes made a flopping sound that echoed through all the house. The air was hot and quiet.She stood still in the middle of the front room for a while, and then she suddenly thought of something.She fished in her pocket and brought out two stubs of chalk—one green and the other red.

Mick drew the big block letters very slowly. At the top she wrote EDISON, and under that she drew the names of DICK TRACY and MUSSOLINI.Then in each corner with the largest letters of all, made with green and outlined in red, she wrote her initials—M.K.When that was done she crossed over to the opposite wall and wrote a very bad word—PUSSY—and beneath that she put her initials, too.

She stood in the middle of the empty room and stared at what she had done. The chalk was still in her hands and she did not feel really satisfied.She was trying to think of the name of this fellow who had written this music she heard over the radio last winter.She had asked a girl at school who owned a piano and took music lessons about him, and the girl asked her teacher.It seemed this fellow was just a kid who had lived in some country in Europe a good while ago.But even if he was just a young kid he had made up all these beautiful pieces for the piano and for the violin and for a band or orchestra too.In her mind she could remember about six different tunes from the pieces of his she had heard.A few of them were kind of quick and tinkling, and another was like that smell in the springtime after a rain.But they all made her somehow sad and excited at the same time.

She hummed one of the tunes, and after a while in the hot, empty house by herself she felt the tears come in her eyes. Her throat got tight and rough and she couldn't sing any more.Quickly she wrote the fellow's name at the very top of the list—MOTSART.

Ralph was tied in the wagon just as she had left him. He sat up quiet and still and his fat little hands held on to the sides.Ralph looked like a little Chinese baby with his square black bangs and his black eyes.The sun was in his face, and that was why he had been hollering.Bubber was nowhere around.When Ralph saw her coming he began tuning up to cry again.She pulled the wagon into the shade by the side of the new house and took from her shirt pocket a blue-colored jelly bean.She stuck the candy in the baby's warm, soft mouth.

“Put that in your pipe and smoke it，”she said to him. In a way it was a waste, because Ralph was still too little to get the real good flavor out of candy.A clean rock would be about the same to him, only the little fool would swallow it.He didn't understand any more about taste than he did about talking.When you said you were so sick and tired of dragging him around you had a good mind to throw him in the river, it was the same to him as if you had been loving him.Nothing much made any difference to him.That was why it was such an awful bore to haul him around.

Mick cupped her hands, clamped them tight together, and blew through the crack between her thumbs. Her cheeks puffed out and at first there was only the sound of air rushing through her fists.Then a high, shrill whistle sounded, and after a few seconds Bubber came out from around the corner of the house.

She rumpled the sawdust out of Bubber's hair and straightened Ralph's cap. This cap was the finest thing Ralph had.It was made out of lace and all embroidered.The ribbon under his chin was blue on one side and white on the other, and over each ear there were big rosettes.His head had got too big for the cap and the embroidery scratched, but she always put it on him when she took him out.Ralph didn't have any real baby carriage like most folks'babies did, or any summer bootees.He had to be dragged around in a tacky old wagon she had got for Christmas three years before.But the fine cap gave him face.

There was nobody on the street, for it was late Sunday morning and very hot. The wagon screeched and rattled.Bubber was barefooted and the sidewalk was so hot it burned his feet.The green oak trees made cool-looking black shadows on the ground, but that was not shade enough.

“Get up in the wagon，”she told Bubber.“And let Ralph sit on your lap.”

“I can walk all right.”

The long summer-time always gave Bubber the colic. He didn't have on a shirt and his ribs were sharp and white.The sun made him pale instead of brown, and his little titties were like blue raisins on his chest.

“I don't mind pulling you，”Mick said.“Get on in.”

“O. K.”

Mick dragged the wagon slowly because she was not in any hurry to get home. She began talking to the kids.But it was really more like saying things to herself than words said to them.

“This is a funny thing—the dreams I've been having lately. It's like I'm swimming.But instead of water I'm pushing out my arms and swimming through great big crowds of people.The crowd is a hundred times bigger than in Kresses store on Saturday afternoon.The biggest crowd in the world.And sometimes I'm yelling and swimming through people, knocking them all down wherever I go—and other times I’m on the ground and people are trompling all over me and my insides are oozing out on the sidewalk.I guess it’s more like a nightmare than a plain dream—”

On Sunday the house was always full of folks because the boarders had visitors. Newspapers rustled and there was cigar smoke, and footsteps always on the stairs.

“Some things you just naturally want to keep private. Not because they are bad, but because you just want them secret.There are two or three things I wouldn't want even you to know about.”

Bubber got out when they came to the corner and helped her lift the wagon down the curb and get it up on the next sidewalk.

“But there's one thing I would give anything for. And that's a piano.If we had a piano I'd practice every single night and learn every piece in the world.That's the thing I want more than anything else.”

They had come to their own home block now. Their house was only a few doors away.It was one of the biggest houses on the whole north side of town—three stories high.But then there were fourteen people in the family.There weren't that many in the real, blood Kelly family—but they ate there and slept there at five dollars a head and you might as well count them on in.Mr.Singer wasn't counted in that because he only rented a room and kept it straightened up himself.

The house was narrow and had not been painted for many years. It did not seem to be built strong enough for its three stories of height.It sagged on one side.

Mick untied Ralph and lifted him from the wagon. She darted quickly through the hall, and from the corner of her eye she saw that the living-room was full of boarders.Her Dad was in there, too.Her Mama would be in the kitchen.They were all hanging around waiting for dinner-time.

She went into the first of the three rooms that the family kept for themselves. She put Ralph down on the bed where her Dad and Mama slept and gave him a string of beads to play with.From behind the closed door of the next room she could hear the sound of voices, and she decided to go inside.

Hazel and Etta stopped talking when they saw her. Etta was sitting in the chair by the window, painting her toenails with the red polish.Her hair was done up in steel rollers and there was a white dab of face cream on a little place under her chin where a pimple had come out.Hazel was flopped out lazy on the bed as usual.

“What were you all jawing about?”

“It's none of your nosy business，”Etta said.“Just you hush up and leave us alone.”

“It's my room just as much as it is either one of yours. I have as good a right in here as you do.”Mick strutted from one corner to the other until she had covered all the floor space.“But then I don't care anything about picking any fight.All I want are my own rights.”

Mick brushed back her shaggy bangs with the palm of her hand. She had done this so often that there was a little row of cowlicks above her forehead.She quivered her nose and made faces at herself in the mirror.Then she began walking around the room again.

Hazel and Etta were O. K.as far as sisters went.But Etta was like she was full of worms.All she thought about was movie stars and getting in the movies.Once she had written to Jeanette MacDonald and had got a typewritten letter back saying that if ever she came out to Hollywood she could come by and swim in her swimming pool.And ever since that swimming pool had been preying on Etta's mind.All she thought about was going to Hollywood when she could scrape up the bus fare and getting a job as a secretary and being buddies with Jeanette MacDonald and getting in the movies herself.

She primped all the day long. And that was the bad part.Etta wasn't naturally pretty like Hazel.The main thing was she didn't have any chin.She would pull at her jaw and go through a lot of chin exercises she had read in a movie book.She was always looking at her side profile in the mirror and trying to keep her mouth set in a certain way.But it didn't do any good.Sometimes Etta would hold her face with her hands and cry in the night about it.

Hazel was plain lazy. She was good-looking but thick in the head.She was eighteen years old, and next to Bill she was the oldest of all the kids in the family.Maybe that was the trouble.She got the first and biggest share of everything—the first whack at the new clothes and the biggest part of any special treat.Hazel never had to grab for anything and she was soft.

“Are you just going to tramp around the room all day?It makes me sick to see you in those silly boy's clothes. Somebody ought to clamp down on you, Mick Kelly, and make you behave，”Etta said.

“Shut up，”said Mick.“I wear shorts because I don't want to wear your old hand-me-downs. I don't want to be like either of you and I don't want to look like either of you.And I won't.That's why I wear shorts.I’d rather be a boy any day, and I wish I could move in with Bill.”

Mick scrambled under the bed and brought out a large hatbox. As she carried it to the door both of them called after her，“Good riddance！”

Bill had the nicest room of anybody in the family. Like a den—and he had it all to himself—except for Bubber.Bill had pictures cut out from magazines tacked on the walls, mostly faces of beautiful ladies, and in another corner were some pictures Mick had painted last year herself at the free art class.There was only a bed and a desk in the room.

Bill was sitting hunched over the desk, reading Popular Mechanics. She went up behind him and put her arms around his shoulders.“Hey, you old son-of-a-gun.”

He did not begin tussling with her like he used to do.“Hey，”he said, and shook his shoulders a little.

“Will it bother you if I stay in here a little while?”

“Sure—I don't mind if you want to stay.”

Mick knelt on the floor and untied the string on the big hatbox. Her hands hovered over the edge of the lid, but for some reason she could not make up her mind to open it.

“I been thinking about what I've done on this already，”she said.“And it may work and it may not.”

Bill went on reading. She still knelt over the box, but did not open it.Her eyes wandered over to Bill as he sat with his back to her.One of his big feet kept stepping on the other as he read.His shoes were scuffed.Once their Dad had said that all Bill's dinners went to his feet and his breakfast to one ear and his supper to the other ear.That was a sort of mean thing to say and Bill had been sour over it for a month, but it was funny.His ears flared out and were very red, and though he was just out of high school he wore a size thirteen shoe.He tried to hide his feet by scraping one foot behind the other when he stood up, but that only made it worse.

Mick opened the box a few inches and then shut it again. She felt too excited to look into it now.She got up and walked around the room until she could calm down a little.After a few minutes she stopped before the picture she had painted at the free government art class for school kids last winter.There was a picture of a storm on the ocean and a seagull being dashed through the air by the wind.It was called“Sea Gull with Back Broken in Storm.”The teacher had described the ocean during the first two or three lessons, and that was what nearly everybody started with.Most of the kids were like her, though, and they had never really seen the ocean with their own eyes.

That was the first picture she had done and Bill had tacked it on his wall. All the rest of her pictures were full of people.She had done some more ocean storms at first—one with an airplane crashing down and people jumping out to save themselves, and another with a trans-atlantic liner going down and all the people trying to push and crowd into one little lifeboat.

Mick went into the closet of Bill's room and brought out some other pictures she had done in the class—some pencil drawings, some water-colors, and one canvas with oils. They were all full of people.She had imagined a big fire on Broad Street and painted how she thought it would be.The flames were bright green and orange and Mr.Brannon's restaurant and the First National Bank were about the only buildings left.People were lying dead in the streets and others were running for their lives.One man was in his nightshirt and a lady was trying to carry a bunch of bananas with her.Another picture was called“Boiler Busts in Factory，”and men were jumping out of windows and running while a knot of kids in overalls stood scrouged together, holding the buckets of dinner they had brought to their Daddies.The oil painting was a picture of the whole town fighting on Broad Street.She never knew why she had painted this one and she couldn't think of the right name for it.There wasn't any fire or storm or reason you could see in the picture why all this battle was happening.But there were more people and more moving around than in any other picture.This was the best one, and it was too bad that she couldn't think up the real name.In the back of her mind somewhere she knew what it was.

Mick put the picture back on the closet shelf. None of them were any good much.The people didn't have fingers and some of the arms were longer than the legs.The class had been fun, though.But she had just drawn whatever came into her head without reason—and in her heart it didn't give her near the same feeling that music did.Nothing was really as good as music.

Mick knelt down on the floor and quickly lifted the top of the big hatbox. Inside was a cracked ukulele strung with two violin strings, a guitar string and a banjo string.The crack on the back of the ukulele had been neatly mended with sticking plaster and the round hole in the middle was covered by a piece of wood.The bridge of a violin held up the strings at the end and some sound-holes had been carved on either side.Mick was making herself a violin.She held the violin in her lap.She had the feeling she had never really looked at it before.Some time ago she made Bubber a little play mandolin out of a cigar box with rubber bands, and that put the idea into her head.Since that she had hunted all over everywhere for the different parts and added a little to the job every day.It seemed to her she had done everything except use her head.

“Bill, this don't look like any real violin I ever saw.”

He was still reading—“Yeah—?”

“It just don't look right. It just don't—”

She had planned to tune the fiddle that day by screwing the pegs. But since she had suddenly realized how all the work had turned out she didn't want to look at it.Slowly she plucked one string after another.They all made the same little hollow-sounding ping.

“How anyway will I ever get a bow?Are you sure they have to be made out of just horses'hair?”

“Yeah，”said Bill impatiently.

“Nothing like thin wire or human hair strung on a limber stick would do?”

Bill rubbed his feet against each other and didn't answer.

Anger made beads of sweat come out on her forehead. Her voice was hoarse.“It's not even a bad violin.It's only a cross between a mandolin and a ukulele.And I hate them.I hate them—”

Bill turned around.

“It's all turned out wrong. It won't do.It's no good.”

“Pipe down，”said Bill.“Are you just carrying on about that old broken ukulele you've been fooling with?I could have told you at first it was crazy to think you could make any violin. That's one thing you don't sit down and make—you got to buy them.I thought anybody would know a thing like that.But I figured it wouldn't hurt yon if you found out for yourself.”

Sometimes she hated Bill more than anyone else in the world. He was different entirely from what he used to be.She started to slam the violin down on the floor and stomp on it, but instead she put it back roughly into the hatbox.The tears were hot in her eyes as fire.She gave the box a kick and ran from the room without looking at Bill.

As she was dodging through the hall to get to the back yard she ran into her Mama.

“What's the matter with you?What have you been into now?”

Mick tried to jerk loose, but her Mama held on to her arm. Sullenly she wiped the tears from her face with the back of her hand.Her Mama had been in the kitchen and she wore her apron and house-shoes.As usual she looked as though she had a lot on her mind and didn't have time to ask her any more questions.

“Mr. Jackson has brought his two sisters to dinner and there won't be but just enough chairs, so today you're to eat in the kitchen with Bubber.”

“That's hunky-dory with me，”Mick said.

Her Mama let her go and went to take off her apron. From the dining-room there came the sound of the dinner bell and a sudden glad outbreak of talking.She could hear her Dad saying how much he had lost by not keeping up his accident insurance until the time he broke his hip.That was one thing her Dad could never get off his mind—ways he could have made money and didn't.There was a clatter of dishes, and after a while the talking stopped.

Mick leaned on the banisters of the stairs. The sudden crying had started her with the hiccups.It seemed to her as she thought back over the last month that she had never really believed in her mind that the violin would work.But in her heart she had kept making herself believe.And even now it was hard not to believe a little.She was tired out.Bill wasn't ever a help with anything now.She used to think Bill was the grandest person in the world.She used to follow after him every place he went—out fishing in the woods, to the clubhouses he built with other boys, to the slot machine in the back of Mr.Brannon's restaurant—everywhere.Maybe he hadn't meant to let her down like this.But anyway they could never be good buddies again.

In the hall there was the smell of cigarettes and Sunday dinner. Mick took a deep breath and walked back toward the kitchen.The dinner began to smell good and she was hungry.She could hear Portia's voice as she talked to Bubber, and it was like she was half-singing something or telling him a story.

“And that is the various reason why I'm a whole lot more fortunate than most colored girls，”Portia said as she opened the door.“Why?”asked Mick.

Portia and Bubber were sitting at the kitchen table eating their dinner. Portia's green print dress was cool-looking against her dark brown skin.She had on green earrings and her hair was combed very tight and neat.

“You all time pounce in on the very tail of what somebody say and then want to know all about it，”Portia said. She got up and stood over the hot stove, putting dinner on Mick's plate.“Bubber and me was just talking about my Grandpapa's home out on the Old Sardis Road.I was telling Bubber how he and my uncles owns the whole place themself.Fifteen and a half acre.They always plants four of them in cotton, some years swapping back to peas to keep the dirt rich, and one acre on a hill is just for peaches.They haves a mule and a breed sow and all the time from twenty to twenty-five laying hens and fryers.They haves a vegetable patch and two pecan trees and plenty figs and plums and berries.This here is the truth.Not many white farms has done with their land good as my Grandpapa.”

Mick put her elbows on the table and leaned over her plate. Portia had always rather talk about the farm than anything else, except about her husband and brother.To hear her tell it you would think that colored farm was the very White House itself.

“The home started with just one little room. And through the years they done built on until there's space for my Grandpapa, his four sons and their wives and childrens, and my brother Hamilton.In the parlor they haves a real organ and a gramophone.And on the wall they haves a large picture of my Grandpapa taken in his lodge uniform.They cans all the fruit and vegetables and no matter how cold and rainy the winter turns they pretty near always haves plenty to eat.”

“How come you don't go live with them, then?”Mick asked.

Portia stopped peeling her potatoes and her long, brown fingers tapped on the table in time to her words.“This here the way it is. See—each person done built on his room for his fambly.They all done worked hard during all these years.And of course times is hard for ever body now.But see—I lived with my Grandpapa when I were a little girl.But I haven't never done any work out there since.Any time, though, if me and Willie and Highboy gets in bad trouble us can always go back.”

“Didn't your Father build on a room?”

Portia stopped chewing.“Whose Father?You mean my Father?”

“Sure，”said Mick.

“You know good and well my Father is a colored doctor right here in town.”

Mick had heard Portia say that before, but she had thought it was a tale. How could a colored man be a doctor?

“This here the way it is. Before the tune my Mama married my Father she had never known anything but real kindness.My Grandpa is Mister Kind hisself.But my Father is different from him as day is from night.”

“Mean?”asked Mick.

“No, he not a mean man，”Portia said slowly.“It just that something is the matter. My Father not like other colored mens.This here is hard to explain.My Father all the time studying by hisself.And a long time ago he taken up all these notions about how a fambly ought to be.He bossed over ever little thing in the house and at night he tried to teach us children lessons.”

“That don't sound so bad to me，”said Mick.

“Listen here. You see most of the time he were very quiet.But then some nights he would break out in a kind of fit.He could get madder than any man I ever seen.Everybody who know my Father say that he was a sure enough crazy man.He done wild, crazy things and our Mama quit him.I were ten years old at the time.Our Mama taken us children with her to Grandpapa's farm and us were raised out there.Our Father all the time wanted us to come back.But even when our Mama died us children never did go home to live.And now my Father stay all by hisself.”

Mick went to the stove and filled her plate a second time. Portia's voice was going up and down like a song, and nothing could stop her now.

“I doesn't see my Father much—maybe once a week—but I done a lot of thinking about him. I feels sorrier for him than anybody I knows.I expect he done read more books than any white man in this town.He done read more books and he done worried about more things.He full of books and worrying.He done lost God and turned his back to religion.All his troubles come down just to that.”

Portia was excited. Whenever she got to talking about God—or Willie, her brother, or Highboy, her husband—she got excited.

“Now, I not a big shouter. I belongs to the Presbyterian Church and us don't hold with all this rolling on the floor and talking in tongues.Us don't get sanctified ever week and wallow around together.In our church we sings and lets the preacher do the preaching.And tell you the truth I don't think a little singing and a little preaching would hurt you, Mick.You ought to take your little brother to the Sunday School and also you plenty big enough to sit in church.From the biggity way you been acting lately it seem to me like you already got one toe in the pit.”

“Nuts，”Mick said.

“Now Highboy he were Holiness boy before us were married. He loved to get the spirit ever Sunday and shout and sanctify hisself.But after us were married I got him to join with me, and although it kind of hard to keep him quiet sometime I think he doing right well.”

“I don't believe in God any more than I do Santa Claus，”Mick said.

“You wait a minute！That's why it sometime seem to me you favor my Father more than any person I ever knowed.”

“Me?You say I favor him?”

“I don't mean in the face or in any kind of looks. I was speaking about the shape and color of your souls.”

Bubber sat looking from one to the other. His napkin was tied around his neck and in his hand he still held his empty spoon.“What all does God eat?”he asked.

Mick got up from the table and stood in the doorway, ready to leave. Sometimes it was fun to devil Portia.She started on the same tune and said the same thing over and over—like that was all she knew.

“Folks like you and my Father who don't attend the church can't never have nair peace at all. Now take me here—I believe and I haves peace.And Bubber, he haves his peace too.And my Highboy and my Willie likewise.And it seem to me just from looking at him this here Mr.Singer haves peace too.I done felt that the first time I seen him.”

“Have it your own way，”Mick said.“You're crazier than any father of yours could ever be.”

“But you haven't never loved God nor even nair person. You hard and tough as cowhide.But just the same I knows you.This afternoon you going to roam all over the place without never being satisfied.You going to traipse all around like you haves to find something lost.You going to work yourself up with excitement Your heart going to beat hard enough to kill you because you don't love and don't have peace.And then some day you going to bust loose and be ruined.Won't nothing help you then.”

“What, Portia?”Bubber asked.“What kind of things does He eat?”

Mick laughed and stamped out of the room.

She did roam around the house during the afternoon because she could not get settled. Some days were just like that.For one thing the thought of the violin kept worrying her.She could never have made it like a real one—and after all those weeks of planning the very thought of it made her sick.But how could she have been so sure the idea would work?So dumb?Maybe when people longed for a thing that bad the longing made them trust in anything that might give it to them.

Mick did not want to go back into the rooms where the family stayed. And she did not want to have to talk to any of the boarders.No place was left but the street—and there the sun was too burning hot.She wandered aimlessly up and down the hall and kept pushing back her rumpled hair with the palm of her hand.“Hell，”she said aloud to herself.“Next to a real piano I sure would rather have some place to myself than anything I know.”

That Portia had a certain kind of niggery craziness, but she was O. K.She never would do anything mean to Bubber or Ralph on the sly like some colored girls.But Portia had said that she never loved anybody.Mick stopped walking and stood very still, rubbing her fist on the top of her head.What would Portia think if she really knew?Just what would she think?

She had always kept things to herself. That was one sure truth.

Mick went slowly up the stairs. She passed the first landing and went on to the second.Some of the doors were open to make a draught and there were many sounds in the house.Mick stopped on the last flight of stairs and sat down.If Miss Brown turned on her radio she could hear the music.Maybe some good program would come on.

She put her head on her knees and tied knots in the strings of her tennis shoes. What would Portia say if she knew that always there had been one person after another?And every time it was like some part of her would bust in a hundred pieces.

But she had always kept it to herself and no person had ever known.

Mick sat on the steps a long time. Miss Brown did not turn on her radio and there was nothing but the noises that people made.She thought a long time and kept hitting her thighs with her fists.Her face felt like it was scattered in pieces and she could not keep it straight.The feeling was a whole lot worse than being hungry for any dinner, yet it was like that.I want—I want—I want—was all that she could think about—but just what this real want was she did not know.

After about an hour there was the sound of a doorknob being turned on the landing above. Mick looked up quickly and it was Mister Singer.He stood in the hall for a few minutes and his face was sad and calm.Then he went across to the bathroom.His company did not come out with him.From where she was sitting she could see part of the room, and the company was asleep on the bed with a sheet pulled over him.She waited for Mister Singer to come out of the bathroom.Her cheeks were very hot and she felt them with her hands.Maybe it was true that she came up on these top steps sometimes so she could see Mister Singer while she was listening to Miss Brown's radio on the floor below.She wondered what kind of music he heard in his mind that his ears couldn't hear.Nobody knew.And what kind of things he would say if he could talk.Nobody knew that either.

Mick waited, and after a while he came out into the hall again. She hoped he would look down and smile at her.And then when he got to his door he did glance down and nod his head.Mick's grin was wide and trembling.He went into his room and shut the door.It might have been he meant to invite her in to see him.Mick wanted suddenly to go into his room.Sometime soon when he didn't have company she would really go in and see Mister Singer.She really would do that.

The hot afternoon passed slowly and Mick still sat on the steps by herself. The fellow Motsart's music was in her mind again.It was funny, but Mister Singer reminded her of this music.She wished there was some place where she could go to hum it out loud.Some kind of music was too private to sing in a house cram full of people.It was funny, too, how lonesome a person could be in a crowded house.Mick tried to think of some good private place where she could go and be by herself and study about this music.But though she thought about this a long time she knew in the beginning that there was no good place.

4

Late in the afternoon Jake Blount awoke with the feeling that he had slept enough. The room in which he lay was small and neat, furnished with a bureau, a table, a bed, and a few chairs.On the bureau an electric fan turned its face slowly from one wall to another, and as the breeze from it passed Jake's face he thought of cool water.By the window a man sat before the table and stared down at a chess game laid out before him.In the daylight the room was not familiar to Jake, but he recognized the man's face instantly and it was as though he had known him a very long time.

Many memories were confused in Jake's mind. He lay motionless with his eyes open and his hands turned palm upward.His hands were huge and very brown against the white sheet.When he held them up to his face he saw that they were scratched and bruised—and the veins were swollen as though he had been grasping hard at something for a long time.His face looked tired and unkempt.His brown hair fell down over his forehead and his mustache was awry.Even his wing-shaped eyebrows were rough and tousled.As he lay there his lips moved once or twice and his mustache jerked with a nervous quiver..

After a while he sat up and gave himself a thump on the side of his head with one of his big fists to straighten himself out. When he moved, the man playing chess looked up quickly and smiled at him.

“God, I'm thirsty，”Jake said.“I feel like the whole Russian army marched through my mouth in its stocking feet.”

The man looked at him, still smiling, and then suddenly he reached down on the other side of the table and brought up a frosted pitcher of ice water and a glass. Jake drank in great panting gulps—standing half-naked in the middle of the room, his head thrown back and one of his hands closed in a tense fist.He finished four glasses before he took a deep breath and relaxed a little.

Instantly certain recollections came to him. He couldn't remember coming home with this man, but things that had happened later were clearer now.He had waked up soaking in a tub of cold water, and afterward they drank coffee and talked.He had got a lot of things off his chest and the man had listened.He had talked himself hoarse, but he could remember the expressions on the man's face better than anything that was said.They had gone to bed in the morning with the shade pulled down so no light could come in.At first he would keep waking up with nightmares and have to turn the light on to get himself clear again.The light would wake this fellow also, but he hadn't complained at all.

“How come you didn't kick me out last night?”

The man only smiled again. Jake wondered why he was so quiet.He looked around for his clothes and saw that his suitcase was on the floor by the bed.He couldn't remember how he had got it back from the restaurant where he owed for the drinks.His books, a white suit, and some shirts were all there as he had packed them.Quickly he began to dress himself.

An electric coffee-pot was perking on the table by the time he had his clothes on. The man reached into the pocket of the vest that hung over the back of a chair.He brought out a card and Jake took it questioningly.The man's name—John Singer—was engraved in the center, and beneath this, written in ink with the same elaborate precision as the engraving, there was a brief message.

I am a deaf-mute, but I read the lips and understand what is said to me.Please do not shout.

The shock made Jake feel light and vacant. He and John Singer just looked at each other.

“I wonder how long it would have taken me to find that out，”he said.

Singer looked very carefully at his lips when he spoke—he had noticed that before. But a dummy！

They sat at the table and drank hot coffee out of blue cups. The room was cool and the half-drawn shades softened the hard glare from the windows.Singer brought from his closet a tin box that contained a loaf of bread, some oranges, and cheese.He did not eat much, but sat leaning back in his chair with one hand in his pocket.Jake ate hungrily.He would have to leave the place immediately and think things over.As long as he was stranded he ought to scout around for some sort of job in a hurry.The quiet room was too peaceful and comfortable to worry in—he would get out and walk by himself for a while.

“Are there any other deaf-mute people here?”he asked.“You have many friends?”

Singer was still smiling. He did not catch on to the words at first, and Jake had to repeat them.Singer raised his sharp, dark eyebrows and shook his head.

“Find it lonesome?”

The man shook his head in a way that might have meant either yes or no. They sat silently for a little while and then Jake got up to leave.He thanked Singer several times for the night's lodging, moving his lips carefully so that he was sure to be understood.The mute only smiled again and shrugged his shoulders.When Jake asked if he could leave his suitcase under the bed for a few days the mute nodded that he could.

Then Singer took his hands from his pocket and wrote carefully on a pad of paper with a silver pencil. He shoved the pad over toward Jake.

I can put a mattress on the floor and you can stay here until you find a place.I am out most of the day.It will not be any trouble.

Jake felt his lips tremble with a sudden feeling of gratefulness. But he couldn't accept.“Thanks，”he said，“I already got a place.”

As he was leaving, the mute handed him a pair of blue overalls, rolled into a tight bundle, and seventy-five cents. The overalls were filthy and as Jake recognized them they aroused in him a whirl of sudden memories from the past week.The money, Singer made him understand, had been in his pockets.

“Adios，”Jake said.“I'll be back sometime soon.”

He left the mute standing in the doorway with his hands still in his pockets and the half-smile on his face. When he had gone down several steps of the stairs he turned and waved.The mute waved back to him and closed his door.

Outside the glare was sudden and sharp against his eyes. He stood on the sidewalk before the house, too dazzled at first by the sunlight to see very clearly.A youngun was sitting on the banisters of the house.He had seen her somewhere before.He remembered the boy's shorts she was wearing and the way she squinted her eyes.

He held up the dirty roll of overalls.“I want to throw these away. Know where I can find a garbage can?”

The kid jumped down from the banisters.“It's in the back yard. I'll show you.”

He followed her through the narrow, dampish alley at the side of the house. When they came to the back yard Jake saw that two Negro men were sitting on the back steps.They were both dressed in white suits and white shoes.One of the Negroes was very tall and his tie and socks were brilliant green.The other was a light mulatto of average height.He rubbed a tin harmonica across his knee.In contrast with his tall companion his socks and tie were a hot red.

The kid pointed to the garbage can by the back fence and then turned to the kitchen window.“Portia！”she called.“Highboy and Willie here waiting for you.”

A soft voice answered from the kitchen.“You neen holler so loud. I know they is.I putting on my hat right now.”

Jake unrolled the overalls before throwing them away. They were stiff with mud.One leg was torn and a few drops of blood stained the front.He dropped them in the can.A Negro girl came out of the house and joined the white-suited boys on the steps.Jake saw that the youngun in shorts was looking at him very closely.She changed her weight from one foot to the other and seemed excited.

“Are you kin to Mister Singer?”she asked.

“Not a bit.”

“Good friend?”

“Good enough to spend the night with him.”

“I just wondered—”

“Which direction is Main Street?”

She pointed to the right.“Two blocks down this way.”

Jake combed his mustache with his fingers and started off. He jingled the seventy-five cents in his hand and bit his lower lip until it was mottled and scarlet.The three Negroes were walking slowly ahead of him, talking among themselves.Because he felt lonely in the unfamiliar town he kept close behind them and listened.The girl held both of them by the arm.She wore a green dress with a red hat and shoes.The boys walked very close to her.

“What we got planned for this evening?”she asked.

“It depend entirely upon you, Honey，”the tall boy said.“Willie and me don't have no special plans.”

She looked from one to the other.“You all got to decide.”

“Well—”said the shorter boy in the red socks.“Highboy and me thought m-maybe us three go to church.”

The girl sang her answer in three different tones.“O-K—And after church I got a notion I ought to go and set with Father for a while—just a short while.”They turned at the first corner, and Jake stood watching them a moment before walking on.

The main street was quiet and hot, almost deserted. He had not realized until now that it was Sunday—and the thought of this depressed him.The awnings over the closed stores were raised and the buildings had a bare look in the bright sun.He passed the New York Café.The door was open, but the place looked empty and dark.He had not found any socks to wear that morning, and the hot pavement burned through the thin soles of his shoes.The sun felt like a hot piece of iron pressing down on his head.The town seemed more lonesome than any place he had ever known.The stillness of the street gave him a strange feeling.When he had been drunk the place had seemed violent and riotous.And now it was as though everything had come to a sudden, static halt.

He went into a fruit and candy store to buy a paper. The Help-Wanted column was very short.There were several calls for young men between twenty-five and forty with automobiles to sell various products on commission.These he skipped over quickly.An advertisement for a truck-driver held his attention for a few minutes.But the notice at the bottom interested him most It read：

Wanted—Experienced Mechanic.Sunny Dixie Show.

Apply Corner Weavers Lane&15th Street.

Without knowing it he had walked back to the door of the restaurant where he had spent his time during the past two weeks. This was the only place on the block besides the fruit store which was not closed.Jake decided suddenly to drop in and see Biff Brannon.

The café　was very dark after the brightness outside.Everything looked dingier and quieter than he had remembered it.Brannon stood behind the cash register as usual, his arms folded over his chest.His good-looking plump wife sat filing her fingernails at the other end of the counter.Jake noticed that they glanced at each other as he came in.

“Afternoon，”said Brannon.

Jake felt something in the air. Maybe the fellow was laughing because he remembered things that had happened when he was drunk.Jake stood wooden and resentful.“Package of Target, please.”As Brannon reached beneath the counter for the tobacco Jake decided that he was not laughing.In the daytime the fellow's face was not as hard-looking as it was at night.He was pale as though he had not slept, and his eyes had the look of a weary buzzard's.

“Speak up，”Jake said.“How much do I owe you?”

Brannon opened a drawer and put on the counter a public-school tablet. Slowly he turned over the pages and Jake watched him.The tablet looked more like a private notebook than the place where he kept his regular accounts.There were long lines of figures, added, divided, and subtracted, and little drawings.He stopped at a certain page and Jake saw his last name written at the corner.On the page there were no figures—only small checks and crosses.At random across the page were drawn little round, seated cats with long curved lines for tails.Jake stared.The faces of the little cats were human and female.The faces of the little cats were Mrs.Brannon.

“I have checks here for the beers，”Brannon said.“And crosses for dinners and straight lines for the whiskey. Let me see—”Brannon rubbed his nose and his eyelids drooped down.Then he shut the tablet.“Approximately twenty dollars.”

“It'll take me a long time，”Jake said.“But maybe you'll get it.”

“There's no big hurry.”

Jake leaned against the counter.“Say, what kind of a place is this town?”

“Ordinary，”Brannon said.“About like any other place the same size.”

“What population?”

“Around thirty thousand.”

Jake opened the package of tobacco and rolled himself a cigarette. His hands were shaking.“Mostly mills?”

“That's right. Four big cotton mills—those are the main ones.A hosiery factory.Some gins and sawmills.”

“What kind of wages?”

“I'd say around ten or eleven a week on the average—but then of course they get laid off now and then. What makes you ask all this?You mean to try to get a job in a mill?”

Jake dug his fist into his eye and rubbed it sleepily.“Don't know. I might and I might not.”He laid the newspaper on the counter and pointed out the advertisement he had just read.“I think I'll go around and look into this.”

Brannon read and considered.“Yeah，”he said finally.“I've seen that show. It's not much—just a couple of contraptions such as a flying-jinny and swings.It corrals the colored people and mill hands and kids.They move around to different vacant lots in town.”

“Show me how to get there.”

Brannon went with him to the door and pointed out the direction.“Did you go on home with Singer this morning?”

Jake nodded.

“What do you think of him?”

Jake bit his lips. The mute's face was in his mind very clearly.It was like the face of a friend he had known for a long time.He had been thinking of the man ever since he had left his room.“I didn't even know he was a dummy，”he said finally.

He began walking again down the hot, deserted street. He did not walk as a stranger in a strange town.He seemed to be looking for someone.Soon he entered one of the mill districts bordering the river.The streets became narrow and unpaved and they were not empty any longer.Groups of dingy, hungry-looking children called to each other and played games.The two-room shacks, each one like the other, were rotten and unpainted.The stink of food and sewage mingled with the dust in the air.The falls up the river made a faint rushing sound.People stood silently in doorways or lounged on steps.They looked at Jake with yellow, expressionless faces.He stared back at them with wide, brown eyes.He walked jerkily, and now and then he wiped his mouth with the hairy back of his hand.

At the end of Weavers Lane there was a vacant block. It had once been used as a junk yard for old automobiles.Rusted pieces of machinery and torn inner tubes still littered the ground.A trailer was parked in one corner of the lot, and nearby was a flying-jinny partly covered with canvas.

Jake approached slowly. Two little younguns in overalls stood before the flying-jinny.Near them, seated on a box, a Negro man drowsed in the late sunshine, his knees collapsed against each other.In one hand he held a sack of melted chocolate.Jake watched him stick his fingers in the miry candy and then lick them slowly.

“Who's the manager of this outfit?”

The Negro thrust his two sweet fingers between his lips and rolled over them with his tongue.“He a red-headed man，”he said when he had finished.“That all I know, Cap'n.”

“Where's he now?”

“He over there behind that largest wagon.”

Jake slipped off his tie as he walked across the grass and stuffed it into his pocket. The sun was beginning to set in the west.Above the black line of housetops the sky was warm crimson.The owner of the show stood smoking a cigarette by himself.His red hair sprang up like a sponge on the top of his head and he stared at Jake with gray, flabby eyes.

“You the manager?”

“Uh-huh. Patterson's my name.”

“I come about the job in this morning's paper.”

“Yeah. I don't want no greenhorn.I need a experienced mechanic.”

“I got plenty of experience，”Jake said.

“What you ever done?”

“I've worked as a weaver and loom-fixer. I've worked in garages and an automobile assembly shop.All sorts of different things.”

Patterson guided him toward the partly covered flying-jinny. The motionless wooden horses were fantastic in the late afternoon sun.They pranced up statically, pierced by their dull gilt bars.The horse nearest Jake had a splintery wooden crack in its dingy rump and the eyes walled blind and frantic, shreds of paint peeled from the sockets.The motionless merry-go-round seemed to Jake like something in a liquor dream.

“I want a experienced mechanic to run this and keep the works in good shape，”Patterson said.

“I can do that all right.”

“It's a two-handed job，”Patterson explained.“You're in charge of the whole attraction. Besides looking after the machinery you got to keep the crowd in order.You got to be sure that everybody gets on has a ticket.You got to be sure that the tickets are O.K.and not some old dance-hall ticket.Everybody wants to ride them horses, and you'd be surprised what niggers will try to put over on you when they don't have no money.You got to keep three eyes open all the time.”

Patterson led him to the machinery inside the circle of horses and pointed out the various parts. He adjusted a lever and the thin jangle of mechanical music began.The wooden cavalcade around them seemed to cut them off from the rest of the world.When the horses stopped, Jake asked a few questions and operated the mechanism himself.

“The fellow I had quit on me，”Patterson said when they had come out again into the lot.“I always hate to break in a new man.”

“When do I start?”

“Tomorrow afternoon. We run six days and nights a week—beginning at four and shutting up at twelve.You're to come about three and help get things going.And it takes about a hour after the show to fold up for the night.”

“What about pay?”

“Twelve dollars.”

Jake nodded, and Patterson held out a dead-white, boneless hand with dirty fingernails.

It was late when he left the vacant lot. The hard, blue sky had blanched and in the east there was a white moon.Dusk softened the outline of the houses along the street.Jake did not return immediately through Weavers Lane, but wandered in the neighborhoods nearby.Certain smells, certain voices heard from a distance, made him stop short now and then by the side of the dusty street.He walked erratically, jerking from one direction to another for no purpose.His head felt very light, as though it were made of thin glass.A chemical change was taking place in him.The beers and whiskey he had stored so continuously in his system set in a reaction.He was sideswiped by drunkenness.The streets which had seemed so dead before were quick with life.There was a ragged strip of grass bordering the street, and as Jake walked along the ground seemed to rise nearer to his face.He sat down on the border of grass and leaned against a telephone pole.He settled himself comfortably, crossing his legs Turkish fashion and smoothing down the ends of his mustache.Words came to him and dreamily he spoke them aloud to himself.

“Resentment is the most precious flower of poverty. Yeah.”

It was good to talk. The sound of his voice gave him pleasure.The tones seemed to echo and hang on the air so that each word sounded twice.He swallowed and moistened his mouth to speak again.He wanted suddenly to return to the mute's quiet room and tell him of the thoughts that were in his mind.It was a queer thing to want to talk with a deaf-mute.But he was lonesome.

The street before him dimmed with the coming evening. Occasionally men passed along the narrow street very close to him, talking in monotones to each other, a cloud of dust rising around their feet with each step.Or girls passed by together, or a mother with a child across her shoulder.Jake sat numbly for some time, and at last he got to his feet and walked on.

Weavers Lane was dark. Oil lamps made yellow, trembling patches of light in the doorways and windows.Some of the houses were entirely dark and the families sat on their front steps with only the reflections from a neighboring house to see by.A woman leaned out of a window and splashed a pail of dirty water into the street.A few drops of it splashed on Jake's face.High, angry voices could be heard from the backs of some of the houses.From others there was the peaceful sound of a chair slowly rocking.

Jake stopped before a house where three men sat together on the front steps. A pale yellow light from inside the house shone on them.Two of the men wore overalls but no shirts and were barefooted.One of these was tall and loose-jointed.The other was small and he had a running sore on the corner of his mouth.The third man was dressed in shirt and trousers.He held a straw hat on his knee.

“Hey，”Jake said.

The three men stared at him with mill-sallow, dead-pan faces. They murmured but did not change their positions.Jake pulled the package of Target from his pocket and passed it around.He sat down on the bottom step and took off his shoes.The cool, damp ground felt good to his feet.

“Working now?”

“Yeah，”said the man with the straw hat.“Most of the time.”

Jake picked between his toes.“I got the Gospel in me，”he said.“I want to tell it to somebody.”

The men smiled. From across the narrow street there was the sound of a woman singing.The smoke from their cigarettes hung close around them in the still air.A little youngun passing along the street stopped and opened his fly to make water.

“There's a tent around the corner and it's Sunday，”the small man said finally.“You can go there and tell all the Gospel you want.”

“It's not that kind. It's better.It's the truth.”

“What kind?”

Jake sucked his mustache and did not answer. After a while he said，“You ever have any strikes here?”

“Once，”said the tall man.“They had one of these here strikes around six years ago.”

“What happened?”

The man with the sore on his mouth shuffled his feet and dropped the stub of his cigarette to the ground.“Well—they just quit work because they wanted twenty cents a hour. There was about three hundred did it.They just hung around the streets all day.So the mill sent out trucks, and in a week the whole town was swarming with folks come here to get a job.”

Jake turned so that he was facing them. The men sat two steps above him so that he had to raise his head to look into their eyes.“Don't it make you mad?”he asked.

“How do you mean—mad?”

The vein in Jake's forehead was swollen and scarlet.“Christamighty, man！I mean mad—m-a-d—mad.”He scowled up into their puzzled, sallow faces. Behind them, through the open front door he could see the inside of the house.In the front room there were three beds and a wash-stand.In the back room a barefooted woman sat sleeping in a chair.From one of the dark porches nearby there was the sound of a guitar.

“I was one of them come in on the trucks，”the tall man said.

“That makes no difference. What I'm trying to tell you is plain and simple.The bastards who own these mills are millionaires.While the doffers and carders and all the people behind the machines who spin and weave the cloth can't hardly make enough to keep their guts quiet.See?So when you walk around the streets and think about it and see hungry, worn-out people and ricket-legged younguns, don't it make you mad?Don't it?”

Jake's face was flushed and dark and his lips trembled. The three men looked at him warily.Then the man in the straw hat began to laugh.

“Go on and snicker. Sit there and bust your sides open.”

The men laughed in the slow and easy way that three men laugh at one. Jake brushed the dirt from the soles of his feet and put on his shoes.His fists were closed tight and his mouth was contorted with an angry sneer.“Laugh—that's all you're good for.I hope you sit there and snicker'til you rot！”As he walked stiffly down the street the sound of their laughter and catcalls still followed him.

The main street was brightly lighted. Jake loitered on a corner, fondling the change in his pocket.His head throbbed, and although the night was hot a chill passed through his body.He thought of the mute and he wanted urgently to go back and sit with him awhile.In the fruit and candy store where he had bought the newspaper that afternoon he selected a basket of fruit wrapped in cellophane.The Greek behind the counter said the price was sixty cents, so that when he had paid he was left with only a nickel.As soon as he had come out of the store the present seemed a funny one to take a healthy man.A few grapes hung down below the cellophane, and he picked them off hungrily.

Singer was at home when he arrived. He sat by the window with the chess game laid out before him on the table.The room was just as Jake had left it, with the fan turned on and the pitcher of ice water beside the table.There was a panama hat on the bed and a paper parcel, so it seemed that the mute had just come in.He jerked his head toward the chair across from him at the table and pushed the chessboard to one side.He leaned back with his hands in his pockets, and his face seemed to question Jake about what had happened since he had left.

Jake put the fruit on the table.“For this afternoon，”he said.“The motto has been：Go out and find an octopus and put socks on it.”

The mute smiled, but Jake could not tell if he had caught what he had said. The mute looked at the fruit with surprise and then undid the cellophane wrappings.As he handled the fruits there was something very peculiar in the fellow's face.Jake tried to understand this look and was stumped.Then Singer smiled brightly.

“I got a job this afternoon with a sort of show. I'm to run the flying-jinny.”

The mute seemed not at all surprised. He went into the closet and brought out a bottle of wine and two glasses.They drank in silence.Jake felt that he had never been in such a quiet room.The light above his head made a queer reflection of himself in the glowing wineglass he held before him—the same caricature of himself he had noticed many times before on the curved surfaces of pitchers or tin mugs—with his face egg-shaped and dumpy and his mustache straggling almost up to his ears.Across from him the mute held his glass in both hands.The wine began to hum through Jake's veins and he felt himself entering again the kaleidoscope of drunkenness.Excitement made his mustache tremble jerkily.He leaned forward with his elbows on his knees and fastened a wide, searching gaze on Singer.

“I bet I'm the only man in this town that's been mad—I'm talking about really mean mad—for ten solid long years. I damn near got in a fight just a little while ago.Sometimes it seems to me like I might even be crazy.I just don't know.”

Singer pushed the wine toward his guest. Jake drank from the bottle and rubbed the top of his head.

“You see, it's like I'm two people. One of me is an educated man.I been in some of the biggest libraries in the country.I read.I read all the time.I read books that tell the pure honest truth.Over there in my suitcase I have books by Karl Marx and Thorstein Veblen and such writers as them.I read them over and over, and the more I study the madder I get.I know every word printed on every page.To begin with I like words.Dialectic materialism—Jesuitical prevarication”—Jake rolled the syllables in his mouth with loving solemnity—“teleological propensity.”

The mute wiped his forehead with a neatly folded handkerchief.

“But what I'm getting at is this. When a person knows and can't make the others understand, what does he do?”

Singer reached for a wineglass, filled it to the brim, and put it firmly into Jake's bruised hand.“Get drunk, huh?”Jake said with a jerk of his arm that spilled drops of wine on his white trousers.“But listen！Wherever you look there's meanness and corruption. This room, this bottle of grape wine, these fruits in the basket, are all products of profit and loss.A fellow can't live without giving his passive acceptance to meanness.Somebody wears his tail to a frazzle for every mouthful we eat and every stitch we wear—and nobody seems to know.Everybody is blind, dumb, and blunt-headed—stupid and mean.”

Jake pressed his fists to his temples. His thoughts had careened in several directions and he could not get control of them.He wanted to go berserk.He wanted to get out and fight violently with someone in a crowded street.

Still looking at him with patient interest, the mute took out his silver pencil. He wrote very carefully on a slip of paper, Are you Democrat or Republican?and passed the paper across the table.Jake crumpled it in his hand.The room had begun to turn around him again and he could not even read.

He kept his eyes on the mute's face to steady himself. Singer's eyes were the only things in the room that did not seem to move.They were varied in color, flecked with amber, gray, and a soft brown.He stared at them so long that he almost hypnotized himself.He lost the urge to be riotous and felt calm again.The eyes seemed to understand all that he had meant to say and to hold some message for him.After a while the room was steady again.

“You get it，”he said in a blurred voice.“You know what I mean.”

From afar off there was the soft, silver ring of church bells. The moonlight was white on the roof next door and the sky was a gentle summer blue.It was agreed without words that Jake would stay with Singer a few days until he found a room.When the wine was finished the mute put a mattress on the floor beside the bed.Without removing any of his clothes Jake lay down and was instantly asleep.

5

Far from the main street, in one of the Negro sections of the town, Doctor Benedict Mady Copeland sat in his dark kitchen alone. It was past nine o'clock and the Sunday bells were silent now.Although the night was very hot, there was a small fire in the round-bellied wood stove.Doctor Copeland sat close to it, leaning forward in a straight-backed kitchen chair with his head cupped in his long, slender hands.The red glow from the chinks of the stove shone on his face—in this light his heavy lips looked almost purple against his black skin, and his gray hair, tight against his skull like a cap of lamb's wool, took on a bluish color also.He sat motionless in this position for a long time.Even his eyes, which stared from behind the silver rims of his spectacles, did not change their fixed, somber gaze.Then he cleared his throat harshly, and picked up a book from the floor beside his chair.All around him the room was very dark, and he had to hold the book close to the stove to make out the print.Tonight he read Spinoza.He did not wholly understand the intricate play of ideas and the complex phrases, but as he read he sensed a strong, true purpose behind the words and he felt that he almost understood.

Often at night the sharp jangle of the doorbell would rouse him from his silence, and in the front room he would find a patient with a broken bone or with a razor wound. But this evening he was not disturbed.And after the solitary hours spent sitting in the dark kitchen it happened that he began swaying slowly from side to side and from his throat there came a sound like a kind of singing moan.He was making this sound when Portia came.

Doctor Copeland knew of her arrival in advance. From the street outside he caught the sound of a harmonica playing a blues song and he knew that the music was played by William, his son.Without turning on the light he went through the hall and opened the front door.He did not step out on the porch, but stood in the dark behind the screen.The moonlight was bright and the shadows of Portia and William and Highboy lay black and solid on the dusty street.The houses in the neighborhood had a miserable look.Doctor Copeland's house was different from any other building nearby.It was built solidly of brick and stucco.Around the small front yard there was a picket fence.Portia said good-bye to her husband and brother at the gate and knocked on the screen door.

“How come you sit here in the dark like this?”

They went together through the dark hall back to the kitchen.

“You haves grand electric lights. It don't seem natural why you all the time sitting in the dark like this.”

Doctor Copeland twisted the bulb suspended over the table and the room was suddenly very bright.“The dark suits me，”he said.

The room was clean and bare. On one side of the kitchen table there were books and an ink-stand—on the other side a fork, spoon, and plate.Doctor Copeland held himself bolt upright with his long legs crossed and at first Portia sat stiffly, too.The father and daughter had a strong resemblance to each other—both of them had the same broad, flat noses, the same mouths and foreheads.But Portia's skin was very light when compared to her Father's.

“It sure is roasting in here，”she said.“Seems to me you would let this here fire die down except when you cooking.”

“If you prefer we can go up to my office，”Doctor Copeland said.

“I be all right, I guess. I don't prefer.”

Doctor Copeland adjusted his silver-rimmed glasses and then folded his hands in his lap.“How have you been since we were last together?You and your husband—and your brother?”

Portia relaxed and slipped her feet out of her pumps.“Highboy and Willie and me gets along just fine.”

“William still boards with you?”

“Sure he do，”Portia said.“You see—us haves our own way of living and our own plan. Highboy—he pay the rent.I buys all the food out of my money.And Willie—he tends to all of our church dues, insurance, lodge dues, and Saturday Night.Us three haves our own plan and each one of us does our parts.”

Doctor Copeland sat with his head bowed, pulling at his long fingers until he had cracked all of his joints. The clean cuffs of his sleeves hung down past his wrists—below them his thin hands seemed lighter in color than the rest of his body and the palms were soft yellow.His hands had always an immaculate, shrunken look, as though they had been scrubbed with a brush and soaked for a long time in a pan of water.

“Here, I almost forgot what I brought，”Portia said.“Haves you had your supper yet?”

Doctor Copeland always spoke so carefully that each syllable seemed to be filtered through his sullen, heavy lips.“No, I have not eaten.”

Portia opened a paper sack she had placed on the kitchen table.“I done brought a nice mess of collard greens and I thought maybe we have supper together. I done brought a piece of side meat, too.These here greens need to be seasoned with that.You don't care if the collards is just cooked in meat, do you?”

“It does not matter.”

“You still don't eat nair meat?”

“No. For purely private reasons I am a vegetarian, but it does not matter if you wish to cook the collards with a piece of meat.”

Without putting on her shoes Portia stood at the table and carefully began to pick over the greens.“This here floor sure do feel good to my feets. You mind if I just walk around like this without putting back on them tight, hurting pumps?”

“No，”said Doctor Copeland.“That will be all right.”

“Then—us'll have these nice collards and some hoecake and coffee. And I going to cut me off a few slices of this here white meat and fry it for myself.”

Doctor Copeland followed Portia with his eyes. She moved slowly around the room in her stockinged feet, taking down the scrubbed pans from the wall, building up the fire, washing the grit from the collards.He opened his mouth to speak once and then composed his lips again.

“So you and your husband and your brother have your own cooperative plan，”he said finally.

“That's right.”

Doctor Copeland jerked at his fingers and tried to pop the joints again.“Do you intend to plan for children?”

Portia did not look at her father. Angrily she sloshed the water from the pan of collards.“There be some things，”she said，“that seem to me to depend entirely upon God.”

They did not say anything else. Portia left the supper to cook on the stove and sat silently with her long hands dropping down limp between her knees.Doctor Copeland's head rested on his chest as though he slept.But he was not sleeping；now and then a nervous tremor would pass over his face.Then he would breathe deeply and compose his face again.Smells of the supper began to fill the stifling room.In the quietness the clock on top of the cupboard sounded very loud, and because of what they had just said to each other the monotonous ticking was like the word“chil-dren, chil-dren，”said over and over.

He was always meeting one of them—crawling naked on a floor or engaged in a game of marbles or even on a dark street with his arms around a girl. Benedict Copeland, the boys were all called.But for the girls there were such names as Benny Mae or Madyben or Benedine Madine.He had counted one day, and there were more than a dozen named for him.

But all his life he had told and explained and exhorted. You cannot do this, he would say.There are all reasons why this sixth or fifth or ninth child cannot be, he would tell them.It is not more children we need but more chances for the ones already on the earth.Eugenic Parenthood for the Negro Race was what he would exhort them to.He would tell them in simple words, always the same way, and with the years it came to be a sort of angry poem which he had always known by heart.

He studied and knew the development of any new theory. And from his own pocket he would distribute the devices to his patients himself.He was by far the first doctor in the town to even think of such.And he would give and explain and give and tell them.And then deliver maybe two score times a week.Madyben and Benny Mae.

That was only one point. Only one.

All of his life he knew that there was a reason for his working. He always knew that he was meant to teach his people.All day he would go with his bag from house to house and on all things he would talk to them.

After the long day a heavy tiredness would come in him. But in the evening when he opened the front gate the tiredness would go away.There were Hamilton and Karl Marx and Portia and little William.There was Daisy, too.

Portia took the lid from the pan on the stove and stirred the collards with a fork.“Father—”she said after a while.

Doctor Copeland cleared his throat and spat into a handkerchief. His voice was bitter and rough.“Yes?”

“Less us quit this here quarreling with each other.”

“We were not quarreling，”said Doctor Copeland.

“It don't take words to make a quarrel，”Portia said.“It look to me like us is always arguing even when we sitting perfectly quiet like this. It just this here feeling I haves.I tell you the truth—ever time I come to see you it mighty near wears me out.So less us try not to quarrel in any way no more.”

“It is certainly not my wish to quarrel. I am sorry if you have that feeling, Daughter.”

She poured out coffee and handed one cup unsweetened to her father. In her own portion she put several spoons of sugar.“I getting hungry and this will taste good to us.Drink your coffee while I tell you something which happened to us a piece back.Now that it all over it seem a little bit funny, but we got plenty reason not to laugh too hard.”

“Go ahead，”said Doctor Copeland.

“Well—sometime back a real fine-looking, dressed-up colored man come in town here. He called hisself Mr.B.F.Mason and said he come from Washington, D.C.Ever day he would walk up and down the street with a walking-cane and a pretty colored shirt on.Then at night he would go to the Society Café.He eaten finer than any man in this town.Ever night he would order hisself a bottle of gin and two pork chops for his supper.He always had a smile for everbody and was always bowing around to the girls and holding a door open for you to come in or go out.For about a week he made hisself mighty pleasant wherever he were.Peoples begun to ask questions and wonder about this rich Mr.B.F.Mason.Then pretty soon, after he acquaints hisself, he begun to settle down to business.”

Portia spread out her lips and blew into her saucer of coffee.“I suppose you done read in the paper about this Government Pincher business for old folks?”

Doctor Copeland nodded.“Pension，”he said.

“Well—he were connected with that. He were from the government.He had to come down from the President in Washington, D.C.，to join everbody up for the Government Pinchers.He went around from one door to the next explaining how you pay one dollar down to join and after that twenty-five cents a week—and how when you were forty-five year old the government would pay you fifty dollars ever month of your life.All the peoples I know were very excited about this.He give everbody that joined a free picture of the President with his name signed under it.He told how at the end of six months there were going to be free uniforms for ever member.The club was called the Grand League of Pincheners for Colored Peoples—and at the end of two months everbody was going to get a orange ribbon with a G.L.P.C.P.on it to stand for the name.You know, like all these other letter things in the government.He come around from house to house with this little book and everbody commenced to join.He wrote their names down and took the money.Ever Saturday he would collect.In three weeks this Mr.B.F.Mason had joined up so many peoples he couldn't get all the way around on Saturday.He have to pay somebody to take up the collections in each three four blocks.I collected early ever Saturday for near where we live and got that quarter.Course Willie had joined at the beginning for him and Highboy and me.”

“I have come across many pictures of the President in various houses near where you live and I remember hearing the name Mason mentioned，”said Doctor Copeland.“He was a thief?”

“He were，”said Portia.“Somebody begun to find out about this Mr. B.F.Mason and he were arrested.They find out he were from just plain Atlanta and hadn't never smelled no Washington, D.C.，or no President.All the money were hid or spent.Willie had just throwed away seven dollars and fifty cents.”

Doctor Copeland was excited.“That is what I mean by—”

“In the hereafter，”Portia said，“that man sure going to wake up with a hot pitchfork in his gut. But now that it all over it do seem a little bit funny, but of course we got plenty reason not to laugh too hard.”

“The Negro race of its own accord climbs up on the cross on every Friday，”said Doctor Copeland.

Portia's hands shook and coffee trickled down from the saucer she was holding. She licked it from her arm.“What you mean?”

“I mean that I am always looking. I mean that if I could just find ten Negroes—ten of my own people—with spine and brains and courage who are willing to give all that they have—”

Portia put down the coffee.“Us was not talking about anything like that.”

“Only four Negroes，”said Doctor Copeland.“Only the sum of Hamilton and Karl Marx and William and you. Only four Negroes with these real true qualities and backbone—”

“Willie and Highboy and me have backbone，”said Portia angrily.“This here is a hard world and it seem to me us three struggles along pretty well.”

For a minute they were silent. Doctor Copeland laid his spectacles on the table and pressed his shrunken fingers to his eyeballs.

“You all the time using that word—Negro，”said Portia.“And that word haves a way of hurting people's feelings. Even old plain nigger is better than that word.But polite peoples—no matter what shade they is—always says colored.”

Doctor Copeland did not answer.

“Take Willie and me. Us aren't all the way colored.Our Mama was real light and both of us haves a good deal of white folks'blood in us.And Highboy—he Indian.He got a good part Indian in him.None of us is pure colored and the word you all the time using haves a way of hurting peoples'feelings.”

“I am not interested in subterfuges，”said Doctor Copeland.“I am interested only in real truths.”

“Well, this here is a truth. Everbody is scared of you.It sure would take a whole lot of gin to get Hamilton or Buddy or Willie or my Highboy to come in this house and sit with you like I does.Willie say he remember you when he were only a little boy and he were afraid of his own father then.”

Doctor Copeland coughed harshly and cleared his throat.

“Everbody haves feelings—no matter who they is—and nobody is going to walk in no house where they certain their feelings will be hurt. You the same way.I seen your feelings injured too many times by white people not to know that.”

“No，”said Doctor Copeland.“You have not seen my feelings injured.”

“Course I realize that Willie or my Highboy or me—that none of us is scholars. But Highboy and Willie is both good as gold.There just is a difference between them and you.”

“Yes，”said Doctor Copeland.

“Hamilton or Buddy or Willie or me—none of us ever cares to talk like you. Us talk like our own Mama and her peoples and their peoples before them.You think out everything in your brain.While us rather talk from something in our hearts that has been there for a long time.That's one of them differences.”

“Yes，”said Doctor Copeland.

“A person can't pick up they children and just squeeze them to which-a-way they wants them to be. Whether it hurt them or not.Whether it right or wrong.You done tried that hard as any man could try.And now I the only one of us that would come in this here house and sit with you like this.”

The light was very bright in Doctor Copeland's eyes and her voice was loud and hard. He coughed and his whole face trembled.He tried to pick up the cup of cold coffee, but his hand would not hold it steadily.The tears came up to his eyes and he reached for his glasses to try to hide them.

Portia saw and went up to him quickly. She put her arms around his head and pressed her cheek to his forehead.“I done hurt my Father's feelings，”she said softly.

His voice was hard.“No. It is foolish and primitive to keep repeating this about hurt feelings.”

The tears went slowly down his cheek and the fire made them take on the colors of blue and green and red.“I be really and truly sorry，”said Portia.

Doctor Copeland wiped his face with his cotton handkerchief.“It is all right.”

“Less us not ever quarrel no more. I can't stand this here fighting between us.It seem to me that something real bad come up in us ever time we be together.Less us never quarrel like this no more.”

“No，”said Doctor Copeland.“Let us not quarrel.”

Portia sniffled and wiped her nose with the back of her hand. For a few minutes she stood with her arms around her father's head.Then after a while she wiped her face for a final time and went over to the pot of greens on the stove.

“It mighty nigh time for these to be tender，”she said cheerfully.“Now I think I'll start making some of them good little hoecakes to go along with them.”

Portia moved slowly around the kitchen in her stockinged feet and her father followed her with his eyes. For a while again they were silent.

With his eyes wet, so that the edges of things were blurred, Portia was truly like her mother. Years ago Daisy had walked like that around the kitchen, silent and occupied.Daisy was not black as he was—her skin had been like the beautiful color of dark honey.She was always very quiet and gentle.But beneath that soft gentleness there was something stubborn in her, and no matter how conscientiously he studied it all out, he could not understand the gentle stubbornness in his wife.

He would exhort her and he would tell her all that was in his heart and still she was gentle. And still she would not listen to him but would go on her own way.

Then later there were Hamilton and Karl Marx and William and Portia. And this feeling of real true purpose for them was so strong that he knew exactly how each thing should be with them.Hamilton would be a great scientist and Karl Marx a teacher of the Negro race and William a lawyer to fight against injustice and Portia a doctor for women and children.

And when they were even babies he would tell them of the yoke they must thrust from their shoulders—the yoke of submission and slothfulness. And when they were a little older he would impress upon them that there was no God, but that their lives were holy and for each one of them there was this real true purpose.He would tell it to them over and over, and they would sit together far away from him and look with their big Negro-children eyes at their mother.And Daisy would sit without listening, gentle and stubborn.

Because of the true purpose for Hamilton, Karl Marx, William, and Portia, he knew how every detail should be. In the autumn of each year he took them all into town and bought for them good black shoes and black stockings.For Portia he bought black woolen material for dresses and white linen for collars and cuffs.For the boys there was black wool for trousers and fine white linen for shirts.He did not want them to wear bright-colored, flimsy clothes.But when they went to school those were the ones they wished to wear, and Daisy said that they were embarrassed and that he was a hard father.He knew how the house should be.There could be no fanciness—no gaudy calendars or lace pillows or knick-knacks—but everything in the house must be plain and dark and indicative of work and the real true purpose.

Then one night he found that Daisy had pierced holes in little Portia's ears for earrings. And another time a kewpie doll with feather skirts was on the mantelpiece when he came home, and Daisy was gentle and hard and would not put it away.He knew, too, that Daisy was teaching the children the cult of meekness.She told them about hell and heaven.Also she convinced them of ghosts and of haunted places.Daisy went to church every Sunday and she talked sorrowfully to the preacher of her own husband.And with her stubbornness she always took the children to the church, too, and they listened.

The whole Negro race was sick, and he was busy all the day and sometimes half the night. After the long day a great weariness would come in him, but when he opened the front gate of his home the weariness would go away.Yet when he went into the house William would be playing music on a comb wrapped in toilet paper, Hamilton and Karl Marx would be shooting craps for their lunch money, Portia would be laughing with her mother.

He would start all over with them, but in a different way. He would bring out their lessons and talk with them.They would sit close together and look at their mother.He would talk and talk, but none of them wanted to understand.

The feeling that would come on him was a black, terrible Negro feeling. He would try to sit in his office and read and meditate until he could be calm and start again.He would pull down the shades of the room so that there would be only the bright light and the books and the feeling of meditation.But sometimes this calmness would not come.He was young, and the terrible feeling would not go away with study.

Hamilton, Karl Marx, William, and Portia would be afraid of him and look at their mother—and sometimes when he realized this the black feeling would conquer him and he knew not what he did.

He could not stop those terrible things, and afterward he could never understand.

“This here supper sure smells good to me，”said Portia.“I expect us better eat now because Highboy and Willie liable to come trooping in any minute.”

Doctor Copeland settled his spectacles and pulled his chair up to the table.“Where have your husband and William been spending the evening?”

“They been throwing horseshoes. This here Raymond Jones haves a horseshoe place in his back yard.This Raymond and his sister, Love Jones, plays ever night.Love is such a ugly girl I don't mind about Highboy or Willie going around to their house any time they wishes.But they said they would come back for me at quarter to ten and I expecting them now any minute.”

“Before I forget，”said Doctor Copeland.“I suppose you hear frequently from Hamilton and Karl Marx.”

“I does from Hamilton. He practically taken over all the work on our Grandpapa's place.But Buddy, he in Mobile—and you know he were never a big hand at writing letters.However, Buddy always haves such a sweet way with peoples that I don't ever worry concerning him.He the kind to always get along right well.”

They sat silently at the table before the supper. Portia kept looking up at the clock on the cupboard because it was time for Highboy and Willie to come.Doctor Copeland bent his head over the plate.He held the fork in his hand as though it were heavy, and his fingers trembled.He only tasted the food and with each mouthful he swallowed hard.There was a feeling of strain, and it seemed as though both of them wanted to keep up some conversation.

Doctor Copeland did not know how to begin. Sometimes he thought that he had talked so much in the years before to his children and they had understood so little that now there was nothing at all to say.After a while he wiped his mouth with his handkerchief and spoke in an uncertain voice.

“You have hardly mentioned yourself. Tell me about your job and what you have been doing lately.”

“Course I still with the Kellys，”said Portia.“But I tells you, Father, I don't know how long I going to be able to keep on with them. The work is hard and it always take me a long time to get through.However, that don't bother me none.It about the pay I worries about.I suppose to get three dollars a week—but sometimes Mrs.Kelly likes a dollar or fifty cents of paying me the full amount.Course she always catches up on it soon as she able.But it haves a way of leaving me in a pinch.”

“That is not right，”said Doctor Copeland.“Why do you stand for it?”

“It ain't her fault. She can't help it，”said Portia.“Half the folks in that house don't pay the rent, and it a big expense to keep everything up.I tell you the truth—the Kellys is just barely keeping one jump ahead of the sheriff.They having a mighty hard time.”

“There ought to be some other job you can get.”

“I know. But the Kellys is really grand white peoples to work for.I really fond of them as I can be.Them three little children is just like some of my own kinfolks.I feel like I done really raised Bubber and the baby.And although Mick and me is always getting into some kind of quarrel together, I haves a real close fondness for her, too.”

“But you must think of yourself，”said Doctor Copeland.

“Mick, now—”said Portia.“She a real case. Not a soul know how to manage that child.She just as biggity and headstrong as she can be.Something going on in her all the time.I haves a funny feeling about that child.It seem to me that one of these days she going to really surprise somebody.But whether that going to be a good surprise or a bad surprise I just don't know.Mick puzzles me sometimes.But still I really fond of her.”

“You must look out for your own livelihood first.”

“As I say, it ain't Mrs. Kelly's fault.It costs so much to run that big old house and the rent just don't be paid.Ain't but one person in the house who pay a decent amount for his room and pay it on the dot without fail.And that man only been living there a short while.He one of these here deaf-and-dumb folks.He the first one of them I ever seen close up—but he a mighty fine white man.”

“Tall, thin, with gray and green eyes?”asked Doctor Copeland suddenly.“And always polite to everyone and very well dressed?Not like someone from this town—more like a Northerner or maybe a Jew?”

“That him，”said Portia.

Eagerness came into Doctor Copeland's face. He crumbled his hoecake into the collard juice in his plate and began to eat with a new appetite.“I have a deaf-mute patient，”he said.

“How come you acquainted with Mr. Singer?”asked Portia.

Doctor Copeland coughed and covered his mouth with his handkerchief.“I have just seen him several times.”

“I better clean up now，”said Portia.“It sure enough time for Willie and my Highboy. But with this here real sink and grand running water these little dishes won't take me two winks.”

The quiet insolence of the white race was one thing he had tried to keep out of his mind for years. When the resentment would come to him he would cogitate and study.In the streets and around white people he would keep the dignity on his face and always be silent.When he was younger it was“Boy”—but now it was“Uncle.”“Uncle, run down to that filling station on the corner and send me a mechanic.”A white man in a car had called out those words to him not long ago.“Boy, give me a hand with this.”—“Uncle, do that.”And he would not listen, but would walk, on with the dignity in him and be silent.

A few nights ago a drunken white man had come up to him and begun pulling him along the street. He had his bag with him and he was sure someone was hurt.But the drunkard had pulled him into a white man's restaurant and the white men at the counter had begun hollering out with their insolence.He knew that the drunkard was making fun of him.Even then he had kept the dignity in him.

But with this tall, thin white man with the gray-green eyes something had happened that had never happened to him with any white man before.

It came about on a dark, rainy night several weeks ago. He had just come from a maternity case and was standing in the rain on a corner.He had tried to light a cigarette and one by one the matches in his box fizzled out.He had been standing with the unlighted cigarette in his mouth when the white man stepped up and held for him a lighted match.In the dark with the flame between them they could see each other's faces.The white man smiled at him and lighted for him his cigarette.He did not know what to say, for nothing like that had ever happened to him before.

They had stood for a few minutes on the street corner together, and then the white man had handed him his card. He wanted to talk to the white man and ask him some questions, but he did not know for sure if he could really understand.Because of the insolence of all the white race he was afraid to lose his dignity in friendliness.

But the white man had lighted his cigarette and smiled and seemed to want to be with him. Since then he had thought this over many times.

“I have a deaf-mute patient，”said Doctor Copeland to Portia.“The patient is a boy five years of age. And somehow I cannot get over the feeling that I am to blame for his handicap.I delivered him, and after two post-delivery visits of course I forgot about him.He developed ear trouble, but the mother paid no attention to the discharges from his ears and did not bring him to me.When it was finally brought to my attention it was too late.Of course he hears nothing and of course he therefore cannot speak.But I have watched him carefully, and it seems to me that if he were normal he would be a very intelligent child.”

“You always had a great interest in little children，”said Portia.“You care a heap more about them than about grown peoples, don't you?”

“There is more hope in the young child，”said Doctor Copeland.“But this deaf boy—I have been meaning to make inquiries and find if there is some institution that would take him.”

“Mr. Singer would tell you.He a truly kind white man and he not a bit biggity.”

“I do not know—”said Doctor Copeland.“I have thought once or twice about writing him a note and seeing if he could give me information.”

“Sure I would if I was you. You a grand letter-writer and I would give it to Mr.Singer for you，”said Portia.“He come down in the kitchen two-three weeks ago with a few shirts he wanted me to rinch out for him.Them shirts were no more dirty than if Saint John the Baptist hisself had been wearing them.All I had to do were dip them in warm water and give the collars a small rub and press them.But that night when I taken them five clean shirts up to his room you know how much he give me?”

“No.”

“He smile like he always do and hand over to me a dollar. A whole dollar just for them little shirts.He one really kind and pleasant white man and I wouldn't be afraid to ask him any question.I wouldn't even mind writing that nice white man a letter myself.You go right ahead and do it, Father, if you wants to.”

“Perhaps I will，”said Doctor Copeland.

Portia sat up suddenly and began arranging her tight, oily hair. There was the faint sound of a harmonica and then gradually the music grew louder.“Here come Willie and Highboy，”Portia said.“I got to go out now and meet them.You take care of yourself now, and send me a word if you needs me for anything.I did enjoy the supper with you and the talking very much.”

The music from the harmonica was very clear now, and they could tell that Willie was playing while he waited at the front gate.

“Wait a minute，”said Doctor Copeland.“I have only seen your husband with you about two times and I believe we have never really met each other. And it has been three years since William has visited his father.Why not tell them to drop in for a little while?”

Portia stood in the doorway, fingering her hair and her earrings.

“Last time Willie come in here you hurted his feelings. You see you don't understand just how—”

“Very well，”said Doctor Copeland.“It was only a suggestion.”

“Wait，”said Portia.“I going to call them. I going to invite them in right now.”

Doctor Copeland lighted a cigarette and walked up and down the room. He could not straighten his glasses to just the right position and his fingers kept trembling.From the front yard there was the sound of low voices.Then heavy footsteps were in the hall and Portia, William, and Highboy entered the kitchen.

“Here we is，”said Portia.“Highboy, I don't believe you and my Father has ever truly been introduced to each other. But you knows who each other is.”

Doctor Copeland shook hands with both of them. Willie hung back shyly against the wall, but Highboy stepped forward and bowed formally.“I has always heard so much about you，”he said.“I be very pleased to make your acquaintance.”

Portia and Doctor Copeland brought in chairs from the hall and the four of them sat around the stove. They were silent and uneasy.Willie gazed nervously around the room—at the books on the kitchen table, the sink, the cot against the wall, and at his father.Highboy grinned and picked at his tie.Doctor Copeland seemed about to speak, and then he wet his lips and was still silent.

“Willie, you were going pretty good with your harp，”said Portia finally.“Look to me like you and Highboy must of got into somebody's gin bottle.”

“No, ma'am，”said Highboy very politely.“Us haven't had anything since Saturday. Us have just been enjoying our horseshoe game.”

Doctor Copeland still did not speak, and they all kept glancing at him and waiting. The room was close and the quietness made everyone nervous.

“I do haves the hardest time with them boys'clothes，”Portia said.“I washes both of them white suits ever Saturday and I presses them twice a week. And look at them now.Course they don't wear them except when they gets home from work.But after two days they seems to be potty black.I ironed them pants just last night and now there not a crease left.”

Still Doctor Copeland was silent. He kept his eyes on his son's face, but when Willie noticed this he bit his rough, blunt fingers and stared at his feet.Doctor Copeland felt his pulse hammering at his wrists and temples.He coughed and held his fist to his chest.He wanted to speak to his son, but he could think of nothing to say.The old bitterness came up in him and he did not have time to cogitate and push it down.His pulse hammered in him and he was confused.But they all looked at him, and the silence was so strong that he had to speak.

His voice was high and it did not sound as though it came from himself.“William, I wonder how much of all the things I have said to you when you were a child have stayed in your mind.”

“I don't know what you m-m-means，”Willie said.

The words came before Doctor Copeland knew what he would say.“I mean that to you and Hamilton and Karl Marx I gave all that was in me. And I put all of my trust and hope in you.And all I get is blank misunderstanding and idleness and indifference.Of all I have put in nothing has remained.All has been taken away from me.All that I have tried to do—”

“Hush，”said Portia.“Father, you promised me that us would not quarrel. This here is crazy.Us can't afford to quarrel.”

Portia got up and started toward the front door. Willie and Highboy followed quickly.Doctor Copeland was the last to come.

They stood in the dark before the front door. Doctor Copeland tried to speak, but his voice seemed lost somewhere deep inside him.Willie and Portia and Highboy stood in a group together.

With one arm Portia held to her husband and brother and with the other she reached out to Doctor Copeland.“Less us all make up now before us goes. I can't stand this here fighting between us.Less us not ever quarrel no more.”

In silence Doctor Copeland shook hands again with each of them.“I am sorry，”he said.

“It quite all right with me，”said Highboy politely.

“It quite all right with me too，”Willie mumbled.

Portia held all of their hands together.“Us just can't afford to quarrel.”

They said good-bye, and Doctor Copeland watched them from the dark front porch as they went together up the street. Their footsteps as they walked away had a lonesome sound and he felt weak and tired.When they were a block away William began playing his harmonica again.The music was sad and empty.He stayed on the front porch until he could neither see nor hear them any longer.

Doctor Copeland turned off the lights in his house and sat in the dark before the stove. But peace would not come to him.He wanted to remove Hamilton and Karl Marx and William from his mind.Each word that Portia had said to him came back in a loud, hard way to his memory.He got up suddenly and turned on the light.He settled himself at the table with his books by Spinoza and William Shakespeare and Karl Marx.When he read the Spinoza aloud to himself the words had a rich, dark sound.

He thought of the white man of whom they had spoken. It would be good if the white man could help him with Augustus Benedict Mady Lewis, the deaf patient.It would be good to write to the white man even if he did not have this reason and these questions to ask.Doctor Copeland held his head in his hands and from his throat there came the strange sound like a kind of singing moan.He remembered the white man's face when he smiled behind the yellow match flame on that rainy night—and peace was in him.

6

By midsummer Singer had visitors more often than any other person in the house. From his room in the evening there was nearly always the sound of a voice.After dinner at the New York Café　he bathed and dressed himself in one of his cool wash suits and as a rule did not go out again.The room was cool and pleasant.He had an icebox in the closet where he kept bottles of cold beer and fruit drinks.He was never busy or in a hurry.And always he met his guests at the door with a welcome smile.

Mick loved to go up to Mister Singer's room. Even if he was a deaf-and-dumb mute he understood every word she said to him.Talking with him was like a game.Only there was a whole lot more to it than any game.It was like finding out new things about music.She would tell him some of her plans that she would not tell anybody else.He let her meddle with his cute little chess men.Once when she was excited and caught her shirt-tail in the electric fan he acted in such a kindly way that she was not embarrassed at all.Except for her Dad, Mister Singer was the nicest man she knew.

When Doctor Copeland wrote the note to John Singer about Augustus Benedict Mady Lewis there was a polite reply and an invitation for him to make a call when he found the opportunity. Doctor Copeland went to the back of the house and sat with Portia awhile in the kitchen.Then he climbed the stairs to the white man's room.There was truly none of the quiet insolence about this man.They had a lemonade together and the mute wrote down the answer to the questions he wished to know.This man was different from any person of the white race whom Doctor Copeland had ever encountered.Afterward he pondered about this white man a long time.Then later, inasmuch as he had been invited in a cordial manner to return, he made another visit.

Jake Blount came every week. When he walked up to Singer's room the whole stairway shook.Usually he carried a paper sack of beers.Often his voice would come out loud and angry from the room.But before he left his voice gradually quieted.When he descended the stairs he did not carry the sack of beers any longer, and he walked away thoughtfully without seeming to notice where he was going.

Even Biff Brannon came to the mute's room one night. But as he could never stay away from the restaurant for long, he left in a half-hour.

Singer was always the same to everyone. He sat in a straight chair by the window with his hands stuffed tight into his pockets, and nodded or smiled to show his guests that he understood.

If he did not have a visitor in the evening, Singer went to a late movie. He liked to sit back and watch the actors talking and walking about on the screen.He never looked at the title of a picture before going into a movie, and no matter what was showing he watched each scene with equal interest.

Then one day in July, Singer suddenly went away without warning. He left the door of his room open, and on the table in an envelope adddessed to Mrs.Kelly there were four dollars for the past week's rent.His few simple possessions were gone and the room was very clean and bare.When his visitors came and saw this empty room they went away with hurt surprise.No one could imagine why he had left like this.

Singer spent all of his summer vacation in the town where Antonapoulos was being kept in the asylum. For months he had planned this trip and imagined about each moment they would have together.Two weeks beforehand his hotel reservation had been made and for a long time he had carried his railroad ticket in an envelope in his pocket.

Antonapoulos was not changed at all. When Singer came into his room he ambled placidly to meet his friend.He was even fatter than before, but the dreamy smile on his face was just the same.Singer had some packages in his arms and the big Greek gave them his first attention.His presents were a scarlet dressing-gown, soft bedroom slippers, and two monogrammed nightshirts.Antonapoulos looked beneath all the tissue papers in the boxes very carefully.When he saw that nothing good to eat had been concealed there, he dumped the gifts disdainfully on his bed and did not bother with them any more.

The room was large and sunny. Several beds were spaced in a row together.Three old men played a game of slapjack in a corner.They did not notice Singer or Antonapoulos, and the two friends sat alone on the other side of the room.

It seemed to Singer that years had passed since they had been together. There was so much to say that his hands could not shape the signs with speed enough.His green eyes burned and sweat glittered on his forehead.The old feeling of gaiety and bliss was so quick in him again that he could not control himself.

Antonapoulos kept his dark, oily eyes on his friend and did not move. His hands fumbled languidly with the crotch of his trousers.Singer told him, among other things, about the visitors who had been coming to see him.He told his friend that they helped take his mind away from his lonesomeness.He told Antonapoulos that they were strange people and always talking—but that he liked to have them come.He drew quick sketches of Jake Blount and Mick and Doctor Copeland.Then as soon as he saw mat Antonapoulos was not interested Singer crumpled the sketches and forgot about them.When the attendant came in to say that their time was up, Singer had not finished half of the things he wanted to say.But he left the room very tired and happy.

The patients could receive their friends only on Thursday and Sunday. On the days when he could not be with Antonapoulos, Singer walked up and down in his room at the hotel.

His second visit to his friend was like the first, except that the old men in the room watched them listlessly and did not play slapjack.

After much trouble Singer obtained permission to take Antonapoulos out with him for a few hours. He planned each detail of the little excursion in advance.They drove out into the country in a taxi, and then at four-thirty they went to the dining-room at the hotel.Antonapoulos greatly enjoyed his extra meal.He ordered half the dishes on the menu and ate very greedily.But when he had finished he would not leave.He held to the table.Singer coaxed him and the cab driver wanted to use force.Antonapoulos sat stolidly and made obscene gestures when they came too close to him.At last Singer bought a bottle of whiskey from the hotel manager and lured him into the taxi again.When Singer threw the unopened bottle out of the window Antonapoulos wept with disappointment and offense.The end of their little excursion made Singer very sad.

His next visit was the last one, for his two weeks'vacation was almost over. Antonapoulos had forgotten what had happened before.They sat in their same corner of the room.The minutes slipped by quickly.Singer's hands talked desperately and his narrow face was very pale.At last it was time for him to go.He held his friend by the arm and looked into his face in the way that he used to do when they parted each day before work.Antonapoulos stared at him drowsily and did not move.Singer left the room with his hands stuffed hard into his pockets.

Soon after Singer returned to his room at the boarding-house, Mick and Jake Blount and Doctor Copeland began to come again. Each one of them wanted to know where he had been and why he had not let them know about his plans.But Singer pretended that he did not understand their questions, and his smile was inscrutable.

One by one they would come to Singer's room to spend the evening with him. The mute was always thoughtful and composed.His many-tinted gentle eyes were grave as a sorcerer's.Mick Kelly and Jake Blount and Doctor Copeland would come and talk in the silent room—for they felt that the mute would always understand whatever they wanted to say to him.And maybe even more than that.

PART TWO

1

This summer was different from any other time Mick could remember. Nothing much happened that she could describe to herself in thoughts or words—but there was a feeling of change.All the time she was excited.In the morning she couldn't wait to get out of bed and start going for the day.And at night she hated like hell to have to sleep again.

Right after breakfast she took the kids out, and except for meals they were gone most of the day. A good deal of the time they just roamed around the streets—with her pulling Ralph's wagon and Bubber following along behind.Always she was busy with thoughts and plans.Sometimes she would look up suddenly and they would be way off in some part of town she didn't even recognize.And once or twice they ran into Bill on the streets and she was so busy thinking he had to grab her by the arm to make her see him.

Early in the mornings it was a little cool and their shadows stretched out tall on the sidewalk in front of them. But in the middle of the day the sky was always blazing hot.The glare was so bright it hurt to keep your eyes open.A lot of times the plans about the things that were going to happen to her were mixed up with ice and snow.Sometimes it was like she was out in Switzerland and all the mountains were covered with snow and she was skating on cold, greenish-colored ice.Mister Singer would be skating with her.And maybe Carole Lombard or Arturo Toscanini who played on the radio.They would be skating together and then Mister Singer would fall through the ice and she would dive in without regard for peril and swim under the ice and save his life.That was one of the plans always going on in her mind.

Usually after they had walked awhile she would park Bubber and Ralph in some shady place. Bubber was a swell kid and she had trained him pretty good.If she told him not to go out of hollering distance from Ralph she wouldn't ever find him shooting marbles with kids two or three blocks away.He played by himself near the wagon, and when she left them she didn't have to worry much.She either went to the library and looked at the National Geographic or else just roamed around and thought some more.If she had any money she bought a dope or a Milky Way at Mister Brannon's.He gave kids a reduction.He sold them nickel things for three cents.

But all the time—no matter what she was doing—there was music. Sometimes she hummed to herself as she walked, and other times she listened quietly to the songs inside her.There were all kinds of music in her thoughts.Some she heard over radios, and some was in her mind already without her ever having heard it anywhere.

In the night-time, as soon as the kids were in bed, she was free. That was the most important time of all.A lot of things happened when she was by herself and it was dark.Right after supper she ran out of the house again.She couldn't tell anybody about the things she did at night, and when her Mama asked her questions she would answer with any little tale that sounded reasonable.But most of the time if anybody called her she just ran away like she hadn't heard.That went for everybody except her Dad.There was something about her Dad's voice she couldn't run away from.He was one of the biggest, tallest men in the whole town.But his voice was so quiet and kindly that people were surprised when he spoke.No matter how much of a hurry she was in, she always had to stop when her Dad called.

This summer she realized something about her Dad she had never known before. Up until then she had never thought about him as being a real separate person.A lot of times he would call her.She would go in the front room where he worked and stand by him a couple of minutes—but when she listened to him her mind was never on the things he said to her.Then one night she suddenly realized about her Dad.Nothing unusual happened that night and she didn't know what it was that made her understand.Afterward she felt older and as though she knew him as good as she could know any person.

It was a night in late August and she was in a big rush. She had to be at this house by nine o'clock, and no maybe either.Her Dad called and she went into the front room.He was sitting slumped over his workbench.For some reason it never did seem natural to see him there.Until the time of his accident last year he had been a painter and carpenter.Before daylight every morning he would leave the house in his overalls, to be gone all day.Then at night sometimes he fiddled around with clocks as an extra work.A lot of times he had tried to get a job in a jewelry store where he could sit by himself at a desk all day with a clean white shirt on and a tie.Now when he couldn't carpenter any more he had put a sign at the front of the house reading“Clocks and Watches Repaired Cheap.”But he didn't look like most jewelers—the ones downtown were quick, dark little Jew men.Her Dad was too tall for his workbench, and his big bones seemed joined together in a loose way.

Her Dad just stared at her. She could tell he didn't have any reason for calling.He only wanted real bad to talk to her.He tried to think of some way to begin.His brown eyes were too big for his long, thin face, and since he had lost every single hair the pale, bald top of his head gave him a naked look.He still looked at her without speaking and she was in a hurry.She had to be at that house by nine sharp and there was no time to waste.Her Dad saw she was in a hurry and he cleared his throat.

“I got something for you，”he said.“Nothing much, but maybe you can treat yourself with it.”

He didn't have to give her any nickel or dime just because he was lonesome and wanted to talk. Out of what he made he only kept enough to have beer about twice a week.Two bottles were on the floor by his chair now, one empty and one just opened.And whenever he drank beer he liked to talk to somebody.Her Dad fumbled with his belt and she looked away.This summer he had gotten like a kid about hiding those nickels and dimes he kept for himself.Sometimes he hid them in his shoes, and other times in a little slit he had cut in his belt.She only half-way wanted to take the dime, but when he held it out her hand was just naturally open and ready.

“I got so much work to do I don't know where to begin，”he said.

That was just the opposite to the truth, and he knew it good as she did. He never had many watches to fix, and when he finished he would fool around the house doing any little job that was needed.Then at night he sat at his bench, cleaning old springs and wheels and trying to make the work last out until bedtime.Ever since he broke his hip and couldn't work steady he had to be doing something every minute.

“I been thinking a lot tonight，”her Dad said. He poured out his beer and sprinkled a few grains of salt on the back of his hand.Then he licked up the salt and took a swallow out of the glass.

She was in such a hurry that it was hard to stand still. Her Dad noticed this.He tried to say something—but he had not called to tell her anything special.He only wanted to talk with her for a little while.He started to speak and swallowed.They just looked at each other.The quietness grew out longer and neither of them could say a word.

That was when she realized about her Dad. It wasn't like she was learning a new fact—she had understood it all along in every way except with her brain.Now she just suddenly knew that she knew about her Dad.He was lonesome and he was an old man.Because none of the kids went to him for anything and because he didn't earn much money he felt like he was cut off from the family.And in his lonesomeness he wanted to be close to one of his kids—and they were all so busy that they didn't know it.He felt like he wasn't much real use to anybody.

She understood this while they were looking at each other. It gave her a queer feeling.Her Dad picked up a watch spring and cleaned it with a brush dipped in gasoline.

“I know you're in a hurry. I just hollered to say hello.”

“No, I'm not in any rush，”she said.“Honest.”

That night she sat down in a chair by his bench and they talked awhile. He talked about accounts and expenses and how things would have been if he had just managed in a different way.He drank beer, and once the tears came to his eyes and he snuffled his nose against his shirt-sleeve.She stayed with him a good while that night.Even if she was in an awful hurry.Yet for some reason she couldn't tell him about the things in her mind—about the hot, dark nights.

These nights were secret, and of the whole summer they were the most important time. In the dark she walked by herself and it was like she was the only person in the town.Almost every street came to be as plain to her in the night-time as her own home block.Some kids were afraid to walk through strange places in the dark, but she wasn't.Girls were scared a man would come out from somewhere and put his teapot in them like they was married.Most girls were nuts.If a person the size of Joe Louis or Mountain Man Dean would jump out at her and want to fight she would run.But if it was somebody within twenty pounds her weight she would give him a good sock and go right on.

The nights were wonderful, and she didn't have time to think about such things as being scared. Whenever she was in the dark she thought about music.While she walked along the streets she would sing to herself.And she felt like the whole town listened without knowing it was Mick Kelly.

She learned a lot about music during these free nights in the summer-time. When she walked out in the rich parts of town every house had a radio.All the windows were open and she could hear the music very marvelous.After a while she knew which houses tuned in for the programs she wanted to hear.There was one special house that got all the good orchestras.And at night she would go to this house and sneak into the dark yard to listen.There was beautiful shrubbery around this house, and she would sit under a bush near the window.And after it was all over she would stand in the dark yard with her hands in her pockets and think for a long time.That was the realest part of all the summer—her listening to this music on the radio and studying about it.

“Cerra fa puerta, señor，”Mick said.

Bubber was sharp as a briar.“Hagame usted el favor, señorita，”he answered as a comeback.

It was grand to take Spanish at Vocational. There was something about speaking in a foreign language that made her feel like she'd been around a lot.Every afternoon since school had started she had fun speaking the new Spanish words and sentences.At first Bubber was stumped, and it was funny to watch his face while she talked the foreign language.Then he caught on in a hurry, and before long he could copy everything she said.He remembered the words he learned, too.Of course he didn't know what all the sentences meant, but she didn't say them for the sense they made, anyway.After a while the kid learned so fast she gave out of Spanish and just gabbled along with made-up sounds.But it wasn't long before he caught her out at that—nobody could put a thing over on old Bubber Kelly.

“I'm going to pretend like I'm walking into this house for the first time，”Mick said.“Then I can tell better if all the decoration looks good or not.”

She walked out on the front porch and then came back and stood in the hall. All day she and Bubber and Portia and her Dad had been fixing the hall and the dining-room for the party.The decoration was autumn leaves and vines and red crêpe paper.On the mantelpiece in the dining-room and sticking up behind the hatrack there were bright yellow leaves.They had trailed vines along the walls and on the table where the punch bowl would be.The red crêpe paper hung down in long fringes from the mantel and also was looped around the backs of the chairs.There was plenty decoration.It was O.K.

She rubbed her hand on her forehead and squinted her eyes. Bubber stood beside her and copied every move she made.“I sure do want this party to turn out all right.I sure do.”

This would be the first party she had ever given. She had never even been to more than four or five.Last summer she had gone to a prom party.But none of the boys asked her to prom or dance, so she just stood by the punch bowl until all the refreshments were gone and then went home.This party was not going to be a bit like that one.In a few hours now the people she had invited would start coming and the to-do would begin.

It was hard to remember just how she got the idea of this party. The notion came to her soon after she started at Vocational.High School was swell.Everything about it was different from Grammar School.She wouldn't have liked it so much if she had had to take a stenographic course like Hazel and Etta had done—but she got special permission and took mechanical shop like a boy.Shop and Algebra and Spanish were grand.English was mighty hard.Her English teacher was Miss Minner.Everybody said Miss Minner had sold her brains to a famous doctor for ten thousand dollars, so that after she was dead he could cut them up and see why she was so smart.On written lessons she cracked such questions as“Name eight famous contemporaries of Doctor Johnson，”and“Quote ten lines from‘The Vicar of Wakefield.'”She called on people by the alphabet and kept her grade book open during the lessons.And even if she was brainy she was an old sourpuss.The Spanish teacher had traveled once in Europe.She said that in France the people carried home loaves of bread without having them wrapped up.They would stand talking on the streets and hit the bread on a lamp post.And there wasn't any water in France only wine.

In nearly all ways Vocational was wonderful. They walked back and forth in the hall between classes, and at lunch period students hung around the gym.Here was the thing that soon began to bother her.In the halls the people would walk up and down together and everybody seemed to belong to some special bunch.Within a week or two she knew people in the halls and in classes to speak to them—but that was all.She wasn't a member of any bunch.In Grammar School she would have just gone up to any crowd she wanted to belong with and that would have been the end of the matter.Here it was different.

During the first week she walked up and down the halls by herself and thought about this. She planned about being with some bunch almost as much as she thought of music.Those two ideas were in her head all the time.And finally she got the idea of the party.

She was strict with the invitations. No Grammar School kids and nobody under twelve years old.She just asked people between thirteen and fifteen.She knew everybody she invited good enough to speak to them in the halls—and when she didn't know their names she asked to find out.She called up those who had a telephone, and the rest she invited at school.

On the telephone she always said the same thing. She let Bubber stick in his ear to listen.“This is Mick Kelly，”she said.If they didn't understand the name she kept on until they got it.“I'm having a prom party at eight o'clock Saturday night and I'm inviting you now.I live at　103　Fourth Street, Apartment A.”That Apartment A sounded swell on the telephone.Nearly everybody said they would be delighted.A couple of tough boys tried to be smarty and kept on asking her name over and over.One of them tried to act cute and said，“I don't know you.”She squelched him in a hurry：“You go eat grass！”Outside of that wise guy there were ten boys and ten girls and she knew that they were all coming.This was a real party, and it would be better and different from any party she had ever gone to or heard about before.

Mick looked over the hall and dining-room one last time. By the hatrack she stopped before the picture of Old Dirty-Face.This was a photo of her Mama's grandfather.He was a major way back in the Civil War and had been killed in a battle.Some kids once drew eyeglasses and a beard on his picture, and when the pencil marks were erased it left his face all dirty.That was why she called him Old Dirty-Face.The picture was in the middle of a three-part frame.On both sides were pictures of his sons.They looked about Bubber's age.They had on uniforms and their faces were surprised.They had been killed in battle also.A long time ago.

“I'm going to take this down for the party. I think it looks common.Don't you?”

“I don't know，”Bubber said.“Are we common, Mick?”

“I'm not.”

She put the picture underneath the hatrack. The decoration was O.K.Mister Singer would be pleased when he came home.The rooms seemed very empty and quiet.The table was set for supper.And then after supper it would be time for the party.She went into the kitchen to see about the refreshments.

“You think everything will be all right?”she asked Portia.

Portia was making biscuits. The refreshments were on top of the stove.There were peanut butter and jelly sandwiches and chocolate snaps and punch.The sandwiches were covered with a damp dishcloth.She peeped at them but didn't take one.

“I done told you forty times that everything going to be all right，”Portia said.“Just soon as I come back from fixing supper at home I going to put on that white apron and serve the food real nice. Then I going to push off from here by nine-thirty.This here is Saturday night and Highboy and Willie and me haves our plans, too.”

“Sure，”Mick said.“I just want you to help out till things sort of get started—you know.”

She gave in and took one of the sandwiches. Then she made Bubber stay with Portia and went into the middle room.The dress she would wear was laying out on the bed.Hazel and Etta had both been good about lending her their best clothes—considering that they weren't supposed to come to the party.There was Etta's long blue crêpe de chine evening dress and some white pumps and a rhinestone tiara for her hair.These clothes were really gorgeous.It was hard to imagine how she would look in them.

The late afternoon had come and the sun made long, yellow slants through the window. If she took two hours over dressing for the party it was time to begin now.When she thought about putting on the fine clothes she couldn't just sit around and wait.Very slowly she went into the bathroom and shucked off her old shorts and shirt and turned on the water.She scrubbed the rough parts of her heels and her knees and especially her elbows.She made the bath take a long time.

She ran naked into the middle room and began to dress. Silk teddies she put on, and silk stockings.She even wore one of Etta's brassières just for the heck of it.Then very carefully she put on the dress and stepped into the pumps.This was the first time she had ever worn an evening dress.She stood for a long time before the mirror.She was so tall that the dress came up two or three inches above her ankles—and the shoes were so short they hurt her.She stood in front of the mirror a long tune, and finally decided she either looked like a sap or else she looked very beautiful.One or the other.

Six different ways she tried out her hair. The cowlicks were a little trouble, so she wet her bangs and made three spit curls.Last of all she stuck the rhinestones in her hair and put on plenty of lipstick and paint.When she finished she lifted up her chin and half-closed eyes like a movie star.Slowly she turned her face from one side to the other.It was beautiful she looked—just beautiful.

She didn't feel like herself at all. She was somebody different from Mick Kelly entirely.Two hours had to pass before the party would begin, and she was ashamed for any of the family to see her dressed so far ahead of time.She went into the bathroom again and locked the door.She couldn't mess up her dress by sitting down, so she stood in the middle of the floor.The close walls around her seemed to press in all the excitement.She felt so different from the old Mick Kelly that she knew this would be better than anything else in all her whole life—this party.

“Yippee！The punch！”

“The cutest dress—”

“Say！You solve that one about the triangle forty-six by twen—”

“Lemme by！Move out my way！”

The front door slammed every second as the people swarmed into the house. Sharp voices and soft voices sounded together until there was just one roaring noise.Girls stood in bunches in their long, fine evening dresses, and the boys roamed around in clean duck pants or R.O.T.C.uniforms or new dark fall suits.There was so much commotion that Mick couldn't notice any separate face or person.She stood by the hatrack and stared around at the party as a whole.

“Everybody get a prom card and start signing up.”

At first the room was too loud for anyone to hear and pay attention. The boys were so thick around the punch bowl that the table and the vines didn't show at all.Only her Dad's face rose up above the boys'heads as he smiled and dished up the punch into the little paper cups.On the seat of the hatrack beside her were a jar of candy and two handkerchiefs.A couple of girls thought it was her birthday, and she had thanked them and unwrapped the presents without telling them she wouldn't be fourteen for eight more months.Every person was as clean and fresh and dressed up as she was.They smelled good.The boys had their hair plastered down wet and slick.The girls with their different-colored long dresses stood together, and they were like a bright hunk of flowers.The start was marvelous.The beginning of this party was O.K.

“I'm part Scotch Irish and French and—”

“I got German blood—”

She hollered about the prom cards one more time before she went into the dining-room. Soon they began to pile in from the hall.Every person took a prom card and they lined up in bunches against the walls of the room.This was the real start now.

It came all of a sudden in a very queer way—this quietness. The boys stood together on one side of the room and the girls were across from them.For some reason every person quit making noise at once.The boys held their cards and looked at the girls and the room was very still.None of the boys started asking for proms like they were supposed to do.The awful quietness got worse and she had not been to enough parties to know what she should do.Then the boys started punching each other and talking.The girls giggled—but even if they didn't look at the boys you could tell they only had their minds on whether they were going to be popular or not.The awful quietness was gone now, but there was something jittery about the room.

After a while a boy went up to a girl named Delores Brown. As soon as he had signed her up the other boys all began to rush Delores at once.When her whole card was full they started on another girl, named Mary.After that everything suddenly stopped again.One or two extra girls got a couple of proms—and because she was giving the party three boys came up to her.That was all.

The people just hung around in the dining-room and the hall. The boys mostly flocked around the punch bowl and tried to show off with each other.The girls bunched together and did a lot of laughing to pretend like they were having a good time.The boys thought about the girls and the girls thought about the boys.But all that came of it was a queer feeling in the room.

It was then she began to notice Harry Minowitz. He lived in the house next door and she had known him all her life.Although he was two years older she had grown faster than him, and in the summer-time they used to wrestle and fight out on the plot of grass by the street.Harry was a Jew boy, but he did not look so much like one.His hair was light brown and straight.Tonight he was dressed very neat, and when he came in the door he had hung a grown man's panama hat with a feather in it on the hatrack.

It wasn't his clothes that made her notice him. There was something changed about his face because he was without the horn-rimmed specs he usually wore.A red, droppy sty had come out on one of his eyes and he had to cock his head sideways like a bird in order to see.His long, thin hands kept touching around his sty as though it hurt him.When he asked for punch he stuck the paper cup right into her Dad's face.She could tell he needed his glasses very bad.He was nervous and kept bumping into people.He didn't ask any girl to prom except her—and that was because it was her party.

All the punch had been drunk. Her Dad was afraid she would be embarrassed, so he and her Mama had gone back to the kitchen to make lemonade.Some of the people were on the front porch and the sidewalk.She was glad to get out in the cool night air.After the hot, bright house she could smell the new autumn in the darkness.

Then she saw something she hadn't expected. Along the edge of the sidewalk and in the dark street there was a bunch of nighborhood kids.Pete and Sucker Wells and Baby and Spareribs—the whole gang that started at below Bubber's age and went on up to over twelve.There were even kids she didn't know at all who had somehow smelled a party and come to hang around.And there were kids her age and older that she hadn't invited either because they had done something mean to her or she had done something mean to them.They were all dirty and in plain shorts or draggle-tailed knickers or old every-day dresses.They were just hanging around in the dark to watch the party.She thought of two feelings when she saw those kids—one was sad and the other was a kind of warning.

“I got this prom with you.”Harry Minowitz made out like he was reading on his card, but she could see nothing was written on it. Her Dad had come onto the porch and blown the whistle that meant the beginning of the first prom.

“Yeah，”she said.“Let's get going.”

They started out to walk around the block. In the long dress she still felt very ritzy.“Look yonder at Mick Kelly！”one of the kids in the dark hollered.“Look at her！”She just walked on like she hadn't heard, but it was that Spareribs, and some day soon she would catch him.She and Harry walked fast along the dark sidewalk, and when they came to the end of the street they turned down another block.

“How old are you now, Mick—thirteen?”

“Going on fourteen.”

She knew what he was thinking. It used to worry her all the time.Five feet six inches tall and a hundred and three pounds, and she was only thirteen.Every kid at the party was a runt beside her, except Harry, who was only a couple of inches shorter.No boy wanted to prom with a girl so much taller than him.But maybe cigarettes would help stunt the rest of her growth.

“I grew three and a fourth inches just in last year，”she said.

“Once I saw a lady at the fair who was eight and a half feet tall. But you probably won't grow that big.”

Harry stopped beside a dark crêpe myrtle bush.Nobody was in sight.He took something out of his pocket and started fooling with whatever it was.She leaned over to see—it was his pair of specs and he was wiping them with his handkerchief.

“Pardon me，”he said. Then he put on his glasses and she could hear him breathe deep.

“You ought to wear your specs all the time.”

“Yeah.”

“How come you go around without them?”

The night was very quiet and dark. Harry held her elbows when they crossed the street.

“There's a certain young lady back at the party that thinks it's sissy for a fellow to wear glasses. This certain person—oh well, maybe I am a—”

He didn't finish. Suddenly he tightened up and ran a few steps and sprang for a leaf about four feet above his head.She just could see that high leaf in the dark.He had a good spring to his jumping and he got it the first time.Then he put the leaf in his mouth and shadow-boxed for a few punches in the dark.She caught up with him.

As usual a song was in her mind. She was humming to herself.

“What's that you're singing?”

“It's a piece by a fellow named Mozart.”

Harry felt pretty good. He was sidestepping with his feet like a fast boxer.“That sounds like a sort of German name.”

“I reckon so.”

“Fascist?”he asked.

“What?”

“I say is that Mozart a Fascist or a Nazi?”

Mick thought a minute.“No. They're new, and this fellow's been dead some time.”

“It's a good thing.”He began punching in the dark again. He wanted her to ask why.

“I say it's a good thing，”he said again.

“Why?”

“Because I hate Fascists. If I met one walking on the street I'd kill him.”

She looked at Harry. The leaves against the street light made quick, freckly shadows on his face.He was excited.

“How come?”she asked.

“Gosh！Don't you ever read the paper?You see, it's this way—”

They had come back around the block. A commotion was going on at her house.People were yelling and running on the sidewalk.A heavy sickness came in her belly.

“There's not time to explain unless we prom around the block again. I don't mind telling you why I hate Fascists.I'd like to tell about it.”

This was probably the first chance he had got to spiel these ideas out to somebody. But she didn't have time to listen.She was busy looking at what she saw in the front of her house.“O.K.I'll see you later.”The prom was over now, so she could look and put her mind on the mess she saw.

What had happened while she was gone?When she left the people were standing around in the fine clothes and it was a real party. Now—after just five minutes—the place looked more like a crazy house.While she was gone those kids had come out of the dark and right into the party itself.The nerve they had！There was old Pete Wells banging out of the front door with a cup of punch in his hand.They bellowed and ran and mixed with the invited people—in their old loose-legged knickers and everyday clothes.

Baby Wilson messed around on the front porch—and Baby wasn't more than four years old. Anybody could see she ought to be home in bed by now, same as Bubber.She walked down the steps one at a time, holding the punch high up over her head.There was no reason for her to be here at all.Mister Brannon was her uncle and she could get free candy and drinks at his place any time she wanted to.As soon as she was on the sidewalk Mick caught her by the arm.“You go right home, Baby Wilson.Go on, now.”Mick looked around to see what else she could do to straighten things out again like they ought to be.She went up to Sucker Wells.He stood farther down the sidewalk, where it was dark, holding his paper cup and looking at everybody in a dreamy way.Sucker was seven years old and he had on shorts.His chest and feet were naked.He wasn't causing any of the commotion, but she was mad as hell at what had happened.

She grabbed Sucker by the shoulders and began to shake him. At first he held his jaws tight, but after a minute his teeth began to rattle.“You go home, Sucker Wells.You quit hanging around where you're not invited.”When she let him go, Sucker tucked his tail and walked slowly down the street.But he didn't go all the way home.After he got to the corner she saw him sit down on the curb and watch the party where he thought she couldn't see him.

For a minute she felt good about shaking the spit out of Sucker. And then right afterward she had a bad worry feeling in her and she started to let him come back.The big kids were the ones who messed up everything.Real brats they were, and with the worst nerve she had ever seen.Drinking up the refreshments and ruining the real party into all this commotion.They slammed through the front door and hollered and bumped into each other.She went up to Pete Wells because he was the worst of all.He wore his football helmet and butted into people.Pete was every bit of fourteen, yet he was still stuck in the seventh grade.She went up to him, but he was too big to shake like Sucker.When she told him to go home he shimmied and made a nose dive at her.

“I been in six different states. Florida, Alabama—”

“Made out of silver cloth with a sash—”

The party was all messed up. Everybody was talking at once.The invited people from Vocational were mixed with the neighborhood gang.The boys and the girls still stood in separate bunches, though—and nobody prommed.In the house the lemonade was just about gone.There was only a little puddle of water with floating lemon peels at the bottom of the bowl.Her Dad always acted too nice with kids.He had served out the punch to anybody who stuck a cup at him.Portia was serving the sandwiches when she went into the dining-room.In five minutes they were all gone.She only got one—a jelly kind with pink sops come through the bread.

Portia stayed in the dining-room to watch the party.“I having too good a time to leave，”she said.“I done sent word to Highboy and Willie to go on with the Saturday Night without me. Everbody so excited here I going to wait and see the end of this party.”

Excitement—that was the word. She could feel it all through the room and on the porch and the sidewalk.She felt excited, too.It wasn't just her dress and the beautiful way her face looked when she passed by the hatrack mirror and saw the red paint on her cheeks and the rhinestone tiara in her hair.Maybe it was the decoration and all these Vocational people and kids being jammed together.

“Watch her run！”

“Ouch！Cut it out—”

“Act your age！”

A bunch of girls were running down the street, holding up their dresses and with the hair flying out behind them. Some boys had cut off the long, sharp spears of a Spanish bayonet bush and they were chasing the girls with them.Freshmen in Vocational all dressed up for a real prom party and acting just like kids.It was half playlike and half not playlike at all.A boy came up to her with a sticker and she started running too.

The idea of the party was over entirely now. This was just a regular playing-out.But it was the wildest night she had ever seen.The kids had caused it.They were like a catching sickness, and their coming to the party made all the other people forget about High School and being almost grown.It was like just before you take a bath in the afternoon when you might wallow around in the back yard and get plenty dirty just for the good feel of it before getting into the tub.Everybody was a wild kid playing out on Saturday night—and she felt like the very wildest of all.

She hollered and pushed and was the first to try any new stunt. She made so much noise and moved around so fast she couldn't notice what anybody else was doing.Her breath wouldn't come fast enough to let her do all the wild things she wanted to do.

“The ditch down the street！The ditch！The ditch！”

She started for it first. Down a block they had put in new pipes under the street and dug a swell deep ditch.The flambeaux around the edge were bright and red in the dark.She wouldn't wait to climb down.She ran until she reached the little wavy flames and then she jumped.

With her tennis shoes she would have landed like a cat—but the high pumps made her slip and her stomach hit this pipe. Her breath was stopped.She lay quiet with her eyes closed.

The party—For a long time she remembered how she thought it would be, how she imagined the new people at Vocational. And about the bunch she wanted to be with every day.She would feel different in the halls now, knowing that they were not something special but like any other kids.It was O.K.about the ruined party.But it was all over.It was the end.

Mick climbed out of the ditch. Some kids were playing around the little pots of flames.The fire made a red glow and there were long, quick shadows.One boy had gone home and put on a dough-face bought in advance for Halloween.Nothing was changed about the party except her.

She walked home slowly. When she passed kids she didn't speak or look at them.The decoration in the hall was torn down and the house seemed very empty because everyone had gone outside.In the bathroom she took off the blue evening dress.The hem was torn and she folded it so the raggedy place wouldn't show.The rhinestone tiara was lost somewhere.Her old shorts and shirt were lying on the floor just where she had left them.She put them on.She was too big to wear shorts any more after this.No more after this night.Not any more.

Mick stood out on the front porch. Her face was very white without the paint.She cupped her hands before her mouth and took a deep breath.“Everybody go home！The door is shut！The party is over！”

In the quiet, secret night she was by herself again. It was not late—yellow squares of light snowed in the windows of the houses along the streets.She walked slow, with her hands in her pockets and her head to one side.For a long time she walked without noticing the direction.

Then the houses were far apart from each other and there were yards with big trees in them and black shrubbery. She looked around and saw she was near this house where she had gone so many times in the summer.Her feet had just taken her here without her knowing.When she came to the house she waited to be sure no person could see.Then she went through the side yard.

The radio was on as usual. For a second she stood by the window and watched the people inside.The bald-headed man and the gray-haired lady were playing cards at a table.Mick sat on the ground.This was a very fine and secret place.Close around were thick cedars so that she was completely hidden by herself.The radio was no good tonight—somebody sang popular songs that all ended in the same way.It was like she was empty.She reached in her pockets and felt around with her fingers.There were raisins and a buckeye and a string of beads—one cigarette with matches.She lighted the cigarette and put her arms around her knees.It was like she was so empty there wasn't even a feeling or thought in her.

One programme came on after another, and all of them were punk. She didn't especially care.She smoked and picked a little bunch of grass blades.After a while a new announcer started talking.He mentioned Beethoven.She had read in the library about that musician—his name was pronounced with an a and spelled with double e.He was a German fellow like Mozart.When he was living he spoke in a foreign language and lived in a foreign place—like she wanted to do.The announcer said they were going to play his third symphony.She only half-way listened because she wanted to walk some more and she didn't care much what they played.Then the music started.Mick raised her head and her fist went up to her throat.

How did it come?For a minute the opening balanced from one side to the other. Like a walk or march.Like God strutting in the night.The outside of her was suddenly froze and only that first part of the music was hot inside her heart.She could not even hear what sounded after, but she sat there waiting and froze, with her fists tight.After a while the music came again, harder and loud.It didn't have anything to do with God.This was her, Mick Kelly, walking in the daytime and by herself at night.In the hot sun and in the dark with all the plans and feelings.This music was her—the real plain her.

She could not listen good enough to hear it all. The music boiled inside her.Which?To hang on to certain wonderful parts and think them over so that later she would not forget—or should she let go and listen to each part that came without thinking or trying to remember?Golly！The whole world was this music and she could not listen hard enough.Then at last the opening music came again, with all the different instruments bunched together for each note like a hard, tight fist that socked at her heart.And the first part was over.

This music did not take a long time or a short time. It did not have anything to do with time going by at all.She sat with her arms held tight around her legs, biting her salty knee very hard.It might have been five minutes she listened or half the night.The second part was black-colored—a slow march.Not sad, but like the whole world was dead and black and there was no use thinking back how it was before.One of those horn kind of instruments played a sad and silver tune.Then the music rose up angry and with excitement underneath.And finally the black march again.

But maybe the last part of the symphony was the music she loved the best—glad and like the greatest people in the world running and springing up in a hard, free way. Wonderful music nice this was the worst hurt there could be.The whole world was this symphony, and there was not enough of her to listen.

It was over, and she sat very stiff with her arms around her knees. Another program came on the radio and she put her fingers in her ears.The music left only this bad hurt in her, and a blankness.She could not remember any of the symphony, not even the last few notes.She tried to remember, but no sound at all came to her.Now that it was over there was only her heart like a rabbit and this terrible hurt.

The radio and the lights in the house were turned off. The night was very dark.Suddenly Mick began hitting her thigh with her fists.She pounded the same muscle with all her strength until the tears came down her face.But she could not feel this hard enough.The rocks under the bush were sharp.She grabbed a handful of them and began scraping them up and down on the same spot until her hand was bloody.Then she fell back to the ground and lay looking up at the night.With the fiery hurt in her leg she felt better.She was limp on the wet grass, and after a while her breath came slow and easy again.

Why hadn't the explorers known by looking at the sky that the world was round?The sky was curved, like the inside of a huge glass ball, very dark blue with the sprinkles of bright stars. The night was quiet.There was the smell of warm cedars.She was not trying to think of the music at all when it came back to her.The first part happened in her mind just as it had been played.She listened in a quiet, slow way and thought the notes out like a problem in geometry so she would remember.She could see the shape of the sounds very clear and she would not forget them.

Now she felt good. She whispered some words out loud：“Lord forgiveth me, for I knoweth not what I do.”Why did she think of that?Everybody in the past few years knew there wasn't any real God.When she thought of what she used to imagine was God she could only see Mister Singer with a long, white sheet around him.God was silent—maybe that was why she was reminded.She said the words again, just as she would speak them to Mister Singer：“Lord forgiveth me, for I knoweth not what I do.”

This part of the music was beautiful and clear. She could sing it now whenever she wanted to.Maybe later on, when she had just waked up some morning, more of the music would come back to her.If ever she heard the symphony again there would be other parts to add to what was already in her mind.And maybe if she could hear it four more times, just four more times, she would know it all.Maybe.

Once again she listened to this opening part of the music. Then the notes grew slower and soft and it was like she was sinking down slowly into the dark ground.

Mick awoke with a jerk. The air had turned chilly, and as she was coming up out of the sleep she dreamed old Etta Kelly was taking all the cover.“Gimme some blanket—”she tried to say.Then she opened her eyes.The sky was very black and all the stars were gone.The grass was wet.She got up in a hurry because her Dad would be worried.Then she remembered the music.She couldn't tell whether the time was midnight or three in the morning, so she started beating it for home in a rush.The air had a smell in it like autumn.The music was loud and quick in her mind, and she ran faster and faster on the sidewalks leading to the home block.

2

By October the days were blue and cool. Biff Brannon changed his light seersucker trousers for dark-blue serge ones.Behind the counter of the Café　he installed a machine that made hot chocolate.Mick was very partial to hot chocolate, and she came in three or four times a week to drink a cup.He served it to her for a nickel instead of a dime and he wanted to give it to her free.He watched her as she stood behind the counter and he was troubled and sad.He wanted to reach out his hand and touch her sunburned, tousled hair—but not as he had ever touched a woman.In him there was an uneasiness, and when he spoke to her his voice had a rough, strange sound.

There were many worries on his mind. For one thing, Alice was not well.She worked downstairs as usual from seven in the morning until ten at night, but she walked very slowly and brown circles were beneath her eyes.It was in the business that she showed this illness most plainly.One Sunday, when she wrote out the day's menu on the typewriter, she marked the special dinner with chicken　à　la king at twenty cents instead of fifty, and did not discover the mistake until several customers had already ordered and were ready to pay.Another time she gave back two fives and three ones as change for ten dollars.Biff would stand looking at her for a long time, rubbing his nose thoughtfully and with his eyes half-closed.

They did not speak of this together. At night he worked downstairs while she slept, and during the morning she managed the restaurant alone.When they worked together he stayed behind the cash register and looked after the kitchen and the tables, as was their custom.They did not talk except on matters of business, but Biff would stand watching her with his face puzzled.

Then in the afternoon of the eighth of October there was a sudden cry of pain from the room where they slept. Biff hurried upstairs.Within an hour they had taken Alice to the hospital and the doctor had removed from her a tumor almost the size of a newborn child.And then within another hour Alice was dead.

Biff sat by her bed at the hospital in stunned reflection. He had been present when she died.Her eyes had been drugged and misty from the ether and then they hardened like glass.The nurse and the doctor withdrew from the room.He continued to look into her face.Except for the bluish pallor there was little difference.He noted each detail about her as though he had not watched her every day for twenty-one years.Then gradually as he sat there his thoughts turned to a picture that had long been stored inside him.

The cold green ocean and a hot gold strip of sand. The little children playing on the edge of the silky line of foam.The sturdy brown baby girl, the thin little naked boys, the half-grown children running and calling out to each other with sweet, shrill voices.Children were here whom he knew, Mick and his niece, Baby, and there were also strange young faces no one had ever seen before.Biff bowed his head.

After a long while he got up from his chair and stood in the middle of the room. He could hear his sister-in-law, Lucile, walking up and down the hall outside.A fat bee crawled across the top of the dresser, and adroitly Biff caught it in his hand and put it out the open window.He glanced at the dead face one more time, and then with widowed sedateness he opened the door that led out into the hospital corridor.

Late the next morning he sat sewing in the room upstairs. Why?Why was it that in cases of real love the one who is left does not more often follow the beloved by suicide?Only because the living must bury the dead?Because of the measured rites that must be fulfilled after a death?Because it is as though the one who is left steps for a time upon a stage and each second swells to an unlimited amount of time and he is watched by many eyes?Because there is a function he must carry out?Or perhaps, when there is love, the widowed must stay for the resurrection of the beloved—so that the one who has gone is not really dead, but grows and is created for a second time in the soul of the living?Why?

Biff bent close over his sewing and meditated on many things. He sewed skillfully, and the calluses on the tips of his fingers were so hard that he pushed the needle through the cloth without a thimble.Already the mourning bands had been sewn around the arms of two gray suits, and now he was on the last.

The day was bright and hot, and the first dead leaves of the new autumn scraped on the sidewalks. He had gone out early.Each minute was very long.Before him there was infinite leisure.He had locked the door of the restaurant and hung on the outside a white wreath of lilies.To the funeral home he went first and looked carefully at the selection of caskets.He touched the materials of the linings and tested the strength of the frames.

“What is the name of the crêpe of this one—georgette?”

The undertaker answered his questions in an oily, unctuous voice.

“And what is the percentage of cremations in your business?”

Out on the street again Biff walked with measured formality. From the west there was a warm wind and the sun was very bright.His watch had stopped, so he turned down toward the street where Wilbur Kelly had recently put out his sign as watchmaker.Kelly was sitting at his bench in a patched bathrobe.His shop was also a bedroom, and the baby Mick pulled around with her in a wagon sat quietly on a pallet on the floor.Each minute was so long that in it there was ample time for contemplation and enquiry.He asked Kelly to explain the exact use of jewels in a watch.He noted the distorted look of Kelly's right eye as it appeared through his watchmaker's loupe.They talked for a while about Chamberlain and Munich.Then as the time was still early he decided to go up to the mute's room.

Singer was dressing for work. Last night there had come from him a letter of condolence.He was to be a pallbearer at the funeral.Biff sat on the bed and they smoked a cigarette together.Singer looked at him now and then with his green observant eyes.He offered him a drink of coffee.Biff did not talk, and once the mute stopped to pat him on the shoulder and look for a second into his face.When Singer was dressed they went out together.

Biff bought the black ribbon at the store and saw the preacher of Alice's church. When all was arranged he came back home.To put things in order—that was the thought in his mind.He bundled up Alice's clothes and personal possessions to give to Lucile.He thoroughly cleaned and straightened the bureau drawers.He even rearranged the shelves of the kitchen downstairs and removed the gaily colored crêpe streamers from the electric fans.Then when this was done he sat in the tub and bathed himself all over.And the morning was done.

Biff bit the thread and smoothed the black band on the sleeve of his coat. By now Lucile would be waiting for him.He and she and Baby would ride in the funeral car together.He put away the work basket and fitted the coat with the mourning band very carefully on his shoulders.He glanced swiftly around the room to see that all was well before going out again.

An hour later he was in Lucile's kitchenette. He sat with his legs crossed, a napkin over his thigh, drinking a cup of tea.Lucile and Alice had been so different in all ways that it was not easy to realize they were sisters.Lucile was thin and dark, and today she had dressed completely in black.She was fixing Baby's hair.The kid waited patiently on the kitchen table with her hands folded in her lap while her mother worked on her.The sunlight was quiet and mellow in the room.

“Bartholomew—”said Lucile.

“What?”

“Don't you ever start thinking backward?”

“I don't，”said Biff.

“You know it's like I got to wear blinders all the time so I won't think sideways or in the past. All I can let myself think about is going to work every day and fixing meals and Baby's future.”

“That's the right attitude.”

“I been giving Baby finger waves down at the shop. But they come out so quick I been thinking about letting her have a permanent.I don't want to give it to her myself—I think maybe I'll take her up to Atlanta when I go to the cosmetologist convention and let her get it there.”

“Motherogod！She's not but four. It's liable to scare her.And besides, permanents tend to coarsen the hair.”

Lucile dipped the comb in a glass of water and mashed the curls over Baby's ears.“No, they don't. And she wants one.Young as Baby is, she already has as much ambition as I got.And that's saying plenty.”

Biff polished his nails on the palm of his hand and shook his head.

“Every time Baby and I go to the movies and see those kids in all the good rôles she feels the same way I do.I swear she does, Bartholomew.I can’t even get her to eat her supper afterward.”

“For goodness'sake，”Biff said.

“She's getting along so fine with her dancing and expression lessons. Next year I want her to start with the piano because I think it'll be a help for her to play some.Her dancing teacher is going to give her a solo in the soirée.I feel like I got to push Baby all I can.Because the sooner she gets started on her career the better it’ll be for both of us.”

“Motherogod！”

“You don't understand. A child with talent can't be treated like ordinary kids.That's one reason I want to get Baby out of this common neighborhood.I can't let her start to talk vulgar like these brats around her or run wild like they do.”

“I know the kids on this block，”Biff said.“They're all right. Those Kelly kids across the street—the Crane boy—”

“You know good and well that none of them are up to Baby's level.”

Lucile set the last wave in Baby's hair. She pinched the kid's little cheeks to put more color in them.Then she lifted her down from the table.For the funeral Baby had on a little white dress with white shoes and white socks and even small white gloves.There was a certain way Baby always held her head when people looked at her, and it was turned that way now.

They sat for a while in the small, hot kitchenette without saying anything. Then Lucile began to cry.“It's not like we was ever very close as sisters.We had our differences and we didn't see much of each other.Maybe it was because I was so much younger.But there's something about your own blood kin, and when anything like this happens—”

Biff clucked soothingly.

“I know how you two were，”she said.“It wasn't all just roses with you and she. But maybe that sort of makes it worse for you now.”

Biff caught Baby under the arms and swung her up to his shoulder. The kid was getting heavier.He held her carefully as he stepped into the living-room.Baby felt warm and close on his shoulder, and her little silk skirt was white against the dark cloth of his coat.She grasped one of his ears very tight with her little hand.

“Unca Biff！Watch me do the split.”

Gently he set Baby on her feet again. She curved both arms above her head and her feet slid slowly in opposite directions on the yellow waxed floor.In a moment she was seated with one leg stretched straight in front of her and one behind.She posed with her arms held at a fancy angle, looking sideways at the wall with a sad expression.

She scrambled up again.“Watch me do a handspring. Watch me do a—”

“Honey, be a little quieter，”Lucile said. She sat down beside Biff on the plush sofa.“Don't she remind you a little of him—something about her eyes and face?”

“Hell, no. I can't see the slightest resemblance between Baby and Leroy Wilson.”

Lucile looked too thin and worn out for her age. Maybe it was the black dress and because she had been crying.“After all, we got to admit he's Baby's father，”she said.

“Can't you ever forget about that man?”

“I don't know. I guess I always been a fool about two things.And that's Leroy and Baby.”

Biff's new growth of beard was blue against the pale skin of his face and his voice sounded tired.“Don't you ever just think a thing through and find out what's happened and what ought to come from that?Don't you ever use logic—if these are the given facts this ought to be the result?”

“Not about him, I guess.”

Biff spoke in a weary manner and his eyes were almost closed.“You married this certain party when you were seventeen, and afterward there was just one racket between you after another. You divorced him.Then two years later you married him a second time.And now he's gone off again and you don't know where he is.It seems like those facts would show you one thing—you two are not suited to each other.And that's aside from the more personal side—the sort of man this certain party happens to be anyway.”

“God knows I been realizing all along he's a heel. I just hope he won't ever knock on that door again.”

“Look, Baby，”Biff said quickly. He laced his fingers and held up his hands.“This is the church and this is the steeple.Open the door and here are God's people.”

Lucile shook her head.“You don't have to bother about Baby. I tell her everything.She knows about the whole mess from A to Z.”

“Then if he comes back you'll let him stay here and sponge on you just as long as he pleases—like it was before?”

“Yeah. I guess I would.Every time the doorbell or the phone rings, every time anybody steps up on the porch, something in the back of my mind thinks about that man.”

Biff spread out the palms of his hands.“There you are.”

The clock struck two. The room was very close and hot.Baby turned another handspring and made a split again on the waxed floor.Then Biff took her up into his lap.Her little legs dangled against his shin.She unbuttoned his vest and burrowed her face into him.

“Listen，”Lucile said.“If I ask you a question will you promise to answer me the truth?”

“Sure.”

“No matter what it is?”

Biff touched Baby's soft gold hair and laid his hand gently on the side of her little head.“Of course.”

“It was about seven years ago. Soon after we was married the first time.And he came in one night from your place with big knots all over his head and told me you caught him by the neck and banged his head against the side of the wall.He made up some tale about why you did it, but I want to know the real reason.”

Biff turned the wedding ring on his finger.“I just never did like Leroy, and we had a fight. In those days I was different from now.”

“No. There was some definite thing you did that for.We been knowing each other a pretty long time, and I understand by now that you got a real reason for every single thing you ever do.Your mind runs by reasons instead of just wants.Now, you promised you'd tell me what it was, and I want to know.”

“It wouldn't mean anything now.”

“I tell you I got to know.”

“All right，”Biff said.“He came in that night and started drinking, and when he was drunk he shot off his mouth about you. He said he would come home about once a month and beat hell out of you and you would take it.But then afterward you would step outside in the hall and laugh aloud a few times so that the neighbors in the other rooms would think you both had just been playing around and it had all been a joke.That's what happened, so just forget about it.”

Lucile sat up straight and there was a red spot on each of her cheeks.“You see, Bartholomew, that's why I got to be like I have blinders on all the time so as not to think backward or sideways. All I can let my mind stay on is going to work every day and fixing three meals here at home and Baby's career.”

“Yes.”

“I hope you'll do that too, and not start thinking backward.”

Biff leaned his head down on his chest and closed his eyes. During the whole long day he had not been able to think of Alice.When he tried to remember her face there was a queer blankness in him.The only thing about her that was clear in his mind was her feet—stumpy, very soft and white with puffy little toes.The bottoms were pink and near the left heel there was a tiny brown mole.The night they were married he had taken off her shoes and stockings and kissed her feet.And, come to think of it, that was worth considering, because the Japanese believe that the choicest part of a woman—

Biff stirred and glanced at his watch. In a little while they would leave for the church where the funeral would be held.In his mind he went through the motions of the ceremony.The church—riding dirge-paced behind the hearse with Lucile and Baby—the group of people standing with bowed heads in the September sunshine.Sun on the white tombstones, on the fading flowers and the canvas tent covering the newly dug grave.Then home again—and what?

“No matter how much you quarrel there's something about your own blood sister，”Lucile said.

Biff raised his head.“Why don't you marry again?Some nice young man who's never had a wife before, who would take care of you and Baby?If you'd just forget about Leroy you would make a good man a fine wife.”

Lucile was slow to answer. Then finally she said：“You know how we always been—we nearly all the time understand each other pretty well without any kind of throbs either way.Well, that's the closest I ever want to be to any man again.”

“I feel the same way，”Biff said.

Half an hour later there was a knock on the door. The car for the funeral was parked before the house.Biff and Lucile got up slowly.The three of them, with Baby in her white silk dress a little ahead, walked in solemn quietness outside.

Biff kept the restaurant closed during the next day. Then in the early evening he removed the faded wreath of lilies from the front door and opened the place for business again.Old customers came in with sad faces and talked with him a few minutes by the cash register before giving their orders.The usual crowd was present—Singer, Blount, various men who worked in stores along the block and in the mills down on the river.After supper Mick Kelly showed up with her little brother and put a nickel into the slot machine.When she lost the first coin she banged on the machine with her fists and kept opening the receiver to be sure that nothing had come down.Then she put in another nickel and almost won the jackpot.Coins came clattering out and rolled along the floor.The kid and her little brother both kept looking around pretty sharp as they picked them up, so that no customer would put his foot on one before they could get to it.The mute was at the table in the middle of the room with his dinner before him.Across from him Jake Blount sat drinking beer, dressed in his Sunday clothes, and talking.Everything was the same as it had always been before.After a while the air became gray with cigarette smoke and the noise increased.Biff was alert, and no sound or movement escaped him.

“I go around，”Blount said. He leaned earnestly across the table and kept his eyes on the mute's face.“I go all around and try to tell them.And they laugh.I can't make them understand anything.No matter what I say I can't seem to make them see, the truth.”

Singer nodded and wiped his mouth with his napkin. His dinner had got cold because he couldn't look down to eat, but he was so polite that he let Blount go on talking.

The words of the two children at the slot machine were high and clear against the coarser voices of the men. Mick was putting her nickels back into the slot.Often she looked around at the middle table, but the mute had his back turned to her and did not see.

“Mister Singer's got fried chicken for his supper and he hasn't eaten one piece yet，”the little boy said.

Mick pulled down the lever of the machine very slowly.“Mind your own business.”

“You're always going up to his room or some place where you know he'll be.”

“I told you to hush, Bubber Kelly.”

“You do.”

Mick shook him until his teeth rattled and turned him around toward the door.“You go on home to bed. I already told you I get a bellyful of you and Ralph in the daytime, and I don't want you hanging around me at night when I'm supposed to be free.”

Bubber held out his grimy little hand.“Well, give me a nickel, then.”When he had put the money in his shirt pocket he left for home.

Biff straightened his coat and smoothed back his hair. His tie was solid black, and on the sleeve of his gray coat there was the mourning band that he had sewn there.He wanted to go up to the slot machine and talk with Mick, but something would not let him.He sucked in his breath sharply and drank a glass of water.A dance orchestra came in on the radio, but he did not want to listen.All the tunes in the last ten years were so alike he couldn't tell one from the other.Since　1928　he had not enjoyed music.Yet when he was young he used to play the mandolin, and he knew the words and the melody of every current song.

He laid his finger on the side of his nose and cocked his head to one side. Mick had grown so much in the past year that soon she would be taller than he was.She was dressed in the red sweater and blue pleated skirt she had worn every day since school started.Now the pleats had come out and the hem dragged loose around her sharp, jutting knees.She was at the age when she looked as much like an overgrown boy as a girl.And on that subject why was it that the smartest people mostly missed that point?By nature all people are of both sexes.So that marriage and the bed is not all by any means.The proof?Real youth and old age.Because often old men's voices grow high and reedy and they take on a mincing walk.And old women sometimes grow fat and their voices get rough and deep and they grow dark little mustaches.And he even proved it himself—the part of him that sometimes almost wished he was a mother and that Mick and Baby were his kids.Abruptly Biff turned from the cash register.

The newspapers were in a mess. For two weeks he hadn't filed a single one.He lifted a stack of them from under the counter.With a practiced eye he glanced from the masthead to the bottom of the sheet.Tomorrow he would look over the stacks of them in the back room and see about changing the system of files.Build shelves and use those solid boxes canned goods were shipped in for drawers.Chronologically from　27　October　1918　on up to the present date.With folders and top markings outlining historical events.Three sets of outlines—one international beginning with the Armistice and leading through the Munich aftermath, the second national, the third all the local dope from the time Mayor Lester shot his wife at the country club up to the Hudson Mill fire.Everything for the past twenty years docketed and outlined and complete.Biff beamed quietly behind his hand as he rubbed his jaw.And yet Alice had wanted him to haul out the papers so she could turn the room into a ladies'toilet.That was just what she had nagged him to do, but for once he had battered her down.For that one time.

With peaceful absorption Biff settled down to the details of the newspaper before him. He read steadily and with concentration, but from habit some secondary part of him was alert to everything around him.Jake Blount was still talking, and often he would hit his fist on the table.The mute sipped beer.Mick walked restlessly around the radio and stared at the customers.Biff read every word in the first paper and made a few notes on the margins.

Then suddenly he looked up with a surprised expression. His mouth had been open for a yawn and he snapped it shut.The radio swung into an old song that dated back to the time when he and Alice were engaged.“Just a Baby's Prayer at Twilight.”They had taken the streetcar one Sunday to Old Sardis Lake and had rented a rowboat.At sunset he played on the mandolin while she sang.She had on a sailor hat, and when he put his arm around her waist she—Alice—

A dragnet for lost feelings. Biff folded the newspapers and put them back under the counter.He stood on one foot and then the other.Finally he called across the room to Mick.“You're not listening, are you?”

Mick turned off the radio.“No. Nothing on tonight.”

All of that he would keep out of his mind, and concentrate on something else. He leaned over the counter and watched one customer after another.Then at last his attention rested on the mute at the middle table.He saw Mick edge gradually up to him and at his invitation sit down.Singer pointed to something on the menu and the waitress brought a Coca-Cola for her.Nobody but a freak like a deaf-mute, cut off from other people, would ask a right young girl to sit down to the table where he was drinking with another man.Blount and Mick both kept their eyes on Singer.They talked, and the mute's expression changed as he watched them.It was a funny thing.The reason—was it in them or in him?He sat very still with his hands in his pockets, and because he did not speak it made him seem superior.What did that fellow think and realize?What did he know?

Twice during the evening Biff started to go over to the middle table, but each time he checked himself. After they were gone he still wondered what it was about this mute—and in the early dawn when he lay in bed he turned over questions and solutions in his mind without satisfaction.The puzzle had taken root in him.It worried him in the back of his mind and left him uneasy.There was something wrong.

3

Many times Doctor Copeland talked to Mr. Singer.Truly he was not like other white men.He was a wise man, and he understood the strong, true purpose in a way that other white men could not.He listened, and in his face there was something gentle and Jewish, the knowledge of one who belongs to a race that is oppressed.On one occasion he took Mr.Singer with him on his rounds.He led him through cold and narrow passages smelling of dirt and sickness and fried fatback.He showed him a successful skin graft made on the face of a woman patient who had been severely burned.He treated a syphilitic child and pointed out to Mr.Singer the scaling eruption on the palms of the hand, the dull, opaque surface of the eye, the sloping upper front incisors.They visited two-room shacks that housed as many as twelve or fourteen persons.In a room where the fire burned low and orange on the hearth they were helpless while an old man strangled with pneumonia.Mr.Singer walked behind him and watched and understood.He gave nickels to the children, and because of his quietness and decorum he did not disturb the patients as would have another visitor.

The days were chilly and treacherous. In the town there was an outbreak of influenza so that Doctor Copeland was busy most of the hours of the day and night.He drove through the Negro sections of the town in the high Dodge automobile he had used for the past nine years.He kept the isinglass curtains snapped to the windows to cut off the draughts, and tight around his neck he wore his gray wool shawl.During this time he did not see Portia or William or Highboy, but often he thought of them.Once when he was away Portia came to see him and left a note and borrowed half a sack of meal.

There came a night when he was so exhausted that, although there were other calls to make, he drank hot milk and went to bed. He was cold and feverish so that at first he could not rest.Then it seemed that he had only begun to sleep when a voice called him.He got up wearily and, still in his long flannel nightshirt, he opened the front door.It was Portia.

“The Lord Jesus help us, Father，”she said.

Doctor Copeland stood shivering with his nightshirt drawn close around his waist. He held his hand to his throat and looked at her and waited.

“It about our Willie. He been a bad boy and done got hisself in mighty bad trouble.And us got to do something.”

Doctor Copeland walked from the hall with rigid steps. He stopped in the bedroom for his bathrobe, shawl, and slippers and went back to the kitchen.Portia was waiting for him there.The kitchen was lifeless and cold.

“All right. What has he done?What is it?”

“Just wait a minute. Just let me find brain room so I can study it all out and tell it to you plain.”

He crushed some sheets of newspaper lying on the hearth and picked up a few sticks of kindling.

“Let me make the fire，”Portia said.“You just sit down at the table, and soon as this here stove is hot us going to have a cup of coffee. Then maybe it all won't seem so bad.”

“There is not any coffee. I used the last of it yesterday.”

When he said this Portia began to cry. Savagely she stuffed paper and wood into the stove and lighted it with a trembling hand.“This here the way it is，”she said.“Willie and Highboy were messing around tonight at a place where they got no business being.You know how I feels like I always got to keep my Willie and my Highboy close to me?Well, if I'd been there none of this trouble would of come about.But I were at the Ladies'Meeting at the church and them boys got restless.They went down to Madame Reba's Palace of Sweet Pleasure.And Father, this is sure one bad, wicked place.They got a man sells tickets on the bug—but they also got these strutting, bad-blood, tail-shaking nigger gals and these here red satin curtains and—”

“Daughter，”said Doctor Copeland irritably. He pressed his hands to the side of his head.“I know the place.Get to the point.”

“Love Jones were there—and she is one bad colored gal. Willie he drunk liquor and shimmied around with her until first thing you know he were in a fight.He were in a fight with this boy named Junebug—over Love.And for a while they fights there with their hands and then this Junebug got out his knife.Our Willie didn't have no knife, so he commenced to bellow and run around the parlor.Then finally Highboy found Willie a razor and he backed up and nearbout cut this Junebug's head off.”

Doctor Copeland drew his shawl closer around him.“Is he dead?”

“That boy too mean to die. He in the hospital, but he going to be out and making trouble again before long.”

“And William?”

“The police come in and taken him to the jail in the Black Maria. He still locked up.”

“And he did not get hurt?”

“Oh, he got a busted eye and a little chunk cut out his behind. But it won't bother him none.What I can't understand is how come he would be messing around with that Love.She at least ten shades blacker than I is and she the ugliest nigger I ever seen.She walk like she have a egg between her legs and don't want to break it.She ain't even clean.And here Willie done cut the buck like this over her.”

Doctor Copeland leaned closer to the stove and groaned. He coughed and his face stiffened.He held his paper handkerchief to his mouth and it became spotted with blood.The dark skin of his face took on a greenish pallor.

“Course Highboy come and tell me soon as it all happened. Understand, my Highboy didn't have nothing to do with these here bad gals.He were just keeping Willie company.He so grieved about Willie he been sitting out on the street curb in front of the jail ever since.”The fire-colored tears rolled down Portia's face.“You know how us three has always been.Us haves our own plan and nothing ever went wrong with it before.Even money hasn't bothered us none.Highboy he pay the rent and I buys the food—and Willie he takes care of Saturday Night.Us has always been like three-piece twinses.”

At last it was morning. The mill whistles blew for the first shift.The sun came out and brightened the clean saucepans hanging on the wall above the stove.They sat for a long time.Portia pulled at the rings on her ears until her lobes were irritated and purplish red.Doctor Copeland still held his head in his hands.

“Seem to me，”Portia said finally，“if us can just get a lot of white peoples to write letters about Willie it might help out some. I already been to see Mr.Brannon.He written exactly what I told him to.He were at his café　after it all happened like he is ever night.So I just went in there and explained how it was.I taken the letter home with me.I done put it in the Bible so I won’t lose it or dirty it.”

“What did the letter say?”

“Mr. Brannon he wrote just hike I asked him to.The letter tell about how Willie has been working for Mr.Brannon going on three year.It tell how Willie is one fine upstanding colored boy and how he hasn't ever been in no trouble before now.It tell how he always had plenty chances to take things in the Café　if he were like some other type of colored boy and how—”

“Pshaw！”said Doctor Copeland.“All that is no good.”

“Us just can't sit around and wait. With Willie locked up in the jail.My Willie, who is such a sweet boy even if he did do wrong tonight.Us just can't sit around and wait.”

“We will have to. That is the only thing we can do.”

“Well, I know I ain't.”

Portia got up from the chair. Her eyes roved distractedly around the room as though searching for something.Then abruptly she went toward the front door.

“Wait a minute，”said Doctor Copeland.“Where do you intend to go now?”

“I got to work. I sure got to keep my job.I sure have to stay on with Mrs.Kelly and get my pay ever week.”

“I want to go to the jail，”said Doctor Copeland.“Maybe I can see William.”

“I going to drop by the jail on my way to work. I got to send Highboy off to his work, too—else he liable to sit there grieving about Willie all the morning.”

Doctor Copeland dressed hurriedly and joined Portia in the hall. They went out into the cool, blue autumn morning.The men at the jail were rude to them and they were able to find out very little.Doctor Copeland then went to consult a lawyer with whom he had had dealings before.The following days were long and full of worried thoughts.At the end of three weeks the trial for William was held and he was convicted of assault with a deadly weapon.He was sentenced to nine months of hard labor and sent immediately to a prison in the northern part of the state.

Even now the strong true purpose was always in him, but he had no time in which to think on it. He went from one house to another and the work was unending.Very early in the morning he drove off in the automobile, and then at eleven o'clock the patients came to the office.After the sharp autumn air outside there would be a hot, stale odor in the house that made him cough.The benches in the hall were always full of sick and patient Negroes who waited for him, and sometimes even the front porch and his bedroom would be crowded.All the day and frequently half the night there was work.Because of the tiredness in him he wanted sometimes to lie down on the floor and beat with his fists and cry.If he could rest he might get well.He had tuberculosis of the lungs, and he measured his temperature four times a day and had an X-ray once a month.But he could not rest.For there was another thing bigger than the tiredness—and this was the strong true purpose.

He would think of this purpose until sometimes, after a long day and night of work, he would become blank so that he would forget for a minute just what the purpose was. And then it would come to him again and he would be restless and eager to take on a new task.But the words often stuck in his mouth, and his voice now was hoarse and not loud as it had been before.He pushed the words into the sick and patient faces of the Negroes who were his people.

Often he talked to Mr. Singer.With him he spoke of chemistry and the enigma of the universe.Of the infinitesimal sperm and the cleavage of the ripened egg.Of the complex million-fold division of the cells.Of the mystery of living matter and the simplicity of death.And also he spoke with him of race.

“My people were brought from the great plains, and the dark, green jungles，”he said once to Mr. Singer.“On the long chained journeys to the coast they died by the thousands.Only the strong survived.Chained in the foul ships that brought them here they died again.Only the hardy Negroes with will could live.Beaten and chained and sold on the block, the least of these strong ones perished again.And finally through the bitter years the strongest of my people are still here.Their sons and daughters, their grandsons and great grandsons.”

“I come to borrow and I come to ask a favor，”Portia said.

Doctor Copeland was alone in his kitchen when she walked through the hall and stood in the doorway to tell him this. Two weeks had passed since William had been sent away.Portia was changed.Her hair was not oiled and combed as usual, her eyes were bloodshot as though she had partaken of strong drink.Her cheeks were hollow, and with her sorrowful, honey-colored face she truly resembled her mother now.

“You know them nice white plates and cups you haves?”

“You may have them and keep them.”

“No, I only wants to borrow. And also I come here to ask a favor of you.”

“Anything you wish，”said Doctor Copeland.

Portia sat down across the table from her father.“First I suppose I better explain. Yesdiddy I got this here message from Grandpapa saying they all coming in tomorrow and spend the night and part of Sunday with us.Course they been mighty worried about Willie, and Grandpapa feel like us all ought to get together again.He right, too.I sure do want to see our folks again.I been mighty homesick since Willie been gone.”

“You may have the plates and anything else you can find around here，”Doctor Copeland said.“But hold up your shoulders, Daughter. Your carriage is bad.”

“It going to be a real reunion. You know this is the first time Grandpapa have spent the night in town for twenty years.He haven't ever slept outside of his own home except two times in his whole life.And anyway he kind of nervous at night.All during the dark he have to get up and drink water and be sure the childrens is covered up and all right.I a little worried about if Grandpapa will be comfortable here.”

“Anything of mine you think you will need—”

“Course Lee Jackson bringing them in，”said Portia.“And with Lee Jackson it going to take them all day to get here. I not expecting them till around supper-time.Course Grandpapa always so patient with Lee Jackson he wouldn't make him hurry none.”

“My soul！Is that old mule still alive?He must be fully eighteen years old.”

“He even older than that. Grandpapa been working him now for twenty years.He done had that mule so long he always say it just like Lee Jackson is one of his blood kin.He understand and love Lee Jackson like he do his own grandchildrens.I never seen a human who know so good what a animal is thinking as Grandpapa.He haves a close feeling for everything that walks and eats.”

“Twenty years is a long time to work a mule.”

“It sure is. Now Lee Jackson is right feeble.But Grandpapa sure do take good care of him.When they plows out in the hot sun Lee Jackson haves a great big straw hat on his head just like Grandpapa—with holes cut for his ears.That mule's straw hat is a real joke, and Lee Jackson won't budge a step when he going to plow without that hat is on his head.”

Doctor Copeland took down the white china dishes from the shelf and began to wrap them in newspaper.“Have you enough pots and pans to cook all the food you will need?”

“Plenty，”Portia said.“I not going to any special trouble. Granpapa, he Mr.Thoughtful hisself—and he always bring in something to help out when the fambly come to dinner.I only going to have plenty meal and cabbage and two pounds of nice mullet.”

“Sounds good.”

Portia laced her nervous yellow fingers together. There one thing I haven't told you yet.A surprise.Buddy going to be here as well as Hamilton.Buddy just come back from Mobile.He helping out on the farm now.”

“It has been five years since I last saw Karl Marx.”

“And that just what I come to ask you about，”said Portia.“You remember when I walked in the door I told you I come to borrow and to ask a favor.”

Doctor Copeland cracked the points of his fingers.“Yes.”

“Well, I come to see if I can't get you to be there tomorrow at the reunion. All your childrens but Willie going to be there.Seem to me like you ought to join us.I sure will be glad if you come.”

Hamilton and Karl Marx and Portia—and William. Doctor Copeland removed his spectacles and pressed his fingers against his eyelids.For a minute he saw the four of them very plainly as they were a long time ago.Then he looked up and straightened his glasses on his nose.“Thank you，”he said.“I will come.”

That night he sat alone by the stove in the dark room and remembered. He thought back to the time of his childhood.His mother had been born a slave, and after freedom she was a washerwoman.His father was a preacher who had once known John Brown.They had taught him, and out of the two or three dollars they had earned each week they saved.When he was seventeen years old they had sent him North with eighty dollars hidden in his shoe.He had worked in a blacksmith's shop and as a waiter and as a bellboy in a hotel.And all the while he studied and read and went to school.His father died and his mother did not live long without him.After ten years of struggle he was a doctor and he knew his mission and he came South again.

He married and made a home. He went endlessly from house to house and spoke the mission and the truth.The hopeless suffering of his people made in him a madness, a wild and evil feeling of destruction.At times he drank strong liquor and beat his head against the floor.In his heart there was a savage violence, and once he grasped the poker from the hearth and struck down his wife.She took Hamilton, Karl Marx, William, and Portia with her to her father's home.He wrestled in his spirit and fought down the evil blackness.But Daisy did not come back to him.And eight years later when she died his sons were not children any more and they did not return to him.He was left an old man in an empty house.

Promptly at five o'clock the next afternoon he arrived at the house where Portia and Highboy lived. They resided in the part of town called Sugar Hill, and the house was a narrow cottage with a porch and two rooms.From inside there was a babble of mixed voices.Doctor Copeland approached stiffly and stood in the doorway holding his shabby felt hat in his hand.

The room was crowded and at first he was not noticed. He sought the faces of Karl Marx and Hamilton.Besides them there was Grandpapa and two children who sat together on the floor.He was still looking into the faces of his sons when Portia perceived him standing in the door.

“Here Father，”she said.

The voices stopped. Grandpapa turned around in his chair.He was thin and bent and very wrinkled.He was wearing the same greenish-black suit that he had worn thirty years before at his daughter's wedding.Across his vest there was a tarnished brass watch chain.Karl Marx and Hamilton looked at each other, then down at the floor, and finally at their father.

“Benedict Mady—”said the old man.“Been a long time. A real long time.”

“Ain't it, though！”Portia said.“This here the first reunion us is all had in many a year. Highboy, you get a chair from the kitchen.Father, here Buddy and Hamilton.”

Doctor Copeland shook hands with his sons. They were both tall and strong and awkward.Against their blue shirts and overalls their skin had the same rich brown color as did Portia's.They did not look him in the eye, and in their faces there was neither love nor hate.

“It sure is a pity everybody couldn't come—Aunt Sara and Jim and all the rest，”said Highboy.“But this here is a real pleasure to us.”

“Wagon too full，”said one of the children.“Us had to walk a long piece'cause the wagon too full anyways.”

Grandpapa scratched his ear with a matchstick.“Somebody got to stay home.”

Nervously Portia licked her dark, thin lips.“It our Willie I thinking about. He were always a big one for any kind of party or to-do.My mind just won't stay off our Willie.”

Through the room there was a quiet murmur of agreement. The old man leaned back in his chair and waggled his head up and down.“Portia, Hon, supposing you reads to us a little while.The word of God sure do mean a lot in a time of trouble.”

Portia took up the Bible from the table in the center of the room.“What part you want to hear now, Grandpapa?”

“It all the book of the Holy Lord. Just any place your eye fall on will do.”

Portia read from the Book of Luke. She read slowly, tracing the words with her long, limp finger.The room was still.Doctor Copeland sat on the edge of the group, cracking his knuckles, his eyes wandering from one point to another.The room was very small, the air close and stuffy.The four walls were cluttered with calendars and crudely painted advertisements from magazines.On the mantel there was a vase of red paper roses.The fire on the hearth burned slowly and the wavering light from the oil lamp made shadows on the wall.Portia read with such slow rhythm that the words slept in Doctor Copeland's ears and he was drowsy.Karl Marx lay sprawled upon the floor beside the children.Hamilton and Highboy dozed.Only the old man seemed to study the meaning of the words.

Portia finished the chapter and closed the book.

“I done pondered over this thing a many a time，”said Grandpapa.

The people in the room came out of their drowsiness.“What?”asked Portia.

“It this way. You recall them parts Jesus raising the dead and curing the sick?”

“Course we does, sir，”said Highboy deferentially.

“Many a day when I be plowing or working，”Grandpapa said slowly，“I done thought and reasoned about the time when Jesus going to descend again to this earth.'Cause I done always wanted it so much it seem to me like it will be while I am living. I done studied about it many a time.And this here the way I done planned it.I reason I will get to stand before Jesus with all my childrens and grandchildrens and great grandchildrens and kinfolks and friends and I say to Him，‘Jesus Christ, us is all sad colored peoples.'And then he will place His holy hand upon our heads and straightway us will be white as cotton.That the plan and reasoning that been in my heart a many and a many a time.”

A hush fell on the room. Doctor Copeland jerked the cuffs of his sleeves and cleared his throat.His pulse beat too fast and his throat was tight.Sitting in the corner of the room he felt isolated and angry and alone.

“Has any of you ever had a sign from Heaven?”asked Grandpapa.

“I has, sir，”said Highboy.“Once when I were sick with the pneumonia I seen God's face looking out the fireplace at me. It were a large white man's face with a white beard and blue eyes.”

“I seen a ghost，”said one of the children—the girl.

“Once I seen—”began the little boy.

Grandpapa held up his hand.“You childrens hush. You, Celia—and you, Whitman—it now the time for you to listen but not be heard，”he said.“Only one time has I had a real sign.And this here the way it come about.It were in the summer of last year, and hot.I were trying to dig up the roots of that big oak stump near the hogpen and when I leaned down a kind of catch, a misery, come suddenly in the small of my back.I straightened up and then all around went dark.I were holding my hand to my back and looking up at the sky when suddenly I seen this little angel.It were a little white girl angel—look to me about the size of a field pea—with yellow hair and a white robe.Just flying around near the sun.After that I come in the house and prayed.I studied the Bible for three days before I went out in the field again.”

Doctor Copeland felt the old evil anger in him. The words rose inchoately to his throat and he could not speak them.They would listen to the old man.Yet to words of reason they would not attend.These are my people, he tried to tell himself—but because he was dumb this thought did not help him now.He sat tense and sullen.

“It a queer thing，”said Grandpapa suddenly.“Benedict Mady, you a fine doctor. How come I get them miseries sometime in the small of my back after I been digging and planting for a good while?How come that misery bother me?”

“How old are you now?”

“I somewhere between seventy and eighty year old.”

The old man loved medicine and treatment. Always when he used to come in with his family to see Daisy he would have himself examined and take home medicine and salves for the whole group of them.But when Daisy left him the old man did not come anymore and he had to content himself with purges and kidney pills advertised in the newspapers.Now the old man was looking at him with timid eagerness.

“Drink plenty of water，”said Doctor Copeland.“And rest as much as you can.”

Portia went into the kitchen to prepare the supper. Warm smells began to fill the room.There was quiet, idle talking, but Doctor Copeland did not listen or speak.Now and then he looked at Karl Marx or Hamilton.Karl Marx talked about Joe Louis.Hamilton spoke mostly of the hail that had ruined some of the crops.When they caught their father's eye they grinned and shuffled their feet on the floor.He kept staring at them with angry misery.

Doctor Copeland clamped his teeth down hard. He had thought so much about Hamilton and Karl Marx and William and Portia, about the real true purpose he had had for them, that the sight of their faces made a black swollen feeling in him.If once he could tell it all to them, from the far away beginning until this very night, the telling would ease the sharp ache in his heart.But they would not listen or understand.

He hardened himself so that each muscle in his body was rigid and strained. He did not listen or look at anything around him.He sat in a corner like a man who is blind and dumb.Soon they went into the supper table and the old man said grace.But Doctor Copeland did not eat.When Highboy brought out a pint bottle of gin, and they laughed and passed the bottle from mouth to mouth, he refused that also.He sat in rigid silence, and at last he picked up his hat and left the house without a farewell.If he could not speak the whole long truth no other word would come to him.

He lay tense and wakeful throughout the night. Then the next day was Sunday.He made half a dozen calls, and in the middle of the morning he went to Mr.Singer's room.The visit blunted the feeling of loneliness in him so that when he said good-bye he was at peace with himself once more.

However, before he was out of the house this peace had left him. An accident occurred.As he started down the stairs he saw a white man carrying a large paper sack and he drew close to the banisters so that they could pass each other.But the white man was running up the steps two at a time, without looking, and they collided with such force that Doctor Copeland was left sick and breathless.

“Christ！I didn't see you.”

Doctor Copeland looked at him closely but made no answer. He had seen this white man once before.He remembered the stunted, brutal-looking body and the huge, awkward hands.Then with sudden clinical interest he observed the white man's face, for in his eyes he saw a strange, fixed, and withdrawn look of madness.

“Sorry，”said the white man.

Doctor Copeland put his hand on the banister and passed on.

4

“Who was that?”Jake Blount asked.“Who was the tall, thin colored man that just come out of here?”

The small room was very neat. The sun lighted a bowl of purple grapes on the table.Singer sat with his chair tilted back and his hands in his pockets, looking out of the window.

“I bumped into him on the steps and he gave me this look—why, I never had anybody to look at me so dirty.”

Jake put the sack of ales down on the table. He realized with a shock that Singer did not know he was in the room.He walked over to the window and touched Singer on the shoulder.

“I didn't mean to bump into him. He had no cause to act like that.”

Jake shivered. Although the sun was bright there was a chill in the room.Singer held up his forefinger and went into the hall.When he returned he brought with him a scuttle of coal and some kindling.Jake watched him kneel before the hearth.Neatly he broke the sticks of kindling over his knee and arranged them on the foundation of paper.He put the coal on according to a system.At first the fire would not draw.The flames quivered weakly and were smothered by a black roll of smoke.Singer covered the grate with a double sheet of newspapers.The draught gave the fire new life.In the room there was a roaring sound.The paper glowed and was sucked inward.A crackling orange sheet of flame filled the grate.

The first morning ale had a fine mellow taste. Jake gulped his share down quickly and wiped his mouth with file back of his hand.

“There was this lady I knew a long time ago，”he said.“You sort of remind me of her, Miss Clara. She had a little farm in Texas.And made pralines to sell in the cities.She was a tall, big, fine-looking lady.Wore those long, baggy sweaters and clodhopper shoes and a man's hat.Her husband was dead when I knew her.But what I'm getting at is this：If it hadn't been for her I might never have known.I might have gone on through life like the millions of others who don't know.I would have just been a preacher or a linthead or a salesman.My whole life might have been wasted.”

Jake shook his head wonderingly.

“To understand you got to know what went before. You see, I lived in Gastonia when I was a youngun.I was a knock-kneed little runt, too small to put in the mill.I worked as pin boy in a bowling joint and got meals for pay.Then I heard a smart, quick boy could make thirty cents a day stringing tobacco not very far from there.So I went and made that thirty cents a day.That was when I was ten years old.I just left my folks.I didn't write.They were glad I was gone.You understand how those things are.And besides, nobody could read a letter but my sister.”

He waved his hand in the air as though brushing something from his face.“But I mean this. My first belief was Jesus.There was this fellow working in the same shed with me.He had a tabernacle and preached every night.I went and listened and I got this faith.My mind was on Jesus all day long.In my spare time I studied the Bible and prayed.Then one night I took a hammer and laid my hand on the table.I was angry and I drove the nail all the way through.My hand was nailed to the table and I looked at it and the fingers fluttered and turned blue.”

Jake held out his palm and pointed to the ragged, dead-white scar in the center.

“I wanted to be an evangelist. I meant to travel around the country preaching and holding revivals.In the meantime I moved around from one place to another, and when I was nearly twenty I got to Texas.I worked in a pecan grove near where Miss Clara lived.I got to know her and at night sometimes I would go to her house.She talked to me.Understand, I didn't begin to know all at once.That's not the way it happens to any of us.It was gradual.I began to read.I would work just so I could put aside enough money to knock off for a while and study.It was like being born a second time.Just us who know can understand what it means.We have opened our eyes and have seen.We're like people from way off yonder somewhere.”

Singer agreed with him. The room was comfortable in a homey way.Singer brought out from the closet the tin box in which he kept crackers and fruit and cheese.He selected an orange and peeled it slowly.He pulled off shreds of pith until the fruit was transparent in the sun.He secitioned the orange and divided the plugs between them.Jake ate two sections at a time and with a loud whoosh spat the seeds into the fire.Singer ate his share slowly and deposited his seeds neatly in the palm of one hand.They opened two more ales.

“And how many of us are there in this country?Maybe ten thousand. Maybe twenty thousand.Maybe a lot more.I been to a lot of places but I never met but a few of us.But say a man does know.He sees the world as it is and he looks back thousands of years to see how it all come about.He watches the slow agglutination of capital and power and he sees its pinnacle today.He sees America as a crazy house.He sees how men have to rob their brothers in order to live.He sees children starving and women working sixty hours a week to get to eat.He sees a whole damn army of unemployed and billions of dollars and thousands of miles of land wasted.He sees war coming.He sees how when people suffer just so much they get mean and ugly and something dies in them.But the main thing he sees is that the whole system of the world is built on a lie.And although it's as plain as the shining sun—the don't-knows have lived with that lie so long they just can't see it.”

The red corded vein in Jake's forehead swelled angrily. He grasped the scuttle on the hearth and rattled an avalanche of coal on the fire.His foot had gone to sleep, and he stamped it so hard that the floor shook.

“I been all over this place. I walk around.I talk.I try to explain to them.But what good does it do?Lord God！”

He gazed into the fire, and a flush from the ale and heat deepened the color of his face. The sleepy tingling in his foot spread up his leg.He drowsed and saw the colors of the fire, the tints of green and blue and burning yellow.“You're the only one，”he said dreamily.“The only one.”

He was a stranger no longer. By now he knew every street, every alley, every fence in all the sprawling slums of the town.He still worked at the Sunny Dixie.During the fall the show moved from one vacant lot to another, staying always within the fringes of the city limit, until at last it had encircled the town.The locations were changed but the settings were alike—a strip of wasteland bordered by rows of rotted shacks, and somewhere near a mill, a cotton gin, or a bottling plant.The crowd was the same, for the most part factory workers and Negroes.The show was gaudy with colored lights in the evening.The wooden horses of the flying-jinny revolved in the circle to the mechanical music.The swings whirled, the rail around the penny throwing game was always crowded.From the two booths were sold drinks and bloody brown hamburgers and cotton candy.

He had been hired as a machinist, but gradually the range of his duties widened. His coarse, bawling voice called out through the noise, and continually he was lounging from one place on the show grounds to another.Sweat stood out on his forehead and often his mustache was soaked with beer.On Saturday his job was to keep the people in order.His squat, hard body pushed through the crowd with savage energy.Only his eyes did not share the violence of the rest of him.Wide gazing beneath his massive scowling forehead, they had a withdrawn and distracted appearance.

He reached home between twelve and one in the morning. The house where he lived was squared into four rooms and the rent was a dollar fifty per person.There was a privy in the back and a hydrant on the stoop.In his room the walls and floor had a wet, sour smell.Sooty, cheap lace curtains hung at the window.He kept his good suit in his bag and hung his overalls on a nail.The room had no heat and no electricity.However, a street light shone outside the window and made a pale greenish reflection inside.He never lighted the oil lamp by his bed unless he wanted to read.The acrid smell of burning oil in the cold room nauseated him.

If he stayed at home he restlessly walked the floor. He sat on the edge of the unmade bed and gnawed savagely at the broken, dirty ends of his fingernails.The sharp taste of grime lingered in his mouth.The loneliness in him was so keen that he was filled with terror.Usually he had a pint of bootleg white lightning.He drank the raw liquor and by daylight he was warm and relaxed.At five o'clock the whistles from the mills blew for the first shift.The whistles made lost, eerie echoes, and he could never sleep until after they had sounded.

But usually he did not stay at home. He went out into the narrow, empty streets.In the first dark hours of the morning the sky was black and the stars hard and bright.Sometimes the mills were running.From the yellow-lighted buildings came the racket of the machines.He waited at the gates for the early shift.Young girls in sweaters and print dresses came out into the dark street.The men came out carrying their dinner pails.Some of them always went to a streetcar café　for Coca-Cola or coffee before going home, and Jake went with them.Inside the noisy mill the men could hear plainly every word that was spoken, but for the first hour outside they were deaf.

In the streetcar Jake drank Coca-Cola with whiskey added. He talked.The winter dawn was white and smoky and cold.He looked with drunken urgency into the drawn, yellow faces of the men.Often he was laughed at, and when this happened he held his stunted body very straight and spoke scornfully in words of many syllables.He stuck his little finger out from his glass and haughtily twisted his mustache.And if he was still laughed at he sometimes fought.He swung his big brown fists with crazed violence and sobbed aloud.

After such mornings he returned to the show with relief. It eased him to push through the crowds of people.The noise, the rank stinks, the shouldering contact of human flesh soothed his jangled nerves.

Because of the blue laws in the town the show closed for the Sabbath. On Sunday he got up early in the morning and took from the suitcase his serge suit.He went to the main street.First he dropped into the New York Café　and bought a sack of ales.Then he went to Singer’s room.Although he knew many people in the town by name or face, the mute was his only friend.They would idle in the quiet room and drink the ales.He would talk, and the words created themselves from the dark mornings spent in the streets or in his room alone.The words were formed and spoken with relief.

The fire had died down. Singer was playing a game of fools with himself at the table.Jake had been asleep.He awoke with a nervous quiver.He raised his head and turned to Singer.“Yeah，”he said as though in answer to a sudden question.“Some of us are Communists.But not all of us—Myself, I'm not a member of the Communist Party.Because in the first place I never knew but one of them.You can bum around for years and not meet Communists.Around here there's no office where you can go up and say you want to join—and if there is I never heard of it.And you just don't take off for New York and join.As I say I never knew but one—and he was a seedy little teetotaler whose breath stunk.We had a fight.Not that I hold that against the Communists.The main fact is I don't think so much of Stalin and Russia.I hate every damn country and government there is.But even so maybe I ought to joined up with the Communists first place.I'm not certain one way or the other.What do you think?”

Singer wrinkled his forehead and considered. He reached for his silver pencil and wrote on his pad of paper that he didn't know.

“But there's this. You see, we just can't settle down after knowing, but we got to act.And some of us go nuts.There's too much to do and you don't know where to start It makes you crazy.Even me—I've done things that when I look back at them they don’t seem rational.Once I started an organization myself.I picked out twenty lintheads and talked to them until I thought they knew.Our motto was one word：Action.Huh！We meant to start riots—stir up all the big trouble we could.Our ultimate goal was freedom—but a real freedom, a great freedom made possible only by the sense of justice of the human soul.Our motto，‘Action，’signified the razing of capitalism.In the constitution（drawn up by myself）certain statutes dealt with the swapping of our motto from‘Action’to‘Freedom’as soon as our work was through.”

Jake sharpened the end of a match and picked a troublesome cavity in a tooth. After a moment he continued：

“Then when the constitution was all written down and the first followers well organized—then I went out on a hitch-hiking tour to organize component units of the society. Within three months I came back, and what do you reckon I found?What was the first heroic action?Had their righteous fury overcome planned action so that they had gone ahead without me?Was it destruction, murder, revolution?”

Jake leaned forward in his chair. After a pause he said somberly：

“My friend, they had stole the fifty-seven dollars and thirty cents from the treasury to buy uniform caps and free Saturday suppers. I caught them sitting around the conference table, rolling the bones, their caps on their heads, and a ham and a gallon of gin in easy reach.”

A timid smile from Singer followed Jake's outburst of laughter. After a while the smile on Singer's face grew strained and faded.Jake still laughed.The vein in his forehead swelled, his face was dusky red.He laughed too long.

Singer looked up at the clock and indicated the time—half past twelve. He took his watch, his silver pencil and pad, his cigarettes and matches from the mantel and distributed them among his pockets.It was dinner-time.

But Jake still laughed. There was something maniacal in the sound of his laughter.He walked about the room, jingling the change in his pockets.His long, powerful arms swung tense and awkward.He began to name over parts of his coming meal.When he spoke of food his face was fierce with gusto.With each word he raised his upper lip like a ravenous animal.

“Roast beef with gravy. Rice.And cabbage and light bread.And a big hunk of apple pie.I'm famished.Oh, Johnny, I can hear the Yankees coming.And speaking of meals, my friend, did I ever tell you about Mr.Clark Patterson, the gentleman who owns the Sunny Dixie Show?He's so fat he hasn't seen his privates for twenty years, and all day he sits in his trailer playing solitaire and smoking reefers.He orders his meals from a short-order joint nearby and every day he breaks his fast with—”

Jake stepped back so that Singer could leave the room. He always hung back at doorways when he was with the mute.He always followed and expected Singer to lead.As they descended the stairs he continued to talk with nervous volubility.He kept his brown, wide eyes on Singer's face.

The afternoon was soft and mild. They stayed indoors.Jake had brought back with them a quart of whiskey.He sat brooding and silent on the foot of the bed, leaning now and then to fill his glass from the bottle on the floor.Singer was at his table by the window playing a game of chess.Jake had relaxed somewhat.He watched the game of his friend and felt the mild, quiet afternoon merge with the darkness of evening.The firelight made dark, silent waves on the walls of the room.

But at night the tension came in him again. Singer had put away his chess-men and they sat facing each other.Nervousness made Jake's lips twitch raggedly and he drank to soothe himself.A backwash of restlessness and desire overcame him.He drank down the whiskey and began to talk again to Singer.The words swelled with him and gushed from his mouth.He walked from the window to the bed and back again—again and again.And at last the deluge of swollen words took shape and he delivered them to the mute with drunken emphasis：

“The things they have done to us！The truths they have turned into lies. The ideals they have fouled and made vile.Take Jesus.He was one of us.He knew.When He said that it is harder for a camel to pass through the eye of a needle than for a rich man to enter the kingdom of God—he damn well meant just what he said.But look what the Church has done to Jesus during the last two thousand years.What they have made of him.How they have turned every word he spoke for their own vile ends.Jesus would be framed and in jail if he was living today.Jesus would be one who really knows.Me and Jesus would sit across the table and I would look at him and he would look at me and we would both know that the other knew.Me and Jesus and Karl Marx could all sit at a table and—

“And look what has happened to our freedom. The men who fought the American Revolution were no more like these D.A.R.dames than I'm a pot-bellied, perfumed Pekingese dog.They meant what they said about freedom.They fought a real revolution.They fought so that this could be a country where every man would be free and equal.Huh！And that meant every man was equal in the sight of Nature—with an equal chance.This didn't mean that twenty per cent of the people were free to rob the other eighty per cent of the means to live.This didn't mean for one rich man to sweat the piss out of ten thousand poor men so that he can get richer.This didn't mean the tyrants were free to get this country in such a fix that millions of people are ready to do anything—cheat, lie, or whack off their right arm—just to work for three squares and a flop.They have made the word freedom a blasphemy.You hear me?They have made the word freedom stink like a skunk to all who know.”

The vein in Jake's forehead throbbed wildly. His mouth worked convulsively.Singer sat up, alarmed, Jake tried to speak again and the words choked in his mouth.A shudder passed through his body.He sat down in the chair and pressed his trembling lips with his fingers.Then he said huskily：

“It's this way, Singer. Being mad is no good.Nothing we can do is any good.That's the way it seems to me.All we can do is go around telling the truth.And as soon as enough of the don't knows have learned the truth then there won't be any use for fighting.The only thing for us to do is let them know.All that's needed.But how?Huh?”

The fire shadows lapped against the walls. The dark, shadowy waves rose higher and the room took on motion.The room rose and fell and all balance was gone.Alone Jake felt himself sink downward, slowly in wavelike motions downward into a shadowed ocean.In helplessness and terror he strained his eyes, but he could see nothing except the dark and scarlet waves that roared hungrily over him.Then at last he made out the thing which he sought.The mute's face was faint and very far away.Jake closed his eyes.

The next morning he awoke very late. Singer had been gone for hours.There was bread, cheese, an orange, and a pot of coffee on the table.When he had finished his breakfast it was time for work.He walked somberly, his head bent, across the town toward his room.When he reached the neighborhood where he lived he passed through a certain narrow street that was flanked on one side by a smoke-blackened brick warehouse.On the wall of this building there was something that vaguely distracted him.He started to walk on, and then his attention was suddenly held.On the wall a message was written in bright red chalk, the letters drawn thickly and curiously formed：

Ye shall eat the flesh of the mighty, and drink the blood of the princes of the earth.

He read the message twice and looked anxiously up and down the street. No one was in sight.After a few minutes of puzzled deliberation he took from his pocket a thick red pencil and wrote carefully beneath the inscription：

Whoever wrote the above meet me here tomorrow at noon, Wednesday, November　29.Or the next day.

At twelve o'clock the next day he waited before the wall. Now and then he walked impatiently to the corner to look up and down the streets.No one came.After an hour he had to leave for the show.

The next day he waited, also.

Then on Friday there was a long, slow winter rain. The wall was sodden and the messages streaked so that no word could be read.The rain continued, gray and bitter and cold.

5

“Mick，”Bubber said.“I come to believe we all gonna drown.”

It was true that it like to never quit raining. Mrs.Wells rode them back and forth to school in her car, and every afternoon they had to stay on the front porch or in the house.She and Bubber played Parcheesi and Old Maid and shot marbles on the living-room rug.It was nearing along toward Christmas time and Bubber began to talk about the Little Lord Jesus and the red bicycle he wanted Santa Claus to bring him.The rain was silver on the windowpanes and the sky was wet and cold and gray.The river rose so high that some of the factory people had to move out of their houses.Then when it looked like the rain would keep on and on forever it suddenly stopped.They woke up one morning and the bright sun was shining.By afternoon the weather was almost warm as summer.Mick came home late from school and Bubber and Ralph and Spareribs were on the front sidewalk.The kids looked hot and sticky and their winter clothes had a sour smell.Bubber had his slingshot and a pocketful of rocks.Ralph sat up in his wagon, his hat crooked on his head, and he was fretful.Spareribs had his new rifle with him.The sky was a wonderful blue.

“We waited for you a long time, Mick，”Bubber said.“Where you been?”

She jumped up the front steps three at a time and threw her sweater toward the hat rack.“Practicing on the piano in the gym.”

Every afternoon she stayed after school for an hour to play. The gym was crowded and noisy because the girls'team had basketball games.Twice today she was hit on the head with the ball.But getting a chance to sit at a piano was worth any amount of knocks and trouble.She would arrange bunches of notes together until the sound came that she wanted.It was eaiser than she had thought.After the first two or three hours she figured out some sets of chords in the bass that would fit in with the main tune her right hand was playing.She could pick out almost any piece now.And she made up new music too.That was better than just copying tunes.When her hands hunted out these beautiful new sounds it was the best feeling she had ever known.

She wanted to learn how to read music already written down. Delores Brown had taken music lessons for five years.She paid Delores the fifty cents a week she got for lunch money to give her lessons.This made her very hungry all through the day.Delores played a good many fast, runny pieces—but Delores did not know how to answer all the questions she wanted to know.Delores only taught her about the different scales, the major and minor chords, the values of the notes, and such beginning rules as those.

Mick slammed the door of the kitchen stove.“This all we got to eat?”

“Honey, it the best I can do for you，”Portia said.

Just cornpones and margarine. As she ate she drank a glass of water to help wash down the swallows.

“Quit acting so greedy. Nobody going to snatch it out your hand.”

The kids still hung around in front of the house. Bubber had put his slingshot in his pocket and now he played with the rifle.Spareribs was ten years old and his father had died the month before and this had been his father's gun.All the smaller kids loved to handle that rifle.Every few minutes Bubber would haul the gun up to his shoulder.He took aim and made a loud pow sound.

“Don't monkey with the trigger，”said Spareribs.“I got the gun loaded.”

Mick finished the cornbread and looked around for something to do. Harry Minowitz was sitting on his front porch banisters with the newspaper.She was glad to see him.For a joke she threw up her arm and hollered to him，“Heil！”

But Harry didn't take it as a joke. He went into his front hall and shut the door.It was easy to hurt his feelings.She was sorry, because lately she and Harry had been right good friends.They had always played in the same gang when they were kids, but in the last three years he had been at Vocational while she was still in grammar school.Also he worked at part-time jobs.He grew up very suddenly and quit hanging around the back and front yards with kids.Sometimes she could see him reading the paper in his bedroom or undressing late at night.In mathematics and history he was the smartest boy at Vocational.Often, now that she was in high school too, they would meet each other on the way home and walk together.They were in the same shop class, and once the teacher made them partners to assemble a motor.He read books and kept up with the newspapers every day.World politics were all the time on his mind.He talked slow, and sweat stood out on his forehead when he was very serious about something.And now she had made him mad with her.

“I wonder has Harry still got his gold piece，”Spareribs said.

“What gold piece?”

“When a Jew boy is born they put a gold piece in the bank for him. That's what Jews do.”

“Shucks. You got it mixed up，”she said.“It's Catholics you're thinking about.Catholics buy a pistol for a baby soon as it's born.Some day the Catholics mean to start a war and kill everybody else.”

“Nuns give me a funny feeling，”Spareribs said.“It scares me when I see one on the street.”

She sat down on the steps and laid her head on her knees. She went into the inside room.With her it was like there was two places—the inside room and the outside room.School and the family and the things that happened every day were in the outside room.Mister Singer was in both rooms.Foreign countries and plans and music were in the inside room.The songs she thought about were there.And the symphony.When she was by herself in this inside room the music she had heard that night after the party would come back to her.This symphony grew slow like a big flower in her mind.During the day sometimes, or when she had just waked up in the morning, a new part of the symphony would suddenly come to her.Then she would have to go into the inside room and listen to it many times and try to join it into the parts of the symphony she remembered.The inside room was a very private place.She could be in the middle of a house full of people and still feel like she was locked up by herself.

Spareribs stuck his dirty hand up to her eyes because she had been staring off at space. She slapped him.

“What is a nun?”Bubber asked.

“A Catholic lady，”Spareribs said.“A Catholic lady with a big black dress that comes up over her head.”

She was tired of hanging around with the kids. She would go to the library and look at pictures in the National Geographic.Photographs of all the foreign places in the world.Paris, France.And big ice glaciers.And the wild jungles in Africa.

“You kids see that Ralph don't get out in the street，”she said.

Bubber rested the big rifle on his shoulder.“Bring me a story back with you.”

It was like that kid had been born knowing how to read. He was only in the second grade but he loved to read stories by himself—and he never asked anybody else to read to him.“What kind you want this time?”

“Pick out some stories with something to eat in them. I like that one a whole lot about them German kids going out in the forest and coming to this house made out of all different kinds of candy and the witch.I like a story with something to eat in it.”

“I'll look for one，”said Mick.

“But I'm getting kinda tired of candy，”Bubber said.“See if you can't bring me a story with something like a barbecue sandwich in it. But if you can't find none of them I'd like a cowboy story.”

She was ready to leave when suddenly she stopped and stared. The kids stared too.They all stood still and looked at Baby Wilson coming down the steps of her house across the street.

“Ain't Baby cute！”said Bubber softly.

Maybe it was the sudden hot, sunny day after all those rainy weeks. Maybe it was because their dark winter clothes were ugly to them on an afternoon like this one.Anyway Baby looked like a fairy or something in the picture show.She had on her last year's soirée costume—with a little pink-gauze skirt that stuck out short and stiff, a pink body waist, pink dancing shoes, and even a little pink pocket-book.With her yellow hair she was all pink and white and gold—and so small and clean that it almost hurt to watch her.She prissed across the street in a cute way, but would not turn her face toward them.

“Come over here，”said Bubber.“Lemme look at your little pink pocket-book—”

Baby passed them along the edge of the street with her head held to one side. She had made up her mind not to speak to them.

There was a strip of grass between the sidewalk and the street, and when Baby reached it she stood still for a second and then turned a handspring.

“Don't pay no mind to her，”said Spareribs.“She always tries to show off. She's going down to Mister Brannon's café　to get candy.He’s her uncle and she gets it free.”

Bubber rested the end of the rifle on the ground. The big gun was too heavy for him.As he watched Baby walk off down the street he kept pulling the straggly bangs of his hair.“That sure is a cute little pink pocket-book，”he said.

“Her Mama always talks about how talented she is，”said Spareribs.“She thinks she's gonna get Baby in the movies.”

It was too late to go look at the National Geographic. Supper was almost ready.Ralph tuned up to cry and she took him off the wagon and put him on the ground.Now it was December, and to a kid Bubber's age that was a long time from summer.All last summer Baby had come out in that pink soirée costume and danced in the middle of the street.At first the kids would flock around and watch her, but soon they got tired of it.Bubber was the only one who would watch her as she came out to dance.He would sit on the curb and yell to her when he saw a car coming.He had watched Baby do her soirée dance a hundred times—but summer had been gone for three months and now it seemed new to him again.

“I sure do wish I had a costume，”Bubber said.

“What kind do you want?”

“A real cool costume. A real pretty one made out of all different colors.Like a butterfly.That's what I want for Christmas.That and a bicycle！”

“Sissy，”said Spareribs.

Bubber hauled the big rifle up to his shoulder again and took aim at a house across the street.“I'd dance around in my costume if I had one. I'd wear it every day to school.”

Mick sat on the front steps and kept her eyes on Ralph. Bubber wasn't a sissy like Spareribs said.He just loved pretty things.She'd better not let old Spareribs get away with that.

“A person's got to fight for every single thing they get，”she said slowly.“And I've noticed a lot of times that the farther down a kid comes in the family the better the kid really is. Youngest kids are always the toughest.I'm pretty hard'cause I've a lot of them on top of me.Bubber—he looks sick, and likes pretty things, but he’s got guts underneath that.If all this is true Ralph sure ought to be a real strong one when he’s old enough to get around.Even though he’s just seventeen months old I can read something hard and tough in that Ralph’s face already.”

Ralph looked around because he knew he was being talked about. Spareribs sat down on the ground and grabbed Ralph's hat off his head and shook it in his face to tease him.

“All right！”Mick said.“You know what I'll do to you if you start him to cry. You just better watch out.”

Everything was quiet. The sun was behind the roofs of the houses and the sky in the west was purple and pink.On the next block there was the sound of kids skating.Bubber leaned up against a tree and he seemed to be dreaming about something.The smell of supper came out of the house and it would be time to eat soon.

“Look it，”Bubber said suddenly.“Here comes Baby again. She sure is pretty in the pink costume.”

Baby walked toward them slowly. She had been given a prize box of popcorn candy and was reaching in the box for the prize.She walked in that same prissy, dainty way.You could tell that she knew they were all looking at her.

“Please, Baby—”Bubber said when she started to pass them.“Lemme see your little pink pocket-book and touch your pink costume.”

Baby started humming a song to herself and did not listen. She passed by without letting Bubber play with her.She only ducked her head and grinned at him a little.

Bubber still had the big rifle up to his shoulder. He made a loud pow sound and pretended like he had shot.Then he called to Baby again—in a soft, sad voice like he was calling a little kitty.“Please, Baby—come here, Baby—”

He was too quick for Mick to stop him. She had just seen his hand on the trigger when there was the terrible ping of the gun.Baby crumpled down to the sidewalk.It was like she was nailed to the steps and couldn't move or scream.Spareribs had his arm up over his head.

Bubber was the only one that didn't realize.“Get up, Baby，”he hollered.“I ain't mad with you.”

It all happened in a second. The three of them reached Baby at the same time.She lay crumpled down on the dirty sidewalk.Her skirt was over her head, showing her pink panties and her little white legs.Her hands were open—in one there was the prize from the candy and in the other the pocket-book.There was blood all over her hair ribbon and the top of her yellow curls.She was shot in the head and her face was turned down toward the ground.

So much happened in a second. Bubber screamed and dropped the gun and ran.She stood with her hands up to her face and screamed too.Then there were many people.Her Dad was the first to get there.He carried Baby into the house.

“She's dead，”said Spareribs.“She's shot through the eyes. I seen her face.”

Mick walked up and down the sidewalk, and her tongue stuck in her mouth when she tried to ask was Baby killed. Mrs.Wilson came running down the block from the beauty parlor where she worked.She went into the house and came back out again.She walked up and down in the street, crying and pulling a ring on and off her finger.Then the ambulance came and the doctor went in to Baby.Mick followed him.Baby was lying on the bed in the front room.The house was quiet as a church.

Baby looked like a pretty little doll on the bed. Except for the blood she did not seem hurt.The doctor bent over and looked at her head.After he finished they took Baby out on a stretcher.Mrs.Wilson and her Dad got into the ambulance with her.

The house was still quiet. Everybody had forgotten about Bubber.He was nowhere around.An hour passed.Her Mama and Hazel and Etta and all the boarders waited in the front room.Mister Singer stood in the doorway.After a long time her Dad came home.He said Baby wouldn't die but that her skull was fractured.He asked for Bubber.Nobody knew where he was.It was dark outside.They called Bubber in the back yard and in the street.They sent Spareribs and some other boys out to hunt for him.It looked like Bubber had gone clear out of the neighborhood.Harry went around to a house where they thought he might be.

Her Dad walked up and down the front porch.“I never have whipped any of my kids yet，”he kept saying.“I never believed in it. But I'm sure going to lay it onto that kid as soon as I get my hands on him.”

Mick sat on the banisters and watched down the dark street.“I can manage Bubber. Once he comes back I can take care of him all right.”

“You go out and hunt for him. You can find him better than anybody else.”

As soon as her Dad said that she suddenly knew where Bubber was. In the back yard there was a big oak and in the summer they had built a tree house.They had hauled a big box up in this oak, and Bubber used to love to sit up in the tree house by himself.Mick left the family and the boarders on the front porch and walked back through the alley of the dark yard.

She stood for a minute by the trunk of the tree.“Bubber—，”she said quietly.“It's Mick.”

He didn't answer, but she knew he was there. It was like she could smell him.She swung up on the lowest branch and climbed slowly.She was really mad with that kid and would have to teach him a lesson.When she reached the tree house she spoke to him again—and still there wasn't any answer.She climbed into the big box and felt around the edges.At last she touched him.He was scrouged up in a corner and his legs were trembling.He had been holding his breath, and when she touched him the sobs and the breath came out all at once.

“I—I didn't mean Baby to fall. She was just so little and cute—seemed to me like I just had to take a pop at her.”

Mick sat down on the floor of the tree house.“Baby's dead，”she said.“They got a lot of people hunting for you.”

Bubber quit crying. He was very quiet.

“You know what Dad's doing in the house?”

It was like she could hear Bubber listening.

“You know Warden Lawes—you heard him over the radio. And you know Sing Sing.Well, our Dad's writing a1　letter to Warden Lawes for him to be a little bit kind to you when they catch you and send you to Sing Sing.”

The words were so awful-sounding in the dark that a shiver came over her. She could feel Bubber trembling.

“They got little electric chairs there—just your size. And when they turn on the juice you just fry up like a piece of burnt bacon.Then you go to Hell.”

Bubber was squeezed up in the corner and there was not a sound from him. She climbed over the edge of the box to get down.“You better stay up here because they got policemen guarding the yard.Maybe in a few days I can bring you something to eat.”

Mick leaned against the trunk of the oak tree. That would teach Bubber all right.She had always managed him and she knew more about that kid than anybody else.Once, about a year or two ago, he was always wanting to stop off behind bushes and pee and play with himself awhile.She had caught on to that pretty quick.She gave him a good slap every time it happened and in three days he was cured.Afterwards he never even peed normal like other kids—he held his hands behind him.She always had to nurse that Bubber and she could always manage him.In a little while she would go back up to the tree house and bring him in.After this he would never want to pick up a gun again in all his life.

There was still this dead feeling in the house. The boarders all sat on the front porch without talking or rocking in the chairs.Her Dad and her Mama were in the front room.Her Dad drank beer out of a bottle and walked up and down the floor.Baby was going to get well all right, so this worry was not about her.And nobody seemed to be anxious about Bubber.It was something else.

“That Bubber！”said Etta.

“I'm shamed to go out of the house after this，”Hazel said.

Etta and Hazel went into the middle room and closed the door. Bill was in his room at the back.She didn't want to talk with them.She stood around in the front hall and thought it over by herself.

Her Dad's footsteps stopped.“It was deliberate，”he said.“It's not like the kid was just fooling with the gun and it went off by accident. Everybody who saw it said he took deliberate aim.”

“I wonder when we'll hear from Mrs. Wilson，”her Mama said.

“We'll hear plenty, all right！”

“I reckon we will.”

Now that the sun was down the night was cold again like November. The people came in from the front porch and sat in the living-room—but nobody lighted a fire.Mick's sweater was hanging on the hat rack, so she put it on and stood with her shoulders bent over to keep warm.She thought about Bubber sitting out in the cold, dark tree house.He had really believed every word she said.But he sure deserved to worry some.He had nearly killed that Baby.

“Mick, can't you think of some place where Bubber might be?”her Dad asked.

“He's in the neighborhood, I reckon.”

Her Dad walked up and down with the empty beer bottle in his hand. He walked like a blind man and there was sweat on his face.“The poor kid's scared to come home.If we could find him I'd feel better.I've never laid a hand on Bubber.He oughtn't be scared of me.”

She would wait until an hour and a half was gone. By that time he would be plenty sorry for what he did.She always could manage that Bubber and make him learn.

After a while there was a big excitement in the house. Her Dad telephoned again to the hospital to see how Baby was, and in a few minutes Mrs.Wilson called back.She said she wanted to have a talk with them and would come to the house.

Her Dad still walked up and down the front room like a blind man. He drank three more bottles of beer.“The way it all happened she can sue my britches off.All she could get would be the house outside of the mortgage.But the way it happened we don't have any comeback at all.”

Suddenly Mick thought about something. Maybe they would really try Bubber in court and put him in a children's jail.Maybe Mrs.Wilson would send him to reform school.Maybe they would really do something terrible to Bubber.She wanted to go out to the tree house right away and sit with him and tell him not to worry.Bubber was always so thin and little and smart.She would kill anybody that tried to send that kid out of the family.She wanted to kiss him and bite him because she loved him so much.

But she couldn't miss anything. Mrs.Wilson would be there in a few minutes and she had to know what was going on.Then she would run out and tell Bubber that all the things she said were lies.And he would really have learned the lesson he had coming to him.

A ten-cent taxicab drove up to the sidewalk. Everybody waited on the front porch, very quiet and scared.Mrs.Wilson got out of the taxi with Mister Brannon.She could hear her Dad grinding his teeth together in a nervous way as they came up the steps.They went into the front room and she followed along after them and stood in the doorway.Etta and Hazel and Bill and the boarders kept out of it.

“I've come to talk over all this with you，”Mrs. Wilson said.

The front room looked tacky and dirty and she saw Mister Brannon notice everything. The mashed celluloid doll and the beads and junk Ralph played with were scattered on the floor.There was beer on her Dad's workbench, and the pillows on the bed where her Dad and Mama slept were right gray.

Mrs. Wilson kept pulling the wedding ring on and off her finger.By the side of her Mister Brannon was very calm.He sat with his legs crossed.His jaws were blue-black and he looked like a gangster in the movies.He had always had this grudge against her.He always spoke to her in this rough voice different from the way he talked to other people.Was it because he knew about the time she and Bubber swiped a pack of chewing gum off his counter?She hated him.

“It all boils down to this，”said Mrs. Wilson.“Your kid shot my baby in the head on purpose.”

Mick stepped into the middle of the room.“No, he didn't，”she said.“I was right there. Bubber had been aiming that gun at me and Ralph and everything around there.He just happened to aim it at Baby and his finger slipped.I was right there.”

Mister Brannon rubbed his nose and looked at her in a sad way. She sure did hate him.

“I know how you all feel—so I want to come to the point right now.”

Mick's Mama rattled a bunch of keys and her Dad sat very still with his big hands hanging over his knees.

“Bubber didn't have it in his mind beforehand，”Mick said.“He just—”

Mrs. Wilson jabbed the ring on and off her finger.“Wait a minute.I know how everything is.I could bring it to court and sue for every cent you own.”

Her Dad didn't have any expression on his face.“I tell you one thing，”he said.“We don't have much to sue for. All we got is—”

“Just listen to me，”said Mrs. Wilson.“I haven't come here with any lawyer to sue you.Bartholomew—Mister Brannon—and I talked it over when we came and we just about agree on the main points.In the first place, I want to do the fair, honest thing—and in the second place, I don't want Baby's name mixed up in no common lawsuit at her age.”

There was not a sound and everybody in the room sat stiff in their chairs. Only Mister Brannon half-way smiled at Mick, but she squinted her eyes back at him in a tough way.

Mrs. Wilson was very nervous and her hand shook when she lighted a cigarette.“I don't want to have to sue you or anything like that.All I want is for you to be fair.I'm not asking you to pay for all the suffering and crying Baby went through with until they gave her something to sleep.There's not any pay that would make up for that.And I'm not asking you to pay for the damage this will do to her career and the plans we had made.She's going to have to wear a bandage for several months.She won’t get to dance in the soirée—maybe there’ll even be a little bald place on her head.”

Mrs. Wilson and her Dad looked at each other like they was hypnotized.Then Mrs.Wilson reached around to her pocket-book and took out a slip of paper.

“The things you got to pay are just the actual price of what it will cost us in money. There's Baby's private room in the hospital and a private nurse until she can come home.There's the operating room and the doctor's bill—and for once I intend the doctor to be paid right away.Also, they shaved all Baby's hair off and you got to pay me for the permanent wave I took her to Atlanta to get—so when her hair grows back natural she can have another one.And there’s the price of her costume and other little extra bills like that.I’ll write all the items down just as soon as I know what they’ll be.I’m trying to be just as fair and honest as I can, and you’ll have to pay the total when I bring it to you.”

Her Mama smoothed her dress over her knees and took a quick, short breath.“Seems to me like the children's ward would be a lot better than a private room. When Mick had pneumonia—”

“I said a private room.”

Mister Brannon held out his white, stumpy hands and balanced them like they was on scales.“Maybe in a day or two Baby can move into a double room with some other kid.”

Mrs. Wilson spoke hard-boiled.“You heard what I said.Long as your kid shot my Baby she certainly ought to have every advantage until she gets well.”

“You're in your rights，”her Dad said.“God knows we don't have anything now—but maybe I can scrape it up. I realize you're not trying to take advantage of us and I appreciate it.We'll do what we can.”

She wanted to stay and hear everything that they said, but Bubber was on her mind. When she thought of him sitting up in the dark, cold tree house thinking about Sing Sing she felt uneasy.She went out of the room and down the hall toward the back door.The wind was blowing and the yard was very dark except for the yellow square that came from the light in the kitchen.When she looked back she saw Portia sitting at the table with her long, thin hands up on her face, very still.The yard was lonesome and the wind made quick, scary shadows and a mourning kind of sound in the darkness.

She stood under the oak tree. Then just as she started to reach for the first limb a terrible notion came over her.It came to her all of a sudden that Bubber was gone.She called him and he did not answer.She climbed quick and quiet as a cat.

“Say！Bubber！”

Without feeling in the box she knew he wasn't there. To make sure she got into the box and felt in all the corners.The kid was gone.He must have started down the minute she left.He was running away for sure now, and with a smart kid like Bubber it was no telling where they'd catch him.

She scrambled down the tree and ran to the front porch. Mrs.Wilson was leaving and they had all come out to the front steps with her.

“Dad！”she said.“We got to do something about Bubber. He's run away.I'm sure he left our block.We all got to get out and hunt him.”

Nobody knew where to go or how to begin. Her Dad walked up and down the street, looking in all the alleys.Mister Brannon telephoned for a ten-cent taxi for Mrs.Wilson and then stayed to help with the hunt.Mister Singer sat on the banisters of the porch and he was the only person who kept calm.They all waited for Mick to plan out the best places to look for Bubber.But the town was so big and the little kid so smart that she couldn't think what to do.

Maybe he had gone to Portia's house over in Sugar Hill. She went back into the kitchen where Portia was sitting at the table with her hands up to her face.

“I got this sudden notion he went down to your house. Help us hunt him.”

“How come I didn't think of that！I bet a nickel my little scared Bubber been staying in my home all the time.”

Mister Brannon had borrowed an automobile. He and Mister Singer and Mick's Dad got into the car with her and Portia.Nobody knew what Bubber was feeling except her.Nobody knew he had really run away like he was escaping to save his life.

Portia's house was dark except for the checkered moonlight on the floor. As soon as they stepped inside they could tell there was nobody in the two rooms.Portia lighted the front lamp.The rooms had a colored smell, and they were crowded with cut-out pictures on the walls and the lace table covers and lace pillows on the bed.Bubber was not there.

“He been here，”Portia suddenly said.“I can tell somebody been in here.”

Mister Singer found the pencil and piece of paper on the kitchen table. He read it quickly and then they all looked at it.The writing was round and scraggly and the smart little kid hadn't misspelled but one word.The note said：

Dear Portia，

I gone to Florada.Tell every body.

Yours truly，

Bubber Kelly

They stood around surprised and stumped. Her Dad looked out the doorway and picked his nose with his thumb in a worried way.They were all ready to pile in the car and ride toward the highway leading south.

“Wait a minute，”Mick said.“Even if Bubber is seven years old he's got brains enough not to tell us where he's going if he wants to run away. That about Florida is just a trick.”

“A trick?”her Dad said.

“Yeah. There only two places Bubber knows very much about.One is Florida and the other is Atlanta.Me and Bubber and Ralph have been on the Atlanta road many a time.He knows how to start there and that's where he's headed.He always talks about what he's going to do when he gets a chance to go to Atlanta.”

They went out to the automobile again. She was ready to climb into the back seat when Portia pinched her on the elbow.“You know what Bubber done?”she said in a quiet voice.“Don't you tell nobody else, but my Bubber done also taken my gold earrings off my dresser.I never thought my Bubber would have done such a thing to me.”

Mister Brannon started the automobile. They rode slow, looking up and down the streets for Bubber, headed toward the Atlanta road.

It was true that in Bubber there was a tough, mean streak. He was acting different today than he had ever acted before.Up until now he was always a quiet little kid who never really done anything mean.When anybody's feelings were hurt it always made him ashamed and nervous.Then how come he could do all the things he had done today?

They drove very slow out the Atlanta road. They passed the last line of houses and came to the dark fields and woods.All along they had stopped to ask if anyone had seen Bubber.“Has a little barefooted kid in corduroy knickers been by this way?”But even after they had gone about ten miles nobody had seen or noticed him.The wind came in cold and strong from the open windows and it was late at night.

They rode a little farther and then went back toward town. Her Dad and Mister Brannon wanted to look up all the children in the second grade, but she made them turn around and go back on the Atlanta road again.All the while she remembered the words she had said to Bubber.About Baby being dead and Sing Sing and Warden Lawes.About the small electric chairs that were just his size, and Hell.In the dark the words had sounded terrible.

They rode very slow for about half a mile out of town, and then suddenly she saw Bubber. The lights of the car showed him up in front of them very plain.It was funny.He was walking along the edge of the road and he had his thumb out trying to get a ride.Portia's butcher knife was stuck in his belt, and on the wide, dark road he looked so small that it was like he was five years old instead of seven.

They stopped the automobile and he ran to get in. He couldn't see who they were, and his face had the squint-eyed look it always had when he took aim with a marble.Her Dad held him by the collar.He hit with his fists and kicked.Then he had the butcher knife in his hand.Their Dad yanked it away from him just in time.He fought like a little tiger in a trap, but finally they got him into the car.Their Dad held him in his lap on the way home and Bubber sat very stiff, not leaning against anything.

They had to drag him into the house, and all the neighbors and the boarders were out to see the commotion. They dragged him into the front room and when he was there he backed off into a corner, holding his fists very tight and with his squinted eyes looking from one person to the other like he was ready to fight the whole crowd.

He hadn't said one word since they came into the house until he began to scream：“Mick done it！I didn't do it. Mick done it！”

There were never any kind of yells like the ones Bubber made. The veins in his neck stood out and his fists were hard as little rocks.

“You can't get me！Nobody can get me！”he kept yelling.

Mick shook him by the shoulder. She told him the things she had said were stories.He finally knew what she was saying but he wouldn't hush.It looked like nothing could stop that screaming.

“I hate everybody！I hate everybody！”

They all just stood around. Mister Brannon rubbed his nose and looked down at the floor.Then finally he went out very quietly.Mister Singer was the only one who seemed to know what it was all about.Maybe this was because he didn't hear that awful noise.His face was still calm, and whenever Bubber looked at him he seemed to get quieter.Mister Singer was different from any other man, and at times like this it would be better if other people would let him manage.He had more sense and he knew things that ordinary people couldn't know.He just looked at Bubber, and after a while the kid quieted down enough so that their Dad could get him to bed.

In the bed he lay on his face and cried. He cried with long, big sobs that made him tremble all over.He cried for an hour and nobody in the three rooms could sleep.Bill moved to the living-room sofa and Mick got into bed with Bubber.He wouldn't let her touch him or snug up to him.Then after another hour of crying and hiccoughing he went to sleep.

She was awake a long time. In the dark she put her arms around him and held him very close.She touched him all over and kissed him everywhere.He was so soft and little and there was this salty, boy smell about him.The love she felt was so hard that she had to squeeze him to her until her arms were tired.In her mind she thought about Bubber and music together.It was like she could never do anything good enough for him.She would never hit him or even tease him again.She slept all night with her arms around his head.Then in the morning when she woke up he was gone.

But after that night there was not much of a chance for her to tease him any more—her or anybody else. After he shot Baby the kid was not ever like little Bubber again.He always kept his mouth shut and he didn't fool around with anybody.Most of the time he just sat in the back yard or in the coal house by himself.It got closer and closer toward Christmas time.She really wanted a piano, but naturally she didn't say anything about that.She told everybody she wanted a Mickey Mouse watch.When they asked Bubber what he wanted from Santa Claus he said he didn't want anything.He hid his marbles and jack-knife and wouldn't let anyone touch his story books.

After that night nobody called him Bubber any more. The big kids in the neighborhood started calling him Baby-Killer Kelly.But he didn't speak much to any person and nothing seemed to bother him.The family called him by his real name—George.At first Mick couldn't stop calling him Bubber and she didn't want to stop.But it was funny how after about a week she just naturally called him George like the others did.But he was a different kid—George—going around by himself always like a person much older and with nobody, not even her, knowing what was really in his mind.

She slept with him on Christmas Eve night. He lay in the dark without talking.“Quit acting so peculiar，”she said to him.“Less talk about the wise men and the way the children in Holland put out their wooden shoes instead of hanging up their stockings.”

George wouldn't answer. He went to sleep.

She got up at four o'clock in the morning and waked everybody in the family. Their Dad built a fire in the front room and then let them go into the Christmas tree and see what they got.George had an Indian suit and Ralph a rubber doll.The rest of the family just got clothes.She looked all through her stocking for the Mickey Mouse watch but it wasn't there.Her presents were a pair of brown Oxford shoes and a box of cherry candy.While it was still dark she and George went out on the sidewalk and cracked nigger-toes and shot firecrackers and ate up the whole two-layer box of cherry candy.And by the time it was daylight they were sick to the stomach and tired out.She lay down on the sofa.She shut her eyes and went into the inside room.

6

At eight o'clock Doctor Copeland sat at his desk, studying a sheaf of papers by the bleak morning light from the window. Beside him the tree, a thick-fringed cedar, rose up dark and green to the ceiling.Since the first year he began to practice he had given an annual party on Christmas Day, and now all was in readiness.Rows of benches and chairs lined the walls of the front rooms.Throughout the house there was the sweet spiced odor of newly baked cake and steaming coffee.In the office with him Portia sat on a bench against the wall, her hands cupped beneath her chin, her body bent almost double.

“Father, you been scrouched over the desk since five o'clock. You got no business to be up.You ought to stayed in bed until time for the to-do.”

Doctor Copeland moistened his thick lips with his tongue. So much was on his mind that he had no attention to give to Portia.Her presence fretted him.

At last he turned to her irritably.“Why do you sit there moping?”

“I just got worries，”she said.“For one thing, I worried about our Willie.”

“William?”

“You see he been writing me regular ever Sunday. The letter will get here on Monday or Tuesday.But last week he didn't write.Course I not really anxious.Willie—he always so good-natured and sweet I know he going to be all right.He been transferred from the prison to the chain gang and they going to work up somewhere north of Atlanta.Two weeks ago he wrote this here letter to say they going to attend a church service today, and he done asked me to send him his suit of clothes and his red tie.”

“Is that all William said?”

“He written that this Mr. B.F.Mason is at the prison, too.And that he run into Buster Johnson—he a boy Willie used to know.And also he done asked me to please send him his harp because he can't be happy without he got his harp to play on.I done sent everything.Also a checker set and a white-iced cake.But I sure hope I hears from him in the next few days.”

Doctor Copeland's eyes glowed with fever and he could not rest his hands.“Daughter, we shall have to discuss this later. It is getting late and I must finish here.You go back to the kitchen and see that all is ready.”

Portia stood up and tried to make her face bright and happy.“What you done decided about that five-dollar prize?”

“As yet I have been unable to decide just what is the wisest course，”he said carefully.

A certain friend of his, a Negro pharmacist, gave an award of five dollars every year to the high-school student who wrote the best essay on a given subject. The pharmacist always made Doctor Copeland sole judge of the papers and the winner was announced at the Christmas party.The subject of the composition this year was“My Ambition：How I Can Better the Position of the Negro Race in Society.”There was only one essay worthy of real consideration.Yet this paper was so childish and ill-advised that it would hardly be prudent to confer upon it the award.Doctor Copeland put on his glasses and re-read the essay with deep concentration.

This is my ambition. First I wish to attend Tuskegee College but I do not wish to be a man like Booker Washington or Doctor Carver.Then when I deem that my education is complete I wish to start off being a fine lawyer like the one who defended the Scottsboro Boys.I would only take cases for colored people against white people.Every day our people are made in every way and by every means to feel that they are inferior.This is not so.We are a Rising Race.And we cannot sweat beneath the white man's burdens for long.We cannot always sow where others reap.

I want to be like Moses, who led the children of Israel from the land of the oppressors. I want to get up a Secret Organization of Colored Leaders and Scholars.All colored people will organize under the direction of these picked leaders and prepare for revolt.Other nations in the world who are interested in the plight of our race and who would like to see the United States divided would come to our aid.All colored people will organize and there will be a revolution, and at the close colored people will take up all the territory east of the Mississippi and south of the Potomac.I shall set up a mighty country under the control of the Organization of Colored Leaders and Scholars.No white person will be allowed a passport—and if they get into the country they will have no legal rights.

I hate the whole white race and will work always so that the colored race can achieve revenge for all their sufferings. That is my ambition.

Doctor Copeland felt the fever warm in his veins. The ticking of the clock on his desk was loud and the sound jarred his nerves.How could he give the award to a boy with such wild notions as this?What should he decide?

The other essays were without any firm content at all. The young people would not think.They wrote only about their ambitions and omitted the last part of the tide altogether.Only one point was of some significance.Nine out of the lot of twenty-five began with the sentence，“I do not want to be a servant.”After that they wished to fly airplanes, or be prizefighters, or preachers or dancers.One girl's sole ambition was to be kind to the poor.

The writer of the essay that troubled him was Lancy Davis. He had known the identity of the author before he turned the last sheet over and saw the signature.Already he had some trouble with Lancy.His older sister had gone out to work as a servant when she was eleven years old and she had been raped by her employer, a white man past middle age.Then a year or so later he had received an emergency call to attend Lancy.

Doctor Copeland went to the filing case in his bedroom where he kept notes on all of his patients. He took out the card marked“Mrs.Dan Davis and Family”and glanced through the notations until he reached Lancy's name.The date was four years ago.The entries on him were written with more care than the others and in ink：“thirteen years old—past puberty.Unsuccessful attempt self-emasculation.Oversexed and hyperthyroid.Wept boisterously during two visits, though little pain.Voluble—very glad to talk though paranoiac.Environment fair with one exception.See Lucy Davis—mother washerwoman.Intelligent and well worth watching and all possible help.Keep contact.Fee：$1（?）”

“It is a difficult decision to make this year，”he said to Portia.“But I suppose I will have to confer the award on Lancy Davis.”

“If you done decide, then—come tell me about some of these here presents.”

The gifts to be distributed at the party were in the kitchen. There were paper sacks of groceries and clothing, all marked with a red Christmas card.Anyone who cared to come was invited to the party, but those who meant to attend had stopped by the house and written（or had asked a friend to write）their names in a guest book kept on the table in the hall for that purpose.The sacks were piled on the floor.There were about forty of them, each one depending in size on the need of the receiver.Some gifts were only small packages of nuts or raisins and others were boxes almost too heavy for a man to lift.The kitchen was crowded with good things.Doctor Copeland stood in the doorway and his nostrils quivered with pride.

“I think you done right well this year. Folks certainly have been kindly.”

“Pshaw！”he said.“This is not a hundredth part of what is needed.”

“Now, there you go, Father！I know good and well you just as pleased as you can be. But you don't want to show it.You got to find something to grumble about.Here we haves about four pecks of peas, twenty sacks of meal about fifteen pounds of side meat, mullet, six dozen eggs, plenty grits, jars of tomatoes and peaches.Apples and two dozen oranges.Also garments.And two mattresses and four blankets.I call this something！”

“A drop in the bucket.”

Portia pointed to a large box in the corner.“These here—what you intend to do with them?”

The box contained nothing but junk—a headless doll, some duty lace, a rabbitskin. Doctor Copeland scrutinized each article.“Do not throw them away.There is use for everything.These are the gifts from our guests who have nothing better to contribute.I will find some purpose for them later.”

“Then suppose you look over these here boxes and sacks so I can commence to tie them up. There ain't going to be room here in the kitchen.Time they all pile in for the refreshments.I just going to put these here presents out on the back steps and in the yard.”

The morning sun had risen. The day would be bright and cold.In the kitchen there were rich, sweet odors.A dishpan of coffee was on the stove and iced cakes filled a shelf in the cupboard.

“And none of this comes from white people. All from colored.”

“No，”said Doctor Copeland.“That is not wholly true. Mr.Singer contributed a check for twelve dollars to be used for coal.And I have invited him to be present today.”

“Holy Jesus！”Portia said.“Twelve dollars！”

“I felt that it was proper to ask him. He is not like other people of the Caucasian race.”

“You right，”Portia said.“But I keep thinking about my Willie. I sure do wish he could enjoy this here party today.And I sure do wish I could get a letter from him.It just prey on my mind.But here！Us got to quit this here talking and get ready.It mighty near time for the party to come.”

Time enough remained. Doctor Copeland washed and clothed himself carefully.For a while he tried to rehearse what he would say when the people had all come.But expectation and restlessness would not let him concentrate.Then at ten o'clock the first guests arrived and within half an hour they were all assembled.

“Joyful Christmas gift to you！”said John Roberts, the postman. He moved happily about the crowded room, one shoulder held higher than the other, mopping his face with a white silk handkerchief.

“Many happy returns of the day！”

The front of the house was thronged. Guests were blocked at the door and they formed groups on the front porch and in the yard.There was no pushing or rudeness；the turmoil was orderly.Friends called out to each other and strangers were introduced and clasped hands.Children and young people clotted together and moved back toward the kitchen.

“Christmas gift！”

Doctor Copeland stood in the center of the front room by the tree. He was dizzy.He shook hands and answered salutations with confusion.Personal gifts, some tied elaborately with ribbons and others wrapped in newspapers, were thrust into his hands.He could find no place to put them.The air thickened and voices grew louder.Faces whirled about him so that he could recognize no one.His composure returned to him gradually.He found space to lay aside the presents in his arms.The dizziness lessened, the room cleared.He settled his spectacles and began to look around him.

“Merry Christmas！Merry Christmas！”

There was Marshall Nicolls, the pharmacist, in a long-tailed coat, conversing with his son-in-law who worked on a garbage truck. The preacher from the Most Holy Ascension Church had come.And two deacons from other churches.Highboy, wearing a loud checked suit, moved sociably through the crowd.Husky young dandies bowed to young women in long, bright-colored dresses.There were mothers with children and deliberate old men who spat into gaudy handkerchiefs.The room was warm and noisy.

Mr. Singer stood in the doorway.Many people stared at him.Doctor Copeland could not remember if he had welcomed him or not.The mute stood by himself.His face resembled somewhat a picture of Spinoza.A Jewish face.It was good to see him.

The doors and the windows were open. Draughts blew through the room so that the fire roared.The noises quieted.The seats were all filled and the young people sat in rows on the floor.The hall, the porch, even the yard were crowded with silent guests.The time had come for him to speak—and what was he to say?Panic tightened his throat.The room waited.At a sign from John Roberts all sounds were hushed.

“My People，”began Doctor Copeland blankly. There was a pause.Then suddenly the words came to him.

“This is the nineteenth year that we have gathered together in this room to celebrate Christmas Day. When our people first heard of the birth of Jesus Christ it was a dark time.Our people were sold as slaves in this town on the courthouse square.Since then we have heard and told the story of His life more times than we could remember.So today our story will be a different one.

“One hundred and twenty years ago another man was born in the country that is known as Germany—a country far across the Atlantic Ocean. This man understood as did Jesus.But his thoughts were not concerned with Heaven or the future of the dead.His mission was for the living.For the great masses of human beings who work and suffer and work until they die.For people who take in washing and work as cooks, who pick cotton and work at the hot dye vats of the factories.His mission was for us, and the name of this man was Karl Marx.

“Karl Marx was a wise man. He studied and worked and understood the world around him.He said that the world was divided into two classes, the poor and the rich.For every rich man there were a thousand poor people who worked for this rich man to make him richer.He did not divide the world into Negroes or white people or Chinese—to Karl Marx it seemed that being one of the millions of poor people or one of the few rich was more important to a man than the color of his skin.The life mission of Karl Marx was to make all human beings equal and to divide the great wealth of the world so that there would be no poor or rich and each person would have his share.This is one of the commandments Karl Marx left to us：“From each according to his ability, to each according to his needs.”

A wrinkled, yellow palm waved timidly from the hall.“Were he the Mark in the Bible?”

Doctor Copeland explained. He spelled the two names and cited dates.“Are there any more questions?I wish each one of you to feel free to start or enter into any discussion.”

“I presume Mr. Marx was a Christian church man?”asked the preacher.

“He believed in the holiness of the human spirit.”

“Were he a white man?”

“Yes. But he did not think of himself as a white man.He said，‘I consider nothing human as alien to myself.'He thought of himself as a brother to all people.”

Doctor Copeland paused a moment longer. The faces around him were waiting.

“What is the value of any piece of property, of any merchandise we buy in a store?The value depends only on one thing—and that is the work it took to make or to raise this article. Why does a brick house cost more than a cabbage?Because the work of many men goes into the making of one brick house.There are the people who made the bricks and mortar and the people who cut down the trees to make the planks used for the floor.There are the men who made the building of the brick house possible.There are the men who carried the materials to the ground where the house was to be built.There are the men who made the wheelbarrows and trucks that carried the materials to this place.Then finally there are the workmen who built the house.A brick house involves the labor of many, many people—while any of us can raise a cabbage in his back yard.A brick house costs more than a cabbage because it takes more work to make.So when a man buys this brick house he is paying for the labor that went to make it.But who gets the money—the profit?Not the many men who did the work—but the bosses who control them.And if you study this further you will find that these bosses have bosses above them and those bosses have bosses higher up—so that the real people who control all this work, which makes any article worth money, are very few.Is this clear so far?”

“Us understand！”

But did they?He started all over and retold what he had said. This time there were questions.

“But don't clay for these here bricks cost money?And don't it take money to rent land and raise crops on?”

“That is a good point，”said Doctor Copeland.“Land, clay, timber—those things are called natural resources. Man does not make these natural resources—man only develops them, only uses them for work.Therefore should any one person or group of persons own these things?How can a man own ground and space and sunlight and rain for crops?How can a man say‘this is mine'about those things and refuse to let others share them?Therefore Marx says that these natural resources should belong to everyone, not divided into little pieces but used by all the people according to their ability to work.It is like this.Say a man died and left his mule to his four sons.The sons could not wish to cut up the mule to four parts and each take his share.They would own and work the mule together.That is the way Marx says all of the natural resources should be owned—not by one group of rich people but by all the workers of the world as a whole.

“We in this room have no private properties. Perhaps one or two of us may own the homes we live in, or have a dollar or two set aside—but we own nothing that does not contribute directly toward keeping us alive.All that we own is our bodies.And we sell our bodies every day we live.We sell them when we go out in the morning to our jobs and when we labor all day.We are forced to sell at any price, at any time, for any purpose.We are forced to sell our bodies so that we can eat and live.And the price which is given us for this is only enough so that we will have the strength to labor longer for the profits of others.Today we are not put up on the platforms and sold at the courthouse square.But we are forced to sell our strength, our time, our souls during almost every hour that we live.We have been freed from one kind of slavery only to be delivered into another.Is this freedom?Are we yet free men?”

A deep voice called out from the front yard.“That the real truth！”

“That how things is！”

“And we are not alone in this slavery. There are millions of others throughout the world, of all colors and races and creeds.This we must remember.There are many of our people who hate the poor of the white race, and they hate us.The people in this town living by the river who work in the mills.People who are almost as much in need as we are ourselves.This hatred is a great evil, and no good can ever come from it.We must remember the words of Karl Marx and see the truth according to his teachings.The injustice of need must bring us all together and not separate us.We must remember that we all make the things of this earth of value because of our labor.These main truths from Karl Marx we must keep in our hearts always and not forget.

“But my people！We in this room—we Negroes—have another mission that is for ourselves alone. Within us there is a strong, true purpose, and if we fail in this purpose we will be forever lost.Let us see, then, what is the nature of this special mission.”

Doctor Copeland loosened the collar of his shirt, for in his throat there was a choked feeling. The grievous love he felt within him was too much.He looked around him at the hushed guests.They waited.The groups of people in the yard and on the porch stood with the same quiet attention as did those in the room.A deaf old man leaned forward with his hand to his ear.A woman hushed a fretful baby with a pacifier.Mr.Singer stood attentively in the doorway.Most of the young people sat on the floor.Among them was Lancy Davis.The boy's lips were nervous and pale.He clasped his knees very tightly with his arms, and his young face was sullen.All the eyes in the room watched, and in them there was hunger for truth.

“Today we are to confer the five-dollar award upon the high-school student who wrote the best essay on the topic，‘My Ambition：How I Can Better the Position of the Negro Race in Society.'This year the award goes to Lancy Davis.”Doctor Copeland took an envelope from his pocket.“There is no need for me to tell you that the value of this award is not wholly in the sum of money it represents—but the sacred trust and faith that goes with it.”

Lancy rose awkwardly to his feet. His sullen lips trembled.He bowed and accepted the award.“Do you wish me to read the essay I have written?”

“No，”said Doctor Copeland.“But I wish you to come and talk with me sometime this week.”

“Yes, sir.”The room was quiet again.

“‘I do not wish to be a servant！'That is the desire I have read over and over in these essays. Servant?Only one in a thousand of us is allowed to be a servant.We do not work！We do not serve！”

The laughter in the room was uneasy.

“Listen！One out of five of us labors to build roads, or to take care of the sanitation of this city, or works in a sawmill or on a farm. Another one out of the five is unable to get any work at all.But the other three out of this five—the greatest number of our people?Many of us cook for those who are incompetent to prepare the food that they themselves eat.Many work a lifetime tending flower gardens for the pleasure of one or two people.Many of us polish slick waxed floors of fine houses.Or we drive automobiles for rich people who are too lazy to drive themselves.We spend our lives doing thousands of jobs that are of no real use to anybody.We labor and all of our labor is wasted.Is that service?No, that is slavery.

“We labor, but our labor is wasted. We are not allowed to serve.You students here this morning represent the fortunate few of our race.Most of our people are not allowed to go to school at all.For each one of you there are dozens of young people who can hardly write their names.We are denied the dignity of study and wisdom.

“‘From each according to his ability, to each according to his needs.'All of us here know what it is to suffer for real need. That is a great injustice.But there is one injustice bitterer even than that—to be denied the right to work according to one's ability.To labor a lifetime uselessly.To be denied the chance to serve.It is far better for the profits of our purse to be taken from us than to be robbed of the riches of our minds and souls.

“Some of you young people here this morning may feel the need to be teachers or nurses or leaders of your race. But most of you will be denied.You will have to sell yourselves for a useless purpose in order to keep alive.You will be thrust back and defeated.The young chemist picks cotton.The young writer is unable to learn to read.The teacher is held in useless slavery at some ironing board.We have no representatives in government.We have no vote.In all of this great country we are the most oppressed of all people.We cannot lift up our voices.Our tongues rot in our mouths from lack of use.Our hearts grow empty and lose strength for our purpose.

“People of the Negro race！We bring with us all the riches of the human mind and soul. We offer the most precious of all gifts.And our offerings are held in scorn and contempt.Our gifts are trampled in the mud and made useless.We are put to labor more useless than the work of beasts.Negroes！We must arise and be whole again！We must be free！”

In the room there was a murmur. Hysteria mounted.Doctor Copeland choked and clenched his fists.He felt as though he had swelled up to the size of a giant.The love in him made his chest a dynamo, and he wanted to shout so that his voice could be heard throughout the town.He wanted to fall upon the floor and call out in a giant voice.The room was full of moans and shouts.

“Save us！”

“Mighty Lord！Lead us from this wilderness of death！”

“Hallelujah！Save us, Lord！”

He struggled for the control in him. He struggled and at last the discipline returned.He pushed down the shout in him and sought for the strong, true voice.

“Attention！”he called.“We will save ourselves. But not by prayers of mourning.Not by indolence or strong drink.Not by the pleasures of the body or by ignorance.Not by submission and humbleness.But by pride.By dignity.By becoming hard and strong.We must build strength for our real true purpose.”

He stopped abruptly and held himself very straight.“Each year at this time we illustrate in our small way the first commandment from Karl Marx. Every one of you at this gathering has brought in advance some gift.Many of you have denied yourselves comfort that the needs of others may be lessened.Each of you has given according to his best ability, without thought to the value of the gift he will receive in return.It is natural for us to share with each other.We have long realized that it is more blessed to give than to receive.The words of Karl Marx have always been known in our hearts：‘From each according to his ability, to each according to his needs.'”

Doctor Copeland was silent a long time as though his words were complete. Then he spoke again：

“Our mission is to walk with strength and dignity through the days of our humiliation. Our pride must be strong, for we know the value of the human mind and soul.We must teach our children.We must sacrifice so that they may earn the dignity of study and wisdom.For the time will come.The time will come when the riches in us will not be held in scorn and contempt.The time will come when we will be allowed to serve.When we will labor and our labor will not be wasted.And our mission is to await this time with strength and faith.”

It was finished. Hands were clapped, feet were stamped upon the floor and on the hard winter ground outside.The odor of hot, strong coffee floated from the kitchen.John Roberts took charge of the presents, calling out the names written on the cards.Portia ladled the coffee from the dishpan on the stove while Marshall Nicolls passed slices of cake.Doctor Copeland moved about among the guests, a little crowd always surrounding him.

Someone nagged at his elbow：“He the one your Buddy named for?”He answered yes. Lancy Davis followed him with questions；he answered yes to everything.The joy made him feel like a drunken man.To teach and exhort and explain to his people—and to have them understand.That was the best of all.To speak the truth and be attended.

“Us certainly have had one fine time at this party.”

He stood in the vestibule saying good-bye. Over and over he shook hands.He leaned heavily against the wall and only his eyes moved, for he was tired.

“I certainly do appreciate.”

Mr. Singer was the last to leave.He was a truly good man.He was a white man of intellect and true knowledge.In him there was none of the mean insolence.When all had departed he was the last to remain.He waited and seemed to expect some final word.

Doctor Copeland held his hand to his throat because his larynx was sore.“Teachers，”he said huskily.“That is our greatest need. Leaders.Someone to unite and guide us.”

After the festivity the rooms had a bare, ruined look. The house was cold.Portia was washing the cups in the kitchen.The silver snow on the Christmas tree had been tracked over the floors and two of the ornaments were broken.

He was tired, but the joy and the fever would not let him rest. Beginning with the bedroom, he set to work to put the house in order.On the top of the filing case there was a loose card—the note on Lancy Davis.The words that he would say to him began to form in his mind, and he was restless because he could not speak them now.The boy's sullen face was full of heart and he could not thrust it from his thoughts.He opened the top drawer of the file to replace the card.A, B，C—he thumbed through the letters nervously.Then his eye was fixed on his own name：Copeland, Benedict Mady.

In the folder were several lung X-rays and a short case history. He held an X-ray up to the light.On the upper left lung there was a bright place like a calcified star.And lower down a large clouded spot that duplicated itself in the right lung farther up.Doctor Copeland quickly replaced the X-rays in the folder.Only the brief notes he had written on himself were still in his hand.The words stretched out large and scrawling so that he could hardly read them.“1920—calcif.of lymph glands—very pronounced thickening of hili.Lesions arrested—duties resumed.1937—lesion reopened—X-ray shows—”He could not read the notes.At first he could not make out the words, and then when he read them clearly they made no reason.At the finish there were three words：“Prognosis：Don't know.”

The old black, violent feeling came in him again. He leaned down and wrenched open a drawer at the bottom of the case.A jumbled pile of letters.Notes from the Association for the Advancement of Colored People.A yellowed letter from Daisy.A note from Hamilton asking for a dollar and a half.What was he looking for?His hands rummaged in the drawer and then at last he arose stiffly.

Time wasted. The past hour gone.

Portia peeled potatoes at the kitchen table. She was slumped over and her face was dolorous.

“Hold up your shoulders，”he said angrily.“And cease moping. You mope and drool around until I cannot bear to look on you.”

“I were just thinking about Willie，”she said.“Course the letter is only three days due. But he got no business to worry me like this.He not that kind of a boy.And I got this queer feeling.”

“Have patience, Daughter.”

“I reckon I have to.”

“There are a few calls I must make, but I will be back shortly.”

“O. K.”

“All will be well，”he said.

Most of his joy was gone in the bright, cool noonday sun. The diseases of his patients lay scattered in his mind.An abscessed kidney.Spinal meningitis.Pott's disease.He lifted the crank of the automobile from the back seat.Usually he hailed some passing Negro from the street to crank the car for him.His people were always glad to help and serve.But today he fitted the crank and turned it vigorously himself.He wiped the perspiration from his face with the sleeve of his overcoat and hurried to get beneath the wheel and on his way.

How much that he had said today was understood?How much would be of any value?He recalled the words he had used, and they seemed to fade and lose their strength. The words left unsaid were heavier on his heart.They rolled up to his lips and fretted them.The faces of his suffering people moved in a swelling mass before his eyes.And as he steered the automobile slowly down the street his heart turned with this angry, restless love.

7

The town had not known a winter as cold as this one for years. Frost formed on the windowpanes and whitened the roofs of houses.The winter afternoons glowed with a hazy lemon light and shadows were a delicate blue.A thin coat of ice crusted the puddles in the streets, and it was said on the day after Christmas that only ten miles to the north there was a light fall of snow.

A change came over Singer. Often he went out for the long walks that had occupied him during the months when Antonapoulos was first gone.These walks extended for miles in every direction and covered the whole of the town.He rambled through the dense neighborhoods along the river that were more squalid than ever since the mills had been slack this winter.In many eyes there was a look of somber loneliness.Now that people were forced to be idle, a certain restlessness could be felt.There was a fervid outbreak of new beliefs.A young man who had worked at the dye vats in a mill claimed suddenly that a great holy power had come in him.He said it was his duty to deliver a new set of commandments from the Lord.The young man set up a tabernacle and hundreds of people came each night to roll on the ground and shake each other, for they believed that they were in the presence of something more than human.There was murder, too.A woman who could not make enough to eat believed that a foreman had cheated on her work tokens and she stabbed him in the throat.A family of Negroes moved into the end house on one of the most dismal streets, and this caused so much indignation that the house was burned and the black man beaten by his neighbors.But these were incidents.Nothing had really changed.The strike that was talked about never came off because they could not get together.All was the same as before.Even on the coldest nights the Sunny Dixie Show was open.The people dreamed and fought and slept as much as ever.And by habit they shortened their thoughts so that they would not wander out into the darkness beyond tomorrow.

Singer walked through the scattered odorous parts of town where the Negroes crowded together. There was more gaiety and violence here.Often the fine, sharp smell of gin lingered in the alleys.Warm, sleepy firelight colored the windows.Meetings were held in the churches almost every night.Comfortable little houses set off in plots of brown grass—Singer walked in these parts also.Here the children were huskier and more friendly to strangers.He roamed through the neighborhoods of the rich.There were houses, very grand and old, with white columns and intricate fences of wrought iron.He walked past the big brick houses where automobiles honked in the driveways and where the plumes of smoke rolled lavishly from chimneys.And out to the very edges of the roads that led from the town to general stores where fanners came on Saturday nights and sat around the stove.He wandered often about the four main business blocks that were brightly lighted and then through the black, deserted alleys behind.There was no part of the town that Singer did not know.He watched the yellow squares of light reflect from a thousand windows.The winter nights were beautiful.The sky was a cold azure and the stars were very bright.

Often it happened now that he would be spoken to and stopped during these walks. All kinds of people became acquainted with him.If the person who spoke to him was a stranger, Singer presented his card so that his silence would be understood.He came to be known through all the town.He walked with his shoulders very straight and kept his hands always stuffed down into his pockets.His gray eyes seemed to take in everything around him, and in his face there was still the look of peace that is seen most often in those who are very wise or very sorrowful.He was always glad to stop with anyone who wished his company.For after all he was only walking and going nowhere.

Now it came about that various rumors started in the town concerning the mute. In the years before with Antonapoulos they had walked back and forth to work, but except for this they were always alone together in their rooms.No one had bothered about them then—and if they were observed it was the big Greek on whom attention was focused.The Singer of those years was forgotten.

So the rumors about the mute were rich and varied. The Jews said that he was a Jew.The merchants along the main street claimed he received a large legacy and was a very rich man.It was whispered in one browbeaten textile union that the mute was an organizer for the C.I.O.A lone Turk who had roamed into the town years ago and who languished with his family behind the little store where they sold linens claimed passionately to his wife that the mute was Turkish.He said that when he spoke his language the mute understood.And as he claimed this his voice grew warm and he forgot to squabble with his children and he was full of plans and activity.One old man from the country said that the mute had come from somewhere near his home and that the mute's father had the finest tobacco crop in all the country.All these things were said about him.

Antonapoulos！Within Singer there was always the memory of his friend. At night when he closed his eyes the Greek's face was there in the darkness—round and oily, with a wise and gentle smile.In his dreams they were always together.

It was more than a year now since his friend had gone away. This year seemed neither long nor short.Rather it was removed from the ordinary sense of time—as when one is drunk or half-asleep.Behind each hour there was always his friend.And this buried life with Antonapoulos changed and developed as did the happenings around him.During the first few months he had thought most of the terrible weeks before Antonapoulos was taken away—of the trouble that followed his illness, of the summons for arrest, and the misery in trying to control the whims of his friend.He thought of times in the past when he and Antonapoulos had been unhappy.There was one recollection, far in the past, that came back to him several times.

They never had no friends. Sometimes they would meet other mutes—there were three of them with whom they became acquainted during the ten years.But something always happened.One moved to another state the week after they met him.Another was married and had six children and did not talk with his hands.But it was their relation with the third of these acquaintances that Singer remembered when his friend was gone.

The mute's name was Carl. He was a sallow young man who worked in one of the mills.His eyes were pale yellow and his teeth so brittle and transparent that they seemed pale and yellow also.In his blue overalls that hung limp over his skinny little body he was like a blue-and-yellow rag doll.

They invited him to dinner and arranged to meet him beforehand at the store where Antonapoulos worked. The Greek was still busy when they arrived.He was finishing a batch of caramel fudge in the cooking room at the back of the store.The fudge lay golden and glossy over the long marble-topped table.The air was warm and rich with sweet smells.Antonapoulos seemed pleased to have Carl watch him as he glided the knife down the warm candy and cut it into squares.He offered their new friend a corner of the fudge on the edge of his greased knife, and showed him the trick that he always performed for anyone when he wished to be liked.He pointed to a vat of syrup boiling on the stove and fanned his face and squinted his eyes to show how hot it was.Then he wet his hand in a pot of cold water, plunged it into the boiling syrup, and swiftly put it back into the water again.His eyes bulged and he rolled out his tongue as though he were in great agony.He even wrung his hand and hopped on one foot so that the building shook.Then he smiled suddenly and held out his hand to show that it was a joke and hit Carl on the shoulder.

It was a pale winter evening, and their breath clouded in the cold air as they walked with their arms interlocked down the street. Singer was in the middle and he left them on the sidewalk twice while he went into stores to shop.Carl and Antonapoulos carried the sacks of groceries, and Singer held to their arms tightly and smiled all the way home.Their rooms were cozy and he moved happily about, making conversation with Carl.After the meal the two of them talked while Antonapoulous watched with a slow smile.Often the big Greek would lumber to the closet and pour out drinks of gin.Carl sat by the window, only drinking when Antonapoulos pushed the glass into his face, and then taking solemn little sips.Singer could not ever remember his friend so cordial to a stranger before, and he thought ahead with pleasure to the time when Carl would visit them often.

Midnight had passed when the thing happened that ruined the festive party. Antonapoulos returned from one of his trips to the closet and his face had a glowering look.He sat on his bed and began to stare repeatedly at their new friend with expressions of offense and great disgust.Singer tried to make eager conversation to hide this strange behavior, but the Greek was persistent.Carl huddled in a chair, nursing his bony knees, fascinated and bewildered by the grimaces of the big Greek.His face was flushed and he swallowed timidly.Singer could ignore the situation no longer, so at last he asked Antonapoulos if his stomach pained him or if he perhaps felt bad and wished to go to sleep.Antonapoulos shook his head.He pointed to Carl and began to make all the gestures of obscenity which he knew.The disgust on his face was terrible to see.Carl was small with fear.At last the big Greek ground his teeth and rose from his chair.Hurriedly Carl picked up his cap and left the room.Singer followed him down the stairs.He did not know how to explain his friend to this stranger.Carl stood hunched in the doorway downstairs, limp, with his peaked cap pulled down over his face.At last they shook hands and Carl went away.

Antonapoulos let him know that while they were not noticing, their guest had gone into the closet and drunk up all the gin. No amount of persuasion could convince Antonapoulos that it was he himself who had finished the bottle.The big Greek sat up in bed and his round face was dismal and reproachful.Large tears trickled slowly down to the neck of his undershirt and he could not be comforted.At last he went to sleep, but Singer was awake in the dark a long time.They never saw Carl again.

Then years later there was the time Antonapoulos took the rent money from the vase on the mantelpiece and spent it all on the slot machines. And the summer afternoon Antonapoulos went downstairs naked to get the paper.He suffered so from the summer heat.They bought an electric refrigerator on the installment plan, and Antonapoulos would suck the cubes of ice constantly and even let a few of them melt in bed with him as he slept.And the time Antonapoulos got drunk and threw a bowl of macaroni in his face.

Those ugly memories wove through his thoughts during the first months like bad threads through a carpet. And then they were gone.All the times that they had been unhappy were forgotten.For as the year went on his thoughts of his friend spiraled deeper until he dwelt only with the Antonapoulos whom he alone could know.

This was the friend to whom he told all that was in his heart. This was the Antonapoulos who no one knew was wise but him.As the year passed his friend seemed to grow larger in his mind, and his face looked out in a very grave and subtle way from the darkness at night.The memories of his friend changed in his mind so that he remembered nothing that was wrong or foolish—only the wise and good.

He saw Antonapoulos sitting in a large chair before him. He sat tranquil and unmoving.His round face was inscrutable.His mouth was wise and smiling.And his eyes were profound.He watched the things that were said to him.And in his wisdom he understood.

This was the Antonapoulos who now was always in his thoughts. This was the friend to whom he wanted to tell things that had come about.For something had happened in this year.He had been left in an alien land.Alone.He had opened his eyes and around him there was much he could not understand.He was bewildered.

He watched the words shape on their lips.

We Negroes want a chance to be free at last. And freedom is only the right to contribute.We want to serve and to share, to labor and in turn consume that which is due to us.But you are the only white man I have ever encountered who realizes this terrible need of my people.

You see, Mister Singer?I got this music in me all the time. I got to be a real musician.Maybe I don't know anything now, but I will when I'm twenty.See, Mister Singer?And then I mean to travel in a foreign country where there's snow.

Let's finish up the bottle. I want a small one.For we were thinking of freedom.That's the word like a worm in my brain.Yes?No?How much?How little?The word is a signal for piracy and theft and cunning.We'll be free and the smartest will then be able to enslave the others.But！But there is another meaning to the word.Of all words this one is the most dangerous.We who know must be wary.The word makes us feel good—in fact the word is a great ideal.But it's with this ideal that the spiders spin their ugliest webs for us.

The last one rubbed his nose. He did not come often and he did not say much.He asked questions.

The four people had been coming to his rooms now for more than seven months. They never came together—always alone.And invariably he met them at the door with a cordial smile.The want for Antonapoulos was always with him—just as it had been the first months after his friend had gone—and it was better to be with any person than to be too long alone.It was like the time years ago when he had made a pledge to Antonapoulos（and even written it on a paper and tacked it on the wall above his bed）—a pledge that he would give up cigarettes, beer, and meat for one month.The first days had been very bad.He could not rest or be still.He visited Antonapoulos so much at the fruit store that Charles Parker was unpleasant to him.When he had finished all the engraving on hand he would dawdle around the front of the store with the watchmaker and the salesgirl or wander out to some soda fountain to drink a Coca-Cola.In those days being near any stranger was better than thinking alone about the cigarettes and beer and meat that he wanted.

At first he had not understood the four people at all. They talked and they talked—and as the months went on they talked more and more.He became so used to their lips that he understood each word they said.And then after a while he knew what each one of them would say before he began, because the meaning was always the same.

His hands were a torment to him. They would not rest.They twitched in his sleep, and sometimes he awoke to find them shaping the words in his dreams before his face.He did not like to look at his hands or to think about them.They were slender and brown and very strong.In the years before he had always tended them with care.In the winter he used oil to prevent chapping, and he kept the cuticles pushed down and his nails always filed to the shape of his finger-tips.He had loved to wash and tend his hands.But now he only scrubbed them roughly with a brush two times a day and stuffed them back into his pockets.

When he walked up and down the floor of his room he would crack the joints of his fingers and jerk at them until they ached. Or he would strike the palm of one hand with the fist of the other.And then sometimes when he was alone and his thoughts were with his friend his hands would begin to shape the words before he knew about it.Then when he realized he was like a man caught talking aloud to himself.It was almost as though he had done some moral wrong.The shame and the sorrow mixed together and he doubled his hands and put them behind him.But they would not let him rest.

Singer stood in the street before the house where he and Antonapoulos had lived. The late afternoon was smoky and gray.In the west there were streaks of cold yellow and rose.A ragged winter sparrow flew in patterns against the smoky sky and at last came to light on a gable of the house.The street was deserted.

His eyes were fixed on a window on the right side of the second story. This was their front room, and behind was the big kitchen where Antonapoulos had cooked all their meals.Through the lighted window he watched a woman move back and forth across the room.She was large and vague against the light and she wore an apron.A man sat with the evening newspaper in his hand.A child with a slice of bread came to the window and pressed his nose against the pane.Singer saw the room just as he had left it—with the large bed for Antonapoulos and the iron cot for himself, the big overstuffed sofa and the camp chair.The broken sugar bowl used for an ash tray, the damp spot on the ceiling where the roof leaked, the laundry box in the corner.On late afternoons like this there would be no light in the kitchen except the glow from the oil-burners of the big stove.Antonapoulos always turned the wicks so that only a ragged fringe of gold and blue could be seen inside each burner.The room was warm and full of the good smells from the supper.Antonapoulos tasted the dishes with his wooden spoon and they drank glasses of red wine.On the linoleum rug before the stove the flames from the burners made luminous reflections—five little golden lanterns.As the milky twilight grew darker these little lanterns were more intense, so that when at last the night had come they burned with vivid purity.Supper was always ready by that time and they would turn on the light and draw their chairs to the table.

Singer looked down at the dark front door. He thought of them going out together in the morning and coming home at night.There was the broken place in the pavement where Antonapoulos had stumbled once and hurt his elbow.There was the mailbox where their bill from the light company came each month.He could feel the warm touch of his friend's arm against his fingers.

The street was dark now. He looked up at the window once more and he saw the strange woman and the man and the child in a group together.The emptiness spread in him.All was gone.Antonapoulos was away；he was not here to remember.The thoughts of his friend were somewhere else.Singer shut his eyes and tried to think of the asylum and the room that Antonapoulos was in tonight.He remembered the narrow white beds and the old men playing slapjack in the corner.He held his eyes shut tight, but that room would not become clear in his mind.The emptiness was very deep inside him, and after a while he glanced up at the window once more and started down the dark sidewalk where they had walked together so many times.

It was Saturday night. The main street was thick with people.Shivering Negroes in overalls loitered before the windows of the ten-cent store.Families stood in line before the ticket box of the movie and young boys and girls stared at the posters on display outside.The traffic from the automobiles was so dangerous that he had to wait a long time before crossing the street.

He passed the fruit store. The fruits were beautiful inside the windows—bananas, oranges, alligator pears, bright little cumquats, and even a few pineapples.But Charles Parker waited on a customer inside.The face of Charles Parker was very ugly to him.Several times when Charles Parker was away he had entered the store and stood around a long while.He had even gone to the kitchen in the back where Antonapoulos made the candies.But he never went into the store while Charles Parker was inside.They had both taken care to avoid each other since that day when Antonapoulos left on the bus.When they met in the street they always turned away without nodding.Once when he had wanted to send his friend a jar of his favorite tupelo honey he had ordered it from Charles Parker by mail so as not to be obliged to meet him.

Singer stood before the window and watched the cousin of his friend wait on a group of customers. Business was always good on Saturday night.Antonapoulos sometimes had to work as late as ten o'clock.The big automatic popcorn popper was near the door.A clerk shoved in a measure of kernels and the corn whirled inside the case like giant flakes of snow.The smell from the store was warm and familiar.Peanut hulls were trampled on the floor.

Singer passed on down the street. He had to weave his way carefully in the crowds to keep from being jostled.The streets were strung with red and green electric lights because of the holidays.People stood in laughing groups with their arms about each other.Young fathers nursed cold and crying babies on their shoulders.A Salvation Army girl in her red-and-blue bonnet tinkled a bell on the corner, and when she looked at Singer he felt obliged to drop a coin into the pot beside her.There were beggars, both Negro and white, who held out caps or crusty hands.The neon advertisements cast an orange glow on the faces of the crowd.

He reached the corner where he and Antonapoulos had once seen a mad dog on an August afternoon. Then he passed the room above the Army and Navy Store where Antonapoulos had had his picture taken every pay-day.He carried many of the photographs in his pocket now.He turned west toward the river.Once they had taken a picnic lunch and crossed the bridge and eaten in a field on his other side.

Singer walked along the main street for about an hour. In all the crowd he seemed the only one alone.At last he took out his watch and turned toward the house where he lived.Perhaps one of the people would come this evening to his room.He hoped so.

He mailed Antonapoulos a large box of presents for Christmas. Also he presented gifts to each of the four people and to Mrs.Kelly.For all of them together he had bought a radio and put it on the table by the window.Doctor Copeland did not notice the radio.Biff Brannon noticed it immediately and raised his eyebrows.Jake Blount kept it turned on all the time he was there, at the same station, and as he talked he seemed to be shouting above the music, for the veins stood out on his forehead.Mick Kelly did not understand when she saw the radio.Her face was very red and she asked him over and over if it was really his and whether she could listen.She worked with a dial for several minutes before she got it to the place that suited her.She sat leaning forward in her chair with her hands on her knees, her mouth open and a pulse beating very fast in her temple.She seemed to listen all over to whatever it was she heard.She sat there the whole afternoon, and when she grinned at him once her eyes were wet and she rubbed them with her fists.She asked him if she could come in and listen sometimes when he was at work and he nodded yes.So for the next few days whenever he opened the door he found her by the radio.Her hand raked through her short rumpled hair and there was a look in her face he had never seen before.

One night soon after Christmas all four of the people chanced to visit him at the same time. This had never happened before.Singer moved about the room with smiles and refreshments and did his best in the way of politeness to make his guests comfortable.But something was wrong.

Doctor Copeland would not sit down. He stood in the doorway, hat in hand, and only bowed coldly to the others.They looked at him as though they wondered why he was there.Jake Blount opened the beers he had brought with him and the foam spilled down on his shirtfront.Mick Kelly listened to the music from the radio.Biff Brannon sat on the bed, his knees crossed, his eyes scanning the group before him and then becoming narrow and fixed.

Singer was bewildered. Always each of them had so much to say.Yet now that they were together they were silent.When they came in he had expected an outburst of some kind.In a vague way he had expected this to be the end of something.But in the room there was only a feeling of strain.His hands worked nervously as though they were pulling things unseen from the air and binding them together.

Jake Blount stood beside Doctor Copeland.“I know your face. We run into each other once before—on the steps outside.”

Doctor Copeland moved his tongue precisely as though he clipped out his words with scissors.“I was not aware that we were acquainted，”he said. Then his stiff body seemed to shrink.He stepped back until he was just outside the threshold of the room.

Biff Brannon smoked his cigarette composedly. The smoke lay in thin layers across the room.He turned to Mick and when he looked at her a blush reddened his face.He half-closed his eyes and in a moment his face was bloodless once more.“And how are you getting on with your business now?”

“What business?”Mick asked suspiciously.

“Just the business of living，”he said.“School—and so forth.”

“O. K.，I reckon，”she said.

Each one of them looked at Singer as though in expectation. He was puzzled.He offered refreshments and smiled.

Jake rubbed his lips with the palm of his hand. He left off trying to make conversation with Doctor Copeland and sat down on the bed beside Biff.“You know who it is that used to write those bloody warnings in red chalk on the fences and walls around the mills?”

“No，”Biff said.“What bloody warnings?”

“Mostly from the Old Testament. I been wondering about that for a long time.”

Each person addressed his words mainly to the mute. Their thoughts seemed to converge in him as the spokes of a wheel lead to the center hub.

“The cold has been very unusual，”Biff said finally.“The other day I was looking through some old records and I found that in the year　1919　the thermometer got down to ten degrees Fahrenheit. It was only sixteen degrees this morning, and that's the coldest since the big freeze that year.”

“There were icicles hanging off the roof of the coal house this morning，”Mick said.

“We didn't take in enough money last week to meet the payroll，”Jake said.

They discussed the weather some more. Each one seemed to be waiting for the others to go.Then on an impulse they all rose to leave at the same time.Doctor Copeland went first and the others followed him immediately.When they were gone Singer stood alone in the room, and as he did not understand the situation he wanted to forget it.He decided to write to Antonapoulos that night.

The fact that Antonapoulos could not read did not prevent Singer from writing to him. He had always known that his friend was unable to make out the meaning of words on paper, but as the months went by he began to imagine that perhaps he had been mistaken, that perhaps Antonapoulos only kept his knowledge of letters a secret from everyone.Also, it was possible there might be a deaf-mute at the asylum who could read his letters and then explain them to his friend.He thought of several justifications for his letters, for he always felt a great need to write to his friend when he was bewildered or sad.Once written, however, these letters were never mailed.He cut out the comic strips from the morning and evening papers and sent them to his friend each Sunday.And every month he mailed a postal money order.But the long letters he wrote to Antonapoulos accumulated in his pockets until he would destroy them.

When the four people had gone, Singer slipped on his warm gray overcoat and his gray felt hat and left his room. He always wrote his letters at the store.Also, he had promised to deliver a certain piece of work the next morning, and he wanted to finish it now so that there would be no question of delay.The night was sharp and frosty.The moon was full and rimmed with a golden light.The rooftops were black against the starlit sky.As he walked he thought of ways to begin his letter, but he had already reached the store before the first sentence was clear in his mind.He let himself into the dark store with his key and switched on the front lights.

He worked at the very end of the store. A cloth curtain separated his place from the rest of the shop so that it was like a small private room.Besides his workbench and chair there was a heavy safe in the corner, a lavatory with a greenish mirror, and shelves full of boxes and worn-out clocks.Singer rolled up the top of his bench and removed from its felt case the silver platter he had promised to have ready.Although the store was cold he took off his coat and turned up the blue-striped cuffs of his shirt so that they would not get in his way.

For a long time he worked at the monogram in the center of the platter. With delicate, concentrated strokes he guided the scriver on the silver.As he worked his eyes had a curiously penetrating look of hunger.He was thinking of his letter to his friend Antonapoulos.Midnight had passed before the work was finished.When he put the platter away his forehead was damp with excitement.He cleared his bench and began to write.He loved to shape words with a pen on paper and he formed the letters with as much care as if the paper had been a plate of silver.

My Only Friend：

I see from our magazine that the Society meets this year at a convention in Macon.They will have speakers and a four-

course banquet.I imagine it.Remember we always planned to attend one of the conventions but we never did.I wish now that we had.I wish we were going to this one and I have imagined how it would be.But of course I could never go without you.They will come from many states and they will all be full of words and long dreams from the heart.There is also to be a special service at one of the churches and some kind of a contest with a gold medal for the prize.I write that I imagine all this.I both do and do not.My hands have been still so long that it is difficult to remember how it is.And when I imagine the convention I think of all the guests being like you, my Friend.

I stood before our home the other day.Other people live in it now.Do you remember the big oak tree in front?The branches were cut back so as not to interfere with the telephone wires and the tree died.The limbs are rotten and there is a hollow place in the trunk.Also, the cat here at the store（the one you used to stroke and fondle）ate something poisonous and died.It was very sad.

Singer held the pen poised above the paper. He sat for a long while, erect and tense, without continuing the letter.Then he stood up and lighted himself a cigarette.The room was cold and the air had a sour stale odor—the mixed smells of kerosene and silver polish and tobacco.He put on his overcoat and muffler and began writing again with slow determination.

You remember the four people I told you about when I was there.I drew their pictures for you, the black man, the young girl, the one with the mustache, and the man who owns the New York Café.There are some things I should like to tell you about them but how to put them in words I am not sure.

They are all very busy people.In fact they are so busy that it will be hard for you to picture them.I do not mean that they work at their jobs all day and night but that they have much business in their minds always that does not let them rest.They come up to my room and talk to me until I do not understand how a person can open and shut his or her mouth so much without being weary.（However, the New York Café　owner is different—he is not just like the others.He has a very black beard so that he has to shave twice daily, and he owns one of these electric razors.He watches.The others all have something they hate.And they all have something they love more than eating or sleeping or wine or friendly company.That is why they are always so busy.）

The one with the mustache I think is crazy.Sometimes he speaks his words very clear like my teacher long ago at the school.Other times he speaks such a language that I cannot follow.Sometimes he is dressed in a plain suit, and the next time he will be black with dirt and smelling bad and in the overalls he wears to work.He will shake his fist and say ugly drunken words that I would not wish you to know about.He thinks he and I have a secret together but I do not know what it is.And let me write you something hard to believe.He can drink three pints of Happy Days whiskey and still talk and walk on his feet and not wish for the bed.You will not believe this but it is true.

I rent my room from the girl’s mother for$16　per month.The girl used to dress in short trousers like a boy but now she wears a blue skirt and a blouse.She is not yet a young lady.I like her to come and see me.She comes all the time now that I have a radio for them.She likes music.I wish I knew what it is she hears.She knows I am deaf but she thinks I know about music.

The black man is sick with consumption but there is not

a good hospital for him to go to here because he is black.He is a doctor and he works more than anyone I have ever seen.He does not talk like a black man at all.Other Negroes I find it hard to understand because their tongues do not move enough for the words.This black man frightens me sometimes.His eyes are hot and bright.He asked me to a party and I went.He has many books.However, he does not own any mystery books.He does not drink or eat meat or attend the movies.

Yah Freedom and pirates.Yah Capital and Democrats, says the ugly one with the mustache.Then he contradicts himself and says, Freedom is the greatest of all ideals.I just got to get a chance to write this music in me and be a musician.I got to have a chance says the girl.We are not allowed to serve, says the black Doctor.That is the Godlike need for my people.Aha, says the owner of the New York Café.He is a thoughtful one.

That is the way they talk when they come to my room.Those words in their heart do not let them rest, so they are always very busy.Then you would think when they are together they would be like those of the Society who meet at the convention in Macon this week.But that is not so.They all came to my room at the same time today.They sat like they were from different cities.They were even rude, and you know how I have always said that to be rude and not attend to the feelings of others is wrong.So it was like that.I do not understand, so I write it to you because I think you will understand.I have queer feelings.But I have written of this matter enough and I know you axe weary of it.I am also.

It has been five months and twenty-one days now.All of that time I have been alone without you.The only thing I can imagine is when I will be with you again.If I cannot come to you soon I do not know what.

Singer put his head down on the bench and rested. The smell and the feel of the slick wood against his cheek reminded him of his schooldays.His eyes closed and he felt sick.There was only the face of Antonapoulos in his mind, and his longing for his friend was so sharp that he held his breath.After some time Singer sat up and reached for his pen.

The gift I ordered for you did not come in time for the Christmas box.I expect it shortly.I believe you will like it and be amused.I think of us always and remember everything.I long for the food you used to make.At the New York Café　it is much worse than it used to be.I found a cooked fly in my soup not long ago.It was mixed with the vegetables and the noodles like letters.But that is nothing.The way I need you is a loneliness I cannot bear.Soon I will come again.My vacation is not due for six months more but I think I can arrange it before then.I think I will have to.I am not meant to be alone and without you who understand.

Always，

JOHN SINGER

It was two o'clock in the morning before he was home again. The big, crowded house was in darkness, but he felt his way carefully up three flights of stairs and did not stumble.He took from his pockets the cards he carried about with him, his watch, and his fountain pen.Then he folded his clothes neatly over the back of his chair.His gray-flannel pajamas were warm and soft.Almost as soon as he pulled the blankets to his chin he was asleep.

Out of the blackness of sleep a dream formed. There were dull yellow lanterns lighting up a dark flight of stone steps.Antonapoulos kneeled at the top of these steps.He was naked and he fumbled with something that he held above his head and gazed at it as though in prayer.He himself knelt half-way down the steps.He was naked and cold and he could not take his eyes from Antonapoulos and the thing he held above him.Behind him on the ground he felt the one with the mustache and the girl and the black man and the last one.They knelt naked and he felt their eyes on him.And behind them there were uncounted crowds of kneeling people in the darkness.His own hands were huge windmills and he stared fascinated at the unknown thing that Antonapoulos held.The yellow lanterns swayed to and fro in the darkness and all else was motionless.Then suddenly there was a ferment.In the upheaval the steps collapsed and he felt himself falling downward.He awoke with a jerk.The early light whitened the window.He felt afraid.

Such a long time had passed that something might have happened to his friend. Because Antonapoulos did not write to him he would not know.Perhaps his friend had fallen and hurt himself.He felt such an urge to be with him once more that he would arrange it at any cost—and immediately.

In the post-office that morning he found a notice in his box that a package had come for him. It was the gift he had ordered for Christmas that did not arrive in time.The gift was a very fine one.He had bought it on the installment plan to be paid for over a period of two years.The gift was a moving-picture machine for private use, with a half-dozen of the Mickey Mouse and Popeye comedies that Antonapoulos enjoyed.

Singer was the last to reach the store that morning. He handed the jeweler for whom he worked a formal written request for leave on Friday and Saturday.And although there were four weddings on hand that week, the jeweler nodded that he could go.

He did not let anyone know of the trip beforehand, but on leaving he tacked a note to his door saying that he would be absent for several days because of business. He traveled at night, and the train reached the place of his destination just as the red winter dawn was breaking.

In the afternoon, a little before time for the visiting hour, he went out to the asylum. His arms were loaded with the parts of the moving-picture machine and the basket of fruit he carried his friend.He went immediately to the ward where he had visited Antonapoulos before.

The corridor, the door, the rows of beds were just as he remembered them. He stood at the threshold and looked eagerly for his friend.But he saw at once that though all the chairs were occupied, Antonapoulos was not there.

Singer put down his packages and wrote at the bottom of one of his cards，“Where is Spiros Antonapoulos?”A nurse came into the room and he handed her the card. She did not understand.She shook her head and raised her shoulders.He went out into the corridor and handed the card to everyone he met.Nobody knew.There was such a panic in him that he began motioning with his hands.At last he met an interne in a white coat.He plucked at the interne's elbow and gave him the card.The interne read it carefully and then guided him through several halls.They came to a small room where a young woman sat at a desk before some papers.She read the card and then looked through some files in a drawer.

Tears of nervousness and fear swam in Singer's eyes. The young woman began deliberately to write on a pad of paper, and he could not restrain himself from twisting around to see immediately what was being written about his friend.

Mr.Antonapoulos has been transferred to the infirmary.He is ill with nephritis.I will have someone show you the way.

On the way through the corridors he stopped to pick up the packages he had left at the door of the ward. The basket of fruit had been stolen, but the other boxes were intact.He followed the interne out of the building and across a plot of grass to the infirmary.

Antonapoulos！When they reached the proper ward he saw him at the first glance. His bed was placed in the middle of the room and he was sitting propped with pillows.He wore a scarlet dressing-gown and green silk pajamas and a turquoise ring.His skin was a pale yellow color, his eyes very dreamy and dark.His black hair was touched at the temples with silver.He was knitting.His fat fingers worked with the long ivory needles very slowly.At first he did not see his friend.Then when Singer stood before him he smiled serenely, without surprise, and held out his jeweled hand.

A feeling of shyness and restraint such as he had never known before came over Singer. He sat down by the bed and folded his hands on the edge of the counterpane.His eyes did not leave the face of his friend and he was deathly pale.The splendor of his friend's raiment startled him.On various occasions he had sent him each article of the outfit, but he had not imagined how they would look when all combined.Antonapoulos was more enormous than he had remembered.The great pulpy folds of his abdomen showed beneath his silk pajamas.His head was immense against the white pillow.The placid composure of his face was so profound that he seemed hardly to be aware that Singer was with him.

Singer raised his hands timidly and began to speak. His strong, skilled fingers shaped the signs with loving precision.He spoke of the cold and of the long months alone.He mentioned old memories, the cat that had died, the store, the place where he lived.At each pause Antonapoulos nodded graciously.He spoke of the four people and the long visits to his room.The eyes of his friend were moist and dark, and in them he saw the little rectangled pictures of himself that he had watched a thousand times.The warm blood flowed back to his face and his hands quickened.He spoke at length of the black man and the one with the jerking mustache and the girl.The designs of his hands shaped faster and faster.Antonapoulos nodded with slow gravity.Eagerly Singer leaned closer and he breathed with long, deep breaths and in his eyes there were bright tears.

Then suddenly Antonapoulos made a slow circle in the air with his plump forefinger. His finger circled toward Singer and at last he poked his friend in the stomach.The big Greek's smile grew very broad and he stuck out his fat, pink tongue.Singer laughed and his hands shaped the words with wild speed.His shoulders shook with laughter and his head hung backward.Why he laughed he did not know.Antonapoulos rolled his eyes.Singer continued to laugh riotously until his breath was gone and his fingers trembled.He grasped the arm of his friend and tried to steady himself.His laughs came slow and painfully like hiccoughs.

Antonapoulos was the first to compose himself. His fat little feet had untucked the cover at the bottom of the bed.His smile faded and he kicked contemptuously at the blanket.Singer hastened to put things right, but Antonapoulos frowned and held up his finger regally to a nurse who was passing through the ward.When she had straightened the bed to his liking the big Greek inclined his head so deliberately that the gesture seemed one of benediction rather than a simple nod of thanks.Then he turned gravely to his friend again.

As Singer talked he did not realize how the time had passed. Only when a nurse brought Antonapoulos his supper on a tray did he realize that it was late.The lights in the ward were turned on and outside the windows it was almost dark.The other patients had trays of supper before them also.They had put down their work（some of them wove baskets, others did leatherwork or knitted）and they were eating listlessly.Besides Antonapoulos they all seemed very sick and colorless.Most of them needed a haircut and they wore seedy gray nightshirts slit down the back.They stared at the two mutes with wonder.

Antonapoulos lifted the cover from his dish and inspected the food carefully. There was fish and some vegetables.He picked up the fish and held it to the light in the palm of his hand for a thorough examination.Then he ate with relish.During supper he began to point out the various people in the room.He pointed to one man in the corner and made faces of disgust.The man snarled at him.He pointed to a young boy and smiled and nodded and waved his plump hand.Singer was too happy to feel embarrassment.He picked up the packages from the floor and laid them on the bed to distract his friend.Antonapoulos took off the wrappings, but the machine did not interest him at all.He turned back to his supper.

Singer handed the nurse a note explaining about the movie. She called an interne and then they brought in a doctor.As the three of them consulted they looked curiously at Singer.The news reached the patients and they propped up on their elbows excitedly.Only Antonapoulos was not disturbed.

Singer had practiced with the movie beforehand. He set up the screen so that it could be watched by all the patients.Then he worked with the projector and the film.The nurse took out the supper trays and the lights in the ward were turned off.A Mickey Mouse comedy flashed on the screen.

Singer watched his friend. At first Antonapoulos was startled.He heaved himself up for a better view and would have risen from the bed if the nurse had not restrained him.Then he watched with a beaming smile.Singer could see the other patients calling out to each other and laughing.Nurses and orderlies came in from the hall and the whole ward was in commotion.When the Mickey Mouse was finished Singer put on a Popeye film.Then at the conclusion of this film he felt that the entertainment had lasted long enough for the first time.He switched on the light and the ward settled down again.As the interne put the machine under his friend's bed he saw Antonapoulos slyly cut his eyes across the ward to be certain that each person realized that the machine was his.

Singer began to talk with his hands again. He knew that he would soon be asked to leave, but the thoughts he had stored in his mind were too big to be said in a short time.He talked with frantic haste.In the ward there was an old man whose head shook with palsy and who picked feebly at his eyebrows.He envied the old man because he lived with Antonapoulos day after day.Singer would have exchanged places with him joyfully.

His friend fumbled for something in his bosom. It was the little brass cross that he had always worn.The dirty string had been replaced by a red ribbon.Singer thought of the dream and he told that, also, to his friend.In his haste the signs sometimes became blurred and he had to shake his hands and begin all over.Antonapoulos watched him with his dark, drowsy eyes.Sitting motionless in his bright, rich garments he seemed like some wise king from a legend.

The interne in charge of the ward allowed Singer to stay for an hour past the visiting time. Then at last he held out his thin, hairy wrist and showed him his watch.The patients were settled for sleep.Singer's hand faltered.He grasped his friend by the arm and looked intently into his eyes as he used to do each morning when they parted for work.Finally Singer backed himself out of the room.At the doorway his hands signed a broken farewell and then clenched into fists.

During the moonlit January nights Singer continued to walk about the streets of the town each evening when he was not engaged. The rumors about him grew bolder.An old Negro woman told hundreds of people that he knew the ways of spirits come back from the dead.A certain piece-worker claimed that he had worked with the mute at another mill somewhere else in the state—and the tales he told were unique.The rich thought that he was rich and the poor considered him a poor man like themselves.And as there was no way to disprove these rumors they grew marvelous and very real.Each man described the mute as he wished him to be.

8

Why?

The question flowed through Biff always, unnoticed, like the blood in his veins. He thought of people and of objects and of ideas and the question was in him.Midnight, the dark morning, noon.Hitler and the rumors of war.The price of loin of pork and the tax on beer.Especially he meditated on the puzzle of the mute.Why, for instance, did Singer go away on the train and, when he was asked where he had been, pretend that he did not understand the question?And why did everyone persist in thinking the mute was exactly as they wanted him to be—when most likely it was all a very queer mistake?Singer sat at the middle table three times a day.He ate what was put before him—except cabbage and oysters.In the battling tumult of voices he alone was silent.He liked best little green soft butter beans and he stacked them in a neat pile on the prongs of his fork.And sopped their gravy with his biscuits.

Biff thought also of death. A curious incident occurred.One day while rummaging through the bathroom closet he found a bottle of Agua Florida that he had overlooked when taking Lucile the rest of Alice's cosmetics.Meditatively he held the bottle of perfume in his hands.It was four months now since her death—and each month seemed as long and full of leisure as a year.He seldom thought of her.

Biff uncorked the bottle. He stood shirtless before the mirror and dabbled some of the perfume on his dark, hairy armpits.The scent made him stiffen.He exchanged a deadly secret glance with himself in the mirror and stood motionless.He was stunned by the memories brought to him with the perfume, not because of their clarity, but because they gathered together the whole long span of years and were complete.Biff rubbed his nose and looked sideways at himself.The boundary of death.He felt in him each minute that he had lived with her.And now their life together was whole as only the past can be whole.Abruptly Biff turned away.

The bedroom was done over. His entirely now.Before it had been tacky and flossy and drab.There were always stockings and pink rayon knickers with holes in them hung on a string across the room to dry.The iron bed had been flaked and rusty, decked with soiled lace boudoir pillows.A bony mouser from downstairs would arch its back and rub mournfully against the slop jar.

All of this he had changed. He traded the iron bed for a studio couch.There was a thick red rug on the floor, and he had bought a beautiful cloth of Chinese blue to hang on the side of the wall where the cracks were worst.He had unsealed the fireplace and kept it laid with pine logs.Over the mantel was a small photograph of Baby and a colored picture of a little boy in velvet holding a ball in his hands.A glassed case in the corner held the curios he had collected—specimens of butterflies, a rare arrowhead, a curious rock shaped like a human profile.Blue-silk cushions were on the studio couch, and he had borrowed Lucile's sewing-machine to make deep red curtains for the windows.He loved the room.It was both luxurious and sedate.On the table there was a little Japanese pagoda with glass pendants that tinkled with strange musical tones in a draught.

In this room nothing reminded him of her. But often he would uncork the bottle of Agua Florida and touch the stopper to the lobes of his ears or to his wrists.The smell mingled with his slow ruminations.The sense of the past grew in him.Memories built themselves with almost architectural order.In a box where he stored souvenirs he came across old pictures taken before their marriage.Alice sitting in a field of daisies.Alice with him in a canoe on the river.Also among the souvenirs there was a large bone hairpin that had belonged to his mother.As a little boy he had loved to watch her comb and knot her long black hair.He had thought that hairpins were curved as they were to copy the shape of a lady and he would sometimes play with them like dolls.At that time he had a cigar box full of scraps.He loved the feel and colors of beautiful cloth and he would sit with his scraps for hours under the kitchen table.But when he was six his mother took the scraps away from him.She was a tall, strong woman with a sense of duty like a man.She had loved him best.Even now he sometimes dreamed of her.And her worn gold wedding ring stayed on his finger always.

Along with the Agua Florida he found in the closet a bottle of lemon rinse Alice had always used for her hair. One day he tried it on himself.The lemon made his dark, white-streaked hair seem fluffy and thick.He liked it.He discarded the oil he had used to guard against baldness and rinsed with the lemon preparation regularly.Certain whims that he had ridiculed in Alice were now his own.Why?

Every morning Louis, the colored boy downstairs, brought him a cup of coffee to drink in bed. Often he sat propped on the pillows for an hour before he got up and dressed.He smoked a cigar and watched the patterns the sunlight made on the wall.Deep in meditation he ran his forefinger between his long, crooked toes.He remembered.

Then from noon until five in the morning he worked downstairs. And all day Sunday.The business was losing money.There were many slack hours.Still at meal-times the place was usually full and he saw hundreds of acquaintances every day as he stood guard behind the cash register.

“What do you stand and think about all the time?”Jake Blount asked him.“You look like a Jew in Germany.”

“I am an eighth part Jew，”Biff said.“My Mother's grandfather was a Jew from Amsterdam. But all the rest of my folks that I know about were Scotch-Irish.”

It was Sunday morning. Customers lolled at the tables and there were the smell of tobacco and the rustle of newspaper.Some men in a corner booth shot dice, but the game was a quiet one.

“Where's Singer?”Biff asked.“Won't you be going up to his place this morning?”

Blount's face turned dark and sullen. He jerked his head forward.Had they quarreled—but how could a dummy quarrel?No, for this had happened before.Blount hung around sometimes and acted as though he were having an argument with himself.But pretty soon he would go—he always did—and the two of them would come in together, Blount talking.

“You live a fine life. Just standing behind a cash register.Just standing with your hand open.”

Biff did not take offense. He leaned his weight on his elbows and narrowed his eyes.“Let's me and you have a serious talk.What is it you want anyway?”

Blount smacked his hands down on the counter. They were warm and meaty and rough.“Beer.And one of them kittle packages of cheese crackers with peanut butter in the inside.”

“That's not what I meant，”Biff said.“But we'll come around to it later.”

The man was a puzzle. He was always changing.He still drank like a crazy fish, but liquor did not drag him down as it did some men.The rims of his eyes were often red, and he had a nervous trick of looking back startled over his shoulder.His head was heavy and huge on his thin neck.He was the sort of fellow that kids laughed at and dogs wanted to bite.Yet when he was laughed at it cut him to the quick—he got rough and loud like a sort of clown.And he was always suspecting that somebody was laughing.

Biff shook his head thoughtfully.“Come，”he said.“What makes you stick with that show?You can find something better than that. I could give you a part-time job here.”

“Christamighty！I wouldn't park myself behind that cash box if you was to give me the whole damn place, lock, stock, and barrel.”

There he was. It was irritating.He could never have friends or even get along with people.

“Talk sense，”Biff said.“Be serious.”

A customer had come up with his check and he made change. The place was still quiet.Blount was restless.Biff felt him drawing away.He wanted to hold him.He reached for two A-l cigars on the shelf behind the counter and offered Blount a smoke.Warily his mind dismissed one question after another, and then finally he asked：

“If you could choose the time in history you could have lived, what era would you choose?”

Blount licked his mustache with his broad, wet tongue.“If you had to choose between being a stiff and never asking another question, which would you take?”

“Sure enough，”Biff insisted.“Think it over.”

He cocked his head to one side and peered down over his long nose. This was a matter he liked to hear others talk about.Ancient Greece was his.Walking in sandals on the edge of the blue Aegean.The loose robes girdled at the waist.Children.The marble baths and the contemplations in the temples.

“Maybe with the Incas. In Peru.”

Biff's eyes scanned over him, stripping him naked. He saw Blount burned a rich, red brown by the sun, his face smooth and hairless, with a bracelet of gold and precious stones on his forearm.When he closed his eyes the man was a good Inca.But when he looked at him again the picture fell away.It was the nervous mustache that did not belong to his face, the way he jerked his shoulder, the Adam's apple on his thin neck, the bagginess of his trousers.And it was more than that.

“Or maybe around　1775.”

“That was a good time to be living，”Biff agreed.

Blount shuffled his feet self-consciously. His face was rough and unhappy.He was ready to leave.Biff was alert to detain him.“Tell me—why did you ever come to this town anyway?”He knew immediately that the question had not been a politic one and he was disappointed with himself.Yet it was queer how the man could land up in a place like this.

“It's the God's truth I don't know.”

They stood quietly for a moment, both leaning on the counter. The game of dice in the corner was finished.The first dinner order, a Long Island duck special, had been served to the fellow who managed the A.and P.store.The radio was turned half-way between a church sermon and a swing band.

Blount leaned over suddenly and smelled Biff's face.

“Perfume?”

“Shaving lotion，”Biff said composedly.

He could not keep Blount longer. The fellow was ready to go.He would come in with Singer later.It was always like this.He wanted to draw Blount out completely so that he could understand certain questions concerning him.But Blount would never really talk—only to the mute.It was a most peculiar thing.

“Thanks for the cigar，”Blount said.“See you later.”

“So long.”

Biff watched Blount walk to the door with his rolling, sailor-like gait. Then he took up the duties before him.He looked over the display in the window.The day's menu had been pasted on the glass and a special dinner with all the trimmings was laid out to attract customers.It looked bad.Right nasty.The gravy from the duck had run into the cranberry sauce and a fly, was stuck in the dessert.

“Hey, Louis！”he called.“Take this stuff out of the window. And bring me that red pottery bowl and some fruit.”

He arranged the fruits with an eye for color and design. At last the decoration pleased him.He visited the kitchen and had a talk with the cook.He lifted the lids of the pots and sniffed the food inside, but without heart for the matter.Alice always had done this part.He disliked it.His nose sharpened when he saw the greasy sink with its scum of food bits at the bottom.He wrote down the menus and the orders for the next day.He was glad to leave the kitchen and take his stand by the cash register again.

Lucile and Baby came for Sunday dinner. The little kid was not so good now.The bandage was still on her head and the doctor said it could not come off until next month.The binding of gauze in place of the yellow curls made her head look naked.

“Say hello to Uncle Biff, Hon，”Lucile prompted.

Baby bridled fretfully.“Hello to Unca Biff Hon，”she gassed.

She put up a struggle when Lucile tried to take off her Sunday coat.“Now you just behave yourself，”Lucile kept saying.“You got to take it off or you'll catch pneumonia when we go out again. Now you just behave yourself.”

Biff took the situation in charge. He soothed Baby with a ball of candy gum and eased the coat from her shoulders.Her dress had lost its set in the struggle with Lucile.He straightened it so that the yoke was in line across her chest.He retied her sash and crushed the bow to just the right shape with his fingers.Then he patted Baby on her little behind.“We got some strawberry ice cream today，”he said.

“Bartholomew, you'd make a mighty good mother.”

“Thanks，”Biff said.“That's a compliment”

“We just been to Sunday School and church. Baby, say the verse from the Bible you learned for your Uncle Biff.”

The kid hung back and pouted.“Jesus wept，”she said finally. The scorn that she put in the two words made it sound like a terrible thing.

“Want to see Louis?”Biff asked.“He's back in the kitchen.”

“I wanna see Willie. I wanna hear Willie play the harp.”

“Now, Baby, you're just trying yourself，”Lucile said impatiently.“You know good and well that Willie's not here. Willie was sent off to the penitentiary.”

“But Louis，”Biff said.“He can play the harp, too. Go tell him to get the ice cream ready and play you a tune.”

Baby went toward the kitchen, dragging one heel on the floor. Lucile laid her hat on the counter.There were tears in her eyes.“You know I always said this：If a child is kept clean and well cared for and pretty then that child will usually be sweet and smart.But if a child's dirty and ugly then you can't expect anything much.What I'm trying to get at is that Baby is so shamed over losing her hair and that bandage on her head that it just seems like it makes her cut the buck all the time.She won't practice her elocution—she won't do a thing.She feels so bad I just can’t manage her.”

“If you'd quit picking with her so much she'd be all right.”

At last he settled them in a booth by the window. Lucile had a special and there was a breast of chicken cut up fine, cream of wheat, and carrots for Baby.She played with her food and spilled milk on her little frock.He sat with them until the rush started.Then he had to be on his feet to keep things going smoothly.

People eating. The wide-open mouths with the food pushed in.What was it?The line he had read not long ago.Life was only a matter of intake and alimentation and reproduction.The place was crowded.There was a swing band on the radio.

Then the two he was waiting for came in. Singer entered the door first, very straight and swank in his tailored Sunday suit.Blount followed along just behind his elbow.There was something about the way they walked that struck him.They sat at their table, and Blount talked and ate with gusto while Singer watched politely.When the meal was finished they stopped by the cash register for a few minutes.Then as they went out he noticed again there was something about their walking together that made him pause and question himself.What could it be?The suddenness with which the memory opened up deep down in his mind was a shock.The big deaf-mute moron whom Singer used to walk with sometimes on the way to work.The sloppy Greek who made candy for Charles Parker.The Greek always walked ahead and Singer followed.He had never noticed them much because they never came into the place.But why had he not remembered this?Of all times he had wondered about the mute to neglect such an angle.See everything in the landscape except the three waltzing elephants.But did it matter after all?

Biff narrowed his eyes. How Singer had been before was not important.The thing that mattered was the way Blount and Mick made of him a sort of home-made God.Owing to the fact he was a mute they were able to give him all the qualities they wanted him to have.Yes.But how could such a strange thing come about?And why?

A one-armed man came in and Biff treated him to a whiskey on the house. But he did not feel like talking to anyone.Sunday dinner was a family meal.Men who drank beer by themselves on weeknights brought their wives and little kids with them on Sunday.The highchair they kept in the back was often needed.It was two-thirty and though many tables were occupied the meal was almost over.Biff had been on his feet for the past four hours and was tired.He used to stand for fourteen or sixteen hours and not notice any effects at all.But now he had aged.Considerably.There was no doubt about it.Or maybe matured was the word.Not aged—certainly not—yet.The waves of sound in the room swelled and subsided against his ears.Matured.His eyes smarted and it was as though some fever in him made everything too bright and sharp.

He called to one of the waitresses：“Take over for me will you, please?I'm going out.”

The street was empty because of Sunday. The sun shone bright and clear, without warmth.Biff held the collar of his coat close to his neck.Alone in the street he felt out of pocket.The wind blew cold from the river.He should turn back and stay in the restaurant where he belonged.He had no business going to the place where he was headed.For the past four Sundays he had done this.He had walked in the neighborhood where he might see Mick.And there was something about it that was—not quite right.Yes.Wrong.

He walked slowly down the sidewalk opposite the house where she lived. Last Sunday she had been reading the funny papers on the front steps.But this time as he glanced swiftly toward the house he saw she was not there.Biff tilted the brim of his felt hat down over his eyes.Perhaps she would come into the place later.Often on Sunday after supper she came for a hot cocoa and stopped for a while at the table where Singer was sitting.On Sunday she wore a different outfit from the blue skirt and sweater she wore on other days.Her Sunday dress was wine-colored silk with a dingy lace collar.Once she had had on stockings—with runs in them.Always he wanted to set her up to something, to give to her.And not only a sundae or some sweet to eat—but something real.That was all he wanted for himself—to give to her.Biff's mouth hardened.He had done nothing wrong but in him he felt a strange guilt.Why?The dark guilt in all men, unreckoned and without a name.

On the way home Biff found a penny lying half concealed by rubbish in the gutter. Thriftily he picked it up, cleaned the coin with his handkerchief, and dropped it into the black pocket purse he carried.It was four o'clock when he reached the restaurant.Business was stagnant.There was not a single customer in the place.

Business picked up around five. The boy he had recently hired to work part time showed up early.The boy's name was Harry Minowitz.He lived in the same neighborhood with Mick and Baby.Eleven applicants had answered the ad in the paper, but Harry seemed to be best bet.He was well developed for his age, and neat.Biff had noticed the boy's teeth while talking to him during the interview.Teeth were always a good indication.His were large and very clean and white.Harry wore glasses, but that would not matter in the work.His mother made ten dollars a week sewing for a tailor down the street, and Harry was an only child.

“Well，”Biff said.“You've been with me a week, Harry. Think you're going to like it?”

“Sure, sir. Sure I like it.”

Biff turned the ring on his finger.“Let's see. What time do you get off from school?”

“Three o'clock, sir.”

“Well, that gives you a couple of hours for study and recreation. Then here from six to ten.Does that leave you enough time for plenty of sleep?”

“Plenty. I don't need near that much.”

“You need about nine and a half hours at your age, son. Pure, wholesome sleep.”

He felt suddenly embarrassed. Maybe Harry would think it was none of his business.Which it wasn't anyway.He started to turn aside and then thought of something.

“You go to Vocational?”

Harry nodded and rubbed his glasses on his shirtsleeve.

“Let's see. I know a lot of girls and boys there.Alva Richards—I know his father.And Maggie Henry.And a kid named Mick Kelly—”He felt as though his ears had caught afire.He knew himself to be a fool.He wanted to turn and walk away and yet he only stood there, smiling and mashing his nose with his thumb.“You know her?”he asked faintly.

“Sure, I live right next door to her. But in school I'm a senior while she's a freshman.”

Biff stored this meager information neatly in his mind to be thought over later when he was alone.“Business will be quiet here for a while，”he said hurriedly.“I'll leave it with you. By now you know how to handle things.Just watch any customers drinking beer and remember how many they've drunk so you won't have to ask them and depend on what they say.Take your time making change and keep track of what goes on.”

Biff shut himself in his room downstairs. This was the place where he kept his files.The room had only one small window and looked out on the side alley, and the air was musty and cold.Huge stacks of newspapers rose up to the ceiling.A home-made filing case covered one wall.Near the door there was an old-fashioned rocking-chair and a small table laid with a pair of shears, a dictionary, and a mandolin.Because of the piles of newspaper it was impossible to take more than two steps in any direction.Biff rocked himself in the chair and languidly plucked the strings of the mandolin.His eyes closed and he began to sing in a doleful voice：

I went to the animal fair.

The birds and the beasts were there，

And the old baboon by the light of the moon

Was combing his auburn hair.

He finished with a chord from the strings and the last sounds shivered to silence in the cold air.

To adopt a couple of little children. A boy and a girl.About three or four years old so they would always feel like he was their own father.Their Dad.Our Father.The little girl like Mick（or Baby?）at that age.Round cheeks and gray eyes and flaxen hair.And the clothes he would make for her—pink crêpe de Chine frocks with dainty smocking at the yoke and sleeves.Silk socks and white buckskin shoes.And a little red-velvet coat and cap and muff for winter.The boy was dark and black-haired.The little boy walked behind him and copied the things he did.In the summer the three of them would go to a cottage on the Gulf and he would dress the children in their sun suits and guide them carefully into the green, shallow waves.And then they would bloom as he grew old.Our Father.And they would come to him with questions and he would answer them.

Why not?

Biff took up his mandolin again.“Tum-ti-tim-ti-tee, ti-tee, the wedd-ing of the painted doll.”The mandolin mocked the refrain. He sang through all the verses and wagged his foot to the time.Then he played“K-K-K-Katie，”and“Love's Old Sweet Song.”These pieces were like the Agua Florida in the way they made him remember.Everything.Through the first year when he was happy and when she seemed happy even too.And when the bed came down with them twice in three months.And he didn't know that all the time her brain was busy with how she could save a nickel or squeeze out an extra dime.And then him with Rio and the girls at her place.Gyp and Madeline and Lou.And then later when suddenly he lost it.When he could lie with a woman no longer.Motherogod！So that at first it seemed everything was gone.

Lucile always understood the whole set-up. She knew the kind of woman Alice was.Maybe she knew about him, too.Lucile would urge them to get a divorce.And she did all a person could to try to straighten out their messes.

Biff winced suddenly. He jerked his hands from the strings of the mandolin so that a phrase of music was chopped off.He sat tense in his chair.Then suddenly he laughed quietly to himself.What had made him come across this?Ah, Lordy Lordy Lord！It was the day of his twenty-ninth birthday, and Lucile had asked him to drop by her apartment when he finished with an appointment at the dentist's.He expected from this some little remembrance—a plate of cherry tarts or a good shirt.She met him at the door and blindfolded his eyes before he entered.Then she said she would be back in a second.In the silent room he listened to her footsteps and when she had reached the kitchen he broke wind.He stood in the room with his eyes blindfolded and pooted.Then all at once he knew with horror he was not alone.There was a titter and soon great rolling whoops of laughter deafened him.At that minute Lucile came back and undid his eyes.She held a caramel cake on a platter.The room was full of people.Leroy and that bunch and Alice, of course.He wanted to crawl up the wall.He stood there with his bare face hanging out, burning hot all over.They kidded him and the next hour was almost as bad as the death of his mother—the way he took it.Later that night he drank a quart of whiskey.And for weeks after—Motherogod！

Biff chuckled coldly. He plucked a few chords on his mandolin and started a rollicking cowboy song.His voice was a mellow tenor and he closed his eyes as he sang.The room was almost dark.The damp chill penetrated to his bones so that his legs ached with rheumatism.

At last he put away his mandolin and rocked slowly in the darkness. Death.Sometimes he could almost feel it in the room with him.He rocked to and fro in the chair.What did he understand?Nothing.Where was he headed?Nowhere.What did he want?To know.What?A meaning.Why?A riddle.

Broken pictures lay like a scattered jigsaw puzzle in his head. Alice soaping in the bathtub.Mussolini's mug.Mick pulling the baby in a wagon.A roast turkey on display.Blount's mouth.The face of Singer.He felt himself waiting.The room was completely dark.From the kitchen he could hear Louis singing.

Biff stood up and touched the arm of his chair to still its rocking. When he opened the door the hall outside was very warm and bright.He remembered that perhaps Mick would come.He straightened his clothes and smoothed back his hair.A warmth and liveliness returned to him.The restaurant was in a hubbub.Beer rounds and Sunday supper had begun.He smiled genially to young Harry and settled himself behind the cash register.He took in the room with a glance like a lasso.The place was crowded and humming with noise.The bowl of fruit in the window was a genteel, artistic display.He watched the door and continued to examine the room with a practiced eye.He was alert and intently waiting.Singer came finally and wrote with his silver pencil that he wanted only soup and whiskey as he had a cold.But Mick did not come.

9

She never even had a nickel to herself any more. They were that poor.Money was the main thing.All the time it was money, money, money.They had to pay through the nose for Baby Wilson's private room and private nurse.But even that was just one bill.By the time one thing was paid for something else always would crop up.They owed around two hundred dollars that had to be paid right away.They lost the house.Their Dad got a hundred dollars out of the deal and let the bank take over the mortgage.Then he borrowed another fifty dollars and Mister Singer went on the note with him.Afterward they had to worry about rent every month instead of taxes.They were mighty near as poor as factory folks.Only nobody could look down on them.

Bill had a job in a bottling plant and made ten dollars a week. Hazel worked as a helper in a beauty parlor for eight dollars.Etta sold tickets at a movie for five dollars.Each of them paid half of what they earned for their keep.Then the house had six boarders at five dollars a head.And Mister Singer, who paid his rent very prompt.With what their Dad picked up it all came to about two hundred dollars a month—and out of that they had to feed the six boarders pretty good and feed the family and pay rent for the whole house and keep up the payments on the furniture.

George and her didn't get any lunch money now. She had to stop the music lessons.Portia saved the leftovers from the dinner for her and George to eat after school.All the time they had their meals in the kitchen.Whether Bill and Hazel and Etta sat with the boarders or ate in the kitchen depended on how much food there was.In the kitchen they had grits and grease and side meat and coffee for breakfast.For supper they had the same thing along with whatever could be spared from the dining-room.The big kids griped whenever they had to eat in the kitchen.And sometimes she and George were downright hungry for two or three days.

But this was in the outside room. It had nothing to do with music and foreign countries and the plans she made.The winter was cold.Frost was on the windowpanes.At night the fire in the living-room crackled very warm.All the family sat by the fire with the boarders, so she had the middle bedroom to herself.She wore two sweaters and a pair of Bill's outgrown corduroy pants.Excitement kept her warm.She would bring out her private box from under the bed and sit on the floor to work.

In the big box there were the pictures she had painted at the government free art class. She had taken them out of Bill's room.Also in the box she kept three mystery books her Dad had given her, a compact, a box of watch parts, a rhinestone necklace, a hammer, and some notebooks.One notebook was marked on the top with red crayon—PRIVATE.KEEP OUT.PRIVATE.—and tied with a string.

She had worked on music in this notebook all the winter. She quit studying school lessons at night so she could have more time to spend on music.Mostly she had written just little tunes—songs without any words and without even any bass notes to them.They were very short.But even if the tunes were only half a page long she gave them names and drew her initials underneath them.Nothing in this book was a real piece or a composition.They were just songs in her mind she wanted to remember.She named them how they reminded her—“Africa”and“A Big Fight”and“The Snowstorm.”

She couldn't write the music just like it sounded in her mind. She had to thin it down to only a few notes；otherwise she got too mixed up to go further.There was so much she didn't know about how to write music.But maybe after she learned how to write these simple tunes fairly quick she could begin to put down the whole music in her mind.

In January she began a certain very wonderful piece called“This Thing I Want, I Know Not What.”It was a beautiful and marvelous song—very slow and soft. At first she had started to write a poem along with it, but she couldn't think of ideas to fit the music.Also it was hard to get a word for the third line to rhyme with what.This new song made her feel sad and excited and happy all at once.Music beautiful as this was hard to work on.Any song was hard to write.Something she could hum in two minutes meant a whole week's work before it was down in the notebook—after she had figured up the scale and the time and every note.

She had to concentrate hard and sing it many times. Her voice was always hoarse.Her Dad said this was because she had bawled so much when she was a baby.Her Dad would have to get up and walk with her every night when she was Ralph's age.The only thing would hush her, he always said, was for him to beat the coal scuttle with a poker and sing“Dixie.”

She lay on her stomach on the cold floor and thought. Later on—when she was twenty—she would be a great world-famous composer.She would have a whole symphony orchestra and conduct all of her music herself.She would stand up on the platform in front of the big crowds of people.To conduct the orchestra she would wear either a real man's evening suit or else a red dress spangled with rhinestones.The curtains of the stage would be red velvet and M.K.would be printed on them in gold.Mister Singer would be there, and afterward they would go out and eat fried chicken.He would admire her and count her as his very best friend.George would bring up big wreaths of flowers to the stage.It would be in New York City or else in a foreign country.Famous people would point at her—Carole Lombard and Arturo Toscanini and Admiral Byrd.

And she could play the Beethoven symphony any time she wanted to. It was a queer thing about this music she had heard last autumn.The symphony stayed inside her always and grew little by little.The reason was this：the whole symphony was in her mind.It had to be.She had heard every note, and somewhere in the back of her mind the whole of the music was still there just as it had been played.But she could do nothing to bring it all out again.Except wait and be ready for the times when suddenly a new part came to her.Wait for it to grow like leaves grow slowly on the branches of a spring oak tree.

In the inside room, along with music, there was Mister Singer. Every afternoon as soon as she finished playing on the piano in the gym she walked down the main street past the store where he worked.From the front window she couldn't see Mister Singer.He worked in the back, behind a curtain.But she looked at the store where he stayed every day and saw the people he knew.Then every night she waited on the front porch for him to come home.Sometimes she followed him upstairs.She sat on the bed and watched him put away his hat and undo the button on his collar and brush his hair.For some reason it was like they had a secret together.Or like they waited to tell each other things that had never been said before.

He was the only person in the inside room. A long time ago there had been others.She thought back and remembered how it was before he came.She remembered a girl way back in the sixth grade named Celeste.This girl had straight blonde hair and a turned-up nose and freckles.She wore a red-wool jumper with a white blouse.She walked pigeon-toed.Every day she brought an orange for little recess and a blue tin box of lunch for big recess.Other kids would gobble the food they had brought at little recess and then were hungry later—but not Celeste.She pulled off the crusts of her sandwiches and ate only the soft middle part.Always she had a stuffed hardboiled egg and she would hold it in her hand, mashing the yellow with her thumb so that the print of her finger was left there.

Celeste never talked to her and she never talked to Celeste. Although that was what she wanted more than anything else.At night she would lie awake and think about Celeste.She would plan that they were best friends and think about the time when Celeste could come home with her to eat supper and spend the night.But that never happened.The way she felt about Celeste would never let her go up and make friends with her like she would any other person.After a year Celeste moved to another part of town and went to another school.

Then there was a boy called Buck. He was big and had pimples on his face.When she stood by him in line to march in at eight-thirty he smelled bad—like his britches needed airing.Buck did a nose dive at the principal once and was suspended.When he laughed he lifted his upper lip and shook all over.She thought about him like she had thought about Celeste.Then there was the lady who sold lottery tickets for a turkey raffle.And Miss Anglin, who taught the seventh grade.And Carole Lombard in the movies.All of them.

But with Mister Singer there was a difference. The way she felt about him came on her slowly, and she could not think back and realize just how it happened.The other people had been ordinary, but Mister Singer was not.The first day he rang the doorbell to ask about a room she had looked a long time into his face.She had opened the door and read over the card he handed her.Then she called her Mama and went back in the kitchen to tell Portia and Bubber about him.She followed him and her Mama up the stairs and watched him poke the mattress on the bed and roll up the shades to see if they worked.The day he moved she sat on the front porch banisters and watched him get out of the ten-cent taxi with his suitcase and his chessboard.Then later she listened to him thump around in his room and imagined about him.The rest came in a gradual way.So that now there was this secret feeling between them.She talked to him more than she had ever talked to a person before.And if he could have talked he would have told her many things.It was like he was some kind of a great teacher, only because he was a mute he did not teach.In the bed at night she planned about how she was an orphan and lived with Mister Singer—just the two of them in a foreign house where in the winter it would snow.Maybe in a little Switzerland town with the high glaciers and the mountains all around.Where rocks were on top of all the houses and the roofs were steep and pointed.Or in France where the people carried home bread from the store without its being wrapped.Or in the foreign country of Norway by the gray winter ocean.

In the morning the first thing she would think of him. Along with music.When she put on her dress she wondered where she would see him that day.She used some of Etta's perfume or a drop of vanilla so that if she met him in the hall she would smell good.She went to school late so she could see him come down the stairs on his way to work.And in the afternoon and night she never left the house if he was there.

Each new thing she learned about him was important. He kept his toothbrush and toothpaste in a glass on his table.So instead of leaving her toothbrush on the bathroom shelf she kept it in a glass, also.He didn't like cabbage.Harry, who worked for Mister Brannon, mentioned that to her.Now she couldn't eat cabbage either.When she learned new facts about him, or when she said something to him and he wrote a few words with his silver pencil, she had to be off by herself for a long time to think it over.When she was with him the main thought in her mind was to store up everything so that later she could live it over and remember.

But in the inside room with music and Mister Singer was not all. Many things happened in the outside room.She fell down the stairs and broke off one of her front teeth.Miss Minner gave her two bad cards in English.She lost a quarter in a vacant lot, and although she and George hunted for three days they never found it.

This happened：

One afternoon she was studying for an English test out on the back steps. Harry began to chop wood over on his side of the fence and she hollered to him.He came and diagrammed a few sentences for her.His eyes were quick behind his hornrimmed glasses.After he explained the English to her he stood up and jerked his hands in and out the pockets of his lumberjack.Harry was always full of energy, nervous, and he had to be talking or doing something every minute.

“You see, there's just two things nowadays，”he said.

He liked to surprise people and sometimes she didn't know how to answer him.

“It's the truth, there's just two things ahead nowadays.”

“What?”

“Militant Democracy or Fascism.”

“Don't you like Republicans?”

“Shucks，”Harry said.“That's not what I mean.”

He had explained all about the Fascists one afternoon. He told how the Nazis made little Jew children get down on their hands and knees and eat grass from the ground.He told about how he planned to assassinate Hitler.He had it all worked out thoroughly.He told about how there wasn't any justice or freedom in Fascism.He said the newspapers wrote deliberate lies and people didn't know what was going on in the world.The Nazis were terrible—everybody knew that.She plotted with him to kill Hitler.It would be better to have four or five people in the conspiracy so that if one missed him the others could bump him off just the same.And even if they died they would all be heroes.To be a hero was almost like being a great musician.

“Either one or the other. And although I don't believe in war I'm ready to fight for what I know is right.”

“Me too，”she said.“I'd like to fight the Fascists. I could dress up like a boy and nobody could ever tell.Cut my hair off and all.”

It was a bright winter afternoon. The sky was blue-green and the branches of the oak trees in the back yard were black and bare against this color.The sun was warm.The day made her feel full of energy.Music was in her mind.Just to be doing something she picked up a ten-penny nail and drove it into the steps with a few good wallops.Their Dad heard the sound of the hammer and came out in his bathrobe to stand around awhile.Under the tree there were two carpenter's horses, and little Ralph was busy putting a rock on top of one and then carrying it over to the other one.Back and forth.He walked with his hands out to balance himself.He was bowlegged and his diapers dragged down to his knees.George was shooting marbles.Because he needed a haircut his face looked thin.Some of his permanent teeth had already come—but they were small and blue like he had been eating blackberries.He drew a line for taw and lay on his stomach to take aim for the first hole.When their Dad went back to his watch work he carried Ralph with him.And after a while George went off into the alley by himself.Since he shot Baby he wouldn't buddy with a single person.

“I got to go，”Harry said.“I got to be at work before six.”

“You like it at the café?Do you get good things to eat free?”

“Sure. And all kinds of folks come in the place.I like it better than any job I ever had.It pays more.”

“I hate Mister Brannon，”Mick said. It was true that even though he never said anything mean to her he always spoke in a rough, funny way.He must have known all along about the pack of chewing-gum she and George swiped that time.And then why would he ask her how her business was coming along—like he did up in Mister Singer's room?Maybe he thought they took things regular.And they didn't.They certainly did not.Only once a little water-color set from the ten-cent store.And a nickel pencil-sharpener.

“I can't stand Mister Brarmon.”

“He's all right，”Harry said.“Sometimes he seems a right queer kind of person, but he's not crabby. When you get to know him.”

“One thing I've thought about，”Mick said.“A boy has a better advantage like that than a girl. I mean a boy can usually get some part-time job that don't take him out of school and leaves him time for other things.But there's not jobs like that for girls.When a girl wants a job she has to quit school and work full time.I'd sure like to earn a couple of bucks a week like you do, but there's just not any way.”

Harry sat on the steps and untied his shoestrings. He pulled at them until one broke.“A man comes to the café　named Mr.Blount.Mr.Jake Blount.I like to listen to him.I learn a lot from the things he says when he drinks beer.He’s given me some new ideas.”

“I know him good. He comes here every Sunday.”

Harry unlaced his shoe and pulled the broken string to even lengths so he could tie it in a bow again.“Listen”—he rubbed his glasses on his lumberjack in a nervous way—“You needn't mention to him what I said. I mean I doubt if he would remember me.He don't talk to me.He just talks to Mr.Singer.He might think it was funny if you—you know what I mean.”

“O. K.”She read between the words that he had a crush on Mister Blount and she knew how he felt.“I wouldn't mention it.”

Dark came on. The moon, white like milk, showed in the blue sky and the air was cold.She could hear Ralph and George and Portia in the kitchen.The fire in the stove made the kitchen window a warm orange.There was the smell of smoke and supper.

“You know this is something I never have told anybody，”he said.“I hate to realize about it myself.”

“What?”

“You remember when you first began to read the newspapers and think about the things you read?”

“Sure.”

“I used to be a Fascist. I used to think I was.It was this way.You know all the pictures of the people our age in Europe marching and singing songs and keeping step together.I used to think that was wonderful.All of them pledged to each other and with one leader.All of them with the same ideals and marching in step together.I didn't worry much about what was happening to the Jewish minorities because I didn't want to think about it.And because at the time I didn't want to think like I was Jewish.You see, I didn't know.I just looked at the pictures and read what it said underneath and didn't understand.I never knew what an awful thing it was.I thought I was a Fascist.Of course later on I found out different.”

His voice was bitter against himself and kept changing from a man's voice to a young boy's.

“Well, you didn't realize then—”she said.

“It was a terrible transgression. A moral wrong.”

That was the way he was. Everything was either very right or very wrong—with no middle way.It was wrong for anyone under twenty to touch beer or wine or smoke a cigarette.It was a terrible sin for a person to cheat on a test, but not a sin to copy homework.It was a moral wrong for girls to wear lipstick or sun-backed dresses.It was a terrible sin to buy anything with a German or Japanese label, no matter if it cost only a nickel.

She remembered Harry back to the time when they were kids. Once his eyes got crossed and stayed crossed for a year.He would sit out on his front steps with his hands between his knees and watch everything.Very quiet and cross-eyed.He skipped two grades in grammar school and when he was eleven he was ready for Vocational.But at Vocational when they read about the Jew in Ivanhoe the other kids would look around at Harry and he would come home and cry.So his mother took him out of school.He stayed out for a whole year.He grew taller and very fat.Every time she climbed the fence she would see him making himself something to eat in his kitchen.They both played around on the block, and sometimes they would wrestle.When she was a kid she liked to fight with boys—not real fights but just in play.She used a combination jujitsu and boxing.Sometimes he got her down and sometimes she got him.Harry never was very rough with anybody.When little kids ever broke any toy they would come to him and he always took the time to fix it.He could fix anything.The ladies on the block got him to fix their electric lights or sewing-machines when something went wrong.Then when he was thirteen he started back at Vocational and began to study hard.He threw papers and worked on Saturdays and read.For a long time she didn't see much of him—until after that party she gave.He was very changed.

“Like this，”Harry said.“It used to be I had some big　　　ambition for myself all the time. A great engineer or a great doctor or lawyer.But now I don't have it that way.All I can think about is what happens in the world now.About Fascism and the terrible things in Europe—and on the other hand Democracy.I mean I can't think and work on what I mean to be in life because I think too much about this other.I dream about killing Hitler every night And I wake up in the dark very thirsty and scared of something—I don't know what.”

She looked at Harry's face and a deep, serious feeling made her sad. His hair hung over his forehead.His upper lip was thin and tight, but the lower one was thick and it trembled.Harry didn't look old enough to be fifteen.With the darkness a cold wind came.The wind sang up in the oak trees on the block and banged the blinds against the side of the house.Down the street Mrs.Wells was calling Sucker home.The dark late afternoon made the sadness heavy inside her.I want a piano—I want to take music lessons, she said to herself.She looked at Harry and he was lacing his thin fingers together in different shapes.There was a warm boy smell about him.

What was it made her act like she suddenly did?Maybe it was remembering the times when they were younger. Maybe it was because the sadness made her feel queer.But anyway all of a sudden she gave Harry a push that nearly knocked him off the steps.“S.O.B.to your Grandmother，”she hollered to him.Then she ran.That was what kids used to say in the neighborhood when they picked a fight.Harry stood up and looked surprised.He settled his glasses on his nose and watched her for a second.Then he ran back to the alley.

The cold air made her strong as Samson. When she laughed there was a short, quick echo.She butted Harry with her shoulder and he got a holt on her.They wrestled hard and laughed.She was the tallest but his hands were strong.He didn't fight good enough and she got him on the ground.Then suddenly he stopped moving and she stopped too.His breathing was warm on her neck and he was very still.She felt his ribs against her knees and his hard breathing as she sat on him.They got up together.They did not laugh any more and the alley was very quiet.As they walked across the dark back yard for some reason she felt funny.There was nothing to feel queer about, but suddenly it had just happened.She gave him a little push and he pushed her back.Then she laughed again and felt all right.

“So long，”Harry said. He was too old to climb the fence, so he ran through the side alley to the front of his house.

“Gosh it's hot！”she said.“I could smother in here.”

Portia was warming her supper in the stove. Ralph banged his spoon on his high-chair tray.George's dirty little hand pushed up his grits with a piece of bread and his eyes were squinted in a faraway look.She helped herself to white meat and gravy and grits and a few raisins and mixed them up together on her plate.She ate three bites of them.She ate until all the grits were gone but still she wasn't full.

She had thought about Mister Singer all the day, and as soon as supper was over she went upstairs. But when she reached the third floor she saw that his door was open and his room dark.This gave her an empty feeling.

Downstairs she couldn't sit still and study for the English test. It was like she was so strong she couldn't sit on a chair in a room the same as other people.It was like she could knock down all the walls of the house and then march through the streets big as a giant.

Finally she got out her private box from under the bed. She lay on her stomach and looked over the notebook.There were about twenty songs now, but she didn't feel satisfied with them.If she could write a symphony！For a whole orchestra—how did you write that?Sometimes several instruments played one note, so the staff would have to be very large.She drew five lines across a big sheet of test paper—the lines about an inch apart.When a note was for violin or'cello or flute she would write the name of the instrument to show.And when they all played the same note together she would draw a circle around them.At the top of the page she wrote SYMPHONY in large letters.And under that MICK KELLY.Then she couldn't go any further.

If she could only have music lessons！

If only she could have a real piano！

A long time passed before she could get started. The tunes were in her mind but she couldn't figure how to write them.It looked like this was the hardest play in the world.But she kept on figuring until Etta and Hazel came into the room and got into bed and said she had to turn the light off because it was eleven o'clock.

10

For six weeks Portia had waited to hear from William. Every evening she would come to the house and ask Doctor Copeland the same question：“You seen anybody who gotten a letter from Willie yet?”And every night he was obliged to tell her that he had heard nothing.

At last she asked the question no more. She would come into the hall and look at him without a word.She drank.Her blouse was often half unbuttoned and her shoestrings loose.

February came. The weather turned milder, then hot.The sun glared down with hard brilliance.Birds sang in the bare trees and children played out of doors barefoot and naked to the waist.The nights were torrid as in midsummer.Then after a few days winter was upon the town again.The mild skies darkened.A chill rain fell and the air turned dank and bitterly cold.In the town the Negroes suffered badly.Supplies of fuel had been exhausted and there was a struggle everywhere for warmth.An epidemic of pneumonia raged through the wet, narrow streets, and for a week Doctor Copeland slept at odd hours, fully clothed.Still no word came from William.Portia had written four times and Doctor Copeland twice.

During most of the day and night he had no time to think. But occasionally he found a chance to rest for a moment at home.He would drink a pot of coffee by the kitchen stove and a deep uneasiness would come in him.Five of his patients had died.And one of these was Augustus Benedict Mady Lewis, the little deaf-mute.He had been asked to speak at the burial service, but as it was his rule not to attend funerals he was unable to accept this invitation.The five patients had not been lost because of any negligence on his part.The blame was in the long years of want which lay behind.The diets of cornbread and sowbelly and syrup, the crowding of four and five persons to a single room.The death of poverty.He brooded on this and drank coffee to stay awake.Often he held his hand to his chin, for recently a slight tremor in the nerves of his neck made his head nod unsteadily when he was tired.

Then during the fourth week of February Portia came to the house. It was only six o'clock in the morning and he was sitting by the fire in the kitchen, warming a pan of milk for breakfast.She was badly intoxicated.He smelled the keen, sweetish odor of gin and his nostrils widened with disgust.He did not look at her but busied himself with his breakfast.He crumpled some bread in a bowl and poured over it hot milk.He prepared coffee and laid the table.

Then when he was seated before his breakfast he looked at Portia sternly.“Have you had your morning meal?”

“I not going to eat breakfast，”she said.

“You will need it. If you intend to get to work today.”

“I not going to work.”

A dread came in him. He did not wish to question her further.He kept his eyes on his bowl of milk and drank from a spoon that was unsteady in his hand.When he had finished he looked up at the wall above her head.“Are you tongue-tied?”

“I going to tell you. You going to hear about it.Just as soon as I able to say it I going to tell you.”

Portia sat motionless in the chair, her eyes moving slowly from one corner of the wall to the other. Her arms hung down limp and her legs were twisted loosely about each other.When he turned from her he had for a moment a perilous sense of ease and freedom, which was more acute because he knew that soon it was to be shattered.He mended the fire and warmed his hands.Then he rolled a cigarette.The kitchen was in a state of spotless order and cleanliness.The saucepans on the wall glowed with the light of the stove and behind each one there was a round, black shadow.

“It about Willie.”

“I know.”He rolled the cigarette gingerly between his palms. His eyes glanced recklessly about him, greedy for the last sweet pleasures.

“Once I mentioned to you this here Buster Johnson were at the prison with Willie. Us knowed him before.He were sent home yesdiddy.”

“So?”

“Buster been crippled for life.”

His head quavered. He pressed his hand to his chin to steady himself, but the obstinate trembling was difficult to control.

“Last night these here friends come round to my house and say that Buster were home and had something to tell me about Willie. I run all the way and this here is what he said.”

“Yes.”

“There were three of them. Willie and Buster and this other boy.They were friends.Then this here trouble come up.”Portia halted.She wet her finger with her tongue and then moistened her dry lips with her finger.“It were something to do with the way this here white guard picked on them all the time.They were out on roadwork one day and Buster he sassed back and then the other boy he try to run off in the woods.They taken all three of them.They taken all three of them to the camp and put them in this here ice-cold room.”

He said yes again. But his head quavered and the word sounded like a rattle in his throat.

“It were about six weeks ago，”Portia said.“You remember that cold spell then. They put Willie and them boys in this room like ice.”

Portia spoke in a low voice, and she neither paused between words nor did the grief in her face soften. It was like a low song.She spoke and he could not understand.The sounds were distinct in his ear but they had no shape or meaning.It was as though his head were the prow of a boat and the sounds were water that broke on him and then flowed past.He felt he had to look behind to find the words already said.

“……and their feets swolled up and they lay there and struggle on the floor and holler out. And nobody come.They hollered there for three days and three nights and nobody come.”

“I am deaf，”said Doctor Copeland.“I cannot understand.”

“They put our Willie and them boys in this here ice-cold room. There were a rope hanging down from the ceiling.They taken their shoes off and tied their bare feets to this rope.Willie and them boys lay there with their backs on the floor and their feets in the air.And their feets swolled up and they struggle on the floor and holler out.It were ice-cold in the room and their feets froze.Their feets swolled up and they hollered for three nights and three days.And nobody come.”

Doctor Copeland pressed his head with his hands, but still the steady trembling would not stop.“I cannot hear what you say.”

“Then at last they come to get them. They quickly taken Willie and them boys to the sick ward and their legs were all swolled and froze.Gangrene.They sawed off both our Willie's feet.Buster Johnson lost one foot and the other boy got well.But our Willie—he crippled for life now.Both his feet sawed off.”

The words were finished and Portia leaned over and struck her head upon the table. She did not cry or moan, but she struck her head again and again on the hard-scrubbed top of the table.The bowl and spoon rattled and he removed them to the sink.The words were scattered in his mind, but he did not try to assemble them.He scalded the bowl and spoon and washed out the dishtowel.He picked up something from the floor and put it somewhere.

“Crippled?”he asked.“William?”

Portia knocked her head on the table and the blows had a rhythm like the slow beat of a drum and his heart took up this rhythm also. Quietly the words came alive and fitted to the meaning and he understood.

“When will they send him home?”

Portia leaned her drooping head on her arm.“Buster don't know that. Soon afterward they separate all three of them in different places.They sent Buster to another camp.Since Willie only haves a few more months he think he liable to be home soon now.”

They drank coffee and sat for a long time, looking into each other's eyes. His cup rattled against his teeth.She poured her coffee into a saucer and some of it dripped down on her lap.

“William—”Doctor Copeland said. As he pronounced the name his teeth bit deeply into his tongue and he moved his jaw with pain.They sat for a long while.Portia held his hand.The bleak morning light made the windows gray.Outside it was still raining.

“If I means to get to work I better go on now，”Portia said.

He followed her through the hall and stopped at the hatrack to put on his coat and shawl. The open door let in a gust of wet, cold air.Highboy sat out on the street curb with a wet newspaper over his head for protection.Along the sidewalk there was a fence.Portia leaned against this as she walked.Doctor Copeland followed a few paces after her and his hands, also, touched the boards of the fence to steady himself.Highboy trailed behind them.

He waited for the black, terrible anger as though for some beast out of the night. But it did not come to him.His bowels seemed weighted with lead, and he walked slowly and lingered against fences and the cold, wet walls of buildings by the way.Descent into the depths until at last there was no further chasm below.He touched the solid bottom of despair and there took ease.

In this he knew a certain strong and holy gladness. The persecuted laugh, and the black slave sings to his outraged soul beneath the whip.A song was in him now—although it was not music but only the feeling of a song.And the sodden heaviness of peace weighted down his limbs so that it was only with the strong, true purpose that he moved.Why did he go onward?Why did he not rest here upon the bottom of utmost humiliation and for a while take his content?

But he went onward.

“Uncle，”said Mick.“You think some hot coffee would make you feel better?”

Doctor Copeland looked into her face but gave no sign that he heard. They had crossed the town and come at last to the alley behind the Kellys'house.Portia had entered first and then he followed.Highboy remained on the steps outside.Mick and her two little brothers were already in the kitchen.Portia told of William.Doctor Copeland did not listen to the words but her voice had a rhythm—a start, a middle, and an end.Then when she was finished she began all over.Others came into the room to hear.

Doctor Copeland sat on a stool in the corner. His coat and shawl steamed over the back of a chair by the stove.He held his hat on his knees and his long, dark hands moved nervously around the worn brim.The yellow insides of his hands were so moist that occesionally he wiped them with a handkerchief.His head trembled, and all of his muscles were stiff with the effort to make it be still.

Mr. Singer came into the room.Doctor Copeland raised up his face to him.“Have you heard of this?”he asked.Mr.Singer nodded.In his eyes there was no horror or pity or hate.Of all those who knew, his eyes alone did not express these reactions.For he alone understood this thing.

Mick whispered to Portia，“What's your father's name?”

“He named Benedict Mady Copeland.”

Mick leaned over close to Doctor Copeland and shouted in his face as though he were deaf.“Benedict, don't you think some hot coffee would make you feel a little better?”

Doctor Copeland started.

“Quit that hollering，”Portia said.“He can hear well as you can.”

“Oh，”said Mick. She emptied the grounds from the pot and put the coffee on the stove to boil again.

The mute still lingered in the doorway. Doctor Copeland still looked into his face.“You heard?”

“What'll they do to those prison guards?”Mick asked.

“Honey, I just don't know，”Portia said.“I just don't know.”

“I'd do something. I'd sure do something about it.”

“Nothing us could do would make no difference. Best thing us can do is keep our mouth shut.”

“They ought to be treated just like they did Willie and them. Worse.I wish I could round up some people and kill those men myself.”

“That ain't no Christian way to talk，”Portia said.“Us can just rest back and know they going to be chopped up with pitchforks and fried everlasting by Satan.”

“Anyway Willie can still play his harp.”

“With both feets sawed off that about all he can do.”

The house was full of noise and unrest. In the room above the kitchen someone was moving furniture about.The dining-room was crowded with boarders.Mrs.Kelly hurried back and forth from the breakfast table to the kitchen.Mr.Kelly wandered about in a baggy pair of trousers and a bathrobe.The young Kelly children ate greedily in the kitchen.Doors banged and voices could be heard in all parts of the house.

Mick handed Doctor Copeland a cup of coffee mixed with watery milk. The milk gave the drink a gray-blue sheen.Some of the coffee had sloshed over into the saucer, so first he dried the saucer and the rim of the cup with his handkerchief.He had not wanted coffee at all.

“I wish I could kill them，”Mick said.

The house quieted. The people in the dining-room went out to work.Mick and George left for school and the baby was shut into one of the front rooms.Mrs.Kelly wrapped a towel around her head and took a broom with her upstairs.

The mute still stood in the doorway. Doctor Copeland gazed up into his face.“You know of this?”he asked again.The words did not sound—they choked in his throat—but his eyes asked the question all the same.Then the mute was gone.Doctor Copeland and Portia were alone.He sat for some time on the stool in the corner.At last he rose to go.

“You sit back down, Father. Us going to stay together this morning.I going to fry some fish and have egg-bread and potatoes for the dinner.You stay on here, and then I means to serve you a good hot meal.”

“You know I have calls.”

“Less us just this one day. Please, Father.I feels like I going to really bust loose.Besides, I don't want you messing around in the streets by yourself.”

He hesitated and felt the collar of his overcoat. It was very damp.“Daughter, I am sorry.You know I have visits.”

Portia held his shawl over the stove until the wool was hot. She buttoned his coat and turned up the collar about his neck.He cleared his throat and spat into one of the squares of paper that he carried with him in his pocket.Then he burned the paper in the stove.On the way out he stopped and spoke to Highboy on the steps.He suggested that Highboy stay with Portia if he could arrange to get leave from work.

The air was piercing and cold. From the low, dark skies the drizzling rain fell steadily.The rain had seeped into the garbage cans and in the alley there was the rank odor of wet refuse.As he walked he balanced himself with the help of a fence and kept his dark eyes on the ground.

He made all the strictly necessary visits. Then he attended to office patients from noon until two o'clock.Afterward he sat at his desk with his fists clenched tight.But it was useless to try to cogitate on this thing.

He wished never again to see a human face. Yet at the same time he could not sit alone in the empty room.He put on his overcoat and went out again into the wet, cold street.In his pocket were several prescriptions to be left at the pharmacy.But he did not wish to speak with Marshall Nicolls.He went into the store and laid the prescriptions upon the counter.The pharmacist turned from the powders he was measuring and held out both his hands.His thick lips worked soundlessly for a moment before he gained his poise.

“Doctor，”he said formally.“You must be aware that I and all our colleagues and the members of my lodge and church—we have your sorrow uppermost in our minds and wish to extend to you our deepest sympathy.”

Doctor Copeland turned shortly and left without a word. That was too little.Something more was needed.The strong, true purpose, the will to justice.He walked stiffly, his arms held close to his sides, toward the main street.He cogitated without success.He could think of no white person of power in all the town who was both brave and just.He thought of every lawyer, every judge, every public official with whose name he was familiar—but the thought of each one of these white men was bitter in his heart.At last he decided on the judge of the Superior Court.When he reached the courthouse he did not hesitate but entered quickly, determined to see the judge that afternoon.

The wide front hall was empty except for a few idlers who lounged in the doorways leading to the offices on either side. He did not know where he could find the judge's office, so he wandered uncertainly through the building, looking at the placards on the doors.At last he came to a narrow passage.half-way through this corridor three white men stood talking together and blocked the way.He drew close to the wall to pass, but one of them turned to stop him.

“What you want?”

“Will you please tell me where the judge's office is located?”

The white man jerked his thumb toward the end of the passage. Doctor Copeland recognized him as a deputy sheriff.They had seen each other dozens of times but the deputy did not remember him.All white people looked similar to Negroes but Negroes took care to differentiate between them.On the other hand, all Negroes looked similar to white men but white men did not usually bother to fix the face of a Negro in their minds.So the white man said, What you want, Reverend?”

The familiar joking title nettled him. I am not a minister，”he said，“I am a physician, a medical doctor.My name is Benedict Mady Copeland and I wish to see the judge immediately on urgent business.”

The deputy was like other white men in that a clearly enunciated speech maddened him.“Is that so?”he mocked. He winked at his friends.“Then I am the deputy sheriff and my name is Mister Wilson and I tell you the judge is busy.Come back some other day.”

“It is imperative that I see the judge，”Doctor Copeland said.“I will wait.”

There was a bench at the entrance of the passage and he sat down. The three white men continued to talk, but he knew that the sheriff watched him.He was determined not to leave.More than half an hour passed.Several white men went freely back and forth through the corridor.He knew that the deputy was watching him and he sat rigid, his hands pressed between his knees.His sense of prudence told him to go away and return later in the afternoon when the sheriff was not there.All of his life he had been circumspect in his dealings with such people.But now something in him would not let him withdraw.

“Come here, you！”the deputy said finally.

His head trembled, and when he arose he was not steady on his feet.“Yes?”

“What you say you wanted to see the judge about?”

“I did not say，”said Doctor Copeland.“I merely said that my business with him was urgent.”

“You can't stand up straight. You been drinking liquor, haven't you?I smell it on your breath.”

“That is a lie，”said Doctor Copeland slowly. 1　have not—”

The sheriff struck him on the face. He fell against the wall.Two white men grasped him by the arm and dragged him down the steps to the main floor.He did not resist.

“That's the trouble with this country，”the sheriff said.“These damn biggity niggers like him.”

He spoke no word and let them do with him as they would. He waited for the terrible anger and felt it arise in him.Rage made him weak, so that he stumbled.They put him into the wagon with two men as guards.They took him to the station and then to the jail.It was only when they entered the jail that the strength of his rage came to him.He broke loose suddenly from their grasp.In a corner he was surrounded.They struck him on the head and shoulders with their clubs.A glorious strength was in him and he heard himself laughing aloud as he fought.He sobbed and laughed at the same time.He kicked wildly with his feet.He fought with his fists and even struck at them with his head.Then he was clutched fast so that he could not move.They dragged him foot by foot through the hall of the jail.The door to a cell was opened.Someone behind kicked him in the groin and he fell to his knees on the floor.

In the cramped cubicle there were five other prisoners—three Negroes and two white men. One of the white men was very old and drunk.He sat on the floor and scratched himself.The other white prisoner was a boy not more than fifteen years of age.The three Negroes were young.As Doctor Copeland lay on the bunk looking up into their faces he recognized one of them.

“How come you here?”the young man asked.“Ain't you Doctor Copeland?”

He said yes.

“My name Dary White. You taken out my sister's tonsils last year.”

The icy cell was permeated with a rotten odor. A pail brimming with urine was in a corner.Cockroaches crawled upon the walls.He closed his eyes and immediately he must have slept, for when he looked up again the small barred window was black and a bright light burned in the hall.Four empty tin plates were on the floor.His dinner of cabbage and cornbread was beside him.

He sat on the bunk and sneezed violently several times. When he breathed the phlegm rattled in his chest.After a while the young white boy began to sneeze also.Doctor Copeland ran out of squares of paper and had to use sheets from a notebook in his pocket.The white boy leaned over the pail in the corner or simply let the water run from his nose onto the front of his shirt.His eyes were dilated, his clear cheeks flushed.He huddled on the edge of a bunk and groaned.

Soon they were led out to the lavatory, and on their return they prepared for sleep. There were six men to occupy four bunks.The old man lay snoring on the floor.Dary and another boy squeezed into a bunk together.

The hours were long. The light in the hall burned his eyes and the odor in the cell made every breath a discomfort.He could not keep warm.His teeth chattered and he shook with a hard chill.He sat up with the dirty blanket wrapped around him and swayed to and fro.Twice he reached over to cover the white boy, who muttered and threw out his arms in sleep.He swayed, his head in his hands, and from his throat there came a singing moan.He could not think of William.Nor could he even cogitate upon the strong, true purpose and draw strength from that.He could only feel the misery in him.

Then the tide of his fever turned. A warmth spread through him.He lay back, and it seemed he sank down into a place warm and red and full of comfort.

The next morning the sun came out. The strange Southern winter was at its end.Doctor Copeland was released.A little group waited outside the jail for him.Mr.Singer was there.Portia and Highboy and Marshall Nicolls were present also.Their faces were confused and he could not see them clearly.The sun was very bright.

“Father, don't you know that ain't no way to help our Willie?Messing around at a white folks'courthouse?Best thing us can do is keep our mouth shut and wait.”

Her loud voice echoed wearily in his ears. They climbed into a ten-cent taxicab, and then he was home and his face pressed into the fresh white pillow.

11

Mick could not sleep all night. Etta was sick, so she had to sleep in the living-room.The sofa was too narrow and short.She had nightmares about Willie.Nearly a month had gone by since Portia had told about what they had done to him—but still she couldn't forget it.Twice in the night she had these bad dreams and woke up on the floor.A bump came out on her forehead.Then at six o'clock she heard Bill go to the kitchen and fix his breakfast.It was daylight, but the shades were down so that the room was half-dark.She felt queer waking up in the living-room.She didn't like it.The sheet was twisted around her, half on the sofa and half on the floor.The pillow was in the middle of the room.She got up and opened the door to the hall.Nobody was on the stairs.She ran in her nightgown to the back room.

“Move over, George.”

The kid lay in the very center of the bed. The night had been warm and he was naked as a jay bird.His fists were shut tight, and even in sleep his eyes were squinted like he was thinking about something very hard to figure out.His mouth was open and there was a little wet spot on the pillow.She pushed him.

“Wait—”he said in his sleep.

“Move over on your side.”

“Wait—Lemme just finish this here dream—this here—”

She hauled him over where he belonged and lay down close to him. When she opened her eyes again it was late, because the sun shone in through the back window.George was gone.From the yard she heard kids'voices and the sound of water running.Etta and Hazel were talking in the middle room.As she dressed a sudden notion came to her.She listened at the door but it was hard to hear what they said.She jerked the door open quick to surprise them.

They were reading a movie magazine. Etta was still in bed.She had her hand half-way over the picture of an actor.“From here up don't you think he favors that boy who used to date with—”

“How you feel this morning, Etta?”Mick asked. She looked down under the bed and her private box was still in the exact place where she had left it.

“A lot you care，”Etta said.

“You needn't try to pick a fight.”

Etta's face was peaked. There was a terrible pain in her stomach and her ovary was diseased.It had something to do with being unwell.The doctor said they would have to cut out her ovary right away.But their Dad said they would have to wait.There wasn't any money.

“How do you expect me to act, anyway?”Mick said.“I ask you a polite question and then you start to nag at me. I feel like I ought to be sorry for you because you're sick, but you won't let me be decent.Therefore I naturally get mad.”She pushed back the bangs of her hair and looked close into the mirror.“Boy！See this bump I got！I bet my head's broke.Twice I fell out last night and it seemed to me like I hit that table by the sofa.I can't sleep in the living-room.That sofa cramps me so much I can't stay in it.”

“Hush that talking so loud，”Hazel said.

Mick knelt down on the floor and pulled out the big box. She looked carefully at the string that was tied around it.“Say, have either of you fooled with this?”

“Shoot！”Etta said.“What would we want to mess with your junk for?”

“You just better not. I'd kill anybody that tried to mess with my private things.”

“Listen to that，”Hazel said.“Mick Kelly, I think you're the most selfish person I've ever known. You don't care a thing in the world about anybody but—”

“Aw, poot！”She slammed the door. She hated both of them.That was a terrible thing to think, but it was true.

Her Dad was in the kitchen with Portia. He had on his bathrobe and was drinking a cup of coffee.The whites of his eyes were red and his cup rattled against his saucer.He walked round and round the kitchen table.

“What time is it?Has Mister Singer gone yet?”

“He been gone, Hon，”Portia said.“It near about ten o'clock.”

“Ten o'clock！Golly！I never have slept that late before.”

“What you keep in that big hatbox you tote around with you?”

Mick reached into the stove and brought out half a dozen biscuits.“Ask me no questions and I'll tell you no lies. A bad end comes to a person who pries.”

“If there's a little extra milk I think I'll just have it poured over some crumbled bread，”her Dad said.“Grave yard soup. Maybe that will help settle my stomach.”

Mick split open the biscuits and put slices of fried white meat inside them. She sat down on the back steps to eat her breakfast.The morning was warm and bright.Spareribs and Sucker were playing with George in the back yard.Sucker wore his sun suit and the other two kids had taken off all their clothes except their shorts.They were scooting each other with the hose.The stream of water sparkled bright in the sun.The wind blew out sprays of it like mist and in this mist there were the colors of the rainbow.A line of clothes flapped in the wind—white sheets, Ralph's blue dress, a red blouse and nightgowns—wet and fresh and blowing out in different shapes.The day was almost like summer-time.Fuzzy little yellow jackets buzzed around the honeysuckle on the alley fence.

“Watch me hold it up over my head！”George hollered.“Watch how the water runs down.”

She was too full of energy to sit still. George had filled a meal sack with dirt and hung it to a limb of the tree for a punching bag.She began to hit this.Puck！Pock！She hit it in time to the song that had been in her mind when she woke up.George had mixed a sharp rock in the dirt and it bruised her knuckles.

“Aoow！You skeeted the water right in my ear. It's busted my eardrum.I can't even hear.”

“Gimme here. Let me skeet some.”

Sprays of the water blew into her face, and once the kids turned the hose on her legs. She was afraid her box would get wet, so she carried it with her through the alley to the front porch.Harry was sitting on his steps reading the newspaper.She opened her box and got out the notebook.But it was hard to settle her mind on the song she wanted to write down.Harry was looking over in her direction and she could not think.

She and Harry had talked about so many things lately. Nearly every day they walked home from school together.They talked about God.Sometimes she would wake up in the night and shiver over what they had said.Harry was a Pantheist.That was a religion, the same as Baptist or Catholic or Jew.Harry believed that after you were dead and buried you changed to plants and fire and dirt and clouds and water.It took thousands of years and then finally you were a part of all the world.He said he thought I that was better than being one single angel.Anyhow it was better than nothing.

Harry threw the newspaper into his hall and then came over.“It's hot like summer，”he said.“And only March.”

“Yeah. I wish we could go swimming.”

“We would if there was any place.”

There's not any place. Except that country club pool.”

“I sure would like to do something—to get out and go somewhere.”

“Me too，”she said，“Wait！I know one place. It's out in the country about fifteen miles.It's a deep, wide creek in the woods.The Girl Scouts have a camp there in the summertime.Mrs.Wells took me and George and Pete and Sucker swimming there one time last year.”

If you want to I can get bicycles and we can go tomorrow. I have a holiday one Sunday a month.”

“We'll ride out and take a picnic dinner，”Mick said.

“O. K.I'll borrow the bikes.”

It was time for him to go to work. She watched him walk down the street.He swung his arms.Half-way down the block there was a bay tree with low branches.Harry took a running jump, caught a limb, and chinned himself.A happy feeling came in her because it was true they were real good friends.Also he was handsome.Tomorrow she would borrow Hazel's blue necklace and wear the silk dress.And for dinner they would take jelly sandwiches and Nehi.Maybe Harry would bring something queer, because they ate orthodox Jew.She watched him until he turned the corner.It was true that he had grown to be a very good-looking fellow.

Harry in the country was different from Harry sitting on the back steps reading the newspapers and thinking about Hitler. They left early in the morning.The wheels he borrowed were the kind for boys—with a bar between the legs.They strapped the lunches and bathing-suits to the fenders and were gone before nine o'clock.The morning was hot and sunny.Within an hour they were far out of town on a red clay road.The fields were bright and green and the sharp smell of pine trees was in the air.Harry talked in a very excited way.The warm wind blew into their faces.Her mouth was very dry and she was hungry.

“See that house up on the hill there?Less us stop and get some water.”

“No, we better wait. Well water gives you typhoid.”

“I already had typhoid. I had pneumonia and a broken leg and a infected foot.”

“I remember.”

“Yeah，”Mick said.“Me and Bill stayed in the front room when we had typhoid fever and Pete Wells would run past on the sidewalk holding his nose and looking up at the window. Bill was very embarrassed.All my hair came out so I was bald-headed.”

“I bet we're at least ten miles from town. We've been riding an hour and a half—fast riding, too.”

“I sure am thirsty，”Mick said.“And hungry. What you got in that sack for lunch?”

“Cold liver pudding and chicken salad sandwiches and pie.”

“That's a good picnic dinner.”She was ashamed of what she had brought.“I got two hard-boiled eggs—already stuffed—with separate little packages of salt and pepper. And sandwiches—blackberry jelly with butter.Everything wrapped in oil paper.And paper napkins.”

“I didn't intend for you to bring anything，”Harry said.“My Mother fixed lunch for both of us. I asked you out here and all.We'll come to a store soon and get cold drinks.”

They rode half an hour longer before they finally came to the filling-station store. Harry propped up the bicycles and she went in ahead of him.After the bright glare the store seemed dark.The shelves were stacked with slabs of white meat, cans of oil, and sacks of meal.Flies buzzed over a big, sticky jar of loose candy on the counter.

“What kind of drinks you got?”Harry asked.

The storeman started to name them over. Mick opened the ice box and looked inside.Her hands felt good in the cold water.“I want a chocolate Nehi.You got any of them?”

“Ditto，”Harry said.“Make it two.”

“No, wait a minute. Here's some ice-cold beer.I want a bottle of beer if you can treat as high as that.”

Harry ordered one for himself, also. He thought it was a sin for anybody under twenty to drink beer—but maybe he just suddenly wanted to be a sport.After the first swallow he made a bitter face.They sat on the steps in front of the store.Mick's legs were so tired that the muscles in them jumped.She wiped the neck of the bottle with her hand and took a long, cold pull.Across the road there was a big empty field of grass, and beyond that a fringe of pine woods.The trees were every color of green—from a bright yellow-green to a dark color that was almost black.The sky was hot blue.

“I like beer，”she said.“I used to sop bread down in the drops our Dad left. I like to lick salt out my hand while I drink.This is the second bottle to myself I've ever had.”

“The first swallow was sour. But the rest tastes good.”

The storeman said it was twelve miles from town. They had four more miles to go.Harry paid him and they were out in the hot sun again.Harry was talking loud and he kept laughing without any reason.

“Gosh, the beer along with this hot sun makes me dizzy. But I sure do feel good，”he said.

“I can't wait to get in swimming.”

There was sand in the road and they had to throw all their weight on the pedals to keep from bogging. Harry's shirt was stuck to his back with sweat.He still kept talking.The road changed to red clay and the sand was behind them.There was a slow colored song in her mind—one Portia's brother used to play on his harp.She pedaled in time to it.

Then finally they reached the place she had been looking for.“This is it！See that sign that says PRIVATE?We got to climb the bob-wire fence and then take that path there—see！”

The woods were very quiet. Slick pine needles covered the ground.Within a few minutes they had reached the creek.The water was brown and swift.Cool.There was no sound except from the water and a breeze singing high up in the pine trees.It was like the deep, quiet woods made them timid, and they walked softly along the bank beside the creek.

“Don't it look pretty.”

Harry laughed.“What makes you whisper?Listen here！”He clapped his hand over his mouth and gave a long Indian whoop that echoed back at them.“Come on. Let's jump in the water and cool off.”

“Aren't you hungry?”

“O. K.Then we'll eat first.We'll eat half the lunch now and half later on when we come out.”

She unwrapped the jelly sandwiches. When they were finished Harry balled the papers neatly and stuffed them into a hollow tree stump.Then he took his shorts and went down the path.She shucked off her clothes behind a bush and struggled into Hazel's bathing-suit.The suit was too small and cut her between the legs.

“You ready?”Harry hollered.

She heard a splash in the water and when she reached the bank Harry was already swimming.“Don't dive yet until I find out if there are any stumps or shallow places，”he said. She just looked at his head bobbing in the water.She had never intended to dive, anyway.She couldn't even swim.She had been in swimming only a few times in her life—and then she always wore water-wings or stayed out of parts that were over her head.But it would be sissy to tell Harry.She was embarrassed.All of a sudden she told a tale：

“I don't dive any more. I used to dive, high dive, all the time.But once I busted my head open, so I can't dive any more.”She thought for a minute.“It was a double jack-knife dive I was doing.And when I came up there was blood all in the water.But I didn't think anything about it and just began to do swimming tricks.These people were hollering at me.Then I found out where all this blood in the water was coming from.And I never have swam good since.”

Harry scrambled up the bank.“Gosh！I never heard about that.”

She meant to add on to the tale to make it sound more reasonable, but instead she just looked at Harry. His skin was light brown and the water made it shining.There were hairs on his chest and legs.In the tight trunks he seemed very naked.Without his glasses his face was wider and more handsome.His eyes were wet and blue.He was looking at her and it was like suddenly they got embarrassed.

“The water's about ten feet deep except over on the other bank, and there it's shallow.”

“Less us get going. I bet that cold water feels good.”

She wasn't scared. She felt the same as if she had got caught at the top of a very high tree and there was nothing to do but just climb down the best way she could—a dead-calm feeling.She edged off the bank and was in ice-cold water.She held to a root until it broke in her hands and then she began to swim.Once she choked and went under, but she kept going and didn't lose any face.She swam and reached the other side of the bank where she could touch bottom.Then she felt good.She smacked the water with her fists and called out crazy words to make echoes.

“Watch here！”

Harry shimmied up a tall, thin little tree. The trunk was limber and when he reached the top it swayed down with him.He dropped into the water.

“Me too！Watch me do it！”

“That's a sapling.”

She was as good a climber as anybody on the block. She copied exactly what he had done and hit the water with a hard smack.She could swim, too.Now she could swim O.K.

They played follow the leader and ran up and down the bank and jumped in the cold brown water. They hollered and jumped and climbed.They played around for maybe two hours.Then they were standing on the bank and they both looked at each other and there didn't seem to be anything new to do.Suddenly she said：

“Have you ever swam naked?”

The woods was very quiet and for a minute he did not answer. He was cold.His titties had turned hard and purple.His lips were purple and his teeth chattered.“I—I don't think so.”

This excitement was in her, and she said something she didn't mean to say.“I would if you would. I dare you to.”

Harry slicked back the dark, wet bangs of his hair.“O. K.”

They both took off their bathing-suits. Harry had his back to her.He stumbled and his ears were red.Then they turned toward each other.Maybe it was half an hour they stood there—maybe not more man a minute.

Harry pulled a leaf from a tree and tore it to pieces.“We better get dressed.”

All through the picnic dinner neither of them spoke. They spread the dinner on the ground.Harry divided everything in half.There was the hot, sleepy feeling of a summer afternoon.In the deep woods they could hear no sound except the slow flowing of the water and the songbirds.Harry held his stuffed egg and mashed the yellow with his thumb.What did that make her remember?She heard herself breathe.

Then he looked up over her shoulder.“Listen here. I think you're so pretty, Mick.I never did think so before.I don't mean I thought you were very ugly—I just mean that—”

She threw a pine cone in the water.“Maybe we better start back if we want to be home before dark.”

“No，”he said.“Let's lie down. Just for a minute.”

He brought handfuls of pine needles and leaves and gray moss. She sucked her knee and watched him.Her fists were tight and it was like she was tense all over.

“Now we can sleep and be fresh for the trip home.”

They lay on the soft bed and looked up at the dark-green pine clumps against the sky. A bird sang a sad, clear song she had never heard before.One high note like an oboe—and then it sank down five tones and called again.The song was sad as a question without words.

“I love that bird，”Harry said.“I think it's a vireo.”

“I wish we was at the ocean. On the beach and watching the ships far out on the water.You went to the beach one summer—exactly what is it like?”

His voice was rough and low.“Well—there are the waves. Sometimes blue and sometimes green, and in the bright sun they look glassy.And on the sand you can pick up these little shells.Like the kind we brought back in a cigar box.And over the water are these white gulls.We were at the Gulf of Mexico—these cool bay breezes blew all the time and there it's never baking hot like it is here.Always—”

“Snow，”Mick said.“That's what I want to see. Cold, white drifts of snow like in pictures.Blizzards.White, cold snow that keeps falling soft and falls on and on and on through all the winter.Snow like in Alaska.”

They both turned at the same time. They were close against each other.She felt him trembling and her fists were tight enough to crack.“Oh, God，”he kept saying over and over.It was like her head was broke off from her body and thrown away.And her eyes looked up straight into the blinding sun while she counted something in her mind.And then this was the way.

This was how it was.

They pushed the wheels slowly along the road. Harry's head hung down and his shoulders were bent.Their shadows were long and black on the dusty road, for it was late afternoon.

“Listen here，”he said.

“Yeah.”

“We got to understand this. We got to.Do you—any?”

“I don't know. I reckon not.”

“Listen here. We got to do something.Let's sit down.”

They dropped the bicycles and sat by a ditch beside the road. They sat far apart from each other.The late sun burned down on their heads and there were brown, crumbly ant beds all around them.

“We got to understand this，”Harry said.

He cried. He sat very still and the tears rolled down his white face.She could not think about the thing that made him cry.An ant stung her on the ankle and she picked it up in her fingers and looked at it very close.

“It's this way，”he said. I never had even kissed a girl before.”

“Me neither. I never kissed any boy.Out of the family.”

“That's all I used to think about—was to kiss this certain girl. I used to plan about it during school and dream about it at night.And then once she gave me a date.And I could tell she meant for me to kiss her.And I just looked at her in the dark and I couldn't That was all I had thought about—to kiss her—and when the time came I couldn't.”

She dug a hole in the ground with her finger and buried the dead ant.

“It was all my fault. Adultery is a terrible sin any way you look at it.And you were two years younger than me and just a kid.”

“No, I wasn't. I wasn't any kid.But now I wish I was, though.”

“Listen here. If you think we ought to we can get married—secretly or any other way.”

Mick shook her head.“I didn't like that. I never will marry with any boy.”

“I never will marry either. I know that And I'm not just saying so—it's true.”

His face scared her. His nose quivered and his bottom lip was mottled and bloody where he had bitten it.His eyes were bright and wet and scowling.His face was whiter than any face she could remember.She turned her head from him.Things would be better if only he would just quit talking.Her eyes looked slowly around her—at the streaked red-and-white clay of the ditch, at a broken whiskey bottle, at a pine tree across from them with a sign advertising for a man for county sheriff.She wanted to sit quiet for a long time and not think and not say a word.

“I'm leaving town. I'm a good mechanic and I can get a job some other place.If I stayed home Mother could read this in my eyes.”

“Tell me. Can you look at me and see the difference?”

Harry watched her face a long time and nodded that he could. Then he said：

“There's just one more thing. In a month or two I'll send you my address and you write and tell me for sure whether you're all right.”

“How you mean?”she asked slowly.

He explained to her.“All you need to write is‘O. K.'and then I'll know.”

They were walking home again pushing the wheels. Their shadows stretched out giant-sized on the road.Harry was bent over like an old beggar and kept wiping his nose on his sleeve.For a minute there was a bright, golden glow over everything before the sun sank down behind the trees and their shadows were gone on the road before them.She felt very old, and it was like something was heavy inside her.She was a grown person now, whether she wanted to be or not.

They had walked the sixteen miles and were in the dark alley at home. She could see the yellow light from their kitchen.Harry's house was dark—his mother had not come home.She worked for a tailor in a shop on a side street.Sometimes even on Sunday.When you looked through the window you could see her bending over the machine in the back or pushing a long needle through the heavy pieces of goods.She never looked up while you watched her.And at night she cooked these orthodox dishes for Harry and her.

“Listen here—”he said.

She waited in the dark, but he did not finish. They shook hands with each other and Harry walked up the dark alley between the houses.When he reached the sidewalk he turned and looked back over his shoulder.A light shone on his face and it was white and hard.Then he was gone.

“This here is a riddle，”George said.

“I listening.”

Two Indians was walking on a trail. The one in front was the son of the one behind but the one behind was not his father.What kin was they?”

“Less see. His stepfather.”

George grinned at Portia with his little square, blue teeth.

“His uncle, then.”

“You can't guess. It was his mother.The trick is that you don't think about a Indian being a lady.”

She stood outside the room and watched them. The doorway framed the kitchen like a picture.Inside it was homey and clean.Only the light by the sink was turned on and there were shadows in the room.Bill and Hazel played black-jack at the table with matches for money.Hazel felt the braids of her hair with her plump, pink fingers while Bill sucked in his cheeks and dealt the cards in a very serious way.At the sink Portia was drying the dishes with a clean checked towel.She looked thin and her skin was golden yellow, her greased black hair slicked neat.Ralph sat quietly on the floor and George was trying a little harness on him made out of old Christmas tinsel.

“This here is another riddle, Portia. If the hand of a clock points to half past two—”

She went into the room. It was like she had expected them to move back when they saw her and stand around in a circle and look.But they just glanced at her.She sat down at the table and waited.

“Here you come traipsing in after ever body done finished supper. Seem to me like I never will get off from work.”

Nobody noticed her. She ate a big plateful of cabbage and salmon and finished off with junket.It was her Mama she was thinking about.The door opened and her Mama came in and told Portia that Miss Brown had said she found a bedbug in her room.To get out the gasoline.

“Quit frowning like that, Mick. You're coming to the age where you ought to fix up and try to look the best you can.And hold on—don't barge out like that when I speak with you—I mean you to give Ralph a good sponge bath before he goes to bed.Clean his nose and ears good.”

Ralph's soft hair was sticky with oatmeal. She wiped it with a dishrag and rinched his face and hands at the sink.Bill and Hazel finished their game.Bill's long fingernails scraped on the table as he took up the matches.George carried Ralph off to bed.She and Portia were alone in the kitchen.

“Listen！Look at me. Do you notice anything different?”

“Sure I notice, Hon.”

Portia put on her red hat and changed her shoes.

“Well—?”

“Just you take a little grease and rub it on your face. Your nose already done peeled very bad.They say grease is the best thing for bad sunburn.”

She stood by herself in the dark back yard, breaking off pieces of bark from the oak tree with her fingernails. It was almost worse this way.Maybe she would feel better if they could look at her and tell.If they knew.

Her Dad called her from the back steps.“Mick！Oh, Mick！”

“Yes, sir.”

“The telephone.”

George crowded up close and tried to listen in, but she pushed him away. Mrs.Minowitz talked very loud and excited.

“My Harry should be home by now. You know where he is?”

“No, ma'am.”

“He said you two would ride out on bicycles. Where should he be now?You know where he is?”

“No, ma'am，”Mick said again.

12

Now that the days were hot again the Sunny Dixie Show was always crowded. The March wind quieted.Trees were thick with their foliage of ochrous green.The sky was a cloudless blue and the rays of the sun grew stronger.The air was sultry.Jake Blount hated this weather.He thought dizzily of the long, burning summer months ahead.He did not feel well.Recently a headache had begun to trouble him constantly.He had gained weight so that his stomach developed a little pouch.He had to leave the top button of his trousers undone.He knew that this was alcoholic fat, but he kept on drinking.Liquor helped the ache in his head.He had only to take one small glass to make it better.Nowadays one glass was the same to him as a quart.It was not the liquor of the moment that gave him the kick—but the reaction of the first swallow to all the alcohol which had saturated his blood during these last months.

A spoonful of beer would help the throbbing in his head, but a quart of whiskey could not make him drunk.

He cut out liquor entirely. For several days he drank only water and Orange Crush.The pain was like a crawling worm in his head.He worked wearily during the long afternoons and evenings.He could not sleep and it was agony to try to read.The damp, sour stink in his room infuriated him.He lay restless in the bed and when at last he fell asleep daylight had come.

A dream haunted him. It had first come to him four months ago.He would awake with terror—but the strange point was that never could he remember the contents of this dream.Only the feeling remained when his eyes were opened.Each time his fears at awakening were so identical that he did not doubt but what these dreams were the same.He was used to dreams, the grotesque nightmares of drink that led him down into a madman's region of disorder, but always the morning light scattered the effects of these wild dreams and he forgot them.

This blank, stealthy dream was of a different nature. He awoke and could remember nothing.But there was a sense of menace that lingered in him long after.Then he awoke one morning with the old fear but with a faint remembrance of the darkness behind him.He had been walking among a crowd of people and in his arms he carried something.That was all he could be sure about.Had he stolen?Had he been trying to save some possession?Was he being hunted by all these people around him?He did not think so.The more he studied this simple dream the less he could understand.Then for some time afterward the dream did not return.

He met the writer of signs whose chalked message he had seen the past November. From the first day of their meeting the old man clung to him like an evil genius.His name was Simms and he preached on the sidewalks.The winter cold had kept him indoors, but in the spring he was out on the streets all day.His white hair was soft and ragged on his neck and he carried around with him a woman's big silk pocketbook full of chalk and Jesus ads.His eyes were bright and crazy.Simms tried to convert him.

“Child of adversity, I smell the sinful stink of beer on thy breath. And you smoke cigarettes.If the Lord had wanted us to smoke cigarettes He would have said so in His Book.The mark of Satan is on thy brow.I see it.Repent.Let me show you the light.”

Jake rolled up his eyes and made a slow pious sign in the air. Then he opened his oil-stained hand.“I reveal this only to you，”he said in a low stage voice.Simms looked down at the scar in his palm.Jake leaned closer and whispered：“And there's the other sign.The sign you know.For I was born with them.”

Simms backed against the fence. With a womanish gesture he lifted a lock of silver hair from his forehead and smoothed it back on his head.Nervously his tongue licked the corners of his mouth.Jake laughed.

“Blasphemer！”Simms screamed.“God will get you. You and all your crew.God remembers the scoffers.He watches after me.God watches everybody but He watches me the most.Like He did Moses.God tells me things in the night.God will get you.”

He took Simms down to a corner store for Coca-Colas and peanut-butter crackers. Simms began to work on him again.When he left for the show Simms ran along behind him.

“Come to this corner tonight at seven o'clock. Jesus has a message just for you.”

The first days of April were windy and warm. White clouds trailed across the blue sky.In the wind there was the smell of the river and also the fresher smell of fields beyond the town.The show was crowded every day from four in the afternoon until midnight.The crowd was a tough one.With the new spring he felt an undertone of trouble.

One night he was working on the machinery of the swings when suddenly he was roused from thought by the sounds of angry voices. Quickly he pushed through the crowd until he saw a white girl fighting with a colored girl by the ticket booth of the flying-jinny.He wrenched them apart, but still they struggled to get at each other.The crowd took sides and there was a bedlam of noise.The white girl was a hunchback.She held something tight in her hand.

“I seen you，”the colored girl yelled.“I ghy beat that hunch off your back, too.”

“Hush your mouth, you black nigger！”

“Low-down factory tag. I done paid my money and I ghy ride.White man, you make her give me back my ticket.”

“Black nigger slut！”

Jake looked from one to the other. The crowd pressed close.There were mumbled opinions on every side.

“I seen Lurie drop her ticket and I watched this here white lady pick it up. That the truth，”a colored boy said.

“No nigger going to put her hands on no white girl while—”

“You quit that pushing me. I ready to hit back even if your skin do be white.”

Roughly Jake pushed into the thick of the crowd.“All right！”he yelled.“Move on—break it up. Every damn one of you.”There was something about the size of his fists that made the people drift sullenly away.Jake turned back to the two girls.

“This here the way it is，”said the colored girl.“I bet I one of the few peoples here who done saved over fifty cents till Friday night. I done ironed double this week.I done paid a good nickel for that ticket she holding.And now I means to ride.”

Jake settled the trouble quickly. He let the hunchback keep the disputed ticket and issued another one to the colored girl.For the rest of that evening there were no more quarrels.But Jake moved alertly through the crowd.He was troubled and uneasy.

In addition to himself there were five other employees at the show—two men to operate the swings and take tickets and three girls to manage the booths. This did not count Patterson.The show-owner spent most of his time playing cards with himself in his trailer.His eyes were dull, with the pupils shrunken, and the skin of his neck hung in yellow, pulpy folds.During the past few months Jake had had two raises in pay.At midnight it was his job to report to Patterson and hand over the takings of the evening.Sometimes Patterson did not notice him until he had been in the trailer for several minutes；he would be staring at the cards, sunk in a stupor.The air of the trailer was heavy with the stinks of food and reefers.Patterson held his hand over his stomach as though protecting it from something.He always checked over the accounts very thoroughly.

Jake and the two operators had a squabble. These men were both former doffers at one of the mills.At first he had tried to talk to them and help them to see the truth.Once he invited them to a pool room for a drink.But they were so dumb he couldn't help them.Soon after this he overheard the conversation between them that caused the trouble.It was an early Sunday morning, almost two o'clock, and he had been checking the accounts with Patterson.When he stepped out of the trailer the grounds seemed empty.The moon was bright.He was thinking of Singer and the free day ahead.Then as he passed by the swings he heard someone speak his name.The two operators had finished work and were smoking together.Jake listened.

“If there's anything I hate worse than a nigger it's a Red.”

“He tickles me. I don't pay him no mind.The way he struts around.I never seen such a sawed-off runt.How tall is he, you reckon?”

“Around five foot. But he thinks he got to tell everybody so much.He oughta be in jail.That's where.The Red Bolshivik.”

“He just tickles me. I can't look at him without laughing.”

“He needn't act biggity with me.”

Jake watched them follow the path toward Weavers Lane. His first thought was to rush out and confront them, but a certain shrinking held him back.For several days he fumed in silence.Then one night after work he followed the two men for several blocks and as they turned a corner he cut in front of them.

“I heard you，”he said breathlessly.“It so happened I heard every word you said last Saturday night. Sure I'm a Red.At least I reckon I am.But what are you?”They stood beneath a street light.The two men stepped back from him.The neighborhood was deserted.“You pasty-faced, shrunk-gutted, ricket-ridden little rats！I could reach out and choke your stringy necks—one to each hand.Runt or no, I could lay you on this sidewalk where they'd have to scrape you up with shovels.”

The two men looked at each other, cowed, and tried to walk on. But Jake would not let them pass.He kept step with them, walking backward, a furious sneer on his face.

“All I got to say is this：In the future I suggest you come to me whenever you feel the need to make remarks about my height, weight, accent, demeanor, or ideology. And that last is not what I take a leak with either—case you don't know.We will discuss it together.”

Afterward Jake treated the two men with angry contempt. Behind his back they jeered at him.One afternoon he found that the engine of the swings had been deliberately damaged and he had to work three hours overtime to fix it.Always he felt someone was laughing at him.Each time he heard the girls talking together he drew himself up straight and laughed carelessly aloud to himself as though thinking of some private joke.

The warm southwest winds from the Gulf of Mexico were heavy with the smells of spring. The days grew longer and the sun was bright.The lazy warmth depressed him.He began to drink again.As soon as work was done he went home and lay down on his bed.Sometimes he stayed there, fully clothed and inert, for twelve or thirteen hours.The restlessness that had caused him to sob and bite his nails only a few months before seemed to have gone.And yet beneath his inertia Jake felt the old tension.Of all the places he had been this was the loneliest town of all.Or it would be without Singer.Only he and Singer understood the truth.He knew and could not get the don't-knows to see.It was like trying to fight darkness or heat or a stink in the air.He stared morosely out of his window.A stunted, smoked-blackened tree at the corner had put out new leaves of a bilious green.The sky was always a deep, hard blue.The mosquitoes from a fetid stream that ran through this part of the town buzzed in the room.

He caught the itch. He mixed some sulphur and hog fat and greased his body every morning.He clawed himself raw and it seemed that the itching would never be soothed.One night he broke loose.He had been sitting alone for many hours.He had mixed gin and whiskey and was very drunk.It was almost morning.He leaned out of the window and looked at the dark silent street.He thought of all the people around him.Sleeping.The don't-knows.Suddenly he bawled out in a loud voice：“This is the truth！You bastards don't know anything.You don't know.You don't know！”

The street awoke angrily. Lamps were lighted and sleepy curses were called to him.The men who lived in the house rattled furiously on his door.The girls from a cat-house across the street stuck their heads out of the windows.

“You dumb dumb dumb dumb bastards. You dumb dumb dumb dumb—”

“Shuddup！Shuddup！”

The fellows in the hall were pushing against the door：“You drunk bull！You'll be a sight dumber when we get thru with you.”

“How many out there?”Jake roared. He banged an empty bottle on the windowsill.“Come on, everybody.Come one, come all.I'll settle you three at a time.”

“That's right, Honey，”a whore called.

The door was giving way. Jake jumped from the window and ran through a side alley.“Hee-haw！Hee-haw！”he yelled drunkenly.He was barefooted and shirtless.An hour later he stumbled into Singer's room.He sprawled on the floor and laughed himself to sleep.

On an April morning he found the body of a man who had been murdered. A young Negro.Jake found him in a ditch about thirty yards from the showground.The Negro's throat had been slashed so that the head was rolled back at a crazy angle.The sun shone hot on his open, glassy eyes and flies hovered over the dried blood that covered his chest.The dead man held a red-and-yellow cane with a tassel like the ones sold at the hamburger booth at the show.Jake stared gloomily down at the body for some time.Then he called the police.No clues were found.Two days later the family of the dead man claimed his body at the morgue.

At the Sunny Dixie there were frequent fights and quarrels. Sometimes two friends would come to the show arm in arm, laughing and drinking—and before they left they would be struggling together in a panting rage.Jake was always alert.Beneath the gaudy gaiety of the show, the bright lights, and the lazy laughter, he felt something sullen and dangerous.

Through these dazed, disjointed weeks Simms nagged his footsteps constantly. The old man liked to come with a soapbox and a Bible and take a stand in the middle of the crowd to preach.He talked of the second coming of Christ.He said that the Day of Judgment would be October　2，1951.He would point out certain drunks and scream at them in his raw, worn voice.Excitement made his mouth fill with water so that his words had a wet, gurgling sound.Once he had slipped in and set up his stand no arguments could make him budge.He made Jake a present of a Gideon Bible, and told him to pray on his knees for one hour each night and to hurl away every glass of beer or cigarette that was offered him.

They quarreled over walls and fences. Jake had begun to carry chalk in his pockets, also.He wrote brief sentences.He tried to word them so that a passer-by would stop and ponder over the meaning.So that a man would wonder.So that a man would think.Also, he wrote short pamphlets and distributed them in the streets.

If it had not been for Singer, Jake knew that he would have left the town. Only on Sunday, when he was with his friend, did he feel at peace.Sometimes they would go for a walk together or play chess—but more often they spent the day quietly in Singer's room.If he wished to talk Singer was always attentive.If he sat morosely through the day the mute understood his feelings and was not surprised.It seemed to him that only Singer could help him now.

Then one Sunday when he climbed the stairs he saw that Singer's door was open. The room was empty.He sat alone for more than two hours.At last he heard Singer's footsteps on the stairs.

“I was wondering about you. Where you been?”

Singer smiled. He brushed off his hat with a handkerchief and put it away.Then deliberately he took his silver pencil from his pocket and leaned over the mantelpiece to write a note.

“What you mean?”Jake asked when he read what the mute had written.“Whose legs are cut off?”

Singer took back the note and wrote a few additional sentences.

“Huh！”Jake said.“That don't surprise me.”

He brooded over the piece of paper and then crumpled it in his hand. The listlessness of the past month was gone and he was tense and uneasy.“Huh！”he said again.

Singer put on a pot of coffee and got out his chessboard. Jake tore the note to pieces and rolled the fragments between his sweating palms.

“But something can be done about this，”he said after a while.“You know it?”

Singer nodded uncertainly.

“I want to see the boy and hear the whole story. When can you take me around there?”

Singer deliberated. Then he wrote on a pad of paper，“Tonight.”

Jake held his hand to his mouth and began to walk restlessly around the room.“We can do something.”

13

Jake and Singer waited on the front porch. When they pushed the doorbell there was no sound of a ring in the darkened house.Jake knocked impatiently and pressed his nose against the screen door.Beside him Singer stood wooden and smiling, with two spots of color on his cheeks, for they had drunk a bottle of gin together.The evening was quiet and dark.Jake watched a yellow light shaft softly through the hall.And Portia opened the door for them.

“I certainly trust you not been waiting long. So many folks been coming that us thought it wise to untach the bell.You gentlemens just let me take you hats—Father been mighty sick.”

Jake tiptoed heavily behind Singer down the bare, narrow hall. At the threshold of the kitchen he stopped short.The room was crowded and hot.A fire burned in the small wood stove and the windows were closed tight.Smoke mingled with a certain Negro smell.The glow from the stove was the only light in the room.The dark voices he had heard back in the hall were silent.

“These here are two white gentlemens come to inquire about Father，”Portia said.“I think maybe he be able to see you but I better go on in first and prepare him.”

Jake fingered his thick lower lip. On the end of his nose there was a latticed impression from the front screen door.“That's not it，”he said.“I come to talk with your brother.”

The Negroes in the room were standing. Singer motioned to them to be seated again.Two grizzled old men sat down on a bench by the stove.A loose-limbed mulatto lounged against the window.On a camp cot in a corner was a boy without legs whose trousers were folded and pinned beneath his stumpy thighs.

“Good evening，”Jake said awkwardly.“Your name Copeland?”

The boy put his hands over the stumps of his legs and shrank back close to the wall.“My name Willie.”

“Honey, don't you worry none，”said Portia.“This here is Mr. Singer that you heard Father speak about.And this other white gentleman is Mr.Blount and he a very close friend of Mr.Singer.They just kindly come to inquire about us in our trouble.”She turned to Jake and motioned to the three other people in the room.“This other boy leaning on the window is my brother too.Named Buddy.And these here over by the stove is two dear friends of my Father.Named Mr.Marshall Nicolls and Mr.John Roberts.I think it a good idea to understand who all is in a room with you.”

“Thanks，”Jake said. He turned to Willie again.“I just want you to tell me about it so I can get it straight in my mind.”

“This the way it is，”Willie said.“I feel like my feets is still hurting. I got this here terrible misery down in my toes.Yet the hurt in my feets is down where my feets should be if they were on my　1-1-legs.And not where my feets is now.It a hard thing to understand.My feets hurt me so bad all the time and I don't know where they is.They never given them back to me.They s-somewhere more than a hundred m-miles from here.”

“I mean about how it all happened，”Jake said.

Uneasily Willie looked up at his sister.“I don't remember—very good.”

“Course you remember, Honey. You done already told us over and over.”

“Well—”The boy's voice was timid and sullen.“Us were all out on the road and this here Buster say something to the guard. The w-white man taken a stick to him.Then this other boy he tries to run off.And I follow him.It all come about so quick I don't remember good just how it were.Then they taken us back to the camp and—”

“I know the rest，”Jake said.“But give me the names and addresses of the other two boys. And tell me the names of the guards.”

“Listen here, white man. It seem to me like you meaning to get me into trouble.”

“Trouble！”Jake said rudely.“What in the name of Christ do you think you're in now?”

“Less us quiet down，”Portia said nervously.“This here the way it is, Mr. Blount.They done let Willie off at the camp before his time were served.But they done also impressed it on him not to—I believe you understand what us means.Naturally Willie he scared.Naturally us means to be careful—'cause that the best thing us can do.We already got enough trouble as is.”

“What happened to the guards?”

“Them w-white men were fired. That what they told me.”

“And where are your friends now?”

“What friends?”

“Why, the other two boys.”

“They n-not my friends，”Willie said.“Us all has had a big falling out.”

“How you mean?”

Portia pulled her earrings so that the lobes of her ears stretched out like rubber.“This here what Willie means. You see, during them three days when they hurt so bad they commenced to quarrel.Willie don't ever want to see any of them again.That one thing Father and Willie done argued about already.This here Buster—”

“Buster got a wooden leg，”said the boy by the window.“I seen him on the street today.”

“This here Buster don't have no folks and it were Father's idea to have him move on in with us. Father want to round up all the boys together.How he reckons us can feed them I sure don't know.”

“That ain't a good idea. And besides us was never very good friends anyway.”Willie felt the stumps of his legs with his dark, strong hands.“I just wish I knowed where my f-f-feets are.That the main thing worries me.The doctor never given them back to me.I sure do wish I knowed where they are.”

Jake looked around him with dazed, gin-clouded eyes. Everything seemed unclear and strange.The heat in the kitchen dizzied him so that voices echoed in his ears.The smoke choked him.The light hanging from the ceiling was turned on but, as the bulb was wrapped in newspaper to dim its strength, most of the light came from between the chinks of the hot stove.There was a red glow on all the dark faces around him.He felt uneasy and alone.Singer had left the room to visit Portia's father.Jake wanted him to come back so that they could leave.He walked awkwardly across the floor and sat down on the bench between Marshall Nicolls and John Roberts.

“Where is Portia's father?”he asked.

“Doctor Copeland is in the front room, sir，”said Roberts.

“Is he a doctor?”

“Yes, sir. He is a medical doctor.”

There was a scuffle on the steps outside and the back door opened. A warm, fresh breeze lightened the heavy air.First a tall boy dressed hi a linen suit and gilded shoes entered the room with a sack in his arms.Behind him came a young boy of about seventeen.

“Hey, Highboy. Hey there, Lancy，”Willie said.“What you all brought me?”

Highboy bowed elaborately to Jake and placed on the table two fruit jars of wine. Lancy put beside them a plate covered with a fresh white napkin.

“This here wine is a present from the Society，”Highboy said.“And Lancy's mother sent some peach puffs.”

“How is the Doctor, Miss Portia?”Lancy asked.

“Honey, he been mighty sick these days. What worries me is he so strong.It a bad sign when a person sick as he is suddenly come to be so strong.”Portia turned to Jake.“Don't you think it a bad sign, Mr.Blount?”

Jake stared at her dazedly.“I don't know.”

Lancy glanced sullenly at Jake and pulled down the cuffs of his outgrown shirt.“Give the Doctor my family's regards.”

“Us certainly do appreciate this，”Portia said.“Father was speaking of you just the other day. He haves a book he wants to give you.Wait just one minute while I get it and rinch out this plate to return to your Mother.This were certainly a kindly thing for her to do.”

Marshall Nicolls leaned toward Jake and seemed about to speak to him. The old man wore a pair of pin-striped trousers and a morning coat with a flower in the buttonhole.He cleared his throat and said：“Pardon me, sir—but unavoidably we overheard a part of your conversation with William regarding the trouble he is now in.Inevitably we have considered what is the best course to take.”

“You one of his relatives or the preacher in his church?”

“No, I am a pharmacist. And John Roberts on your left is employed in the postal department of the government.”

“A postman，”repeated John Roberts.

“With your permission—”Marshall Nicolls took a yellow silk handkerchief from his pocket and gingerly blew his nose.“Naturally we have discussed this matter extensively. And without doubt as members of the colored race here in this free country of America we are anxious to do our part toward extending amicable relationships.”

“We wish always to do the right thing，”said John Roberts.

“And it behooves us to strive with care and not endanger this amicable relationship already established. Then by gradual means a better condition will come about.”

Jake turned from one to the other.“I don't seem to follow you.”The heat was suffocating him. He wanted to get out.A film seemed to have settled over his eyeballs so that all the faces around him were blurred.

Across the room Willie was playing his harp. Buddy and Highboy were listening.The music was dark and sad.When the song was finished Willie polished his harp on the front of his shirt.“I so hungry and thirsty the slobber in my mouth done wet out the tune.I certainly will be glad to taste some of that boogie-woogie.To have something good to drink is the only thing m-made me forget this misery.If I just knowed where my f-feets are now and could drink a glass of gin ever night I wouldn't mind so much.”

“Don't fret, Hon. You going to have something，”Portia said.“Mr.Blount, would you care to take a peach puff and a glass of wine?”

“Thanks，”Jake said.“That would be good.”

Quickly Portia laid a cloth on the table and set down one plate and a fork. She poured a large tumblerful of the wine.“You just make yourself comfortable here.And if you don't mind I going to serve the others.”

The fruit jars were passed from mouth to mouth. Before Highboy passed a jar to Willie he borrowed Portia's lipstick and drew a red line to set the boundary of the drink.There were gurgling noises and laughter.Jake finished his puff and carried his glass back with him to his place between the two old men.The home-made wine was rich and strong as brandy.Willie started a low dolorous tune on his harp.Portia snapped her fingers and shuffled around the room.

Jake turned to Marshall Nicolls.“You say Portia's father is a doctor?”

“Yes, sir. Yes, indeed.A skilled doctor.”

“What's the matter with him?”

The two Negroes glanced warily at each other.

“He were in an accident，”said John Roberts.

“What kind of an accident?”

“A bad one. A deplorable one.”

Marshall Nicolls folded and unfolded his silk handkerchief.“As we were remarking a while ago, it is important not to impair these amicable relations but to promote them in all ways earnestly possible. We members of the colored race must strive in all ways to uplift our citizens.The Doctor in yonder has strived in every way.But sometimes it has seemed to me like he had not recognized fully enough certain elements of the different races and the situation.”

Impatiently Jake gulped down the last swallows of his wine.“Christ'sake, man, speak out plain, because I can't understand a thing you say.”

Marshall Nicolls and John Roberts exchanged a hurt look. Across the room Willie still sat playing music.His lips crawled over the square holes of the harmonica like fat, puckered caterpillars.His shoulders were broad and strong.The stumps of his thighs jerked in time to the music.Highboy danced while Buddy and Portia clapped out the rhythm.

Jake stood up, and once on his feet he realized that he was drunk. He staggered and then glanced vindictively around him, but no one seemed to have noticed.“Where's Singer?”he asked Portia thickly.

The music stopped.“Why, Mr. Blount, I thought you knowed he was gone.While you were sitting at the table with your peach puff he come to the doorway and held out his watch to show it were time for him to go.You looked straight at him and shaken your head.I thought you knowed that.”

“Maybe I was thinking about something else.”He turned to Willie and said angrily to him：“I never did even get to tell you what I come here for, I didn't come to ask you to do anything. All I wanted—all I wanted was this.You and the other boys were to testify what happened and I was to explain why.Why is the only important thing—not what.I would have pushed you all around in a wagon and you would have told your story and afterward I would have explained why.And maybe it might have meant something.Maybe it—”

He felt they were laughing at him. Confusion caused him to forget what he had meant to say.The room was full of dark, strange faces and the air was too thick to breathe.He saw a door and staggered across to it.He was in a dark closet smelling of medicine.Then his hand was turning another doorknob.

He stood on the threshold of a small white room furnished only with an iron bed, a cabinet, and two chairs. On the bed lay the terrible Negro he had met on the stairs at Singer's house.His face was very black against the white, stiff pillows.The dark eyes were hot with hatred but the heavy, bluish lips were composed.His face was motionless as a black mask except for the slow, wide flutters of his nostrils with each breath.

“Get out，”the Negro said.

“Wait—”Jake said helplessly.“Why do you say that?”

“This is my house.”

Jake could not draw his eyes away from the Negro's terrible face.“But why?”

“You are a white man and a stranger.”

Jake did not leave. He walked with cumbersome caution to one of the straight white chairs and seated himself.The Negro moved his hands on the counterpane.His black eyes glittered with fever.Jake watched him.They waited.In the room there was a feeling tense as conspiracy or as the deadly quiet before an explosion.

It was long past midnight. The warm, dark air of the spring morning swirled the blue layers of smoke in the room.On the floor were crumpled balls of paper and a half-empty bottle of gin.Scattered ashes were gray on the counterpane.Doctor Copeland pressed his head tensely into the pillow.He had removed his dressing-gown and the sleeves of his white cotton nightshirt were rolled to the elbow.Jake leaned forward in his chair.His tie was loosened and the collar of his shirt had wilted with sweat.Through the hours there had grown between them a long, exhausting dialogue.And now a pause had come.

“So the time is ready for—”Jake began.

But Doctor Copeland interrupted him.“Now it is perhaps necessary that we—”he murmured huskily. They halted.Each looked into the eyes of the other and waited.“I beg your pardon，”Doctor Copeland said.

“Sorry，”said Jake.“Go on.”

“No, you continue.”

“Well—”Jake said.“I won't say what I started to say. Instead we'll have one last word about the South.The strangled South.The wasted South, The slavish South.”

“And the Negro people.”

To steady himself Jake swallowed a long, burning draught from the bottle on the floor beside him. Then deliberately he walked to the cabinet and picked up a small, cheap globe of the world that served as a paperweight.Slowly he turned the sphere in his hands.“All I can say is this：The world is full of meanness and evil.Huh！Three fourths of this globe is in a state of war or oppression.The liars and fiends are united and the men who know are isolated and without defense.But！But if you was to ask me to point out the most uncivilized area on the face of this globe I would point here—”

“Watch sharp，”said Doctor Copeland.“You're out in the ocean.”

Jake turned the globe again and pressed his blunt, grimy thumb on a carefully selected spot.“Here. These thirteen states.I know what I'm talking about.I read books and I go around.I been in every damn one of these thirteen states.I've worked in every one.And the reason I think like I do is this：We live in the richest country in the world.There's plenty and to spare for no man, woman, or child to be in want.And in addition to this our country was founded on what should have been a great, true principle—the freedom, equality, and rights of each individual.Huh！And what has come of that start?There are corporations worth billions of dollars—and hundreds of thousands of people who don't get to eat.And here in these thirteen states the exploitation of human beings is so that—that it's a thing you got to take in with your own eyes.In my life I seen things that would make a man go crazy.At least one third of all Southerners live and die no better off than the lowest peasant in any European Fascist state.The average wage of a worker on a tenant farm is only seventy-three dollars per year.And mind you, that’s the average！The wages of sharecroppers run from thirty-five to ninety dollars per person.And thirty-five dollars a year means just about ten cents for a full day’s work.Everywhere there’s pellagra and hookworm and anaemia.And just plain, pure starvation.But！”Jake rubbed his lips with the knuckles of his dirty fist.Sweat stood out on his forehead.“But！”he repeated.Those are only the evils you can see and touch.The other things are worse.I’m talking about the way that the truth has been hidden from the people.The things they have been told so they can’t see the truth.The poisonous lies.So they aren’t allowed to know.”

“And the Negro，”said Doctor Copeland.“To understand what is happening to us you have to—”

Jake interrupted him savagely.“Who owns the South?Corporations in the North own three fourths of all the South. They say the old cow grazes all over—in the south, the west, the north, and the east.But she's milked in just one place.Her old teats swing over just one spot when she's full.She grazes everywhere and is milked in New York.Take our cotton mills, our pulp mills, our harness factories, our mattress factories.The North owns them.And what happens?”Jake's mustache quivered angrily.“Here's an example.Locale, a mill village according to the great paternal system of American industry.Absentee ownership.In the village is one huge brick mill and maybe four or five hundred shanties.The houses aren't fit for human beings to live in.Moreover, the houses were built to be nothing but slums in the first place.These shanties are nothing but two or maybe three rooms and a privy—built with far less forethought than barns to house cattle.Built with far less attention to needs than sties for pigs.For under this system pigs are valuable and men are not.You can’t make pork chops and sausage out of skinny little mill kids.You can’t sell but half the people these days.But a pig—”

“Hold on！”said Doctor Copeland.“You are getting off on a tangent. And besides, you are giving no attention to the very separate question of the Negro.I cannot get a word in edgeways.We have been over all this before, but it is impossible to see the full situation without including us Negroes.”

“Back to our mill village，”Jake said.“A young linthead begins working at the fine wage of eight or ten dollars a weeks at such times as he can get himself employed. He marries.After the first child the woman must work in the mill also.Their combined wages come to say eighteen dollars a week when they both got work.Huh！They pay a fourth of this for the shack the mill provides them.They buy food and clothes at a company-owned or dominated store.The store overcharges on every item.With three or four younguns they are held down the same as if they had on chains.That is the whole principle of serfdom.Yet here in America we call ourselves free.And the funny thing is that this has been drilled into the heads of sharecroppers and lintheads and all the rest so hard that they really believe it.But it's taken a hell of a lot of lies to keep them from knowing.”

“There is only one way out—”said Doctor Copeland.

“Two ways. And only two ways.Once there was a time when this country was expanding.Every man thought he had a chance.Huh！But that period has gone—and gone for good.Less than a hundred corporations have swallowed all but a few leavings.These industries have already sucked the blood and softened the bones of the people.The old days of expansion are gone.The whole system of capitalistic democracy is—rotten and corrupt.There remains only two roads ahead.One：Fascism.Two：reform of the most revolutionary and permanent kind.”

“And the Negro. Do not forget the Negro.So far as I and my people are concerned the South is Fascist now and always has been.”

“Yeah.”

“The Nazis rob the Jews of their legal, economic, and cultural life. Here the Negro has always been deprived of these.And if wholesale and dramatic robbery of money and goods has not taken place here as in Germany, it is simply because the Negro has never been allowed to accrue wealth in the first place.”

“That's the system，”Jake said.

“The Jew and the Negro，”said Doctor Copeland bitterly.“The history of my people will be commensurate with the interminable history of the Jew—only bloodier and more violent. Like a certain species of sea gull.If you capture one of the birds and tie a red string of twine around his leg the rest of the flock will peck him to death.”

Doctor Copeland took off his spectacles and rebound a wire around a broken hinge. Then he polished the lenses on his nightshirt.His hand shook with agitation.“Mr.Singer is a Jew.”

“No, you're wrong there.”

“But I am positive that he is. The name, Singer.I recognized his race the first time I saw him.From his eyes.Besides, he told me so.”

“Why, he couldn't have，”Jake insisted.“He's pure Anglo-Saxon if I ever saw it. Irish and Anglo-Saxon.”

“But—”

“I'm certain. Absolutely.”

“Very well，”said Doctor Copeland.“We will not quarrel.”

Outside the dark air had cooled so that there was a chill in the room. It was almost dawn.The early morning sky was deep, silky blue and the moon had turned from silver to white.All was still.The only sound was the clear, lonely song of a spring bird in the darkness outside.Though a faint breeze blew in from the window the air in the room was sour and close.There was a feeling both of tenseness and exhaustion.Doctor Copeland leaned forward from the pillow.His eyes were bloodshot and his hands clutched the counterpane.The neck of his nightshirt had slipped down over his bony shoulder.Jake's heels were balanced on the rungs of his chair and his giant hands folded between his knees in a waiting and childlike attitude.Deep black circles were beneath his eyes, his hair was unkempt.They looked at each other and waited.As the silence grew longer the tenseness between them became more strained.

At last Doctor Copeland cleared his throat and said：“I am certain you did not come here for nothing. I am sure we have not discussed these subjects all through the night to no purpose.We have talked of everything now except the most vital subject of all—the way out.What must be done.”

They still watched each other and waited. In the face of each there was expectation.Doctor Copeland sat bolt upright against the pillows.Jake rested his chin in his hand and leaned forward.The pause continued.And then hesitantly they began to speak at the same time.

“Excuse me，”Jake said.“Go ahead.”

“No, you. You started first.”

“Go on.”

“Pshaw！”said Doctor Copeland.“Continue.”

Jake stared at him with clouded, mystical eyes.“It's this way. This is how I see it.The only solution is for the people to know.Once they know the truth they can be oppressed no longer.Once just half of them know the whole fight is won.”

“Yes, once they understand the workings of this society. But how do you propose to tell them?”

“Listen，”Jake said.“Think about chain letters. If one person sends a letter to ten people and then each of the ten people sends letters to ten more—you get it?”He faltered.“Not that I write letters, but the idea is the same.I just go around telling.And if in one town I can show the truth to just ten of the don't knows, then I feel like some good has been done.See?”

Doctor Copeland looked at Jake in surprise. Then he snorted.“Do not be childish！You cannot just go about talking.Chain letters indeed！Knows and don't-knows！”

Jake's lips trembled and his brow lowered with quick anger.“O. K.What have you got to offer?”

“I will say first that I used to feel somewhat as you do on this question. But I have learned what a mistake that attitude is.For half a century I thought it wise to be patient.”

“I didn't say be patient.”

“In the face of brutality I was prudent. Before injustice I held my peace.I sacrificed the things in hand for the good of the hypothetical whole.I believed in the tongue instead of the fist.As an armor against oppression I taught patience and faith in the human soul.I know now how wrong I was.I have been a traitor to myself and to my people.All that is rot.Now is the time to act and to act quickly.Fight cunning with cunning and might with might.”

“But how?”Jake asked.“How?”

“Why, by getting out and doing things. By calling crowds of people together and getting them to demonstrate.”

“Huh！That last phrase gives you away—‘getting them to demonstrate.'What good will it do if you get them to demonstrate against a thing if they don't know. You're trying to stuff the hog by way of his ass.”

“Such vulgar expressions annoy me，”Doctor Copeland said prudishly.

“For Christ'sake！I don't care if they annoy you or not.”

Doctor Copeland held up his hand.“Let us not get so overheated，”he said.“Let us attempt to see eye to eye with each other.”

“Suits me. I don't want to fight with you.”

They were silent. Doctor Copeland moved his eyes from one corner of the ceiling to the other.Several times he wet his lips to speak and each time the word remained half-formed and silent in his mouth.Then at last he said：“My advice to you is this.Do not attempt to stand alone.”

“But—”

“But, nothing，”said Doctor Copeland didactically.“The most fatal thing a man can do is try to stand alone.”

“I see what you're getting at.”

Doctor Copeland pulled the neck of his nightshirt up over his bony shoulder and held it gathered tight to his throat.“You believe in the struggle of my people for their human rights?”

The Doctor's agitation and his mild and husky question made Jake's eyes brim suddenly with tears. A quick, swollen rush of love caused him to grasp the black, bony hand on the counterpane and hold it fast.“Sure，”he said.

“The extremity of our need?”

“Yes.”

“The lack of justice?The bitter inequality?”

Doctor Copeland coughed and spat into one of the squares of paper which he kept beneath his pillow.“I have a program. It is a very simple, concentrated plan.I mean to focus on only one objective.In August of this year I plan to lead more than one thousand Negroes in this county on a march.A march to Washington.All of us together in one solid body.If you will look in the cabinet yonder you will see a stack of letters which I have written this week and will deliver personally.”Doctor Copeland slid his nervous hands up and down the sides of the narrow bed.“You remember what I said to you a short while ago?You will recall that my only advice to you was：Do not attempt to stand alone.”

“I get it，”Jake said.

“But once you enter this it must be all. First and foremost.Your work now and forever.You must give of your whole self without stint, without hope of personal return, without rest or hope of rest.”

“For the rights of the Negro in the South.”

“In the South and here in this very county. And it must be either all or nothing.Either yes or no.”

Doctor Copeland leaned back on the pillow. Only his eyes seemed alive.They burned in his face like red coals.The fever made his cheekbones a ghastly purple.Jake scowled and pressed his knuckles to his soft, wide, trembling mouth.Color rushed to his face.Outside the first pale light of morning had come.The electric bulb suspended from the ceiling burned with ugly sharpness in the dawn.

Jake rose to his feet and stood stiffly at the foot of the bed. He said flatly：“No.That's not the right angle at all.I'm dead sure it's not.In the first place, you'd never get out of town.They'd break it up by saying it’s a menace to public health—or some such trumped-up reason.They’d arrest you and nothing would come of it.But even if by some miracle you got to Washington it wouldn’t do a bit of good.Why, the whole notion is crazy.”

The sharp rattle of phlegm sounded in Doctor Copeland's throat. His voice was harsh.“As you are so quick to sneer and condemn, what do you have to offer instead?”

“I didn't sneer，”Jake said.“I only remarked that your plan is crazy. I come here tonight with an idea much better than that.I wanted your son, Willie, and the other two boys to let me push them around in a wagon.They were to tell what happened to them and afterward I was to tell why.In other words, I was to give a talk on the dialectics of capitalism—and show up all of its lies.I would explain so that everyone would understand why those boys'legs were cut off.And make everyone who saw them know.”

“Pshaw！Double pshaw！”said Doctor Copeland furiously.“I do not believe you have good sense. If I were a man who felt it worth my while to laugh I would surely laugh at that.Never have I had the opportunity to hear of such nonsense first hand.”

They stared at each other in bitter disappointment and anger. There was the rattle of a wagon in the street outside.Jake swallowed and bit his lips.“Huh！”he said finally.“You're the only one who's crazy.You got everything exactly backward.The only way to solve the Negro problem under capitalism is to geld every one of the fifteen million black men in these states.”

“So that is the kind of idea you harbor beneath your ranting about justice.”

“I didn't say it should be done. I only said you couldn't see the forest for the trees.”Jake spoke with slow and painful care.“The work has to start at the bottom.The old traditions smashed and the new ones created.To forge a whole new pattern for the world.To make man a social creature for the first time, living in an orderly and controlled society where he is not forced to be unjust in order to survive.A social tradition in which—”

Doctor Copeland clapped ironically.“Very good，”he said.“But the cotton must be picked before the cloth is made. You and your crackpot do-nothing theories can—”

“Hush！Who cares whether you and your thousand Negroes straggle up to that stinking cesspool of a place called Washington?What difference does it make?What do a few people matter—a few thousand people, black, white, good or bad?When the whole of our society is built on a foundation of black lies.”

“Everything！”Doctor Copeland panted.“Everything！Everything！

“Nothing！”

“The soul of the meanest and most evil of us on this earth is worth more in the sight of justice than—”

“Oh, the Hell with it！”Jake said.“Balls！”

“Blasphemer！”screamed Doctor Copeland.“Foul blasphemer！”

Jake shook the iron bars of the bed. The vein in his forehead swelled to the point of bursting and his face was dark with rage.“Short-sighted bigot！”

“White—”Doctor Copeland's voice failed him. He struggled and no sound would come.At last he was able to bring forth a choked whisper：“Fiend.”

The bright yellow morning was at the window. Doctor Copeland's head fell back on the pillow.His neck twisted at a broken angle, a fleck of bloody foam on his lips.Jake looked at him once before, sobbing with violence, he rushed headlong from the room.

14

Now she could not stay in the inside room. She had to be around somebody all the time.Doing something every minute.And if she was by herself she counted or figured with numbers.She counted all the roses on the living-room wallpaper.She figured out the cubic area of the whole house.She counted every blade of grass in the back yard and every leaf on a certain bush.Because if she did not have her mind on numbers this terrible afraidness came in her.She would be walking home from school on these May afternoons and suddenly she would have to think of something quick.A good thing—very good.Maybe she would think about a phrase of hurrying jazz music.Or that a bowl of jello would be in the refrigerator when she got home.Or plan to smoke a cigarette behind the coal house.Maybe she would try to think a long way ahead to the time when she would go north and see snow, or even travel somewhere in a foreign land.But these thoughts about good things wouldn't last.The jello was gone in five minutes and the cigarette smoked.Then what was there after that?And the numbers mixed themselves up in her brain.And the snow and the foreign land were a long, long time away.Then what was there?

Just Mister Singer. She wanted to follow him everywhere.In the morning she would watch him go down the front steps to work and then follow along a half a block behind him.Every afternoon as soon as school was over she hung around at the corner near the store where he worked.At four o'clock he went out to drink a Coca-Cola.She watched him cross the street and go into the drugstore and finally come out again.She followed him home from work and sometimes even when he took walks.She always followed a long way behind him.And he did not know.

She would go up to see him in his room. First she scrubbed her face and hands and put some vanilla on the front of her dress.She only went to visit him twice a week now, because she didn't want him to get tired of her.Most always he would be sitting over the queer, pretty chess game when she opened the door.And then she was with him.

“Mister Singer, have you ever lived in a place where it snowed in the winter-time?”

He tilted his chair back against the wall and nodded.

“In some different country than this one—in a foreign place?”

He nodded yes again and wrote on his pad with his silver pencil. Once he had traveled to Ontario, Canada—across the river from Detroit.Canada was so far up north that the white snow drifted up to the roofs of the houses.That was where the Quints were and the St.Lawrence River.The people ran up and down the streets speaking French to each other.And far up in the north there were deep forests and white ice igloos.The arctic region with the beautiful northern lights.

“When you was in Canada did you go out and get any fresh snow and eat it with cream and sugar?Once I read where it was mighty good to eat that way.”

He turned his head to one side because he didn't understand. She couldn't ask the question again because suddenly it sounded silly.She only looked at him and waited.A big, black shadow of his head was on the wall behind him.The electric fan cooled the thick, hot air.All was quiet.It was like they waited to tell each other things that had never been told before.What she had to say was terrible and afraid.But what he would tell her was so true that it would make everything all right.Maybe it was a thing that could not be spoken with words or writing.Maybe he would have to let her understand this in a different way.That was the feeling she had with him.

“I was just asking you about Canada—but it didn't amount to anything, Mister Singer.”

Downstairs in the home rooms there was plenty of trouble. Etta was still so sick that she couldn't sleep crowded three in a bed.The shades were drawn and the dark room smelled bad with a sick smell.Etta's job was gone, and that meant eight dollars less a week besides the doctor's bill.Then one day when Ralph was walking around in the kitchen he burned himself on the hot kitchen stove.The bandages made his hands itch and somebody had to watch him all the time else he would bust the blisters.On George's birthday they had bought him a little red bike with a bell and a basket on the handlebars.Everybody had chipped in to give it to him.But when Etta lost her job they couldn't pay, and after two installments were past due the store sent a man out to take the wheel away.George just watched the man roll the bike off the porch, and when he passed George kicked the back fender and then went into the coal house and shut the door.

It was money, money, money all the time. They owed to the grocery and they owed the last payment on some furniture.And now since they had lost the house they owed money there too.The six rooms in the house were always taken, but nobody ever paid the rent on time.

For a while their Dad went over every day to hunt another job. He couldn't do carpenter work any more because it made him jittery to be more than ten feet off the ground.He applied for many jobs but nobody would hire him.Then at last he got this notion.

“It's advertising, Mick，”he said.“I've come to the conclusion that's all in the world the matter with my watch-repairing business right now. I got to sell myself.I got to get out and let people know I can fix watches, and fix them good and cheap.You just mark my words.I'm going to build up this business so I'll be able to make a good living for this family the rest of my life.Just by advertising.”

He brought home a dozen sheets of tin and some red paint. For the next week he was very busy.It seemed to him like this was a hell of a good idea.The signs were all over the floor of the front room.He got down on his hands and knees and took great care over the printing of each letter.As he worked he whistled and wagged his head.He hadn't been so cheerful and glad in months.Every now and then he would have to dress in his good suit and go around the corner for a glass of beer to calm himself.On the signs at first he had：

Wilbur Kelly

Watch Repairing

Very Cheap and Expert

“Mick, I want them to hit you right bang in the eye. To stand out wherever you see them.”

She helped him and he gave her three nickels. The signs were O.K.at first.Then he worked on them so much that they were ruined.He wanted to add more and more things—in the corners and at the top and bottom.Before he had finished the signs were plastered all over with“Very Cheap”and“Come At Once”and“You Give Me Any Watch And I Make It Run.”

“You tried to write so much in the signs that nobody will read anything，”she told him.

He brought home some more tin and left the designing up to her. She painted them very plain, with great big block letters and a picture of a clock.Soon he had a whole stack of them.A fellow he knew rode him out in the country where he could nail them to trees and fence-posts.At both ends of the block he put up a sign with a black hand pointing toward the house.And over the front door there was another sign.

The day after this advertising was finished he waited in the front room dressed in a clean shirt and a tie. Nothing happened.The jeweler who gave him overflow work to do at half price sent in a couple of clocks.That was all.He took it hard.He didn't go out to look for other jobs any more, but every minute he had to be busy around the house.He took down the doors and oiled the hinges—whether they needed it or not.He mixed the margarine for Portia and scrubbed the floors upstairs.He worked out a contraption where the water from the ice box could be drained through the kitchen window.He carved some beautiful alphabet blocks for Ralph and invented a little needle-threader.Over the few watches that he had to work on he took great pains.

Mick still followed Mister Singer. But she didn't want to.It was like there was something wrong about her following after him without his knowing.Two or three days she played hooky from school.She walked behind him when he went to work and hung around on the corner near his store all day.When he ate his dinner at Mister Brannon's she went into the café　and spent a nickel for a sack of peanuts.Then at night she followed him on these dark, long walks.She stayed on the opposite side of the street from him and about a block behind.When he stopped, she stopped also—and when he walked fast she ran to keep up with him.So long as she could see him and be near him she was right happy.But sometimes this queer feeling would come to her and she knew that she was doing wrong.So she tried hard to keep busy at home.

She and her Dad were alike in the way that now they always had to be fooling with something. She kept up with all that went on in the house and the neighborhood.Sparerib's big sister won fifty dollars at a movie bank night.Baby Wilson had the bandage off her head now, but her hair was cut short like a boy's.She couldn't dance in the soirée this year, and when her mother took her to see it Baby began to yell and cut up during one of the dances.They had to drag her out of the Opera House.And on the sidewalk Mrs.Wilson had to whip her to make her behave.And Mrs.Wilson cried, too.George hated Baby.He would hold his nose and stop up his ears when she passed by the house.Pete Wells ran away from home and was gone three weeks.He came back barefooted and very hungry.He bragged about how he had gone all the way to New Orleans.

Because of Etta, Mick still slept in the living-room. The short sofa cramped her so much that she had to make up sleep in study hall at school.Every other night Bill swapped with her and she slept with George.Then a lucky break came for them.A fellow who had a room upstairs moved away.When after a week had gone by and nobody answered the ad in the paper, their Mama told Bill he could move up to the vacant room.Bill was very pleased to have a place entirely by himself away from the family.She moved in with George.He slept like a little warm kitty and breathed very quiet.

She knew the night-time again. But not the same as in the last summer when she walked in the dark by herself and listened to the music and made plans.She knew the night a different way now.In bed she lay awake.A queer afraidness came to her.It was like the ceiling was slowly pressing down toward her face.How would it be if the house fell apart?Once their Dad had said the whole place ought to be condemned.Did he mean that maybe some night when they were asleep the walls would crack and the house collapse?Bury them under all the plaster and broken glass and smashed furniture?So that they could not move or breathe?She lay awake and her muscles were stiff.In the night there was creaking.Was that somebody walking—somebody else awake besides her—Mister Singer?

She never thought about Harry. She had made up her mind to forget him and she did forget him.He wrote that he had a job with a garage in Birmingham.She answered with a card saying“O.K.”as they had planned.He sent his mother three dollars every week.It seemed like a very long time had passed since they went to the woods together.

During the day she was busy in the outside room. But at night she was by herself in the dark and figuring was not enough.She wanted somebody.She tried to keep George awake.“It sure is fun to stay awake and talk in the dark.Less us talk awhile together.”

He made a sleepy answer.

“See the stars out the window. It's a hard thing to realize that every single one of those little stars is a planet as large as the earth.”

“How do they know that?”

“They just do. They got ways of measuring.That's science.”

“I don't believe in it.”

She tried to egg him on to an argument so that he would get mad and stay awake. He just let her talk and didn't seem to pay attention.After a while he said：

“Look, Mick！You see that branch of the tree?Don't it look like a pilgrim forefather lying down with a gun in his hand?”

“It sure does. That's exactly what it's like.And see over there on the bureau.Don't that bottle look like a funny man with a hat on?”

“Naw，”George said.“It don't look a bit like one to me.”

She took a drink from a glass of water on the floor.“Less me and you play a game—the name game. You can be It if you want to.Whichever you like.You can choose.”

He put his little fists up to his face and breathed in a quiet, even way because he was falling asleep.

“Wait, George！”she said.“This'll be fun. I'm somebody beginning with an M.Guess who I am.”

George sighed and his voice was tired.“Are you Harpo Marx?”

“No, Fm not even in the movies.”

“I don't know.”

“Sure you do. My name begins with the letter M and I live in Italy.You ought to guess this.”

George turned over on his side and curled up in a ball. He did not answer.

“My name begins with an M but sometimes I'm called a name beginning with D. In Italy.You can guess.”

The room was quiet and dark and George was asleep. She pinched him and twisted his ear.He groaned but did not awake.She fitted in close to him and pressed her face against his hot little naked shoulder.He would sleep all through the night while she was figuring with decimals.

Was Mister Singer awake in his room upstairs?Did the ceiling creak because he was walking quietly up and down, drinking a cold orange crush and studying the chess-men laid out on the table?Had ever he felt a terrible afraidness like this one?No. He had never done anything wrong.He had never done wrong and his heart was quiet in the night-time.Yet at the same time he would understand.

If only she could tell him about this, then it would be better. She thought of how she would begin to tell him.Mister Singer—I know this girl not any older than I am—Mister Singer, I don't know whether you understand a thing like this or not—Mister Singer.Mister Singer.She said his name over and over.She loved him better than anyone in the family, better even than George or her Dad.It was a different love.It was not like anything she had ever felt in her life before.

In the mornings she and George would dress together and talk. Sometimes she wanted very much to be close to George.He had grown taller and was pale and peaked.His soft, reddish hair lay raggedly over the tops of his little ears.His sharp eyes were always squinted so that his face had a strained look.His permanent teeth were coming in, but they were blue and far apart like his baby teeth had been.Often his jaw was crooked because he had a habit of feeling out the sore new teeth with his tongue.

“Listen here, George，”she said.“Do you love me?”

“Sure. I love you O.K.”

It was a hot, sunny morning during the last week of school. George was dressed and he lay on the floor doing his number work.His dirty little fingers squeezed the pencil tight and he kept breaking the lead point.When he was finished she held him by the shoulders and looked hard into his face.“I mean a lot.A whole lot.”

“Lemme go. Sure I love you.Ain't you my sister?”

“I know. But suppose I wasn't your sister.Would you love me then?”

George backed away. He had run out of shirts and wore a dirty pullover sweater.His wrists were thin and blue-veined.The sleeves of the sweater had stretched so that they hung loose and made his hands look very small.

“If you wasn't my sister then I might not know you. So I couldn't love you.”

“But if you did know me and I wasn't your sister.”

“But how do you know I would?You can't prove it.”

“Well, just take it for granted and pretend.”

“I reckon I would like you all right. But I still say you can't prove—”

“Prove！You got that word on the brain. Prove and trick.Everything is either a trick or it's got to be proved.I can't stand you, George Kelly.I hate you.”

“O. K.Then I don't like you none either.”

He crawled down under the bed for something.

“What you want under there?You better leave my things alone. If I ever caught you meddling in my private box I'd bust your head against the side of the wall.I would.I'd stomp on your brains.”

George came out from under the bed with his spelling book. His dirty little paw reached in a hole in the mattress where he hid his marbles.Nothing could faze that kid.He took his time about choosing three brown agates to take with him.“Aw, shucks, Mick，”he answered her.George was too little and too tough.There wasn't any sense in loving him.He knew even less about things than she did.

School was out and she had passed every subject—some with A plus and some by the skin of her teeth. The days were long and hot.Finally she was able to work hard at music again.She began to write down pieces for the violin and piano.She wrote songs.Always music was in her mind.She listened to Mister Singer's radio and wandered around the house thinking about the programs she had heard.

“What ails Mick?”Portia asked.“What kind of cat is it got her tongue?She walk around and don't say a word. She not even greedy like she used to be.She getting to be a regular lady these days.”

It was as though in some way she was waiting—but what she waited for she did not know. The sun burned down glaring and white-hot in the streets.During the day she either worked hard at music or messed with kids.And waited.Sometimes she would look all around her quick and this panic would come in her.Then in late June there was a sudden happening so important that it changed everything.

That night they were all out on the porch. The twilight was blurred and soft.Supper was almost ready and the smell of cabbage floated to them from the open hall.All of them were together except Hazel, who had not come home from work, and Etta, who still lay sick in bed.Their Dad leaned back in a chair with his sock-feet on the banisters.Bill was on the steps with the kids.Their Mama sat on the swing fanning herself with the newspaper.Across the street a girl new in the neighborhood skated up and down the sidewalk on one roller skate.The lights on the block were just beginning to be turned on, and far away a man was calling someone.

Then Hazel come home. Her high heels clopped up the steps and she leaned back lazily on the banisters.In the half-dark her fat, soft hands were very white as she felt the back of her braided hair.“I sure do wish Etta was able to work，”she said.“I found out about this job today.”

“What kind of a job?”asked their Dad.“Anything I could do, or just for girls?”

“Just for a girl. A clerk down at Woolworth's is going to get married next week.”

“The ten-cent store—”Mick said.

“You interested?”

The question took her by surprise. She had just been thinking about a sack of wintergreen candy she had bought there the day before.She felt hot and tense.She rubbed her bangs up from her forehead and counted the first few stars.

Their Dad flipped his cigarette down to the sidewalk.“No，”he said.“We don't want Mick to take on too much responsibility at her age. Let her get her growth out.Her growth through with, anyway.”

“I agree with you，”Hazel said.“I really do think it would be a mistake for Mick to have to work regular. I don't think it would be right.”

Bill put Ralph down from his lap and shuffled his feet on the steps.“Nobody ought to work until they're around sixteen. Mick should have two more years and finish at Vocational—if we can make it.”

“Even if we have to give up the house and move down in mill town，”their Mama said.“I rather keep Mick at home for a while.”

For a minute she had been scared they would try to corner her into taking the job. She would have said she would run away from home.But the way they took the attitude they did touched her.She felt excited.They were all talking about her—and in a kindly way.She was ashamed for the first scared feeling that had come to her.Of a sudden she loved all of the family and a tightness came in her throat.

“About how much money is in it?”she asked.

“Ten dollars.”

“Ten dollars a week?”

“Sure，”Hazel said.“Did you think it would be only ten a month?”

“Portia don't make but about that much.”

“Oh, colored people—”Hazel said.

Mick rubbed the top of her head with her fist.“That's a whole lot of money. A good deal.”

“It's not to be grinned at，”Bill said.“That's what I make.”

Mick's tongue was dry. She moved it around in her mouth to gather up spit enough to talk.“Ten dollars a week would buy about fifteen fried chickens.Or five pairs of shoes or five dresses.Or installments on a radio.”She thought about a piano, but she did not mention that aloud.

“It would tide us over，”their Mama said.“But at the same time I rather keep Mick at home for a while. Now, when Etta—”

“Wait！”She felt hot and reckless.“I want to take the job. I can hold it down.I know I can.”

“Listen to little Mick，”Bill said.

Their Dad picked his teeth with a matchstick and took his feet down from the banisters.“Now, let's not rush into anything. I rather Mick take her time and think this out.We can get along somehow without her working.I mean to increase my watch work by sixty per cent soon as—”

“I forgot，”Hazel said.“I think there's a Christmas bonus every year.”

Mick frowned.“But I wouldn't be working then. I'd be in school.I just want to work during vacation and then go back to school.”

“Sure，”Hazel said quickly.

“But tomorrow I'll go down with you and take the job if I can get it.”

It was as though a great worry and tightness left the family. In the dark they began to laugh and talk.Their Dad did a trick for George with a matchstick and a handkerchief.Then he gave the kid fifty cents to go down to the corner store for Coca-Colas to be drunk after supper.The smell of cabbage was stronger in the hall and pork chops were frying.Portia called.The boarders already waited at the table.Mick had supper in the dining-room.The cabbage leaves were limp and yellow on her plate and she couldn't eat.When she reached for the bread she knocked a pitcher of iced tea over the table.

Then later she waited on the front porch by herself for Mister Singer to come home. In a desperate way she wanted to see him.The excitement of the hour before had died down and she was sick to the stomach.She was going to work in a ten-cent store and she did not want to work there.It was like she had been trapped into something.The job wouldn't be just for the summer—but for a long time, as long as she could see ahead.Once they were used to the money coming in it would be impossible to do without again.That was the way things were.She stood in the dark and held tight to the banisters.A long time passed and Mister Singer still did not come.At eleven o'clock she went out to see if she could find him.But suddenly she got frightened in the dark and ran back home.

Then in the morning she bathed and dressed very careful. Hazel and Etta loaned her the clothes to wear and primped her to look nice.She wore Hazel's green silk dress and a green hat and high-heeled pumps with silk stockings.They fixed her face with rouge and lipstick and plucked her eyebrows.She looked at least sixteen years old when they were finished.

It was too late to back down now. She was really grown and ready to earn her keep.Yet if she would go to her Dad and tell him how she felt he would tell her to wait a year.And Hazel and Etta and Bill and their Mama, even now, would say that she didn't have to go.But she couldn't do it.She couldn't lose face like that.She went up to see Mister Singer.The words came all in a rush：

“Listen—I believe I got this job. What do you think?Do you think it's a good idea?Do you think it's O.K.to drop out of school and work now?You think it's good?”

At first he did not understand. His gray eyes half-closed and he stood with his hands deep down in his pockets.There was the old feeling that they waited to tell each other things that had never been told before.The thing she had to say now was not much.But what he had to tell her would be right—and if he said the job sounded O.K.then she would feel better about it.She repeated the words slowly and waited.

“You think it's good?”

Mister Singer considered. Then he nodded yes.

She got the job. The manager took her and Hazel back to a little office and talked with them.Afterward she couldn't remember how the manager looked or anything that had been said.But she was hired, and on the way out of the place she bought ten cents'worth of Chocolate and a little modeling clay set for George.On June the fifth she was to start work.She stood for a long while before the window of Mister Singer's jewelry store.Then she hung around on the corner.

15

The time had come for Singer to go to Antonapoulos again. The journey was a long one.For, although the distance between them was something less than two hundred miles, the train meandered to points far out of the way and stopped for long hours at certain stations during the night.Singer would leave the town in the afternoon and travel all through the night and until the early morning of the next day.As usual, he was ready far in advance.He planned to have a full week with his friend this visit.His clothes had been sent to the cleaner's, his hat blocked, and his bags were in readiness.The gifts he would carry were wrapped in colored tissue paper—and in addition there was a de luxe basket of fruits done up in cellophane and a crate of late-shipped strawberries.On the morning before his departure Singer cleaned his room.In his ice box he found a bit of left-over goose liver and took it out to the alley for the neighborhood cat.On his door he tacked the same sign he had posted there before, stating that he would be absent for several days on business.During all these preparations he moved about leisurely with two vivid spots of color on his cheekbones.His face was very solemn.

Then at last the hour for departure was at hand. He stood on the platform, burdened with his suitcases and gifts, and watched the train roll in on the station tracks.He found himself a seat in the day coach and hoisted his luggage on the rack above his head.The car was crowded, for the most part with mothers and children.The green plush seats had a grimy smell.The windows of the car were dirty and rice thrown at some recent bridal pair lay scattered on the floor.Singer smiled cordially to his fellow-travelers and leaned back in his seat.He closed his eyes.The lashes made a dark, curved fringe above the hollows of his cheeks.His right hand moved nervously inside his pocket.

For a while his thoughts lingered in the town he was leaving behind him. He saw Mick and Doctor Copeland and Jake Blount and Biff Brannon.The faces crowded in on him out of the darkness so that he felt smothered.He thought of the quarrel between Blount and the Negro.The nature of this quarrel was hopelessly confused in his mind—but each of them had on several occasions broken out into a bitter tirade against the other, the absent one.He had agreed with each of them in turn, though what it was they wanted him to sanction he did not know.And Mick—her face was urgent and she said a good deal that he did not understand in the least.And then Biff Brannon at the New York Café.Brannon with his dark, iron-like jaw and his watchful eyes.And strangers who followed him about the streets and buttonholed him for unexplainable reasons.The Turk at the linen shop who flung his hands up in his face and babbled with his tongue to make words the shape of which Singer had never imagined before.A certain mill foreman and an old black woman.A businessman on the main street and an urchin who solicited soldiers for a whorehouse near the river.Singer wriggled his shoulders uneasily.The train rocked with a smooth, easy motion.His head nodded to rest on his shoulder and for a short while he slept.

When he opened his eyes again the town was far behind him. The town was forgotten.Outside the dirty window there was the brilliant midsummer countryside.The sun slanted in strong, bronze-colored rays over the green fields of the new cotton.There were acres of tobacco, the plants heavy and green like some monstrous jungle weed.The orchards of peaches with the lush fruit weighting down the dwarfed trees.There were miles of pastures and tens of miles of wasted, washed-out land abandoned to the hardier weeds.The train cut through deep green pine forests where the ground was covered with the slick brown needles and the tops of the trees stretched up virgin and tall into the sky.And farther, a long way south of the town, the cypress swamps—with the gnarled roots of the trees writhing down into the brackish waters, where the gray, tattered moss trailed from the branches, where tropical water flowers blossomed in dankness and gloom.Then out again into the open beneath the sun and the indigo-blue sky.

Singer sat solemn and timid, his face turned fully toward the window. The great sweeps of space and the hard, elemental coloring almost blinded him.This kaleidoscopic variety of scene, this abundance of growth and color, seemed somehow connected with his friend.His thoughts were with Antonapoulos.The bliss of their reunion almost stifled him.His nose was pinched and he breathed with quick, short breaths through his slightly open mouth.

Antonapoulos would be glad to see him. He would enjoy the fresh fruits and the presents.By now he would be out of the sick ward and able to go on an excursion to the movies, and afterward to the hotel where they had eaten dinner on the first visit.Singer had written many letters to Antonapoulos, but he had not posted them.He surrendered himself wholly to thoughts of his friend.

The half-year since he had last been with him seemed neither a long nor a short span of time. Behind each waking moment there had always been his friend.And this submerged communion with Antonapoulos had grown and changed as though they were together in the flesh.Sometimes he thought of Antonapoulos with awe and self-abasement, sometimes with pride—always with love unchecked by criticism, freed of will.When he dreamed at night the face of his friend was always before him, massive and gentle.And in his waking thoughts they were eternally united.

The summer evening came slowly. The sun sank down behind a ragged line of trees in the distance and the sky paled.The twilight was languid and soft.There was a white full moon, and low purple clouds lay over the horizon.The earth, the trees, the unpainted rural dwellings darkened slowly.At intervals mild summer lightning quivered in the air.Singer watched all of this intently until at last the night had come, and his own face was reflected in the glass before him.

Children staggered up and down the aisle of the car with dripping paper cups of water. An old man in overalls who had the seat before Singer drank whiskey from time to time from a Coca-Cola bottle.Between swallows he plugged the bottle carefully with a wad of paper.A little girl on the right combed her hair with a sticky red lollipop.Shoeboxes were opened and trays of supper were brought in from the dining-car.Singer did not eat.He leaned back in his seat and kept desultory account of all that went on around him.At last the car settled down.Children lay on the broad plush seats and slept, while men and women doubled up with their pillows and rested as best they could.

Singer did not sleep. He pressed his face close against the glass and strained to see into the night.The darkness was heavy and velvety.Sometimes there was a patch of moonlight or the flicker of a lantern from the window of some house along the way.From the moon he saw that the train had turned from its southward course and was headed toward the east.The eagerness he felt was so keen that his nose was too pinched to breathe through and his cheeks were scarlet.He sat there, his face pressed close against the cold, sooty glass of the window, through most of the long night journey.

The train was more than an hour late, and the fresh, bright summer morning was well under way when they arrived. Singer went immediately to the hotel, a very good hotel where he had made reservations in advance.He unpacked his bags and arranged the presents he would take to Antonapoulos on the bed.From the menu the bell boy brought him he selected a luxurious breakfast—broiled bluefish, hominy, French toast, and hot black coffee.After breakfast he rested before the electric fan in his underwear.At noon he began to dress.He bathed and shaved and laid out fresh linen and his best seersucker suit.At three o'clock the hospital was open for visiting hours.It was Tuesday and the eighteenth of July.

At the asylum he sought Antonapoulos first in the sick ward where he had been confined before. But at the doorway of the room he saw immediately that his friend was not there.Next he found his way through the corridors to the office where he had been taken the time before.He had his question already written on one of the cards he carried about with him.The person behind the desk was not the same as the one who had been there before.He was a young man, almost a boy, with a half-formed, immature face and a lank mop of hair.Singer handed him the card and stood quietly, his arms heaped with packages, his weight resting on his heels.

The young man shook his head. He leaned over the desk and scribbled loosely on a pad of paper.Singer read what he had written and the spots of color drained from his cheekbones instantly.He looked at the note a long time, his eyes cut sideways and his head bowed.For it was written there that Antonapoulos was dead.

On the way back to the hotel he was careful not to crush the fruit he had brought with him. He took the packages up to his room and then wandered down to the lobby.Behind a potted palm tree there was a slot machine.He inserted a nickel but when he tried to pull the lever he found that the machine was jammed.Over this incident he made a great to-do.He cornered the clerk and furiously demonstrated what had happened.His face was deathly pale and he was so beside himself that tears rolled down the ridges of his nose.He flailed his hands and even stamped once with his long, narrow, elegantly shoed foot on the plush carpet.Nor was he satisfied when his coin was refunded, but insisted on checking out immediately.He packed his bag and was obliged to work energetically to make it close again.For in addition to the articles he had brought with him he carried away three towels, two cakes of soap, a pen and a bottle of ink, a roll of toilet paper, and a Holy Bible.He paid his bill and walked to the railway station to put his belongings in custody.The train did not leave until nine in the evening and he had the empty afternoon before him.

This town was smaller than the one in which he lived. The business streets intersected to form the shape of a cross.The stores had a countrified look；there were harnesses and sacks of feed in half of the display windows.Singer walked listlessly along the sidewalks.His throat felt swollen and he wanted to swallow but was unable to do so.To relieve this strangled feeling he bought a drink in one of the drugstores.He idled in the barber shop and purchased a few trifles at the ten-cent store.He looked no one full in the face and his head drooped down to one side like a sick animal's.

The afternoon was almost ended when a strange thing happened to Singer. He had been walking slowly and irregularly along the curb of the street.The sky was overcast and the air humid.Singer did not raise his head, but as he passed the town pool room he caught a sidewise glance of something that disturbed him.He passed the pool room and then stopped in the middle of the street.Listlessly he retraced his steps and stood before the open door of the place.There were three mutes inside and they were talking with their hands together.All three of them were coatless.They wore bowler hats and bright ties.Each of them held a glass of beer in his left hand.There was a certain brotherly resemblance between them.

Singer went inside. For a moment he had trouble taking his hand from his pocket.Then clumsily he formed a word of greeting.He was clapped on the shoulder.A cold drink was ordered.They surrounded him and the fingers of their hands shot out like pistons as they questioned him.

He told his own name and the name of the town where he lived. After that he could think of nothing else to tell about himself.He asked if they knew Spiros Antonapoulos.They did not know him.Singer stood with his hands dangling loose.His head was still inclined to one side and his glance was oblique.He was so listless and cold that the three mutes in the bowler hats looked at him queerly.After a while they left him out of their conversation.And when they had paid for the rounds of beers and were ready to depart they did not suggest that he join them.

Although Singer had been adrift on the streets for half a day he almost missed his train. It was not clear to him how this happened or how he had spent the hours before.He reached the station two minutes before the train pulled out, and barely had time to drag his luggage aboard and find a seat.The car he chose was almost empty.When he was settled he opened the crate of strawberries and picked them over with finicky care.The berries were of a giant size, large as walnuts and in fullblown ripeness.The green leaves at the top of the rich-colored fruit were like tiny bouquets.Singer put a berry in his mouth and though the juice had a lush, wild sweetness there was already a subtle flavor of decay.He ate until his palate was dulled by the taste and then rewrapped the crate and placed it on the rack above him.At midnight he drew the windowshade and lay down on the seat.He was curled in a ball, his coat pulled over his face and head.In this position he lay in a stupor of half-sleep for about twelve hours.The conductor had to shake him when they arrived.

Singer left his luggage in the middle of the station floor. Then he walked to the shop.He greeted the jeweler for whom he worked with a listless turn of his head.When he went out again there was something heavy in his pocket.For a while he rambled with bent head along the streets.But the unrefracted brilliance of the sun, the humid heat, oppressed him.He returned to his room with swollen eyes and an aching head.After resting he drank a glass of iced coffee and smoked a cigarette.Then when he had washed the ash tray and the glass he brought out a pistol from his pocket and put a bullet in his chest.